so true is true but you can cast stuff
in JavaScript so we could make true cast
to one if we wanted to which means you
could do true plus true equals to anyone
know what this is going to do pulse see
what else I got the top of my head just
for fun the array one's fun yeah anyone
know what's going to happen here it's
true as you'd expect in the double
equals operator or sometimes called the
abstract equals operator it'll cast the
thing on the right so if I'm doing this
it's actually false and when something
is false on the right it's going to cast
it to an integer which means it will
cast the other side to an integer which
effectively is like saying is 1 equal to
1 which is why this guy is equal to this
guy another way to do this would be to
say false
you get the idea it let's talk
about we're supposed to talk about so my
name's Brian i work in adobe with
christopher joseph here and you probably
know that we work on the phone gap team
but we also started working on a new
problem at adobe and that was CSS and so
our answer is top coat and the sort of
pitch tagline is it CSS for building
fast and clean apps and everybody is
already thinking well why the hell are
these guys doing another CSS framework
and there's a lot of them right we've
got Twitter bootstrap we've got a serb
foundation there's a new thing from
yahoo called pure which is cool the
problem that we were running into
consistently at least in phonegap land
people will go to build an application
and they'll quickly grab twitter
bootstrap they'll throw it in there and
their app will be slow and they'll be
like oh phonegap sucks which isn't
entirely true so twitter bootstrap is a
meg of CSS is a good chance you do not
need that much CSS to make your buttons
consistent on single platform the other
problem is Twitter bootstrap changes all
the time so there's upgrades that you
have to do and they change their class
names when they're doing it and so
maintenance is a huge problem yeah so
another huge issues the the patterns
that are inside of bootstrapper are huge
and then kind of all-encompassing and
comprehensive and think about the
context of being a website not a nap so
these were all the problems that we're
running into and then Christopher was
working on the reflow team in Adobe and
they were running the same kind of
problems building desktop applications
and we thought well okay if we're
building desktop apps and we're building
native mobile apps using HTML CSS and
JavaScript and we're running these
problems maybe we can work together to
solve them so another issue with CSS is
the dogpile syndrome so you'll take
you'll take your Twitter bootstrap or
your ZURB foundation you'll have this
gigantic file and you'll want to start
adding stuff to it and instead of going
and looking at what all those other
classes or you'll just start adding
stuff to it which means you
more and more CSS over time this is
terrible for maintenance and it's really
hard to perform upgrades and so you end
up just getting more and more CSS added
at the end and not less and if you look
at a lot of tools and analyze CSS now
it's really common to have like a class
gets used once in an application which
is crazy so we we want to fix this first
thing that we decide to do is to focus
on performance I don't think any other
CSS framework has ever been approached
this way they have I'm sorry but what
we're doing we're not just saying that
we're focusing on performance but were
benchmarking everything we do so I was
talking to the brackets team and I'm
like okay how you guys doing performance
and they're crazy there was a talk about
this yesterday where they were using
high-speed cameras to like see people's
type speed all kinds of nutty stuff and
I mentioned it a Paul Irish and he's
like oh you should just use the chrome
telemetry API and I'm like oh that's
cool what's that he's like hot well it's
not really documented but you can find
out about it so we did we dug in and
chrome telemetry API lets us measure all
kinds of performance metrics on on page
load on layout and on frames per second
and so as we're building topcoat we have
all these discrete components were
taking them and adding a whole bunch to
a page and we're scrolling that page up
and down are you going for oh yeah okay
we scroll the page up and down a whole
bunch of times and we take that data and
so we know on each commit whether or not
we're making topcoat faster or slower
and so by saying performance is our
first consideration this isn't just a
statement like we're you know marketing
to you but we're actually trying to be
empirical about it and know that we're
getting faster over time this all this
stuff by the way is open source and so
we're hoping at some point once we tool
this up and we get it working well
enough for ourselves it will be able to
share this or you'll be able to use this
for your topcoat based application so
you as your app the bulbs over time
you'll know if you're making it faster
or slower
yeah it's lent this is cool so like
these are all the various data points
that you can pull out I love that jank
is not only a word now it's a technical
term actually looked it up the other day
and the person who created the word jank
is actually in the audience right over
here names Joe nearest Elka so it's a
bit of a synthetic benchmarking though
our assumption right now is that if
we're making things faster in chrome it
gets faster everywhere else which is not
probably a really true statement and
once the other browsers give us the
ability to instrument them and get this
kind of data out of them we're totally
going to approach those two right now
Chrome's our best bet and I think it's
pretty safe to say if it gets slower in
chrome it's going to be slower elsewhere
this is a preview of a topcoat based
application this app was built for adobe
max for iOS and Android both handset and
tablet form factors in four weeks which
is amazing it performs really great you
can check it out for yourself that gives
you an idea what it looks like so
Christopher did a lot of the development
and we have a lot of sort of different
design goals that are not necessarily
complimentary or competing they're just
things that are important to us that I
don't think have been important to
traditional CSS frameworks so the first
thing that's important to us that we
want to be able to compose our builds
and Christopher is going to give a demo
of this in a minute but the idea here is
that we're separating the reset from the
layout from the aesthetic from the
platform that's running on and so if
you're on iOS you don't get a bunch of
gecko prefixes but when you go over to
Firefox OS you'll get all the right
Mozilla prefixes you might not want all
the aesthetics turned on or off so maybe
you just want the reset so you can
compose builds of all these controls
with just those things and as a kind of
consequence of having an architecture
that has discrete builds and performance
as a first characteristic we wanted to
make this thing super modular for our
own purposes too so making these things
separate boils right down to how we
manage ourselves in github so if you
jump in and github / top coat this does
look a little crazy but all of the
controls are an individual git repos but
this
wins us a huge benefit that that means
that when you're developing using top
coat and we update the button for a bug
only button updates and you don't have
to upgrade your entire top code
installation right now when you're
working with something like Twitter
bootstrap reserved foundation it's an
all-or-nothing proposition you have to
change a lot of files these builds
aren't discrete and they're not
independently version when they update
button they have to rev this entire CSS
file which is not ideal extensibility is
another thing so I showed you the
benchmark server which I'm really
excited about we talked to a whole bunch
of JavaScript and CSS developers about
how they're building applications and
they basically especially pros like Dave
Shay said I'm not going to use this
I'm a craftsman more like okay well
that's cool and then he saw our
benchmarking stuff and he's like but I
want that and so we think the more
important output of top coat isn't
actually the CSS that you can use
although that's a cool thing it's
probably the tools we're using to build
top coat itself so we're hoping that
this is kind of a something that will
encourage people to start building
applications that are performant by
default instead of talking a huge one
Meg CSS file at us and telling us we're
slow another angle is it and this is
funny because I'm at jas comp but top
code is only CSS but ironically almost
all top code is written using javascript
node so we didn't want any client
dependency I personally hated that about
other CSS frameworks that they're like
oh we're a framework but you also have
to load a whole bunch of jQuery plugins
for some reason not everybody likes
jQuery like me so mm Pete Hagan's I
guess topcoats open source like
everything we do to patch you to license
everything's on github we're looking for
people to help us build it our audience
is the web community but that's
everybody that's building apps and this
is also a little bit of a fuzzy
consideration it's not something I think
you should take too seriously but we're
building top coat for people building
applications and in particular
applications that are installed things
like brackets and reflow but also
phonegap and when you're building an app
there's a slight UI design idioms that
are different than
you're building a website top coat will
work for websites but instead of making
websites the first consideration we want
to make the interaction and design
patterns for web apps which where we
think the web is going and it's maybe
not just the web is going this way but
operating systems are going this way
you've got Chrome OS windows blue I
guess they're calling it now it was like
Windows RT or Metro before but it's
essentially JavaScript Firefox OS ties
in and we won't talk about webos these
are all these are all web operating
systems so you've got google microsoft
mozilla samsung Intel and I guess LG all
betting on the web is the future for
operating systems so topcoats probably
got a good feature in those places and
in the rest of it we can deal with
phonegap so if you want to check out the
controls themselves we've done a really
kind of Ponte job but of showing this
stuff off but if you go to the top coat
IO domain we're going to do a new site
very soon you can get a preview of what
the different controls look like there's
not a lot of surprises here this is just
CSS and these are just like basic
controls this aesthetic is generated
these aren't things that you were
telling you you have to build it this
stuff looks very Adobe and that's
probably because it's coming out of
Adobe but the theming capability allows
you to change absolutely every attribute
of these controls I kind of mentioned
that there's some perceived competitors
I don't think they really are until they
get into well I say this all the time
too and people think it's but the the
principles of topcoat are around
performance modularity discreteness and
accessibility basically everything that
these things don't do we do so I don't
know if they are competitors there's a
whole bunch of stuff for top coat so its
CSS generally but we also have a bunch
of grunt based tooling you get generated
style guides which Christopher show you
sample apps starter apps we have a PSD
for prototyping we also have a whole
bunch of SVG icons which are pretty
sweet that came out of Adobe and two
fonts which will probably grow given the
type kit thing
so there's no j/s yet but that's not to
say there won't be jeaious at some point
in the future we're really not stoked on
the idea of creating a JavaScript
framework but there is some that
the web just does not do properly yet
like touch events that we may want to
polyfill for controls but we don't tell
you how to do templating we don't tell
you how to build your framework we're
not going to we're not going to touch
any of that because there's no right or
wrong way so top codes being released on
the same match already strained at
phonegap and Apache Cordova follow so
it's released every month not a release
every six months and it falls major
minor patch you can check out our
backlog on github it's actually kind of
sweet we using a thing called Hugh board
which I had never heard of but i like it
i know the wifis hosed oh wait no its
back sweep so I just scroll down a
little bit off top coat you can go check
out our backlog this Hugh board things
pretty sweet as you can see we've got a
lot coming down the pipeline and we have
a lot of ideas on what we'd like to see
happens if you want to check that out
please go ahead filing issues is
contributing yeah release train
empirical to see I driven you got that
platform support I originally was going
to put like a bunch of browsers with
their numbers on them but browsers
update every six weeks and I don't feel
like updating slides every six weeks so
whatever modern browsers you get it
there's three ways to use topcoat you
can use it the same ways bootstrap today
by including everything don't recommend
doing that for production there's an ala
carte way of building it right now which
will show you it's super easy uses a
package.json you can choose which
controls you want which aesthetic you
want and which platforms you want to
support and as a bonus you get a style
guide as you're building it oh and
theming steaming is kind of different
this is something that's totally up for
debate we agonized about baking themes
something off the each control
themselves but we're putting themes into
its own singular git repo right now for
the moment
and we don't know if this is completely
correct or not but essentially you would
fork top coat / theme there's a bunch of
variable files in here some of them are
kind of gross they're not bad to give
you an idea you would give it a theme
dash whatever and it will create that
theme for this one good example oh yeah
we're using stylus also we're not
totally locked into that but we think
it's you know better than some of the
alternatives and we wanted to be no D
about things yeah so you would just fork
this you'd modify the variables and
you'd have your own theme current status
it's we just did a point 3 release we're
going to do a point for probably any day
now people are building apps already
using top coat today it's only going to
get better in the future as we add more
more more controls there are some
concerns that remain so the first thing
people have been asking us if you go to
the top coat home page you'll see that
we're treating desktop and mobile is
separate which is making responsive
design people mad at us and I think it's
it's a valid thing to like strive for
responsive design but I also don't think
that it's something that has been fully
solved with the technology we have today
responsive design boils down to the idea
of media queries and match media and the
JavaScript side of things and when you
want to do it you have a whole bunch of
CSS and then you can you have to
download all that CSS and then you
basically conditionally will decide
which stuff you're going to show when
this is really inefficient especially as
we have tons and tons of devices out
there if you're downloading all the
desktop CSS to your phone on an edge
connection just a load a small subset of
it you're taking a huge network penalty
but you're also taking a big penalty to
the heap when it's trying to parse all
this CSS so we're treating these are
separate problems I think a lot of these
controls will actually will become
responsive as it were and they'll be all
in one thing but for the moment we're
not convinced and I don't think the
technology is completely there either so
we're going to again be empirical about
it and approach it discreetly we're
using stylus some people like that some
people don't but you're not using stylus
contributing to top coat is
different than consuming it you're
consuming CSS that's the abstraction
layer you're at if you don't like
stylist that's cool tell us what you do
I guess and there's complexity
trade-offs in our approach we have lots
of git repos which means that we have
lots of versions of things i think this
complexity is worth the trade-off when
you start architecting a larger
application but that's that's definitely
up for debate too there's definitely
risks so first thing that to address is
that we're not trying to build flex
again at Adobe in fact we want to create
a much larger community around the idea
of open web stuff and we want to fix the
performance characteristics we see built
in apps today this isn't a framework
code sizing quality is kind of the thing
that we're most concerned about so we
have to stay on top of ourselves with
that but that's what the CI
infrastructures for and for operation
with other JavaScript frameworks is also
a huge thing that we want to make sure
is is first class so we're talking to
the Ember guys we told the backbone guys
they don't care and the angular guys so
there's going to be bindings for all
these JavaScript frameworks so they
interoperate and our idea is that if you
know whatever way you build an app will
work with you I bring up revenue drivers
because people a store like well is it
Dobie just going to do this thing and
then abandon it and the answer is no
there is a big internal win for us to
have reused at Adobe but there's also a
larger win when we see our tooling start
adopting this stuff and treating it as a
first class citizen you could imagine
the benchmarking data we're doing could
become available in the tool like
brackets in the future which is a huge
opportunity so we should be shipping
point for I guess in the next day or
else I'm a liar and point five coming in
june and then july i think we're going
to ship one for phonegap day there's a
ton of stuff in our roadmap I won't go
through all of these because you can
read I'll just highlight one of them
it's called turbo mode we think we found
a way to make CSS even faster still if
you're curious about that ask me later
what what the hell is turbo mode and we
have all the common sort of community
touch points github is probably the best
place to go but topco do we want to see
the web be a first-class deb platform by
building apps that are fast by default
instead of one
is that are slow in order for us to do
that we need your help and you can find
out more at Topkapi oh we're going to
demo it for you now I guess you want to
use your machine or mine okay
Christopher's got the latest bits he's
going to build an app really quickly and
then I'll pull that down from github and
I'll build it into phonegap and then we
can go get pool beers
nice
okay let me just yell at me I've been
talked about I'm in the top coat
directory um yeah and so let's show show
you what we're doing here so i have this
package.json file and we're actually
thinking about moving the top coat part
out into its own Jason file let us know
what you think about that oh you didn't
mention that the Google mailing list we
should probably yeah we're going to
start posted we're going to be posting
all these ideas and considerations on
the Google mailing list so people can
tell us how down we are in chollas to
death we've seen other people so there's
like component and Bauer are having a
cat fight over who gets to own component
JSON and we didn't really want to get
involved and then we're like well
everyone has a package.json now we'll
just put it under a top coat global
seems like a fairly okay thing to do
because there's that file there already
we already have like license notice get
ignore package.json grunt file we didn't
really want to add another one
necessarily so well I don't know yeah I
mean and also we got burned pretty bad
when we switched from the adobe order to
taco org and Bauer can unregister us so
we actually couldn't push our bits up so
we had to go with this which I actually
am pretty happy with as Brian talked
about these are corresponding these
skins are corresponding to github repos
so let's just talk about / button if you
had your own button to be your username
/ button these numbers these version
numbers are actually the tag versions of
the components and of the github repo so
we actually have support for night least
by just removing the tag number and then
you can get a nightly version of the
component so if you're doing development
time you could actually see that so this
is the list of components I'm going to
build right so I just run grunt and my
five should work goes down pulls down
all those tag versions with zips
obviously if I have a nightly would just
do a shallow clone instead puts it into
the right place runs a compile step
using stylus and I've done the same kind
of stuff that you would want to write
like I've sequestered the brain damage
of compile into it
task so if we wasn't were to switch to a
like rework or something we could just
switch that one file and everything
would work the same fewer if you really
wanted to do sass like I saw someone
fork topcoat removed all the modularity
and started putting sass in as get sub
modules would have been much easier just
to change the compile task to use sass
instead of stylist and that's why I
built that way we totally want to work
with these like open package managers
and stuff but we think the space is like
immature and broken so we're just using
grunt because we're pretty sure you are
too but I'm like fully open to like
trying to figure out a better way to do
this there's that new initiative from
google that used to be called tool
kitchen with a polymer polymer so like I
think the features web components but I
don't think the future is here yet and
so we're just sticking to JavaScript and
CSS as the Ross for impossible until
such time as the tools are better right
so this is we're using style delco right
now for generated style guides give us
feedback on that we actually have
another version that looks more like our
designer generated style guides that we
can switch to but this tends to have all
the features that you could possibly
have rights of the kitchen sink of style
guide features so people wanted to vote
on which ones they wanted to keep it
basically will show you all of the
components that I had in that
package.json already compiled it with
use examples so you can just copy and
paste so you go down here you know lists
nav header nav bar and actually has a
working button as an example and then
you know we talked about responsive and
like this header is responsive if right
but it's not made in the responsive way
doesn't use media queries it's actually
just a percentage-based header you could
use it that way this is kind of a nice
whoa sorry I think like a super nice
feature because if you saw Nicole's
presentation if you don't have a living
style guide then you probably have a
static one and you end up with 50
buttons that look the same copy paste
CSS so our hope is that people use this
tool to build out their apps it'll jump
into this generated style guide and then
they will copy and paste but they'll be
copy and pasting from something more
canonical and managed right
so oh that's it so basically if you
follow the readme it just you just
include whichever version of the style
guide CSS CSS team that you want just
you thinking like CSS because it's just
CSS and then you just copy and paste
from from here the uses these guys and I
I encourage people to play with these
like you know leave something out of the
list or leave something out of the
header and see what it does we're
separating things like layout if you
look it's like layout and positioning
you know this is I have these really
dumb layout classes like quarter half
full but I'm totally intending people to
use their own grid system or their own
layout classes for the elements and then
I also want to see what people use so
that I can actually build those things
in or make it support those things
better we have our own grid system but I
don't want to impose that on anyone so
we separate all the concerns so I went
and did a really quick and dirty example
using topcoat and I just all I did was I
went in length of CSS and then copy and
pasted the styles and then I added
really minimal JavaScript just for the
click handler and added some we're going
to separate transitions too so we'll
have a whole set of transitions under
top coat that just use CSS animations
actually we're both super interested in
if you have opinions about this one we
don't really have an answer but is slide
left component may be right I'm not
totally sure and what I am sure of is
when you look into backbone apps very
often you will see a shitload of visual
display logic or will be like sliding
things left and right or whatever and I
don't know if your controller should
know that right like I think your
controller should know about the state
of the models that are around like it
should know that you know i'm showing
users right now but should it know that
the users came in from the bottom no no
if it should and that's kind of the nice
thing about CSS is very declarative and
you keep that presentation business out
of your controllers so talk to us about
that right so we're trying to separate
concerns in the way that we're
approaching people saying so I actually
got a bug an issue request saying hey
you should have a slide-out menu
component and I said to that I'm like
well the way that we're handling those
requests is we're actually to make
examples right we're going to make
examples in composing these different
patterns and then give you all the
pieces and you can compose
I figure you could come up with
something way more creative than the
slide menu if you had all the pieces and
you could put them together like legos
right so that's that I push this up to
github again it was just quick and dirty
this morning like trying to get this
working so that we could dental it no
all right so let's see if we can
phonegap it ya doin out here yeah I'll
swap with you so oh yeah i confuse me
hit you what's up
ok cool uh so I downloaded a fresh build
a phonegap 2.7 2.8 should be coming out
today Steve here is it coming out today
or what all right good enough I'm not
I'm not hating Steve so when you
download phonegap you get a Lib
directory and well inside of there
there's a bunch of mobile platforms in
the future we're going to have a CLI
tool it wraps all this up so you don't
have to look at these guts but you'll
always have these guts available to you
and I'm going to go iOS then create we
have these command line tools the normal
lines all the weird at different
platforms do and one of them is create
and so I'm going to create a project on
my desktop I'm going to call it I don't
know Jess calm whoa top coat I owed up
Brian Jess comp just call top coat oops
so that's going to generate a native
project on my desktop called jazz comp
top coat here it is right here this is
just an iOS project and it's got ww
folder so let's let's quickly build that
to make sure that I didn't break the
world
so we have these command line tools like
Cordova run which is consistent across
platforms creating projects logging
emulating building whatever so if you're
working inside of iOS you can just which
context to Android with with out too
much trouble so that should it worked
and it did there's an app that we built
that's exciting so I'm going to open
this directory up and I'm just going to
delete everything except for that
Cordova JS file and I think I pulled
down your uh oh okay I'm gonna jump onto
my desktop git clone I don't remember
it's like github / Krista I did it did
it got your name right okay so you
already had a that's fine yeah well
I don't know never seen it do that
before what's up of that oh the line
wrapping that's cool that's it's all
it's all of our splash screens it's our
overzealous designer 15 Meg splash
screen I wish I was joking I'm not it's
got a sweet gradient though so where is
that topcoat phonegap just give a copy
and paste that mess to desktop j/s off
top coat ww place all this stuff across
our fingers
we recompile did it I have to kill the
simulator first I'm also running the
android sdk on a mac air so that always
works out well let's try this again
there we go ah ah bad cash hold on all
right this is a native dev demo God's
combo of Awesome so sometimes you got to
go into Xcode and and the running joke
is that don't worry about Xcode it's
just like eclipse it's if it looks like
itunes and eid like a building clean
is that actually this might just
work
come on xcode get your together
it is launching
right oh wait whoa I went into an ipad I
guess yay there's our native mobile
operating on an iPad so I guess we could
improve this by doing this in a iOS
context let's just quickly do this
enough handset so you could media query
this up all you want we're not going to
tell you how to build your app because
people people that do suck there we go
um listen that was the Android one yeah
they have one hey you are you talking to
you buddy there we go Alex looks good
though right there you go and we don't
have an hour so we're not going to show
you android
so yeah top coat it's thing we need your
help check out top coat do tweet at us
and let us know the types of stuff
you're looking for for phonegap we're
hoping to start pre-loading with lots of
example apps so that building apps
across platforms that look good by
default and they're fast our thing
thanks and questions yes yeah
yeah we're into Bauer soon as they
closed a few bugs will totally do that
we've liked them and component and all
these different client-side package
managers are almost there they're just
not quite there in the particular case
for Bauer we did publish there and then
we changed repo names and they have a
bug where we can't change repo names and
so yeah yep
yeah well yeah it's open source now
telemetry is a little tricky to get at
today you have to do your own compile a
custom build of CEF which isn't as bad
as it sounds but at the future the idea
would be this tooling is fully automated
on an app per app level so that you as a
developer would get notified that hey
you just made slower when you
change something oh I should repeat your
question the question was are we going
to expose topcoats benchmarking
facilities to the public it already is
it's a top coat the github / top coat /
top coat dash server it's weird like I'm
umbilical to you so we're doing at a at
a component level right now but then
we're going to work on like you said at
am at a page like a whole app level as
well right we're just we just haven't
gotten to that part because we've only
been working on it for a couple months
any other questions oh yeah well so at
the moment we just give you CSS and oh
the question is we have desktop and we
have mobile and you know how what do we
recommend you know how do you know when
to use which we're right now just giving
you the CSS flat-out we're leaving it up
to you to decide how to architect your
app I'm hoping in the future like we're
going to be doing lots of experiments
around responsive style designs to to
see for ourselves for right now the
state where at is we're actually just
building a bunch of apps we don't want
to get to enterprise architect on this
and tell people that the right way
before we've actually you know used it
so that's our that's our approach yep
are we creating replacements for the
native like controls yep those are all
coming so we're taking big lists we
actually did a ton of design research
around what apps are using and what
types of controls they need and selects
and all that stuff is coming for sure
like really soon yeah the design
research is all available yeah actually
oh man pub like a plan it's it's under
top yeah yeah it's at 404 no I did he
really find it it's in there it's under
the there's also some in our wiki yeah
I'm actually the design research was
really interesting if you've got to if
you were lucky enough to get to go to
CSS comp we we had the design manager
walk through it all
dawn yeah recommendation is to know I
was really close oh we're just muttering
to ourselves right now there's been
absolutely no content in the last minute
don't worry just trying to find where
the design research is a kind of a
really awesome benefit of being at
adobe's that we have a lot of badass XD
people that really love nerding out on
this and so they did a ton of research
into how could we create something
that's visually clean easily style and
we'll come on come off as fast when it
gets implemented all that research is
open source to were like you said we're
redoing the website right now to make to
expose the research documentation as
well yeah any other questions oh no no
other questions oh yes Remy ah ok I'll
talk a little bit about sort so Remy's
asking what's turbo mode it's something
that we're looking at bringing in the
future it's an idea extracted from femo
us these guys created a crazy demo where
they have this amazing sphere that's
moving around like lightning speeds and
if you look at their source the way they
did this was by avoiding the render
pipeline in WebKit and the way they do
that is by setting style attribute on
every single element in the Dom using a
physics engine to programmatically
position everything in a 3d space using
a matrix-matrix transform so if it
sounds gross it is but it's also super
fast and so we think we can apply this
technique in the top coat to do like
really crazy transitions like super high
speeds it's only going to work in WebKit
but yeah that's what turbo mode will be
famous yeah wiki 40 49 typing on a match
killing me I was trying to show there's
a bunch of slides from eat top coat and
it's not working I'll put those up in a
way that you can't do a bit you can
actually step through there's some slide
there's some slides you can step through
and actually shows step by step of
research process alright thanks
everybody