hey guys I guess we all get started as
people coming to the room so this my
name is Andrew my name is things are
going wrong already great things I'm
Andrew Lonnie and this this talks will
hang over that Jess I apologize to
Jonathan Julian who presented on the
with the same title last year I thought
it was a great title so I took it about
me I work at my Toby in vancouver bc i
have a humorous job title that
compensates for my poor salary we are we
make a pro we work on a project for
phonegap for building native mobile
applications with web technologies and i
personally work on a web service called
phonegap build that does the the
phonegap stuff in the cloud but this
talk is not going to be about about
phonegap so if you're not sure if you
want to stay for this talk then here's
the summary is kind of about code called
e city code is a social problem not a
technical one and there aren't solid
solutions to that there are just
heuristics about about how we can deal
with that this isn't as I say this is
not going to be a technical talk and if
you want to go get some coffee i would
not be offended by that yeah sure that
no one in the room gets that joke
Thanks right cool so hangovers hopefully
you all came prepared and brought your
own there's a pretty great book called
everyday drinking which is you can guess
what the subject is and it's that's a
good article in there about hangovers
and the rider Kingsley a mess he
distinguishes between a physical
hangover so when you have a headache or
your whole body aches and a metaphysical
hangover he describes a metaphysical
hangover as an ineffable compound of
depression sadness anxiety self-hatred
sense of failure and fear for the future
now why would I mention this oh yeah
we're at ojo circumference so it's
possible that some of us have written
all have dealt with other people's code
that would give us a metaphysical
hangover or this metaphor is getting
really stretched at this point anyway
I'll try and make a case I think
javascript is a bit of a self-loathing
language and I guess we'll see how well
I goes the next 15 minutes this is
another dumb joke but a if you guys all
know around doll he had this tweet on
the first night of Jess come for about
prom and rains really smart so i'm going
to assume this was like really
insightful so I guess chase conf is like
prom for JavaScript developers it
doesn't really work but
so we should all maybe consider runs
tweet for a moment
now move on cool so jess conf is is
pretty fun and what I like about Joe's
company you kind of get a vacation from
application code you see obviously not
this presentation but you see good
presentations which have you know all
these sexy new libraries and open source
projects and frameworks and if you're
like me you think it sounds great I
can't wait to hack on this I'm going to
I'm going to build a new app using
Batman or Joe or any of the binary AP is
David planning and talked about you
think yeah i wanna i want to go home and
get them and that's great because all
these presentations are new code bases
and new code bases are great because
they're they don't have much in them so
new code bases i think are a bit like
robert smith during the 1980s they're
very slick they're stylish the sleek
their exciting there sexy and you really
want to keep writing code because it's
such a such a fun time and that's the
feeling I get from attending j/s conf
then after Jess conf you are you go back
to work and you return to your
application and it's the same shitty
code you've been working on for months
at a time and all through the code base
there are two do comments and fix meas
and there's some crafty code you don't
really want to fix because your project
manager is saying you've got to
implement a new feature and you don't
wanna go behind deadlines so blah blah
blah I think this is the worst slide in
the history of juice conf I realize
that's a bold claim but um I think it
stands up to that so an old code base is
more like Robert Smith in this decade
it's kind of flabby disheveled
unmaintained bull embarrassing and you
wouldn't want to work with it or be
anywhere nearer
so we're back to the metaphysical
hangover depression sadness anxiety
self-hatred sense of failure and fear
for the future there's a picture of a
man looking sad so I've talked about
generalities so I think maybe if I chose
an actual bad code that i don't like
from a project that i work on it it kind
of shows the sort of thing that people
are a bit too lazy to fix because
they're all kind of dependencies in the
projects and and you don't to fix it so
this is probably the worst well the next
slide is the worst one but this is the
second worst function in phonegap iphone
and it's called get function name it
takes a function and it returns the name
of the function there's John David
Dalton the audience and he can tell you
all the things that are incorrect about
this code as well as it being ugly and
I'm maintainable but essentially if I'm
correct it'll return them if there's a
name properly it will turn the name if
it's anonymous function expression it
will call this an on to name funk
function so this is what this looks like
we have an object called a
non-functioning we have a variable
called a non funk map next ID and then
we have this function a non turn named
funk you guys can stop me at any point
it create it uses this a non funk map
next ID variable to create a unique
identifier for the function and then it
creates a new function which is it
applies itself to the original function
and then it deletes itself from the map
of functions and then it returns that
identifier so this is some gross stuff
we've done to try and manage callbacks
coming back from native code into
JavaScript and
it doesn't work in all cases you kind of
have to have a globally scoped function
or you end up with this weird anon funk
man thing but at the same time we've
we'd like to get a 1 point 0 release out
so we're working on implementing new
api's and we don't wanna go and fix that
and that's kind of the the problem with
old code bases sorry about so that code
was pretty horrible so here's a picture
of a man surfing the web so here's
another tangent javascript is kind of a
good cop bad cop language so in terms of
the language itself you have a great
deal of expressiveness in the syntax and
semantics and there's a wide range of
freedom and expression you can
accomplish and if any of you guys saw
Andrew DuPont's talk yesterday he gave a
good example of extending built-ins
which is really nice unfortunately you
have the bad cop which is the JavaScript
environment and we have all these best
practices and these recommendations for
performance and compatibility and memory
usage and code sides that mean that all
the time you can't use all the newest ap
is or the newest features of the
language so in jazz community the good
cop bad cop is basically Brendan Eich
and Douglas Crockford Brendan tells us
about the cool new language features
that we can all do to improve the
expressiveness and the beauty of our
code and then we have bad cop Crockfords
who tells us that our our codes not very
good so we should stop trying to be so
clever and we should be worried about
security so I think there's a technical
solution to this problem there's not a
kind of constant time thing you can do
to fix code called it something you have
to follow flow every day and try and
make sure things get better each time
it's a bit like the old joke about how
do you lose weight without changing your
diet or doing any exercise and the
answer is you get a
you get a tape one which works which
does help you lose weight but it may
cause problems later later on the thing
and the thing with these heuristics is
that there's an obvious question and the
answers are quite well known instantly I
think this image is copyright
shutterstock it seemed like a good idea
four o'clock in the morning I don't know
so how can you avoid bad code well the
trouble with this is it's kind of like
the diet example or the losing weight
example actually what you should do is
really obvious and you don't need
someone like me to tell you you should
write tests you should write docs you
shouldn't Tran be too clever you
shouldn't be a you shouldn't code like
an asshole but unfortunately because we
have all these external pressures of
whether it's deadlines or the kind of
inertia of these big project projects we
don't always follow them so all I can
say is that too to improve the quality
of your code it's really just about
discipline and dedication and rather
than any kind of technique so that was