good morning who's ready to talk about
feelings I'm just kidding actually I'm
not we're totally gonna talk about
feelings right now so as you know my
name is Jen and I'm here to talk to you
about emotional safety so let's start
doing that so what is emotional safety
well I think that's a terrible question
I mean to ask that question presupposes
that in a room of maybe the smartest
most talented technologists gathered at
this very moment that they don't
understand why the way a person feels
wouldn't be important while they're at
work but the way a person feels doesn't
have any sort of impact on their work
could that be true
well statistics tell us a story
according to the World Health
Organization in 2012 so two years ago
the leading causes of death in high to
upper middle income countries so think
like here in the US and in the EU the
leading causes of death were heart
disease stroke and chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease or COPD so that's
things like chronic bronchitis or
emphysema in 2012 265 thousand people
died from heart attacks or heart disease
221 thousand people died from strokes
and 81 thousand people died from
the OPD contributing factors to most of
these preventable conditions were things
like high blood pressure high
cholesterol diabetes conditions in which
stress can be a major contributor and in
2012 over half a million people lost
their lives because of it and that might
not seem like a lot of people but think
about it in this way that's the same as
nearly everyone in the city of Portland
dying within a year just one year how
can this be you're asking yourself right
now surely the stress that those people
experience in their jobs is not the one
that I experienced in mine they must be
like crazy
Oprah levels of busy and overwhelmed and
stressed out to the complete max that
could be but I think it's far more
likely that the stresses they are
experiencing are the same that are now
considered to be normal work stress
experiences explain this to me Jen
you're saying well okay that's totally
why I'm here so welcome to the polyvagal
theory don't worry it's a quick trip oh
wait a second
this is gonna make it more official oh
no I knew this was gonna happen okay
feeling official let's take a look Oh
gross
oh so basically in the polyvagal system
your autonomous nervous system or I'm
gonna call it the ANS because I totally
love abbrevs
it's the system that's taking in all of
the stimulus that you're experiencing
right now it controls a lot of the
things that you're doing automatically
get it autonomic automatic okay so it's
controlling the things you're doing
automatically like breathing or blinking
without you even thinking and this
involuntary support system is a
wonderful feature of the human body
however one of its central bosses is
this vagus nerve that's part of your
brainstem like I know it's gross and
it's connected to all of your crucial
inner element elem inner elements like
your heart and respiratory and
gastrointestinal tracts all those guys
the polyvagal theory suggests that the
vagus nerve triggers these crucial
systems in three different ways
via information gleaned by your ANS
without your control or your knowing
you've all heard a fight-or-flight
before right those survival type
instincts well your ANS is constantly
scanning your environment all around you
to determine what your current mode of
survival should be there are three modes
of survival safety danger and too late
basically just kidding the last one is
life throw you guys can see that so
let's talk about safety mode when your
nervous system determines that you are
safe you are operating at your body's
optimum mental and emotional levels your
ANS goes into rest and digest mode which
basically means that it's operating at
its full capacity so that you don't have
to consciously think about how on all of
your systems are they just are this is
the level that you want to be at to do
your best work all of your work danger
mode it's not really as cool as it
sounds when you're exposed to danger
unconsciously your body goes into
hyperdrive your heart rate increases
your ANS jumps into action and it limits
the rest of your systems ability in
order to keenly focus on the danger and
to do this it floods your system with
norepinephrine which is a fun hormone
that causes vigilant concentration
additionally in danger mode you're more
prone to unexpected bouts of rage or
panic and this is the fight or flight of
the fight-or-flight impulse and it's all
happening subconsciously but your body
is preparing you for one of those two
outcomes and last life threat mode when
your ANS perceives a life threat it
shuts everything down your heartrate
actually decreases your muscles tense
and ready for action
that will most likely never come does
anybody hear experienced back or neck
pain from being stressed at work that's
the result of tension that never gets
discharged in life threat mode you can't
hear reason this is the freeze mode of
fight flight or freeze and based on the
information that the ANS is giving to
the vagus nerve your body is constantly
but unconsciously occupying one of those
three modes for example my body is
currently in danger mode although I can
be hyperbolic so it feels like life
threat mode right now
I'm like super close to shutting down so
why is any of this important well with
the knowledge of that mini biology
lesson how is it not which mode do you
think you're operating in right now what
about when you have an argument with
someone what mode does that look like
which mode are you operating in when you
get critical and really hard to hear but
absolutely necessary feedback which mode
are you operating in when you're in a
conflict about a really hard but
important decision recognizing what mode
you've been operating in is crucial
because spending a prolonged length of
time in danger mode or life threat mode
has serious physical and mental health
consequences so here's a list of some of
them and looking at that you're probably
thinking well those are some normal
reactions to stress Jen there's more
well things got a little bit worse
are you done identifying with any of
those when you think about work it's not
good
prolonged stress can even lead to drug
or alcohol abuse withdrawal from social
situations or most disturbingly in my
opinion the chronic suppression of your
immune system the very thing that's
intact to keep you safe protect your
body from harm your body will start to
suppress that this is important your
body craves safety this is not about me
being a woman or being in touch with my
feelings more than you are this is
biological and it is a fact that we are
killing ourselves with stress if safety
first is a thing you ever heard and not
it along to or believed this is
important to quote our intern Heather on
her first day at an yet happy smart
people are productive smart people you
cannot deny the existence or the
importance of your feelings and the
impact they have on your whole being
that's the person that you take to work
every day to do so as childish and
ignorant and it doesn't even make sense
who would even do that anyway oh that's
me but okay so I only did that for like
the first twenty nine years of my life
so not that long the difference between
the person that I was for those 29 years
and the person that I've worked so hard
to become over the last two
that I've come to truly believe that
everyone has value and everyone deserves
respect
because if I believe that I have value
and that I deserve respect I absolutely
have to believe that of the people
around me for it to be true about myself
people are the value added to everything
that you do you just have to be able to
see that and yet we say people first and
if you're lucky enough the types of
products and projects that you're
working on those will change but the
people that you work on those projects
and products with the clients that you
work with they might change too but they
might not regardless
people don't ever just go away I hate to
break it to you but you're actually
surrounded by people right now they're
all around you and they're all around
you and you're at work and at home and
people are they're kind of here to stay
and I think that emotional safety is
important because it's creating a space
for people to be safe to feel safe to be
people which I know that everyone here
is really cool but we are all we're all
people here still if you forgot every
person on your team actually every
person that you come into contact with
has an entire universe of contributions
just waiting inside of them think about
that how many universes are in this room
or on your team
but people will always be afraid to let
that out to take those steps if they
feel like they don't matter because they
don't feel safe so you're asking
yourself how can I have this emotional
safety thing now well how can you
achieve it it it can't be achieved so
that's the end of my talk thank you very
much I'm totally kidding emotional
safety can be something that is
respected it can be something that's
prioritized that's pointed to that's
discussed but I have to be clear that
emotional safety is not a destination
creating a safe place for your people to
be people it has to be a fluid thing
because I mean I'm not even going to
stand up here and and try to tell you
how fast things change especially people
I do have some advice for starting to
create a safer environment if you're
interested in that it's also worth
pointing out that emotional safety is
the responsibility of every single
person I'll get into this more in a
minute but I really want to emphasize
that it's truly a personal
responsibility but I think more
importantly leaders and I know you're
here you've taken up the mantle of
leading people like it or not creating
emotional safety is your responsibility
people right now they could be sitting
at the same table as you they're looking
to you to show them that they can be
safe with you they just need to see it
to believe it
don't keep them waiting you will not
regret it
it will improve the health of your team
tenfold I can guarantee it
I have seen it I have lived it I know
that there are many of you who didn't
set out to be leaders and hearing this
just adds to the list of things that are
already frustrating you I get
discouraged too quite easily when I
discover the limits of my understanding
about what it means for me to lead if
you are a people first person if you
find yourself shying away from leading
because of the challenges it presents
because of so many unanswered questions
than we need you I'm a person who cares
about other people but I need
encouragement to keep leading if you
feel like you need encouragement too or
you feel like you have some to offer
please check this out my team at Andy
and I are going to very soon announce a
new endeavor called leadership II it's
early and I can't say much more than
what I've already said now but if these
feelings I'm describing resonate with
you then we really need you so go to
leadership be calm to check that out and
if you're not a leader or you work alone
I think emotional safety is still worth
paying attention to because it will
improve the quality of your
relationships working or otherwise and
the quality of your life and it's
something you should expect from your
leaders so how to do this I'll tell you
guys where I started first and foremost
figuring out a way to understand and
identify your emotions is crucial from
what I hear it's like learning a
programming language I don't know any of
them what I did to start educating
myself was read I wanted to logically
understand these emotion things and
figure out what that meant for me a book
that I read that helped change my life
was called positive intelligence by
Sherrod she mean after that I started
going to counseling and who I said a
counseling stigma word but I think the
stigma of the girl that was feeling like
a crazy person every day at work and
couldn't manage your emotions and didn't
have the tools or the ability to have a
dialogue about what was going on I think
that's a way where stigma
than the person that passionately goes
after improving their mental health in
their situation so I'm comfortable with
that stigma and I think one of the most
important things you can do to educate
yourself is to start practicing having
uncomfortable conversations and I don't
mean that you're having conversations
with the intent to make someone feel
uncomfortable but emotional safety is
about being able to talk to people about
your emotions and if you don't know how
to do that you need to start practicing
having those conversations and I've done
that with my team trust was built as a
result of that so I would encourage you
to look into that reactions when I talk
about emotional safety people usually
feel like it will make the workplace
murky and that's absolutely false so
much of learning about mental health is
understanding the absolute necessity for
boundaries and learning to identify your
personal boundaries is key water
boundaries well I actually can't tell
you that because everybody is are
different but I can lead you in the
direction of a book by Henry cloud
called boundaries and this dude he knows
stuff so if you take one thing away from
this talk let it be the mention of this
book because this book will definitely
help you clarify but I'll give you a
couple of my boundaries that I've set
for an example the first one is that I
don't ever talk about anything related
to a sexual nature at work there's just
too much there that can offend people
and it's never ever never ever never
never never never ever worth it
another hard boundary that I've had to
set for myself is that if I'm leading a
group of my teammates I won't vent about
one of them to anybody else in that
group
and it can be hard to do I have learned
this by screwing it up so I know now
it's a valuable thing I've
I've set that boundary the last thing I
would suggest is learning to move toward
conflict and not in a way that's
aggressive or that you are wanting to
thrive off of conflict but moving toward
it with the intention to resolve the
intention to solve the problem and this
is maybe the hardest thing in the world
to do for me at least because it
requires putting your personal things
aside not being triggered by the
circumstances of the conflict
it requires learning to manage your
emotions recognizing what survival mode
you're in being able to take all of that
into account and be able to productively
and proactively work through the problem
that the conflict presents so obviously
there needs to be a plug for non-violent
communication here I added the end this
morning it said nonviolent communication
so dr. Marshall Rosenberg wrote this
wonderful book which essentially gives
you insight into conflict and a
framework for how to begin to
productively engage conflict and working
through it so I definitely recommend
checking the book but I want to give you
that framework as well so this is the
structure which is aimed at giving
people a template to express both their
feelings and their needs in a productive
way so I'll give you an example when I
see you take all of the credit for that
site I feel hurt because I worked on
that too and I need to feel like my can
my contribution was valued so can we
talk about this would be one way to
start having a conversation
good question I can tell you why I care
about this that is Mila and she is very
proud of her muscles and I want her to
be strong especially in all of the ways
that I am weak
I've been trying to demonstrate
principles and tools that I've been
learning to my five-year-old so that by
the time she is 29 she doesn't have to
do all the heavy lifting that I'm doing
now it will already be ingrained in her
and she'll be like a million light years
ahead of where I am in this moment I'll
be learning from her when she's my age
but I believe just as importantly
gaining a perspective on emotional
safety teaches you empathy emotional
researchers generally define empathy is
the ability to sense other people's
emotions coupled with the ability to
imagine what someone else must be
thinking or feeling
so you see empathy is different from
sympathy in that you don't pity the
other person for their circumstances but
instead you take on their circumstances
put yourself in their place and truly
try to navigate their thoughts and
feelings empathy is hard work
it requires emotional endurance it
requires you to do the work of gaining
additional perspectives so I'll tell you
a story about empathy it's a hard one to
tell too recently I was in a situation
where a male teammate disagreed with a
decision that I had made and suggested
that my tone regarding the situation
needed to be addressed my tone
I was pissed
I was so instantly pissed off like a lot
a lot of being pissed off I felt that if
the same argument had been had between
two men that there would be absolutely
no way that tone would be brought into
that conversation at all
I stood about this for two days I wanted
to summon the fury of a thousand Jen's
and just write this guy off as being
small-minded and sexist and I just
didn't want to deal with him but for all
of the angry things that I wanted I knew
something had to happen I had a hard
time seeing blight begrudgingly I knew
that somewhere in the back of me there
was this tiny quiet voice from Cascadia
j/s saying something about personal
growth and I'm not sure what that was it
was really hard to hear over the anger
fortunately I had the support of others
on my team to help me through the
decisions that lay before me because I
could take the path that led to more
conflict and engendered arguments and
indulge those triggers or I could engage
in problem-solving and see that action
for what it was and try to look at the
problem from a different perspective and
it was hard it didn't come to me
immediately or it never came to me on my
own I had to ask for help I brought
another person in a neutral third party
to mediate a face-to-face meeting with
my other teammate and it was super
uncomfortable I had a stomach ache that
whole morning but out of that meeting
came wonderful things we were both able
to hear each other and get the context
of where the other person was coming
from
and it's worth noting that our notorious
exchange took place over two over
instant-message so it's fair to say that
we were both reading way different
things than the other person had been
typing we both apologize and with the
tension nearly evaporating I was able to
commit to helping this man this other
person in the situation my teammate
improve so that we could achieve our
shared goal together and not find
ourselves in the situation again only
with empathy were we both able to look
at the situation and recognize that what
was needed wasn't damning that other
person but committing that we can both
do better I chose the path of emotional
safety not just for me but for both of
us I'm saying this because the person
involved is my collaborator on a project
that I am leading which is why I feel I
have a greater responsibility for his
emotional safety and why I'm holding
myself to this standard and at this
point in the story I want to tell you
that we lived happily ever after and the
project was great and we continued to
collaborate evenly and it was awesome
but the truth is that immediately as in
a week later I turned around and screwed
it all up another situation happened
between us that was a thing that we had
spoke about in that meeting happened and
it just it pissed me off again and this
time absolutely zero emotional Safety's
then came to me I got so angry I just
said screw it and I indulge my triggers
and I acted passively aggressive
Liat towards my teammate and just fail
wailed everywhere all over the place for
a week and all of this was directed at a
guy I had committed to teaming up with
say a week ago to do better fortunately
I have trusted teammates who reminded me
of my commitment who kept me accountable
to my standards and forced me to have a
face-to-face with this teammate and it
was horrible but you know what I did I
mean I cried I cried a lot I knew I
failed I failed him I failed you
I felt like emotional safety is too hard
and how can I even be all about this if
I can't keep myself together over one
conflict how am i any different from
anyone else but in that meeting I owned
my failures and I owned my fears and my
hopes I was able to admit to all of the
people in that meeting my failure and I
apologized because I think if there's
anything that makes it makes me
different it's that I do care and I do
want to get this right emotional safety
is really hard and I'm not here to tell
you that it's not you won't always get
it right and you definitely won't be
able to do that alone emotional safety
is a personal responsibility that can be
reinforced by good leaders so yes I
truly believe empathy is a quality every
person can be taught that will improve
the quality of their life significantly
it'll improve the quality of their
interactions the quality of their
conversations I know it will improve the
quality of their conflicts and their
relationships I'm just gonna say this I
haven't said it before but it's
important feelings are important to me
no one deserves to feel like crap
and we all have we all know how that
feels
our bodies our bodies unconsciously
crave safety everyone wants to feel good
and I believe that everyone wants to do
good statistics tell us a story but I
think we can start a better one