so guten tag we get we get so very
speaks torch that's quite many I can't
actually fake a presentation in in
German so I was hoping for fewer hands
and anyway what are we talking about
here today is about well we're
JavaScript comes from and how it works
generally and how you can use it for
pretty interesting stuff and what I
won't be covering is for implementations
in browsers or the Dom or anything other
it's just annoying so I'll just talk
about nice things and in the beginning
we basically as a web developer had
nothing when we're developing web pages
I was only stale great web pages and if
we're really fancy we had some kind of
line going down there in the middle two
separate content and that was it and
then this wonderful man came along by
the name of Brendan I can brandon had a
vision to to make well the content a bit
more alive on the web and the way I see
Brendan to me brendan is yoda brendan is
the master that hopefully I don't know
hopefully lives somewhere out in the
woods and just telling how the force
should work so what is javascript really
it's something Brendan came up with in
1995 and at the end of 95 in beta
Netscape to and first version of
JavaScript slow so alive and well first
was called mocha and live script but
eventually got the name javascript and I
think in august/september of 1996
Microsoft had reverse-engineer
JavaScript and turned it into a script
and where we see JavaScript array is
pretty much everywhere on the web like
you know it
counting characters or small reply
whatever I just like this image because
it seems very cute at first but then if
you look at it it seems like something
you would pay extra for in Bangkok or
Berlin for that matter and we also have
it in more interesting applications like
well gmail I think email is probably the
biggest one that have just shown the
power of JavaScript and to have two
applications on the web so when I was
doing my my research before this talk I
just for fun I searched for JavaScript
and the first hit on google is Java
which is a bit depressing after well 14
years something from 13 and the problem
is there that JavaScript doesn't really
have anything to do with Java and syntax
wise sure I mean we have to call the
races semicolon to that and that's
pretty much it so we're trying to get
rid of that and just move on so and
where we are today is one I think it's
just exploded in the last few years that
JavaScript has become one of the world's
most popular programming languages and
with web browser free have an
interpreter and every machine that can
just run JavaScript and pretty much
everywhere now in our cell phones and
devices and all that there's also some
standard sizes standard sizing going on
with activist crypt which is a work in
progress right now but what's good about
it is that it's being realistic so it's
based on what works now and kind of
bailed on top of that exactly like with
html5 look at what works in browsers now
when building it they said I'm having
some something that would be perfect in
theory but would take about 20 years to
implement in practice also what's very
exciting for me is that I can write the
same code and it just gets faster and
faster because web browsers have sort of
a little JavaScript engine war
going on with Safari and then Google and
Firefox and opera doing a good bit there
too well as well no one of them is a bit
slow otherwise but at least I have some
indication that Microsoft are really
trying about improving performance and
taking some really interesting measures
to make it better as well I just hope
they live up to it another person that I
have to mention we talked about
javascript is if brendan eich is the
godfather or the Yoda of JavaScript
Douglas Crockford has come up with lots
of interesting techniques and ideas how
to use it and how to implement better
and better practices and how to find the
good part in JavaScript so if if Ben is
sorry Douglas is Ben obi-wan Kenobi for
me and some of the things I won't really
go into detail with him but he's behind
Jason or as he humbly would same cells
that he only wrote the spec but the
approach was already there he's also
behind jslint for validating JavaScript
syntax and find out the best way to
write JavaScript to avoid problems and
to work together in teams and similar
and also something like Jas Mann for
just minifying the other script file so
don't weigh as much killed by twice so
it gets faster load them in a web page
so usually when I give presentations I
would like to have a theme so the theme
today is going to be Ben Affleck and the
code would pretty much cover band in his
life I would say so if you start startup
very easy how many here thing okay this
sounds offensive but how many here think
they know JavaScript okay so that was
just scary I think everyone in actually
knows java script so I'll go pretty fast
here in the beginning and I'll kind of
slow down and if it goes weird just way
or won't leave the basics of java script
is well as basic as it gets we can just
define the variable that's it you just
have a VAR keyword a name for it then it
equals a value and the same goes for
functions that's pretty much it we have
a function we have a name and just the
content of the function I know well
worth the money so far probably learning
a lot right now but when it starts to
get interesting is when we talk about
conditionals and we have four types and
conditionals in JavaScript you have if
statements which statements we also have
shortened assignments and ternary
operators and then they're pretty close
to each other and shortened assignment
is basically for us cool developers who
want to do one liners or actually
readable as well is as you see here if
we send in the parameter with Liv Tyler
if that is equals true the value will be
true for the variable lines here we just
have the or in the middle so it goes to
fall so you can just assign something
online it's pretty close to the ternary
operators which is just a small if case
basically so you have within the party
sis you have a value to sorry and
if it equals true that value comes
through otherwise the other things
happen and that's with any other
language we have the one equal sign to
assign the value regular assignment and
two equal science is to check equality
but javascript also has this funky
syntax with three equal signs which
usually mess people up and the reaction
is usually I haven't seen this anywhere
else you know screw it i'll use the two
but it actually makes a difference in
practice and you know one is just
assignment as you see here but the thing
here with equality with two equal signs
is that the number 5 equals the string 5
and that's because javascript is trying
to be nice and kind of figure out what
you actually meant
comparative values so to cover up for
something like that instead you want to
use three equal signs because the three
equal signs will not only compare the
value it will also compare the type of
what you're comparing so both of them
have to be a number or a string to be
true and as with any language javascript
is based on short circuit logic which
means that you don't analysis it all the
time when I work as a consultant than
people are nest about 15 if closest and
it's 400 lines and code you don't need
to do that it just evaluate the first
value and if it doesn't become true it
won't go on in or and similar so as you
see in the last line here you can just
check if the object actually exists
first and if true it goes on you can
check the property without throwing an
error otherwise it'd just be false and
what I was talking about here with the
double and triple equal signs is
something referenced as type coercion
and what type coercion does is is the
magic of trying to help you but just
messing things up for you basically
which is one of the four parts of
JavaScript and as you saw five number
equals five the string and also you
should try to add a string together with
numbers it will become a string because
the string will win in that case so to
cover up for something like that if you
know that the values might be of
different types you don't really want to
rely and you have a script and just hope
it goes well so instead you can use the
parseint method if you actually want the
number and complement it with equal
signs and such another thing that well
it's still a bit scary to me actually
and that is that a number of different
values all equal false or something at
least close to false if I'm trying to
check them with if or something similar
so no undefined 0 false actually an
empty string as well the name of the
string is the same as the building of
false if I try to check the value of it
so all of this code all these different
values when I checking them will not go
through when they will stop the
execution and in JavaScript we have
basically five different data types we
have strings numbers bullion's we have
the interesting value undefined but
beside that everything else is an object
the object is the mother of everything
and JavaScript and different types of
objects are functions arrays data object
reg legs etc and to complement that like
we had an empty string that would equal
false if you want to check the type offf
instead just to see the actual well type
that gets sent in and if it's all right
type and then you can check the value
and it just complements that the
different object types in Java Script we
have strings numbers Foley and etc so if
you look at that in code if a variable
that doesn't have a value yet it will be
undefined a string will naturally be a
string a number will be a number and
also a function will also be a function
I think this is probably good advice as
well to always have a number one go-to
guy if you have a dead hooker in your
hotel room
but we kind of get tricked as if you
have a JavaScript object just an empty
curly braces here you check type of that
will be an object but if you like type
of for an array it will also say object
which is a bit scary because then you
have no idea it doesn't really help it
is more like the null is null error
messages in internet explorer so what
you can do is use something called
instance of the complement type of and
there you can check if it's an instance
of an actual core object in JavaScript
so you have a variable and you have the
object and that's not an instance of an
array but array is an instance of the
module array that exists and there also
a number of different types of functions
you have the regular procedural
functions which is just a function you
can also assign functions directly to a
variable and then just use that variable
name as the new name of the function we
can have anonymous function for those
that don't even deserve a name we're
just going to use them for short amount
of time or just write a little code we
just give it into event or another value
and that's pretty much it but where it
gets a bit interesting is where you have
the self invoking functions that we just
call themselves right away so as we see
here you have a cup of apple so a couple
of parentheses at the end which makes
the function run right away
and when I talk to people that they work
with C++ or Java or similar and they
work with method overloading and
different versions of doing something
that doesn't really exist in JavaScript
so if you have a function you can
actually just omit any argument you want
or you can add some more that the
function doesn't actually expect as well
and what we have instead of overloading
is the arguments collection in
JavaScript so if we have a regular
function here and it's expecting three
values and the ABC the first one will
work because it gets the three well is
it once but last one would just return
the nun which means not a number and to
cover up for that we have the arguments
collection that you can iterate over and
I just want to point out that it's not
an actual array it's a collection so you
can loop through all these values but
you can't use array methods like push or
concat or similar so instead if we had
the concat function here what we can do
is that within every function in
JavaScript you don't need to declare it
at all you have something called
arguments and that will be all the
parameters that get sent in no matter if
it's 115 or 500 well I haven't actually
maxed it out but at least what I think
and then you can send in any values and
kind of use this approach instead and
within the function do you're
overloading instead of having different
sets of the same function
and if you want to construct objects in
JavaScript at Google way that you see it
in every well proper language as some
people see it you have a band object
here and use this keyword to assign
properties to it this dot name is a spam
and got an Oscar etc and at the bottom
here I just create an instance of that
object and then I check the value of a
property of that instance but if you
want of the cool kids that syntax isn't
that really the one that goes you want
to use the object literal instead where
the idea is just a shorter syntax
bicycle that you have the curly braces
instead and we should note also in here
so if you don't have the equal signs for
assigning properties you have the colon
and you don't have a semicolon at the
end of each shrine each line just have
the comma sign but you don't have it
after the last one but if you want to
work with that object it's the same way
you just have the instance name and
check a property on it
and as with any code everywhere there
are also different schools how you want
to assign a value or read the value
personally I prefer the dot notation
that bound the dot arms here but what's
pretty good about the other one here is
that you can a dynamic value sent in so
instead of having lots of lots of lines
checking different properties in a
function and you can just send in a
variable here instead of arms and first
I can check the arms and legs etc in
there and just have one line of code for
it what's also a bit funny about
javascript is that you can extend or
change anything about JavaScript and you
can change anything about core java
script when you run it in a web browser
and just override how JavaScript thought
it would work so if i have an object
error i can have an integral as the
property name like 1972 or a string or i
can actually have a boolean as a
property on an object and i can also do
this to the native objects in JavaScript
like with a string object or the array
object or reggae club yet and you know
just for fun I can have a number here
that has a new value and maybe this just
seems like a geeky thing so yeah I can
break something or make something weird
but where it becomes very useful is that
if you have different web browsers not
dropping any names some of them aren't
as competent as others so if they have
something faulty or not good enough in
their JavaScript implementation I can
override it myself so we had in a web
browser was around for quite a long time
it didn't support the push method on
array objects so instead they can just
write the code and actually implement
the push method on my own then I can use
to push method in all my code and just
kind of fix JavaScript and the web
browser so total freedom
and when we have an object here to check
values it's not like an array that can
iterate over so instead you can just use
a for loop that goes through each item
in that object and just beads out the
name of that property and the value of
that property and as you saw before with
the empty string or undefined or similar
that just equals false if you want to be
sure that that doesn't happen you can
instead use the syntax here to check if
here we're here is the name of the
property and the good movie object
exists and it could be an empty string
then and this if Clause would still
equal true it's just a way to make sure
that it rotor is there and not just
checking it's value
in JavaScript we do something called
prototype based inheritance instead of
classified as we have in virtually any
other language out there and the
interesting thing about prototype it
just shakes it instance and just works
its way up through everything it has
inherited so far so if we start by
creating a simple objectivity super
object if you will called being it has a
property and you just use the prototype
syntax as the being bailed prototype to
assign a method to all instances of the
being object that will just return the
value hello so if you remember this
please we create the band object here
and then we say that the band object is
a prototype of the being object that
means that the band object here will
have everything that the being object
has and more you can override anything
that has been inherited from the being
object if you want to as well and it
also has a method here just to say
something so if we create an instance of
the band now you can always create an
instance by using the new keyword and
then you run the method on the band
object and we'll just return to the
value I feel like famous wasted on me
that's all fine but then if you run the
grid method the greet method doesn't
actually exist on the band object it
came from the being object should have a
JavaScript works is that I first check
the band instance like do does this
specific instance have a great method
now okay just a prototype fell off sorry
for all been objects have it no it goes
up to the being prototype all right
there's a great method fine let's just
execute it down and if the being our
vehicle don't have it either it goes up
to the object because as I said before
object is on the top of it all
everything goes up to object
there are a number of people way smarter
than I am that have tried to implement
it well syntax for use in class based in
heritage in JavaScript so you can write
code the same way and just make sure to
cover up for where javascript doesn't
actually work that way I think the first
example here is done my John Resig who's
actually here somewhere and the other
one is by Dean Edwards who so JavaScript
God and the last one is from the
prototype JavaScript library and why
included this is if you understand the
code in the pages that are linked to
hear you know everything you will ever
need to know about JavaScript and then
you're all set then you can retire
because there's nothing more to learn
but it's interesting to look at it and
take their code and mess it up and kind
of see how JavaScript behaves as well
what I would like to argue for using the
prototype syntax that exists in
JavaScript because even if the other
solutions but other people are very
smart it's not really native JavaScript
it's not the way JavaScript actually
works and if you use the prototype
syntax anyone that knows java script
will understand your code right away
without some special code that you wrote
and just to cover up for it and
especially for me what I say in
different projects like a developer
works on something for about six months
and then he gets thrown into another
project and new developer comes in and
new developer has to learn their own
developers special methods to fix things
and it doesn't really work and well the
Godfather JavaScript Douglas Crockford
is also writing code to do this and his
conclusion is basically that well you
can use a super function or uber
function if you will and call that but
you don't really need it that's not
really how you usually use JavaScript
actually asking about three days ago if
it still stood by the statement and he
seemed to not so this still goes
and something that's very good to know
when javascript is scope like where do
you have access to something and why and
how do you all right things and how can
your code collide with other parts of
your code and basically what what scope
is is for variables and functions are
accessible and what context we are in
right now and it's pretty easy in
JavaScript we have a global scope which
is pretty much everywhere or we have a
local scope in the function you're in so
if you have in a javascript file we just
have a variable that's just lying there
it likes to play it's accessible
everywhere and within a function use the
bar likes to play that makes it local
and a very very common problem in
JavaScript these people forgetting to
use the VAR keyword within a function
and if you forget the VAR keyword in a
function it automatically becomes global
which is messy because people miss it
and they override something else and you
have a problem and also if you come from
other languages you use something called
block scope like you could happen if the
class here and just have something
that's only available in that context
but that's not really not really how
JavaScript works in JavaScript you can
have a nice clothes here and just
decline sort of declare the variable
within there but you can still access it
anywhere outside of it of that clause
anywhere within the function you can
access a variable declared declared
within the function and the same goes
for function is global you can access it
anywhere but then we can you know take a
step forward and just start nesting
functions and this one it becomes a bit
interesting because then you can run
things within a certain context that's
not available anywhere else so the inner
function you can only run it or access
it from within the outer function
and I see a lot of people trying to use
the disc keyword in Java Script like
this dot something and then don't really
know why this is a certain value or how
to control that value so what you can do
with a function is they can use the call
or the apply method on a function to set
the actual context for that function
it's just built in for every function
you don't need to declare it anywhere
and if you generally in a web browser if
you have a function here and you have
the onload event on the window it calls
the function that this keyword here
equals to window object because it's the
global object in a web browser let's say
you want it to be something else then we
can have the on click event here and you
have the set name function and if you
see it at the bottom here is uses dot
call which means that it will call the
set name function in the context I want
it to be so the first parameter here
it's document it could be anything I
want and what I said is the first
parameter here will be the disk keyword
in the receiving function and if I had a
number of parameters up there like you
see the name parameter that will not be
the document name so if you use the call
method the first one only says context
it not the first parameter to the
receiving function and the apply method
is pretty much the same with the call
method yes sending a comma-separated
thing with different values the apply
method is for you send in an array or a
collection instead so what you can use
here we were talking about arguments
before that in the call set names
function here we can just take all the
arguments setting to that function and
just pass them on to the other function
and you supply to run it in the context
of the document object
and then we have closures and closest
are the best thing in the world and then
just to get the right state of mind I
think about closure is I want you to go
to your happy place you know just back
down and feel nice about it what makes
you happy what makes you relax what
makes you what makes you feel good and
when you are in that state you're pretty
much ready to to grasp closures and what
closes are its expressions that you use
to create your own context and where you
can access certain values in a context
that you control and as we saw before
with inner functions nested in outer
functions the inner functions can always
reference something in the containing
function which is just a bunch of words
I'm saying so let's see some code for it
and no it's what's fun presenting when
people just start gaping but the thing
here is that we have the bar add five
variable here which equals a call to the
add method with the value of five as you
see in the add method it returns the
function where it applies an outdoor
value with an inner value and then I can
use it the result to that call in
another function which is usually I
explain it and we're pretty much here in
our relationship so if you break it down
here you send in the x value the first
time the add function is being called
and as you said inner functions can
always reference values of its
containing function so it would remember
the value of x at the time it was being
called and it was always always remember
that so the way javascript actually sees
to add the five function that we declare
with a variable here is like the bottom
here like it remembers the value five
forever
because it was five at the time it was
called and then just applies the new
values you can take this code and mess
around with it and that will make some
more sense I hope and to have a more
real live context words and actually got
this question last night because a
person had this problem which made me
very happy because it it should imply
that this example is good and is that
the people usually have loops in a web
page and they just like here you create
five link elements you will give them a
value like link 0 link 1 etc you also
apply an on-click event to it and you
want when the link is being clicked that
it should say it's number now the first
one should be 0 the next one should be 1
etc but what happens with this code is
that every link you click in the web
page will say 5 which makes people go a
bit crazy because that's not really what
they thought it would be and the reason
here is that the function here that's
applied to the on click event it's not
actually called when you apply it to the
link and that's the key reason here like
we said before it would just remember
the value of its outer function so it
will remember the value of I when the
function is finished so what you would
want to do instead is where we have the
on click event here is that you apply it
to what we talked about before a salt
invoking function that sounds in the
value I at that moment in time at that
specific iteration so as you see here it
linked on click equals function blah
blah blah but it also calls itself right
away at the end with the value of I ok
and the value of I is something as the
parameter nom and then it returns a
function that remembers the value of num
and that what what creating closure is
all about it it just consumed that value
and the inner function will always
remember the value of this outer
function just when it happened not when
you click it or or five years later just
that moment in time and to take use of
all this code its have something
nicknamed at Yahoo JavaScript module
pattern and again mr. Crawford and it's
a singleton pattern to create an object
and two in JavaScript even though is not
supported you can have private members
and public members of an object so I
shouldn't mention first just to be fair
to ban this is actually a good movie I
was a bit scared when I saw it start and
so directed by ben affleck and no damn
but it was actually good anyway what you
do here is we were talking about the
thing of having functions calling
themselves right away to create a
closure I a context where you can just
access whatever you want but not from
the outside so what we have here is just
a regular function but you see down here
that recalls itself right away and it
also has a return statement here and
what you have in the return statement is
what will be global as a result from
this so in practice then everything you
have declared a bomb like the Devourer
keyword for the movie title and they
extracted by van variables that will
only be accessible from within this
function so you have private members of
an object what you could also do just to
show a different version of the syntax
if you have the same property name same
object name is that the return statement
part because some people program ap is
and similar that in the return statement
you only want to have the names of
something that you expose basically it's
just easier to read so if you have heard
a title equals to us
colon title and directed by ben colon
the one behind the colon could be any
name of the function declared above with
the VAR keyword is just to make it
easier and also with we're talking about
the prototype inheritance and also
people coming from or classical
languages inheritance is good but
inheritance is also something that
people seem to keep fixated with and
then you start inheriting things in 10
different lines and you get performance
problem sometimes similar so I just want
to bring up the concept of name spacing
in JavaScript and a name spacing could
pretty much mean anything so what I'm
talking about here is well first we want
to avoid global variables because
they're evil that's one of the things
all the stage started to help us make
sure you're on the same page it was also
about code structure and about extending
code without having an actual
inheritance relationship so if we have
just a regular object air we have a band
object and on the band object you call
something band the dot director and as
you saw before i'm using the module
pattern just to create something with a
private member and then a public method
you can call so the movies method here
you can call it band director dot movies
and say you have another object here the
band dot actor object you can add all
its own methods and variables and
members and all that but if you want to
it could also utilize what the band that
director object offers so we were
talking about using the call method
before to call something in a certain
context so what we do here is if we call
the dot movies method of the director
object but within the context of the
band actor object I should also say that
the top part here is is usually a little
thing just in JavaScript that if you try
to do something like penndot actor and
the band na bo doesn't exist you will
get an error so it's just about creating
an empty
object to avoid us
and when it comes to program we also
want to use all these well different
terms like sugaring and currying which
implies that there's something really
cool going on and sugaring is something
that cover before it's basically that
you kind of sprinkle some sugar on the
existing objects and make them a little
better so string here is the native
JavaScript string object use prototype
on that and you add your own trim method
because it doesn't exist one and then it
will just replace all the well empty
spaces in the beginning or at the end of
that value and return that value that's
sugaring pretty easy pretty now it's
pretty useful for some cases and then
this is probably i usually have it here
just to mess with your minds because i
will present this and you will wonder
what the hell happened and then i will
move on so for you to read the code
later on as well but if you start with a
regular function here we have the add
function and it utilizes the arguments
collection as you said before so it
basically takes any kind of argument in
iterates over that adds them together
and returns the sum ok so then we bring
crockford into the picture again
actually try to write the better version
and I failed side use this version here
and what it does it we have the core
JavaScript object to function object
here you extend it through prototype
with a method called curry and then a
lot of weird goes on here that will
in essence create magic and just to
bring up some of the lines here did the
first one here is a bit funky and we
have the variable slice that equals
array dot prototype tight slice what I
do here is that I'm actually stealing
the slice method from the array object
without having an actual array I can
just pick the Sherry's I want from an
object and put them on my objects or
call them but in my context if I want to
so what I do is after I've stolen the
slice method from the array object is
that I call that slice object with the
apply method that we had before to call
it in a certain context and I call it
with the arguments ie all the params
that were sent into that function so
there's a lot of weird code what it
actually means and why it's being done
is you remember I said before that
arguments is a collection and not an
array anything is I want to use array
methods on it so that's why I use the
slice method because the result of the
slice method will return an array I know
but it goes on we have the disc keyword
and this keyword is for serve and it's
about the context when it's being called
and also with inner functions having
access to outer functions just save it
any variable called at that instead so
what happens every time that we call
this function further on is that we
remember the value of args which is just
the arguments as an array so I can use
the concat method on it and just use
slice again for the new arguments that
get sent in so I can just send them all
together or add them all up and you know
it just seems well annoying and you know
should I really know this and where it
becomes powerful is that it's a bit of a
meta programming in JavaScript just
remembering the result of some action
and then keep on working from that
result so instead of starting from
scratch all the time so what we do here
is that we have just like before when
we're adding up numbers that the first
time we call the chiro method with any
number of arguments we want it will
remember the result to thats or
actually be the value of all those
parameters then when we call that again
with nother one actually means we can
have two functions called with any
number of arguments and will
just pack it all together and give you
the result of that so this is nice and
if you code HTML or CSS or something you
have validators and you can point out
your own flaws or other people's flaws
if you want to because it says so in the
specification has to be a certain way
it's not really the same way in
JavaScript it's more about best
practices what works what won't crash
over time what what seems to be the most
solid approach and I mentioned before
with gaius lint jslint is a tool just to
check your JavaScript syntax and it
checks for small things like you forgot
a semicolon or similar but it also
checks for regular problems when will
people or make the call to race or
something so the code will run but it
will not run as some people expect so I
strongly recommend trying that too on
your code and just see the feedback and
I guess also my message today because
i'm the boring guy I'm just presenting
JavaScript how it actually works i'm not
showing funky demos or videos or people
moving i pause or telling about how much
sex sells i'm just talking about
javascript but what i wanted you to take
with you it's javascript is something
else it's not see your job hour or any
of those languages and don't truly try
to make it into that as well i mean it's
like in your private life if you move on
from a relationship to a new
relationship i mean you can have them
dye their hair and dress up as a nurse
but it's not the same person so kind of
drop it except javascript and and learn
to love it instead and that's how we
javascript is row thank you