[Music]
hello everyone do you know that feeling
where you spent months handcrafting a
webpage and then you test it and then
you deploy it and as soon as somebody
visited some link is broken something is
missing I know that feeling and if you
do as well then I have a tool for you
which I built
it's called hyperlink so I can show you
how I would test my own blog here and do
it recursively I need to type in the URL
correctly this will go on and crawl my
entire website and tell me all about
whatever what errors I might have which
links might be broken which links might
be leading to permanent redirect and I
should probably update it it will check
fragment identifiers if they're correct
and everything it's outputting tap which
is supposed to be machine readable not
human readable so you can take the
output and pipe it into a reporter for
example tap spot and it'll tell you that
you have these errors you're linking to
LinkedIn which is responding HTTP 9 9 9
this is basically because LinkedIn does
not like to be scraped I'm linking to a
meetup page which has a broken 404 and
I'm linking to something on Jenkins
which has a 403 because they don't like
to be scraped either you can run this on
local files you can run it on remote
HTTP URLs and get this output and it
fails correctly on the command line so
if you want to tie this into your CI
integration system you can do that and
it's available on NPM NPM install hyper
link and the command line help is
hopefully useful otherwise there is a
readme thank you
[Applause]