thank you look Amy okay
so i would like to tell you a story
about the firefox OS and html5 games
quick question how many of you heard
about Firefox OS awesome right how many
of you are html5 game developers ok feo
ok cool so my name is Angie mizzou and I
started a small company called enclaves
games in which I just make html5 games
for fun it's not even a company at it's
just you know working on something that
I love in every time I ran the jest 18k
Games competition that will end tomorrow
any one of you heard about the
competition ok nice thank you I run a
meetup scene were so game of joyous
meetups only a couple of them it's not
so so big so I also write on the block I
can find me on Twitter and on github and
I will tell you about the game I created
with my friend I did the cutting part
and heated the graphics and game I would
like to tell you was prepared for the
Firefox OS platform especially and the
story goes like this it's it's very
simple game it's not complicated you
just fly with your rocket and avoid the
asteroids so so the idea was to have a
very simple game but polished and
finished
that you can ship the the finished
product it was built with impact Gia's
game engine quite popular one and
optimized for Firefox OS you will seen
in the presentation that it wasn't so is
so hard to to prepare the version for
the Firefox OS it's very easy and the
submit process was also done in a minute
so after a week or two off of time spent
on development to submit that in the
marketplace and a few days earlier later
the game was in the marketplace and you
could just download it and play so few
words about the Firefox OS so it's a
mobile operating system developed by
Mozilla and the thing that that this
system is different from the others is
that it's built with html5 and
JavaScript it's awesome for me for a
front-end developer that worked for a
couple of years in JavaScript that I
have I can have a whole play operating
system on my mobile device that runs
java script I can change one CSS style
and the icons will be squares so it's
very easy to customize its open sourced
it's on github you can check it you can
commit your changes as I said you can
easily modify it for now it's targeted
for low-end devices so it will work on
our cheap phones but there is a plan to
have devices with more hardware better
hardware and its new all the consistent
because you don't have to well if you
have experience with html5 and
JavaScript you're already prepared to
build applications for
firefox because it's just just the web
the problem with the html5 is the
question is if it's ready for for gaming
because there are some problems that we
face but there are also good things it's
it html5 is free of course you don't
have to pay for a license you can create
a gaming one code base and just deploy
it in different environments as I said
earlier there are already developer
student have to learn a new language
it's cross-platform you can create the
game and put it in five stars different
stores and only the only thing that you
need is just a browser so you can play
your game on a smartphone on a tablet on
your laptop maybe on a TV maybe on your
fridge if you want to if it have a
browser the distribution distribution is
very easy because you can just send the
link to the game chatting with your
friend and he can play it to 17 he don't
need to have any plugins to play it and
it's easy to learn from far from the
code you get instant access you don't
have to wait two weeks to have your next
version except that you just change your
code and refresh the browser and the
changes are there and its story
independent you don't have to stick to
the one store you can share the game
wherever you want so the Firefox OS just
takes the good good parts of the html5
and gives the hardware the technology on
which the
the applications the the camera so at
least for me at the Firefox OS is just
the mobile web on which I will I was
waiting for some words about the weak
spots because the technology isn't
perfect there are still some problems
with the audio api performance model
cessation and working of line the Web
Audio API is looking quite decent it's
it's okay on the desktop machines it's
still problem on mobile devices but I
think it in a few months it will be
better and better because the the the
the guys from the specification are
working on it the performance there are
many accusations that the performance is
bad but if you gave the device to which
you can have access to from the
JavaScript and access the camera or
other contacts etc and other things then
the the boost of the performances is
quite quite high and the monetization
problem if you focus on one store you
can optimize everything to make it work
there but the the problem is with html5
games that there are still not so many
publishers and platforms that help you
sell your game so here the Mozilla
marketplace comes into place and you can
of course sell your game there in the
marketplace but as I said earlier it's
it's independent from the stars so you
can put it there you can put it
your own website you can package it
using for example phonegap and put it in
the app store so yeah it's it's
independent and you can put the in-app
purchases using the html5 AP ice of
course you can you can add
advertisements to the game you can sell
the license so there are many many ways
you can monetize the game and it's a
getting better and better every month
because I am receiving the emails from
the publishers and that they are waiting
for for me to make more games because I
made one game it's okay I saw the
license and there are still not so many
developers and many publishers that want
working games so it's some it's
situation where the publishers are
waiting for the developers and need the
games so if you start working on the
games it won't be a problem to sell the
license and money working offline yeah
so theoretically html5 app is website so
as a website it's in the internet and it
it works in the internet so if you turn
off the Wi-Fi it won't work but we have
the offline stuff like different
technologies that that will help you
store your data on the machine of the
of the the guy that that browse the
website and we'll start the holding all
the information and he will he will look
at the website when it's offline and it
will work the Firefox OS goes further
and gives you the possibility to have a
package zap so we can just zip out the
resources and it will work everywhere
without the internet of course you can
also host the host the game files on
your own and implement the storage so it
will also work offline and will you will
have a full control and you will have
the option to upgrade it instantly so
let's talk about the the Firefox itself
how to start the development what to
look for first you can test your game or
application in the browser the Firefox
OS has a plug-in that works as Firefox
OS simulator and it works pretty nice
there are great tools that will help you
in the development process and of course
you can look for a device the first ones
was the geeksphone Keong that were given
to the developers it looks like this and
it it's theoretically a quite low budget
but but the game works very smooth and
if you compare it to the phone that that
you can buy for the same money running
and Android especially if it's 2.3 it
will work with like five frames per
second or something like
this so it's a huge difference that you
have you have direct access to the
hardware of the device and there are
more devices coming there are a new
countries that start selling that the
phones with Firefox OS yeah so the
optimization part you could just pack it
your app put it in the missoula
marketplace and it will work so if you
don't want to optimize it you can just
leave it but it's a great improvement it
will it will work a lot faster so these
are the optimization methods that you
can you can use in your own html5
applications or games it's not firefox
OS specific so it's a for example whole
pig surrendering when you're rendering
the the whole pixels not the parts of
the pixels and it's a huge difference so
if you're interested in this you can you
can search for more information you
could for example caused catch the
drawing on the different screen node
which is quite popular because you can
draw it on the canvas that is not
visible and it will be just shown on the
copied to the visible canvas there is
one thing that this Firefox OS specific
it's using mouse opaque on the canvas
tag that it's I've tested it on the same
code base and it was like running 30
frames per second compared to 60 frames
per second so I was amazed that it's a
huge difference with only 11 tag you can
also scale the canvas using css3
transforms
instead of scaling it using javascript
there are there are ups and downs but
I've noticed that this way it's not
perfect for every game there are games
that you have to if if the screen on
which the player is playing is different
on different devices then playing on on
different devices can give advantages to
the one player and the other player now
so so so it's important to adjust this
to the game that you are working on but
for most of the games it's the easiest
way to scale the canvas and just fill
the screen and that you don't have to
worry about screen resolution another
optimization technique is using CSS for
background images if you don't have to
if you have a big background that you
are still rendering every frame then you
can just drop it and use the image set
as a background of of a deeper canvas
just to show it once and just it will
stay there and the rendering loop in the
canvas will render all of the things and
the background will stay the same and
you can of course use different multiple
canvases for a different layers of your
games so you can shout the background on
the separate layer I do the UI on a
separate and the player with with bosses
and enemies on another and there are
great there is a great article on the
Mozilla hugs I will give the address of
the slides so we can check the article
about the optimization techniques that I
mentioned here and so let's talk about
the Firefox marketplace a bit
it's a marketplace hello and it works as
a place where you can put your game as I
said it's it's not you're not forced to
use only this you you you don't have to
use it at all but it's it's a great
place to start there are not so many
games and applications so you can start
early and outrun the competition and
there are two types of applications for
a Firefox OS the packaged ones and the
self-hosted ones that i mentioned
earlier the package one you you just
upload the zip package and it's
distributed and the self-hosted just you
host it on your website there is a
concept of install instant install
button that you can put on your website
and just install the game directly you
don't have to go to the marketplace to
install the game you don't have to
search for it you can just put it on
your website tell your friend just click
the button and we'll if it if he goes to
the website and from the firefox OS
clicks the button and have the game
installed and and yeah as I said it's
almost no competition so it's a great
time to to start early and for example
my game is very simple it was built like
a week or two weeks and it's it's quite
popular in the marketplace so it's easy
to start and to to be there before
others let's talk about preparing your
game it's easy because it's html5 so you
don't have to learn new technology you
don't have to learn your language the
only thing that you need
there's a manifest file which this is
the basic version in which you see just
the name of your application description
etc you can of course at the more
information to the manifest but it's the
basic one that will just work and the
information will be provided to the
marketplace this can be shown on your
website etc and when you have your
manifest file already and your game zip
ting the into the package you can just
use the submit form send the file add
the description screen shots etc and
just submitted wait like two or three
days and the game will be in the
marketplace so here's here is the
screenshot of the game in the
marketplace the game itself is in
English but the description is like in
eight languages or so so if the if the
someone enters the market place from
different country he will get the
description in his own language mmm yeah
and the actual device I will be here you
can grab me and see the device it's the
geeksphone key on and I can show you the
device I can show you the game it runs
pretty smoothly okay listen lessons
learned from the making of the game for
that platform it was it was very easy
because as I said it's just html5 and
JavaScript so you don't have to do much
to implement
the to adapt to the the Firefox OS and
to upload it to the marketplace the
documentation is ready if you're looking
for if something is not working you can
google for it and get the answer most of
the problems are not perfect so specific
so you can just look for a problem in if
you have a problem in JavaScript you can
find the answers the documentation for
the Firefox s is there so so you can use
it the the whole thing with with the
game came from the from the event that I
attended and it was good to see that the
the technologist is new and you have
influence on it there was a one-day
hackathon that we managed to find like
three bucks or four bucks in the Firefox
OS in the early version and I think two
are fixed almost immediately so so if
you have like feature requests or ideas
or whatever you can just send the
feedback or change something by yourself
because that the whole system is hosted
on github and it's very easy to add
something change something etc so to
summarize the the presentation and how
idea making a game for a Firefox Oasis
is very easy it's very easy to build and
very easy to publish in the marketplace
just the manifest file just a few
optimizations and it works perfectly you
have the device to which you have access
to from the JavaScript
for me it's awesome and you're building
not for the Firefox OS but you're
building for the web because the the
Firefox OS itself is a web app built in
html5 and JavaScript so the applications
and the games also are just web web
applications just html5 games so you can
just put it on your website it will work
and there will be a conference in or so
in like a week about html5 games and if
anyone anyone wants to go to the
conference you can tweet this and you
will get the free ticket like five of
them to give away it's one hour flight
to also or a few hours to by train so
it's quite close and the conference is
awesome yeah okay thank you what's it