Empathy is not enough\h the power of engaging
hard to reach users
Ariba Jahan
PARISS: Hey, everyone.
Again.
This is our final talk of the evening.
So, this next speaker coming up, she climbed
mountain Kilimanjaro, isn't that crazy, okay.
So, this is who is not in the room: Building
better products by engaging hard to reach
users.
Let's give a warm welcome to Ariba Jahan.
[ Applause ]
ARIBA: Hi.
Just so you know, you'll see me stepping on
and stepping off a stool here.
I'm 4 foot 11 inches so some adjustments needed
to be made.
So, I'm gonna give you a second to kind of
read some of these headlines that showcase
what's been happening in our industry.
So, this\h this is what we get when we don't
challenge our assumptions.
Hi, I'm Ariba Jahan.
And today I'm here to share with you four
ways you can challenge your assumptions to
avoid headlines like those.
And instead build better and more impactful
products for your audience.
And the four methods\h oh, okay.
And the four methods I'll share with you are
helping us think through product development
in a new way at the ad council.
And I'm hoping they'll be helpful for you
as you bring these back to your work.
So, for context, the Ad Council, we're a nonprofit
organization that leverages the power of communication
to tackle the nation's biggest challenges
like preventing wildfires and LGBTQ rights
awareness and diversity and inclusion and
promoting girls in STEM.
We bring together industry leaders to develop
campaigns to create social impact and create
action.
And as the director of innovation at the Ad
Council, my responsibility is to facilitate
innovative thinking and work in our teams
as well as cultivate a culture where experimentation
and curiosity can thrive.
And I get to do that in many ways including
training our whole staff on Splash Box, which
is our approach to innovation.
And it incorporates methodologies from LEAN
as well as human centered design with mindsets
to cultivate in our teams.
And to date we've trained 80% of the organization,
giving us a shared proposal and toolset to
innovate.
And as a way to bring the training\h the skills
people learn at the training to life and make
them more tangible, we created a project where
our new innovators can apply their skills
to create a digital prototype for one of our
campaign issues.
So, today I'm really excited to share with
you one of these digital prototype projects
where our assumptions got in the way and we
had to use these\h the four methods I mentioned
to uncover our assumptions and to really challenge
them.
So, the campaign issue we chose was teen bullying
prevention.
And the task at hand was, well, how do we
leverage the power of technology, what it
is today, to answer this big question?
How might we influence teens to reduce peer
mistreatment and empower one another by building
and perpetuating a more empathetic, supportive
and inclusive culture?
Our target audience for this project were
teens ranging from the ages 13 to 17 years
old who fell into the category of "Good eggs."
We defined" Good eggs 'as teens who believe
they're good people and value kindness and
respect of one another and they want to be
the best version of themselves.
So, as you can imagine, we were really excited
to contribute towards creating a more inclusive
world for our next generations.
So, as any good team, we dug in n and did
a tremendous amount of research.
From reading every single research report
we could get our hands on about Gen Z, and
interviewing teens, teachers, as well as issue
experts.
And our research gave us so many insightful
findings, that we were able to come up with
over a hundred ideas and 20 concepts.
And we then showed our strongest ideas to
team to get some early feedback on which ideas
do we refine, how do we refine them?
And which ideas should we be leaving behind?
After this many rounds of research and getting
early user feedback directly from teens, we
felt pretty confident in our direction.
And we knew that whatever solution we create
in order to solve for bullying has to solve
the three goals.
Our research told us that good eggs have an
innate desire to create the change they wanted
to see in the world.
We wanted to show them that and their actions,
hoping they will adopt the kinder behaviors.
And two, we should double down on social media.
We found out that 91% of Gen Z are on social
media.
So, we knew immediately that we needed to
prioritize and emphasize the role of social
media in our digital solution.
And three, leverage the rise of CGI influencers.
See, at the time, four computer generated
based influencers are garnered over 1 million
followers on Instagram.
And we were kind of blown away by those and
we need to do something with this.
Whether it's to do storytelling or to model
good behaviors to teens in hopes that it works
for them.
So, keeping these three goals in mind, we
refined our 20 concepts into five promising
ideas.
And then we took these ideas to teams to get
some more validation and then start building
them.
And the main thing we learned at this round
with teens is that we were wrong on all fronts.
What we focused on as goals were actually
just assumptions.
Starting with the word bullying.
It turns out that the only people that use
the word bullying is a bunch of adults who
want to end bullying.
[ Laughter ]
And, you know, we learned that because we
talked to teens and when we asked them, hey,
can you share your experience with bullying?
They didn't have much to share.
But when we changed our wording and asked,
can you share the last time someone hurt you?
Or maybe when you've hurt someone else?
They shared stories about being excluded,
shaming, blaming.
And there was just so much more vulnerability
involved.
So, it turned out that their language around
mistreatment looked very different than ours.
And they're actually way more self aware than
we give them credit for.
We asked them, can you think about a moment
where you mistreated someone or you hurt someone.
And when they did that, they used words like
regret, guilt, is upset as how they felt afterwards.
So, they're clearly fully aware of the implications
of their actions.
And it turned out that even though 91% of
Gen Z are on social, they value privacy and
authenticity way more than what we knew.
To the point where they have two types of
Instagram accounts.
One is called Finsta which is fake Instagram
account.
And that is where they are their most authentic
self.
Photos are unfiltered, they keep it private.
No crafted captions and they keep the number
of people who can follow that account very
small.
And then they have the Rinsta, the real Instagram
account where it's hyper curated, well crafted
captions.
Perhaps even song lyrics and that's where
they want to have a lot of followers.
And when it came down to CGI influencers,
only like a few teens knew what a CGI influencer
was.
And even the ones that followed them only
did it out of curiosity for the character's
fashion.
And if you\h I'm not so sure if you can read
it, but if you can look at their handwritten
feedback on the screen, you'll notice what
they wanted instead was someone relatable.
Someone who might have had a tough childhood.
Someone who has gone through issues.
And they also wanted someone funny.
I really think just wanted Kevin Hart.
[ Laughter ]
So, our assumptions were checked.
You know?
And before I dive into the four tactics that
allowed us to uncover these assumptions, I
want to talk about assumptions for a second.
You know, assumptions\h assumption is something
we believe to be true without any evidence.
And the reason it's so easy for our assumptions
and biases to come into our work or to creep
up even after tremendous amount of research,
is because our brain is constantly making
assumptions just in the interest of efficiency.
See, the thing is, over the course of 200,000
years, our brain has created several mental
shortcuts to help us cope and survive and
deal with the tremendous amounts of innovation
in our world.
So, we end up having shortcuts that help us
make sense of large amounts of information.
Shortcuts that help us determine what's important
to remember and what to recall.
Shortcuts that create explanations for us
when we don't have enough meaning or when
there is not enough context.
And shortcuts that help us act quickly.
These ready shorts that help us remember how
to ride a bike, know 2 plus 2, help us detect
joy or frustration in someone's voice and
to run from perceived danger.
While all of those sound necessary, these
are the same shortcuts that cause us to make
assumptions, make snap judgments, jump to
conclusions and make decisions based on our
biases.
And these mental shortcuts are more commonly
known as cognitive biases.
And the thing is, with 180 of these mental
shortcuts active in our brain all the time,
it's kind of hard to spot when they're getting
in the way or when they're active.
So, I'll call out three that got in our way
and we didn't even notice it.
See, we have a mental shortcut that causes
us to be easily influenced by what is stored
in our memory or what's familiar.
And that's the way\h that's the reason why
all of us use the word bullying to describe
that interaction.
Even without even questioning does that language
even resonate?
Does it even work?
We have another mental shortcut that causes
us to make judgments and impressions by relying
only on the information made available to
us.
And that's why when we see data like 91% of
teens are on social media and they spend 9
hours consuming media, we're just like, oh
my god.
They must be sharing everything and they're
on it all the time.
Let's just like do everything social media
related.
What we don't do is actively question, well,
does this 91% do the same exact thing?
Did they all use the same features in the
same exact way?
Do they all feel the same way?
We don't do that.
And the last mental shortcut I'll call out
is that we're just naturally drawn to details
that confirm our own existing beliefs.
It's just what we do.
This is why we have friends.
This is how we make friends.
I'll look for someone who likes the same thing
as I do.
Now we're friends.
And the thing is, that same bias is what causes
us to find things that validate us.
So, when we were super hyped up about CGI
influencers, we ended up paying a lot more
closer attention to headlines like these that
said, oh, my god, CGI influencers are the
future of the influencer marketing.
And that's what happens.
So, while great for survival, mental shortcuts
are not great for innovation.
And that's how easy it is for mental shortcuts
that are designed to help us cope to get in
the way of us making products that are right
for our audience.
So, for the rest of my talk, I will focus
on how we used\h is it jumping on the screen?
Because it's jumping here.
So, I just wanted to double check.
It's jumping?
Okay.
I'm gonna assume someone's gonna take care
of that.
[ Laughter ]
But I'll keep going.
So, yes.
I'll focus on how we used these four methods
in the teen bullying prevention prototype
projects.
And I hope it gives you inspiration on how
you can take some of these methods back into
your projects so you can challenge your assumption.
Okay.
So, the first one being mapping\h oh!
Mapping assumptions.
I'll just read for a second so you can have
the slides while I talk.
All right.
We're up.
So, the first one I'll talk about is mapping
assumptions.
It's an activity where we actively\h what
slide is that?
Oh, that's not moving.
All right.
Now we're there.
So, it's an activity where we actively uncover
critical uncertainties, unknowns and blind
spots about our audience, challenge and solutions
we're thinking about exploring.
And the thing about assumptions, as we saw,
is that they don't always look and feel like
assumptions.
They feel like facts.
So, it's really good to have a diverse team
in the room so that we can all help each other
spot each other's blind spots and challenge
each other's assumptions.
So, for our project, in order to map assumptions,
we started by asking ourselves questions around
teens' experiences with mistreatment.
So, we tried to figure out like how much do
we know the audience?
What type of language do they use?
What's their lifestyle?
What brings them joy?
What are their priority, pain points?
And how do they use technology?
And then we asked ourselves, well, what do
we believe to be true about teen mistreatment?
How does mistreatment show up in their lives
and how do they solve it?
And is this a challenge they need solved by
us?
And just in general, what else do they know
that we should know about and whose voices
have been heard?
When we did this, we had more questions than
answers.
And despite all the research we did, we didn't
know much about teens.
So, we took all of our assumptions and needed
to figure out, where do we go from here?
So, to prioritize what we needed to dig into,
we mapped on a 2x2 grid.
From known to unknown, and the Y axis was
very important to not very important.
It and helped us tease out the critical uncertainties
that we needed to figure out before going
any further.
To recap, mapping assumptions can really help
us uncover our blind spots, what we believe
to be true versus what is actually true.
And critical gaps in the team's overall knowledge.
And answering these questions about the audience
and the challenge we're solving for is a great
way to know where to go next, what to explore
before going any further or investing any
further in the project.
So, after rounds of interviewing with teens
and doing brainstorms within our teams, we
had about 20 fleshed out concepts and we loved
them all.
But we had no clue which idea would work.
And instead of just choosing an idea, just
praying something works, we decided to test
five of our strongest concepts.
So, we ran several experiments to explore
Whether or not our ideas could create the
desired outcome we were hoping for and to
garner any new knowledge.
And while mapping assumptions is a great place
to start, testing hypothesis kind of allows
you to uncover all the invisible assumptions
that we didn't even notice yet.
So, to test multiple hypothesis, we do two
things.
We created hypothesis statements to get really
specific on what we were hope our ideas can
do.
And then that helped us hone in on what are
we hoping to uncover through test something
and then we identified our riskiest assumptions
which were, what are the beliefs we're holding
about our ideas that if disproven completely
break ours idea altogether?
So, in order to create these hypothesis statements,
we reframed each of our ideas into a hypothesis
by using a Madeline framework like this.
You fill in the parentheses with the relevant
information in your project.
So, we believe this audience has a problem
doing this.
We believe this solution can help.
They will do this engagement resulting in
the desired outcome.
So, going back to our CGI project, this is
an example, our assumptions and our hypothesis
is, we believe that teens have a problem noticing
the impact of their actions which leads them
to mistreat each other.
We believe that a fictional CGI character
whose life captures the dramatic realities
of the teen experience, including teachable
moments where the character models kindness,
can help.
And we believe that teens will follow and
relate to the character causing them to reflect
and adopt the modeled positive behaviors in
real life.
So, it really gets the team to focus on, what
are we doing here?
What are we hoping to do?
Versus getting tied up in the features and
the color and the UI of the product.
So, we did that for all five ideas.
And then we needed to identify our riskiest
assumption.
We did that by first asking, well, what must
be true in order for this idea to work?
Like at all?
And what must be true in order for this idea
to add value to the teens' lives?
And then when we answered these questions,
we looked through them and tried to identify
the ones that, if disproven, completely breaks
our idea.
So, going back to our CGI project, we came
up with a lot of things that we're assuming
and hoping to be true in order for this idea
to work.
And what really stood out to us as our riskiest
assumption was our belief that teens will
resonate with the CGI character.
See, if teens don't relate or follow the CGI
person, like this whole idea is irrelevant
and we're not going to do anything.
But what's great about testing is that we
can know that without ever spending any time
investing in, developing and putting the CGI
character together.
So, by the time we did this for each one of
our ideas, we ended up with like a list of
elements and interactions that we were assuming
teens would love and engage with.
But had no proof.
So, all of the\h all of them needed to be
tested.
Like does anonymity really matter?
Do teens care about interacting with things
in real time and user generated content?
And do they really value influencer oriented
things?
And then we took those and we wanted to test
them without having to build anything.
So, we used simple things like surveys and
design prototypes to test all of those features
to figure out, like, where are we going?
So, to recap, the simple act of reframing
an idea into a hypothesis is such a great
reminder that regardless of how exciting our
ideas may sound, we don't really know yet
if any of them will work.
So, they need to be tested in order for us
to move forward.
And to help prioritize what to even test first,
we really hone in on the beliefs we're holding
on to about our ideas that if invalidated
our idea needs to be scrapped.
And the thing is, being able to test our ideas
before building anything is actually gave
us a lot of freedom from creativity.
It gave us the liberty to dream just a little
bigger knowing that our audience would let
us know what to refine and what to leave behind.
So, let's go big.
So, testing multiple ideas with our users
was super insightful.
But there's a limitation to how much we could
learn through testing.
Because the thing is, when we have prototypes
that we're showing and asking questions to
teens, they're only reacting to whatever we're
giving them.
And that's why engaging and working with and
empowering our users to create their own solutions
was so critical to see.
We coordinated with a high school in New York
City and we\h we hosted three co creation
sessions.
And we really wanted to understand how do
teens perceive bullying today?
What types of digital interactions do they
even enjoy?
And that list of riskiest elements that we
were so excited about?
We wanted to invalidate or validate some of
them.
And lastly, we wanted to see how would teens
solve this?
So, what you see up here is a snapshot of
the solutions students came up with when we
asked them to design a digital tool that could
help people be more mind and inclusive of
others.
And/or to help people avoid hurting someone's
feelings.
We purposely didn't use words like teen or
bullying because we didn't to want mislead
them or drive them in a direction that's not
natural for them.
We then got our user feedback on these new
ideas as well.
So, the co creation sessions validated some
hypotheses while invalidating others.
And what we learned from teens directly helped
us design three new cocreated prototypes.
And the thing about co creations is, you saw
how insightful they were.
But they also uncovered ideas that we couldn't
have come up with on our own.
For example, our students came up with this
brilliant idea which they called In My Bag.
In my bag is a phrase teens use to indicate
when they are feeling emotionally unavailable
or sad.
So, this is an app that would allow users
to air drop or somehow alert their friends
when they are not feeling emotionally available
and they want to be left alone.
And you can see the handwritten feedback from
other students on this idea.
And their feedback on this idea was super
enthusiastic and very validating.
They said thing like, it's fire.
And you can tell people around you how you're
actually feeling.
See?
Their comments showed us that they wanted
to be vulnerable.
And they wanted to share how they were feeling.
Which is contrary to the social pressure they
have to be tough.
So, the ability to uncover new learnings about
our audience and hear ideas that we couldn't
have ever come up with on our own, is what
makes co creation so powerful.
And by creating space for our users to join
us in the process, we get out of our own way.
So, it's been quite a journey.
From identifying opportunities and researching
for insights to coming up with over a hundred
ideas to then testing those hypothesis with
teens and then co designing some with them,
there were moments when our ideas were invalidated
and our assumptions were checked.
and the thing is, that's what learning looks
like.
And also we made progress, it didn't come
easily.
We went out of our way to find a diverse mix
of teens to interview and worked with our
local high school to organize these co creations.
And we needed parents to sign permission slips,
we had to work around exam schedules, homework
schedules, and we had to be totally okay if
a teen suddenly flaked on a phone interview.
But you know what?
All of that\h all of that relentless effort
was worth it.
Because the audience we were looking to serve
was not in the room and their perspective
was crucial.
And to empower teams to be this relentless,
to chase after these unknowns, we must create
a culture where curiosity and innovation can
thrive.
And what does that look like?
It's a team where there's less of a monoculture
of thoughts and ideas but has people who seek
perspectives unlike their own.
Where we spend less time defending ideas and
spend more time testing our hypothesis with
a diverse representation of our audience.
We spent less time looking for that one right
answer.
And realized that we must create space for
everyone to embrace the unknown and ambiguity
and just stay curious.
And instead of using language and reward systems
in our workplace to heighten our sense of
fear or failure, let's just create a culture
that's open to being wrong.
So, rounding off, I want you to remember that
our brain has many mental shortcuts that are
really just constantly on and just trying
to help us survive and hope and process the
world around us.
But those same shortcuts also make us do\h
make decisions based on our biases, make snap
judgments, and make assumptions and miss critical
information that others wouldn't miss.
So, while we'd all like to believe that we're
not that biased or maybe we're not as biased
as the other people, that thought in itself
is a bias.
It's called bias blind spot.
So, this bias blind spot can cause us to let
our assumptions go unchecked and affecting
our ability to make the right product for
our audience.
So, I want you to remember to do these four
things.
Let's try to map our assumptions and unknowns
about the challenge we're trying to tackle
and the people that we're trying to solve
for, and the solutions that we think that
would help them so we can uncover the gaps
of knowledge in our teams and figure out,
what do we have to really explore to move
any forward?
Let's test multiple ideas to see if they really
create the outcome we were hoping for?
And a great place to start with that is really
going after the beliefs that we're holding
on to that if proven wrong can completely
invalidate our idea.
And let's bring our audience more into our
process by cocreating with them so that they
can solve the things themselves and show us
ideas that we can't come up with on our own.
And let's be relentless in making sure that
the people that we're trying to serve, that
their voices are heard and that we have a
diverse team in place to hear them and that
we are making sure that we're aligned with
our product, goals and ethics.
And lastly, nurture a team that seeks perspectives
unlike their own, values testing and can stay
curious.
So, instead of fighting the 180 mental shortcuts,
evolution has ingrained in us, Let's use these
four methods to uncover and challenge our
assumptions so that we can make better and
more impactful products for our audience.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
PARISS: How are you feel something
KATIE: I'm pretty tired.
I'm pretty tired.
I just did some yoga on stage in the other
room.
That took a lot out of me.
But I'm feeling good.
I had a good day can you have a good day?
PARISS: I had a really good day.
KATIE: Did y'all have a good day?
PATRICIA: Again, I want to thank the speakers.
You did amazing.
I know you were all nervous.
You killed it.
Great job.
Round of applause.