[Applause]
[Music]
so funny story yesterday I was walking
down the streets of Budapest admiring
the architecture and I wasn't paying
social the cobblestones and I fell and
actually broke my arm no but it's okay
because this is good because I think
people tell you when you're about to get
on stage like break a leg and I broke my
arm and I feel like this is gonna mean
that this is gonna be the most amazing
talk ever but I'm not here to talk about
how clumsy I am even though that'll be
pretty funny I'm here to talk about the
shady web and how we can use our CSS
powers for good and not evil one second
all right so what we're gonna first talk
about how frustrating the web is today
and then we're gonna talk about how we
can be intentional about our strategies
that we use to make our web more
functional and then lastly some steps to
bring that back home and actually get
your web more animated so first a little
bit about me my name is Heidi I'm an
American from Portland Oregon and a
senior a full-service agency called ear
I at Erie where we got the clients like
Nike and Taco Bell and some other
American ones they probably don't know
about and my twitter handle is here as
well my code pens so if you want to
follow me and ask me questions there
please feel free but like you said I've
been a developer about nine or ten years
and when I first got into development I
was so excited to learn everything first
I learned HTML and CSS and then I saw
that other websites had these cool
slideshows at these jQuery and so I was
like yeah I want to learn jQuery but
then I realized that I didn't understand
how jQuery worked at all so I learned
JavaScript and then I wanted to use data
in my site so I learned PHP and all this
was fine and good but a couple years in
I kind of realized that I didn't really
like anything I was making it was you
know they looked nice
they were functional but something was
missing and I realized that all the
other developers that I was following
we're doing some really cool concept in
some really cool executions and I was
like man what am I missing and I realize
that I've been focused so much on how to
do the thing
so they don't really think about why I
was actually doing it and I think this
contributes a lot to why the web is so
frustrating and I think that we're all
kind of guilty that this a little bit
for example this fell we happen to you a
lot you read a blog you're like halfway
through agreeing to the good meat of it
no some of those video pops up and it
starts playing music now imagine you're
at work and your headphones are not in
and all sudden your whole work knows
that you're procrastinating not working
super frustrating my probably Lee's
favorite experience is if you're on a
mobile device right so you start you
know struggling through the blog and
then Olsen this ad comes up and you have
to scroll carefully to get to the top
and if you accidentally tap a going to
another site and then you know you're
not gonna come back and this is so
frustrating and the problem is is that
people like us are making those
experiences we're the ones who are
guilty and you know developers get
really mad about that and I think I just
want to give developers the benefit
adult-like maybe they're not evil people
like maybe they just don't intend to
make these experiences so awful and I
think there's two things that happen I
think the first is that we abuse new
technologies until more sophisticated
way of doing things emerges right we
like the shiny brand-new things and I'm
definitely guilty of this
when CSS animations we're starting to
get supported I was like ooh like
animate all the things it's like a party
my browser but problem was is that
people weren't coming to the site so I
was developing to like look at the cool
is that I was animating they were
actually there to do a thing and I was
just getting in the way of that the
second thing that I think happens is
that we prioritize like business goals
and metrics over the user experience
take pop-ups for example really common
used to get email acquisition and
there's a lot of blog posts to talk
about how successful they are right you
get like 20 or 30 percent more emails
woohoo
but everybody hates them so why are we
using them well I think it's I think
that the illusion that you do get those
emails but there's actually a couple
things are happening you're getting in
the way of the person's tasks that
they're trying to complete and so even
if they go past your pop-up they're
going to be fresher
with you maybe not come back to your
site also people are gonna put fakey
mattresses in there it's gonna be like
fart at fart calm edu or whatever and
just to get past that because and then
you know you have fake emails in your
list and then let's say they're nice
people they actually give you their real
email address when those people receive
an email from you they're gonna be like
they're not going to open it because
they didn't really choose to do that in
the first place and so you've all seen
this quote before I think maybe like the
million presentations I've had it but
it's a really good quote good design
when done well becomes invisible and
that's because we need to get out of the
way of our users and let them create the
function at hand so that's what we
really want to talk about being
intentional and I think this is really
important when you think about CSS
animations because a lot of times are
used for decoration so is that getting
in the way is there even a use for using
animation at all and I actually argue
yes because animation is a really unique
way to make the user feel like it's
something that's in real life so for
example this is Ryan Gosling he's
receiving some information pausing and
then shaking his head and without even
understanding or hearing anything that
he's doing you understand that he does
not agree with whatever was told to him
now look this example from Striped check
out the user is trying to submit without
filling out the fields so in addition to
just outlining the fields with red which
has come in practice it's actually
shaking like no and that's universally
known so it's helping the user
understand oh I messed up I need to do
something before the submits and this is
because what happens when you're
reducing what's called cognitive load
and so kind of load refers to the total
amount of information your working
memory can handle and so this is how
this works every day you receive so much
sensory information and stuff that you
can feel or you see or you hear and your
sensory memory actually stores the most
important information in your cognitive
load but what can also happen is when
you receive so much information that
your sensory memory can distinguish
what's the most important and this is
when you become really frustrated
and decisions are really hard to make
this awesome dude professor John sweller
actually did a lot of studies about
cognitive load theory and with that he
figured out a couple different
strategies to help create these
techniques to help people learn so three
of these strategies that we can use in
the web our show-and-tell
connecting context and Collin responds
studies have shown that people respond
better to image and narration versus
text and narration this is why seasoned
speakers encourage you not to have a
giant wall of text on a slide because
the audience will attempt to read the
slide while listening to you it get
distracted here's an actual good example
of it this is a blog post about group
texting in a really crazy climate I'm
sure you understand that states are a
little frustrating right now so instead
of just having a blog post with you know
text and some images they're actually
showing group text to help incorporate
into that narration it really helps you
understand exactly what they're trying
to communicate a lot easier than trying
to read those blocks of text the second
concept is connecting context so let's
say you have a cat I have two and you
see it coming around the corner and also
it looks behind it real quick and
they're like oh god what is it and so
you start to create a mental model of
what you think is happening based off of
whatever you're seeing it's not based
necessarily a fact but you need to
inform yourself if they actually gonna
take next and so you might be like oh no
is there a mouse even though it's just a
can cats are just weird they do what
they want
and this is really important for the web
because there's so many different screen
sizes when I first started making
websites is so awesome because it's like
800 by 600 go we're good but now it's
just impossible to create one experience
for one screen size and so you're gonna
often have a lot of stuff that's off
screen they're going to need to let the
user know that exists so these are a
couple examples from Google material
design and in this first example you can
see that when the user taps on the name
it reloads a new page now this is fine
when it's just one into like one
situation like that but imagine if you
keep going down a rabbit
and you don't understand where you are
so in the second example which is using
animation to help connect that context
when you click on the name is actually
showing where that content is coming
from and so you just already start to
know where you need to go back to in
this last strategy is called color
response so this is really important
because let's say you're driving a car
you accelerate and the car goes faster
you brake and the car goes slower but
imagine if you've never had an odometer
and how scary that would be because you
would press the pedal you're like I
think it's gonna stop or you know you
might be accelerating and this is really
important for animation because you can
really provide feedback so let's say
someone submits a form you can let them
know what the current status is the
outcome and then what the future status
is with using all these parameters we
can or these strategies rather we can
really start to make a more functional
web and so when we start to want to
incorporate these into our work and
making sure we're using it for good and
not evil we need to identify the
problems that animation can solve so the
first problem that we can solve is I
need to demonstrate the functionality of
a new product and I think oftentimes the
way that people approach this is they'll
either have like a video where you can
see all the different features or they
have a bunch of documentation in this
example by chase they actually have an
entire pop-up that blocks the navigation
and the content and even more
interesting and I would love to know
someone who works here they have a CTA
that says see a slide show like someone
would actually want to see a slide show
about more of the features but it's one
way to execute it now a better way to
execute it is to use animation and so go
ahead and play this is a website for
MailChimp but MailChimp does is a
software that sends email campaigns and
they're promoting a new integration for
Facebook ad campaigns so as you're
scrolling down the page you can see that
they do have a video where you can
actually see the whole process but if
you're not convinced there they can
actually show you just little bits of
animation coupled with text to show you
what this functionality looks like
they're removing the non-essential
content and they're keeping these
animations really short so you're not
going to
there and watch the whole thing another
example is zoom care zoom care is
actually a convenient care clinic in the
States and so if you were to fall on a
sidewalk in the United States
you'd want to go to zoom care and they
would help you and so the way that this
one works they wanted to promote their
app app and as you scroll down you can
see that they're giving some like little
bits of information but what's really
cool is that they're actually fixing the
mobile device and as you scroll each
different feature they go ahead and show
you in the app what that looks like and
this is really great because it's
breaking this content into smaller
digestible pieces and they're placing
the words really close to the animation
that demonstrates it so let's go on to
another problem I have a shopping cart
on my website and I think often websites
what they do is that you're on a product
page and you go ahead and add to cart
and then they actually bring you to a
whole nother page and this is just rep
t'v because they're not really
encouraging to buy more products they
might recommend different products but
still it's not it's not keeping you an
experience where as one of my favorite
t-shirt sites once you go ahead and add
to the shopping cart a drawer will be
revealed and it shows you where that
shopping cart is located and then if you
go up to the shopping cart icon it will
actually close it again they have the
same animation on the menu as well to
keep it consistent so you start to
remember you start to learn and you
start to anticipate these actions let's
look a little closer at icons so when
they're inactive they're like the
standard shopping Hut icon that's very
recognizable same with the hamburger
menu but when you hover over it it shows
you the direction that it's going to go
and then when it's active and you want
to close it it shows you that arrow as
well and so those cues for interaction
are really important because it's your
not going to want to you want people to
understand where these things are thar
off campus and the last problem that
we're going to solve I need to let the
user know that an action is taking place
behind the scenes and so let's say you
have a form submit or you're trying to
load screens in an app common thing is
to just create a standard loading gift
now this is fine
but if your process is going to take any
more than 4 SEC's
people are going to get so frustrated
with you especially if you use a loading
gift like this because anybody who's
this Mac it knows what this means is
like the wheel of death and so you want
to make it a little bit more like a
progress bar right so you could
virtually visually confirm what's
happening behind the scenes so you can
tell them where they've been what's
currently happening what's about to
happen and according to studies it feels
twelve percent faster even if it is the
same amount of time another thing that's
been really like popular these days is
skeleton screens and it's interesting
because there's actually like
conflicting information about a lot of
people think it feels a lot faster
because you're giving a hint of the
content to come so you know what to
anticipate but some people find it
distracting because it's a new pattern
that's just starting to emerge and so I
bet that you know a couple months down
the line when more apps are using this
it's gonna feel more intuitive to the
user and it's gonna feel a lot faster
and so those are all really great
executions of it but I think as
developers we have a hard time bringing
it back to practice at our workspaces
and so for this next part I'd like to go
over some steps that helped me bring it
to my work common challenges that I
think a lot of us have our time creating
animations seems really time-consuming
and often times they come in late in the
process and we don't feel like we have
enough time to give it its due diligence
establishing process to create that
language between you and the designers
or any of the strategists can be
complicated and also skill there's so
much to learn and so many different
options for it and it can be a little
intimidating so the first step is to
start the discussion about animation
early in the process oftentimes people
treat animation as decoration and so it
comes like at the very end like ooh we
should make the hover state of a CTA
animated or oh we have a form submit we
should probably create an animated gif
but you really want to couple it as far
in advance as possible but definitely
after you start to talk about the
animation or information architecture
and start asking those questions like
what can animation help solve the second
step is to use storyboards
to brainstorm ideas quickly now this is
that pretty but this is a real thing
that I've used to be able to create an
animation what's nice about it when you
bring something to pen and paper is this
disposable you don't get attached to it
like you would if you created a
prototype right away and it's really
easy to a bunch of ideas out and to be
able to work with others on it once you
and the team feels really good about
that
you can go ahead and create a prototype
or motion mock-up and that could be a
really good base of discussion because
it's actually animated there's a couple
of different tools that are really
awesome for this
the first tool framer and principal are
kind of more drag-and-drop so they're
really great for like standard
animations and they have a lower entry
point so like your designers can work in
it as well however if you need to do
something that's really custom you might
want to look into something like green
sock JavaScript which is amazing but it
is you know it does require
understanding JavaScript for me I just
like opening up a code pen and creating
a pen I think it's really nice to be
able to have all that code there and
then to sit with the designers and
strategists and kind of noodle with it
and make sure that the duration is good
the timing is good etc the next step
once you guys feel really good about
where the animation is is want to test
test and test some more and there's two
components to this the first is you want
to ask people who have not seen the
animation before a couple questions one
is it legible and that's not even just
text but like do you understand what's
going on and second how does it make you
feel you can really understand a lot
about if they're animation is creating
anxiety or is creating calm or how that
feels by asking that question and these
questions are really important because
the more you work with animation the
more you're going to start to think that
it's too slow because you already know
what's gonna say and then secondarily if
people are you know not sure if they
want to animate something a B test to
validate those decisions v once you
actually decide to ship go ahead and
document those designs design design
decisions in your digital style guide so
if you have a digital style guide which
you should you can go ahead and document
those decisions in it it's really
important
when you do this to show what you have
done in what you've already tried and
you don't want to do that'll help
other developers in the future make good
decisions you also want to provide code
snippets that include the duration
easing and timing because that's going
to help make the animations a lot more
efficient when they build new modules
and then you also want to establish
naming conventions it's you know how
messy it can get if everyone's on the
same page but especially with animation
to create classes that are meaningful
will help a lot
and then lastly keep learning and have
fun here's a lot of resources that I've
used to help educate me and I'll be
putting these slides online so don't
worry about like keeping track of that
and that's it for me