hi everybody well that was loud I know
the schedule says awesomer MVC with 0
CSS but I called an audible on my on my
talk so we're going to be talking about
why rjs today a new library that
provides inversion of control
aspect-oriented programming and a lot of
other stuff to help you bootstrap kick
off and write apps in a very structured
way in JavaScript so if you were here
this morning for John hands talk on
modules you probably saw this little app
here pirate script or noob script where
you can pick which one you think is more
piratey we'll go with this one hey all
right play our little game here all
right I got them both right and so
you've probably built an app that sort
of looks similar to that under the hood
and it probably looks something like
this you've got on the front end you've
got some views you've got a controller
so we're managing those guys you've got
some models that are accessing some data
and all those are communicating with one
another but who creates those things
those are the application who creates
the controller the controller creates
the views who creates the models if the
controller who creates the controller if
the controller creates the models who
who does all that
that a little smaller so one thing you
can do and you've probably done this and
I've done it is you write some piece of
code that you load the whatever
mechanism and it does all of that for
you you write programmatic code to new
your controller new your views hand them
to the controller new your models do all
of that stuff set everything up set it
all in motion and then your code looks
like this and everything's good except
you kind of keep doing that over and
over for every page in your application
and every application you're right and
it always kind of goes the same way you
create some views you create a
controller you create some modules you
realize that I should have done it in
this order because hey I can do a bunch
of this stuff before damas the DOM is
ready so i can give the user a better
experience so i can do some x hr's
pulling some data all right let's
refactor all right first we'll load some
models will wait for Dom ready we'll
create some views will create a
controller ah I could create the
controller before dawn ready to okay we
refactor again we load some more models
we create a controller crap my
controller expected my views in the
constructor so I've got to refactor my
controller oh geez okay I do all of this
I debug I fix all the errors finally I
have a running app right no I get a
blank page so I debug again I fix all of
those errors and then I'm fed up right I
do I'm doing all this just so I can run
my app not this is not really my appt at
all and even if you're writing a single
page application and you only have to
write one loader well so you think
you're probably going to want to
structure your applications so that you
have if it's a single page app you have
different areas of your application that
the user can navigate to and you don't
want to load all of that in the
beginning so you have a user preferences
area that has a few tabs some HTML
templates for each of the tabs some
JavaScript driving at all you don't
really want to load that at least
most of the time until the user actually
needs it because how often do users
change their preferences maybe once then
they first log in so you go and you
write some code to load your user
preferences and create all the objects
and set the whole thing in motion and it
looks kinda like this so you do it all
over again and then you have another
section of your application and you do
it all over again and you write this
same code over and over even though it's
a single page app and not only do you
have to create it all you have to clean
it all up when the user clicks save or
cancel in their preferences you have to
destroy all those Dom nodes that you
created get it off the screen free all
your objects you know make the browser
happy don't keep it all around so can we
automate or make this process easier how
can we do that and that's what why rjs
aims to do it aims to allow you to
declaratively specify what your
controller is what your views are what
your models are what Dom nodes you need
other things like what events should be
hooked up between your view and your
controller so the controller can respond
to actions that the user takes in the
view and it allows you to do that all
declaratively you don't have to worry
about the order you don't have to worry
about when Dom ready happens why I was
going to figure all of that out for you
assemble it all into a running
application kick it off
so you write a JavaScript object literal
or you know Jason like spec that wire
assembles into a running app or a
running section of your app for you and
manages that so that you can then
destroy it with a single line of code
later so these are the things that wire
does we already mentioned component
lifecycle management it also provides
dependency injection including Dom nodes
so if you have a view that you want to
create in wire and it needs a dom node a
Dom container where it's going to put at
HTML you can hand that Dom node to the
view in the wire spec and again wire
will work out the order of things it
provides a set of connectors which allow
you to hook up your objects to one
another hook your views up to your
controllers hook your models up to your
views hook plain old objects up to each
other and it provides some
aspect-oriented programming we'll take a
look at that a little bit later so why
are managers life cycles by allowing you
to create configure initialize and
destroy components and it does this
through a plug-in architecture so that
you can do this with any type of object
it supports plain JavaScript objects out
of the box but it comes with a plug-in
now that allows you to do this with
digits so that if you don't want to use
dojo type in your HTML to create digits
you can create them in wire and it will
create them for you and then clean them
up when you when you want the to destroy
that section of your application you
could also there'll be plugins coming
for jQuery since jQuery widgets are sort
of non-standard JavaScript objects they
you have to create them through the
widget factory and you have to destroy
them through the jQuery API so you can't
just knew a JavaScript object so that
can be handled through wire plugins also
so remember that user preferences screen
that we had to write a loader for to
bring it into existence set up all the
events we had to knew all the the the
views and the controller hook them up
and then remember to destroy it all when
we're done you can wire that whole thing
into existence with one line of code you
write a spec for it wire it into
existence wire will manage all of that
for you hook it all up the user
interacts with it and then when the user
is done they click save or cancel in
your spec you've hooked up that save or
cancel event to your controller your
controller then destroys the wired
container and all of that stuff goes
away but isn't this when we're talking
about dependencies so if we have a view
that depends on some data isn't this
what we already talked about when we
talk about an AMD loader yes and no
we're going to divert just a second and
talk about why that's the case good
software is built on abstractions we
know this we'd like to be able to write
generic components that can be
configured to solve this problem in a
specific situation for us so we don't
have to write that component over and
over and over and over again and if you
do that you can mix and match them dojo
data stores are a good example of this
they provide a JSON rest or they provide
a memory store and they provide a
standard API for accessing those get put
add remove they also provide some
decorators that allow you to do caching
allow you to observe new objects being
added to the store
in your in your application so you can
react to that display a new item in the
list and the reason this all works is
because they created a standard API that
matches what we expect from a rest
endpoint so you could with this API
design of you that's very generic and
could draw its data from a rest endpoint
or from a memory store for testing or
maybe you have some data that you just
want to you don't need to fetch it from
from a rest store it's a small amount of
data like you know name prefixes mr.
mrs. things like that it's not going to
change so you just use a memory store
for that you could design a view that
could use either of those or any
combination of those things and so
really there are many kinds of
dependencies there are integral
dependencies which your component just
simply can't function without these it
needs these exact things and AMD is
really good and other module loaders
dependency managers are really good at
solving that problem those are also
required dependencies it just can't work
without those but then there also a set
of configurable dependencies like a data
store you might want to point a data
store at this rest endpoint or you might
want to use a memory store and you might
want to hand either one of those to a
view you don't want to specify that data
store as a dependency in your module
dependencies because then you can't use
that component anywhere else and then
there are optional dependencies your
component may behave in one way if you
give it some extra information but maybe
that information is a isn't available or
you don't need it in a particular
situation so you'd like your component
to still function but maybe in a more
limited way and that's perfectly
reasonable so there are optional
dependencies module loaders don't
necessarily solve the configurable and
optional dependencies problem they
certainly solve the integral and
required dependencies problem
and this is the whole one of the holes
that why rjs fills it allows you to
inject specific dependencies concrete
dependencies the actual objects that are
going to be used when the application
runs for the specific situation that you
need so if you have a view you want to
use multiple times you want to give it
different kinds of data just instantiate
three copies of it and inject the data
stores that each one needs so for
example let's take a look at what that
looks like
this is actually code from the pirate
script or nude script application and
this is a wire spec this is what you
would write to bring all the components
of your application together you'll
notice that it itself is an AMD module
but it's just basically a JavaScript
object literal and you can see down here
at the bottom we're declaring that hey
I've got a view called codes view it's
comes from this AMD module instantiate
me one of these I want to pass it it's I
want to pass its constructor a dom node
that i'm going to query for it has the
class codes container which might return
many but i want the first one I've got
heading view which was up at the top you
saw the pictures of the Pirates that
comes that's going to instantiate this
AMD module called Hayt heading view
again we're going to hand at a dom node
I've got some results that we're going
to put in this results container but
notice there's no results view here we
don't need that when we start we'll see
how that happens later and then we've
got our controller and it's a pirate
script controller and we're going to
create it we're going to call its
constructor with no arguments and then
we're going to set a bunch of properties
on it and if you're familiar with JSON
referencing the syntax dollar ref this
is wire uses Jason referencing syntax so
what we're saying is there's a coat
underscore codes view property on the
controller and hey make it point to this
view up here that we just created so I'm
wiring in the views the codes view some
data a node that the controller is going
to manage for the whole application and
and some data turns and thresholds up
here so these can be just plain old
JavaScript objects if you want they can
be arrays they can be value
they can be strings they can be whatever
you want but wire is going to create all
of this it's going to manage the order
of creating these views it's going to
make sure the dom is ready before it
creates this view and before it hands it
to the controller because the controller
can't really do anything with it until
the view is ready and the view can't be
ready until the dom is ready and i just
mentioned that the ordering very
important wire takes care of that for
you if you notice you could move this
stuff around in this spec and the
application would still work so you
don't have to think about it I'll take
this controller and put it up here
Oh
let's just lent that real quick oh haha
all right let's reload oh no anyway must
have it comma to have a comment there
anyway I might worry about commas right
now okay so you have component a that
needs component of B that needs
component C D and E and C needs a dom
node normally you'd have to think about
that you would have to write the code
create the objects in the right order
access the Dom use your Dom ready
function put the right set of code
inside of that Dom ready call back make
sure you've got your variable scope
correctly for all of that you don't need
to worry about that here just declare
what you need and wire will make it
happen when it needs to happen
connectors is the next thing that wire
offers and these are when you draw a box
in line diagram these are the lines
these are just as important how your
components communicate are just as
important as the components themselves
and wire offers a couple of these out of
the box you can inject dependencies
directly so that objects get references
to other objects and you can call
methods on them that's one type of
connector but that's pretty tight
tightly coupled but sometimes you need
it it's less tightly coupled and
actually creating the object inside
you're inside your component and then
you're using it because here you could
swap different ones in but you can also
hook up events and pub sub and wire does
this through plugins right now it
supports dojo so it actually has a
plug-in that when you use the wire event
connector and you're using the dojo
plug-in it's using dojo connect under
the under the scenes same with pub sub
if you do pub sub and even you use the
dojo plugin it's going to use dojo pub
sub so you're integrating with if you're
already using dojo
pub sub you can leverage that you don't
have another pub sub system to take care
of and work with
and lastly it provides aspect-oriented
programming also through a plug-in and
if you're not familiar with aop it's a
way that you can augment and customize
the functionality of existing components
maybe you wrote maybe you didn't write
without actually modifying the source
code it allows you to add aspects to
components some examples of those you
can apply decorators you can add advice
before after around you can introduce
mix-ins in the fly introduce new methods
introduce new interfaces into an object
and you know these are all useful in
various specific situations one the sort
of canonical aop example is adding
logging to some component that you don't
have access to all right that's great
but it's kind of boring so more fun is
to take dojos Jason rest or write
yourself a validating decorator for it
that uses JSON schema use wire to inject
the schema into your decorator and then
apply your decorator to dojos Jason rest
or and then inject that store into your
controller all without changing any of
the code in Jason restore or your
controller so let's see what some of
this stuff looks like so we already saw
this example this is from pirate script
or noob script and here's another
example that I've pulled from an
application where wire is being used
it's going to be a production
application and some pieces of this I'm
using some wire plugins this is just an
array there's nothing special about it
why are just notices that hey these
modules are plugins as it loads them and
instantiate them as plugins so in this
app we're going to have some we're going
to have some data stores we've got a
JSON rest or that points to some people
and hey we're going to decorate that
with this and what is this well up here
in the wire aop module we're declaring
some decorators we're saying hey there's
a caching decorator and it is going to
use dojos cashing store we've got a
validating decorator that we wrote
ourselves so down here we're going to
apply a validating decorator to the JSON
rest or that we're creating for people
and we're going to hand it a schema that
we're loading here this is AMD module
AMD loading we're loading a schema
handing it to our decorator and then
applying the decorator to the Jason rest
or all without changing any of those in
the JSON dress store we've got another
store for occupations and hey we're
going to use a caching decorator here
because I know that these occupations
just don't change very very often so
while the users logged in I don't care
you know i'm just going to present them
always with the same set of occupations
so we apply a caching decorator and
we're going to use the dojo memory
stored as thick as the backing store for
the cash then we've got some name
prefixes that we're going to load to
this is something else that wire
provides is the notion of reference
resolvers you'll see this in a couple of
places this is resolving a reference to
a rest resource so what this ends up
being is actually another Jason rest
store and this is just shorthand oh it's
not going to be a jason rusch store i'm
sorry it's going to create a Jason rest
or issue a query on it and return a
promise so that when that when that data
comes back from the server name prefixes
is going to be the actual data not a
store and that's fine because that's
what I need I need the prefixes I don't
need the store here we're going to
create a view hand at a Dom reference
and then we're going to create a
controller from our our application
going to set some properties on it we're
going to hand our stores to our
controller because we want our
controller to be managing the data not
the view the controller can decide how
to hand that data to the view and then
we're going to apply an event connector
this is one of wires supported
connectors and up at the top we're using
the dojo events plugin so this is going
to use dojo connect to do this operation
so you know you could load the jQuery
events plugin and it would use jQuery to
do this so what this is saying is I want
to connect person views on save event to
the controller's handle save person
method so you can imagine when the user
clicks the Save button in the view the
view fires a non-save event and the
controller's handles save method gets
gets called same thing with with on
cancel cause the controller's handle
cancel method and what's interesting
here is if you were writing this app
yourself without wire or maybe with a
framework or something like that you
might be tempted to actually give a
reference of the view to the controller
and have it do that but the controller
really doesn't care it doesn't need to
have a reference to the view all it
really needs to know is when the data
was either saved or canceled so here we
can avoid that very loose coupling we
just care about the events we don't care
about the reference itself about the
view itself
and that's it that's why rjs you can
find it on github the currently released
version like I said supports dojo
through set of plugins there'll be
jQuery plugins coming soon and if you've
heard a lot of the talk about modules at
this this conference wire works really
well with modules and AMD so if you're
using AMD or you want to use AMD that's
another reason to check out why rjs