thanks everyone coming out I
that I was recently working on that I
was meant to solve a lot of like the
nitty-gritty annoying stuff that I have
to deal with on a day-to-day basis when
it comes to making projects go live so
one of the gentlemen here asked me you
know what is the dsl what does dsl stand
for its domain specific language so what
I saw to do was write a custom language
that could describe and solve the
problems that I was facing on like day
to day basis so this all began with a
realization that i had that dad but this
is a villain programming is fun but
deployment it's not so much fun this is
when it comes to making a project go
live i found myself constantly running
into the same things again and again i
would zip up the project i'll copy
remotely i would ssh into the remote
machine somewhere unzip it run a setup
script do a health check and then repeat
and it got to the point where i just
thought to myself what if I could just
automate all of this so I thought about
the problem a lot and I came to a
solution that had two main pieces one is
a background process running on the
remote machine that would it would hook
into native file system events and then
one a change event was fired it would
look at a file that was recently added
search for a zip file unzip it and then
run a setup script the reason you would
need to have something remotely is
because without it you would have to do
a lot of manual things you'd have to ssh
directly in and run all the commands
which is something I'm sure many of you
have already done but I wanted to avoid
doing it because I just thought it was a
pain and as a developer I try to make my
life as easy as possible and as lazy as
possible so that's kind of where this
came from the second part is the setup
script itself which is basically a list
of instructions that would unbundle the
project and get it up and running so
just real quickly the demon process
itself for it to be consistent I thought
that the best way to do it was to have a
landing zone
then call a landing zone a directory
that was watched and whenever a file was
added it would look for a zip file unzip
it and then run the setup script a set
of script is where the dsl actually
comes in and it's where i decided to
have a little fun so this is the good
stuff now i could have easily placed a
shell script into the packaging call
today but i saw this as an opportunity
to write my own language and I took it
for science so why even do this at all
why even like constructed dsl is because
every project I would ever need to work
on would require a different setup a
different environment different entry
point so why not come up with a way to
extract all that way so I came up with
this is a very simple language now I'm
not going to spend time going into the
everything into the structure everything
about the structure and implementation
of computer programming computer
programming languages because there are
literally entire libraries folder things
that I don't know but what I do know for
sure is that to transform any language
to run on a machine you need a compiler
so I wrote myself a toy compiler to make
sure that this language ran and did what
I wanted it to do so just to take you
through some of the basics so dave told
me that a lot of you guys are mid-level
and beyond so i don't i'm not going to
spend too much time on like the
nitty-gritty of what's going on but
every compiler has three basic parts and
you have the lexer the parser and the
evaluator the lexer is usually broken up
into something called a scanner and a
tokenizer but depending on which
distribution in which library or which
compiler you're using sometimes the
things are merged together sometimes
they're not I chose to write a separate
scanner and a separate tokenizer and
i'll go into what these things actually
do I know so the scanner is what breaks
the body of language into into lexemes
which are the basic building blocks of a
languages syntax so just as an example
you have just a snippet from the setup
script that I have
a task called task name and then its
commands so the leg seems there would be
just the string literal text and task
name colon left parentheses a newline
character and then whatever the sooner
shell script was the tokenizer reads
each like semen adds metadata and this
metadata is what corresponds to the
actual grammar of the language this is
important because the form that a
language takes and its structure are
actually two different things like try
to come up with a good example for this
and so if I was to use the English
sentence I went to the store english
grammar would break it down as subject
verb object so if I was to break it up
into lexemes the lexemes would be I went
and then to the store whereas the
metadata attached to them would be I
comma subject went comma verb and to the
store comma object so that's how you see
the grammar tied to the individual
lexemes and this becomes important later
on when you parse them into a meaningful
structure because the tokens don't
actually have any meaning by themselves
they only have meaning in the context of
other tokens so there's this kind of
like just alt aspect to something that I
found really cool when I was writing
this now the parser is what provides
that context it takes the tokens and
derives what program is called semantic
meaning and without I'm trying to throw
as little jargon at you as possible but
basically this is like what I was saying
before that each token can only have
real value when interpreted in the
context of other tokens so the parser
behaves more or less like a state
machine which is something I'm about to
go into but just to see now I totally
understand if I just throw a bunch of
code at you like it won't really make
any sense so please feel free to ask me
to clarify any of this stuff afterward
I'm trying to do the best kind of tie
together the project that I build and
things that would make sense the
presentation now the same machine is
what actually constructs the context and
this
an example of the same machine now there
are third-party libraries that make a
state graph and basically why this is
important because you could have two
different lexemes of the same type just
to show you an example if I was to go to
the example of the language right here
like you'll see that task name and echo
are both strings but they have different
meaning in that task name is declaring a
task and echo is a component of a task
and the way you can differentiate that
is through the state whereas as the
parser is parsing this file the state
changes when it encounters this left
parenthesis and that's just one example
of how the state graph allows you to
build a complex contextual structure
from small building blocks so the last
part of this is the evaluator which
takes the syntax tree which is right
here and evaluates it into actual
meaningful code that can be run by the
machine now most compilers transform the
language of native machine code that
much was overkill for what I was doing I
really just wanted a wrapper for shell
scripts so the evaluator it takes this
syntax tree and just runs it as a
combination of selling of shell scripts
in order and i'm going to show you an
example of that right now so i'm not
sure if you guys can see this can you
guys see it no you go about now tell me
to stop
how many of you were able to see my
slides there about get that that's okay
so I was like this is rich either really
deep where people cannot understand what
I'm saying okay well if you have any
questions anything oh I hope you can
hear me at least please ask questions
but anyway this is the setup script you
can see very simple syntax you declare
using the colon and then you put the
body of the Declaration inside the curly
brackets you can invoke any task by
using a semicolon so this is a basic one
where just echoes two lines it runs NPM
install it goes another line it runs a
setup JS file and then prints a little
line to the console so let's see what
actually happens here can you guys you
think cool don't don't cheat we go boom
there we go now npm failed because the
package Jace I don't think is valid but
when you can see is that it printed
these lives to the console and you see
this line right here where it says it
worked this is actually a line inside
the project boom which on its surface
it's like yeah this is really simple but
this is this is something that could be
uploaded to any machine anywhere in the
world and the script would be run
without ever having to SSH into this
machine without ever having to do
anything manually the language of the
compiler take care of all this stuff for
you I've managed to use this to great
success and it helped me be as lazy as
possible when I was programming which is
great so that is my entire process from
beginning to end so you might be asking
like again like why would you do this
well one course for fun too you could
say you could say doctor could be used
for something like this and dr. I'm a
big fan of Doctor I use it at work and
at home all the time but I found dr. and
production to be kind of unstable the
doctor demon shuts down randomly
sometimes once you opt in a doctor you
opt into dr. machine and dr. Campos
dr. swarm and all the stuff which isn't
terrible but it's also not a reason to
completely ignore a side project like
this because you could run the demon
process right alongside dr. inside the
container and have it do all the stuff
that are already knows yeah ship it is
another library I've used in the past so
JavaScript ssh client you can do
anything that you could do with normal
ssh but you still have to do it manually
which is something i was trying to avoid
and if there are others please let me
know i'm always looking for ways to
improve right now sorry there's still a
couple things that I have to do to make
this a complete project one is having a
proper recursive grammar what that means
is having a grammar that can refer to
its own components an example of this
was if you were to define a task in
terms of strings string would be one
component and then a task declaration
would be parentheses plus string +
parentheses that way it kind of refers
to itself that is something that every
proper programming language has or
something that I'm probably going to
build out at some point built-in
commands as I was using this kind of
wish there was a way to set the
environment just by using a command like
set the environment to node 5.4 or
something like that and lastly a client
to talk to the demon process that way
you know whether everything has worked
because if you have to SSH into figure
out everything happened then kind of
defeats the entire purpose but yeah
there's a lot more stuff to do and if
there's anything else that you think
needs to be added please fork the
project or get in touch with me I'd love
to hear anything that you guys have to
say here we go let's open the floor
test of people now the name of the
project is is view ha it's view ha dash
demon but yeah it's it's v kashti view
house actually it's a Sanskrit word that
means formation and it's kind of what
those set up scripts are it's like a
loose abstract definition of a project
all right have you thought about other
potential applications for this type of
new programming language here oh yeah
totally uh well it can be used for
basically anything so the language
itself can be used to describe anything
that you could break down into a series
of tasks the parser itself is geared
toward bash commands but that isn't
something that set in stone off the top
of my head could be anything from I
don't tallying up your budget like what
you're spending money on it could be
anything that you do want like a
day-to-day basis like shopping for
groceries good if you have like the IOT
set up in your home you could like turn
on lights stuff like that really the
sky's the limit but I mean yeah anything
that you could break down into a series
of commands you have to repeat over and
over this would be ideal for me so you
see we actually use dr. to gain your
eyes your infrastructure and have the
beautiful of a structure and all that
containers and with your bad experience
with dr. compose and other
infrastructure of ecosystem tools of dr.
I have you turned away from the whole
containerization approaching
i early or are you still on that and
just using alternative tools to make it
happen I don't think you can turn away
from containerization because there's a
lot more that containers do to to to
stabilize an isolated particular
environment like docker containers like
is an entire file system this was to
facilitate prototyping projects mainly
but if you're going to run a process
inside a container this would be ideal
for that so Dan's answer your question I
would not turn away from dr completely
but I would not use docker to prototype
doing that in the past has led to like
lots of frustration sorry any plan do
you have any digression p.m. to or
implanted in great confusion p.m. with
the process management dr offender
that's a good question p.m. to so i've
used no tamale no demon p.m. 2 i'm not
sure doesn't hook into the file system
profile system events aight i mean i
could totally see some kind of like
cross play in the future I haven't
looked into p.m. to in association with
this yet so 470 totally please it says
it on the slide no by all means please
get in touch please fork any last
questions ok give it up
you
I've been seeing a lot of rainbows
lately like everywhere not just in opals
glitters or those reflective signs but
when I squint my eyes look at my hair or
glance out the window for some reason
the more I find them the more I am able
to find them it's weird how this works
this mysterious cycle of rainbow
spotting it does work though and I'm
sure of it because even now I can see it
on my screen or on the edge of any of
those lights this is a place when I go