[Music]
welcome everybody thanks for coming
this is the talk your credit card was
made with JavaScript this is me my
handle on all sorts of wherever social
media Twitter sort of stuff and where I
work and where we created a or produced
a smart card that goes on credit cards
for ever for this was post and in the
process of doing that we didn't just
produce the the module we also did the
entire integration for this for this
product which included writing the
programs for the machines that actually
produce the cards later on and those
programs are written in JavaScript so
this talk is a bit of a curiosity I
guess most of you won't be programming
credit cards or personalized and credit
cards so it's sort of hard for me and
sorry it's a brother abstract topic
there's a lot of bits and bytes and it's
kind of boring
so I want to try to get get you guys a
general feeling I think you know some
people are interested in in smart cards
what all this is about how these things
work to just get a general feeling of
how the smart cards work have a look at
that at these api's that are used on on
the machines and there's an there's
actually an open source implementation
that you can that you can run on a
normal laptop which you could use with
just a normal reader to just look into
your cards to see what they're actually
doing and how they work so this is more
of a preparation for you know maybe
hacking a little bit with with the smart
cards that you guys have in your pockets
so basically when I when I said your
credit card is made with JavaScript
we're talking about these things the
the card number that's that's punched
into the card the magstripe data that's
prepared the CVV that's that's that's
calculated and put onto the back of the
card and all of the keys and stuff that
are inside of the that are started
inside of the chip and if there's any
questions you can feel free to just
interrupt or if I'm going too fast or
too slow
[Music]
one of the main so this is the next
several slides are going to be just sort
of in general what smart cards are how
they work and one of the main
misconceptions is that even with the
with the magstripe is that sort of when
you take your card put it in the ATM the
ATM reads the PIN or whatever off of the
mag stripe and then you types of painin
and it compares the two and that the
that the that the chip basically does
the same it's just a store of data but
the chip is really a full computer on
the on the card so what typically
happens and said that the data is
exchanged you have these keys in the
card and that are part that are specific
to your card and they can find
themselves into the into the into the
chip this is when the chips in the
factory being produced and when the
merchant who accepts your card what they
will do is they will they will give the
card some data that they want signed
from the card and just like in your
computer there's a little man inside of
it that can calculate and he has access
to the to the keys and he can he can
generate a cryptogram which then the
merchant can use to prove towards the
credit card organizations that yes
did actually have this person in my
store doing this transaction
[Music]
so again just getting going across some
of the things that if you ever want to
play around with this stuff and it's
fairly easy to play around with that you
know that you need to sort of have heard
and this is gonna be really quick the
whole thing is seven eight one six those
are just the ISO norms that do
everything with with chip cards and this
is chip cards in general it's not
specific to credit cards the one in two
is really low physical layer we're
talking centimeters how how big the
little module is and where it is on a
card and fault and and what the
different pads on the thing mean level
three is sort of this in between type of
thing this is one of the few pictures
and one of the nice elements in the and
the specification suite where it's a
little bit higher up it's on an on a
signal level of how to communicate with
the card if anybody does anything with
with hardware it's it's it's basically
just a UART you could just connect an
rs-232 serial cable to it to a card and
talk to it if you get voltages right
there's only two three terms though out
of this that you would ever come across
and that you know you need to know it's
T equals zero T equals one those are
different modes of communication to the
card and the only thing you need to know
about those is that nobody ever uses T
equals one and hgri TR is the thing that
the card sends back to you to identify
itself and that you can identify the
card with when you get one and this next
level four is the area where it gets
interesting and this is what we're also
going to see when we when we look at
these when we look at these api's these
are the APD use APD use or sort of the
frames and they're anything from sort of
an IP frame all the way to an HTTP
request/response
pair
they're very reduced but these are all
these define how to talk with the card
on a on an application layer their
commands that you sent to the card and
this is what a what a pack of like that
looks like you start off it's it's
always four bytes the first quite is the
class which is sort of metadata about
this will the payload be encrypted is
this a is this an iso standardized
command things like that the second one
is the actual command that's that that's
being performed that could be something
like select a file or an application on
the card or I want to give you I want to
present you a pin for me to to verify
for me then p1 and p2 are parameters for
the command and then optionally you can
send data then you do an LC where you
would say how many bytes of data you
send and then the bytes that you send
and if you want the command to answer
back you would you would send le the
length of the expected data that you
sent back so the way this okay well you
can skip over these bits I think there's
different sorts of files that the whole
thing defines and the files can be more
or less anything they just have names
but the way that they can either be a
big chunk of data they can be variable
or fixed length records they can be
circular buffers so to be a little bit
more concrete how this how this works
this would be an APU that a terminal
sends to to a card and so it starts the
first bit the clasp is 0 the instruction
is a 4 that means select select an
application on the card the parameter of
for that bit set says selected by name
please share 0 and then I tell it I have
to tell it the name that I want to
select so I'm going to send it e eb hex
e that's up 14 bytes and that last bit
if you
you're gonna ASCII and hex it's called
it's one basis DDF or one that's what
all credit cards basically happens there
base application what everybody starts
out so lightly and what you get back is
the response code says word one says for
two usually you will you would want 9000
9000 as sort of the is sort of the 200
okay of the smart card world 61 is sort
of a almost okay but I can't there's
some technical problems that the card
can send back data in response to a
command that sent it data so this it's
it's a bit of a problem so the 61 says I
would like to send you back data it's
technically not possible though but
there's 12 hex bytes of data I want to
send you back so the next command and
these are the only two commands don't
worry that I'm I'm going to show C 0 is
a get response it doesn't take any
parameters it doesn't have any data that
it sends but it says I'm expecting
12-day 12 bytes of data back from you
and in that case the the card responds
with with the data and the all this data
is tag length value people know deal
with its darren coded if people deal
with SSL you might have heard of it so
this is a tag this 6f byte says the
following data is 6f data and 6f happens
to be file meta information
there'll be hex 10 bytes of it because
the first two bytes already taken up by
the tagging at length the next this is a
tag again and it's it's file name and
we're back at the file name it was a
bytes long that says one paces block and
the 9000 that
okay is at the end good so this level
four thing these APD use and files and
things that you can do are sort of like
XML they define a lot of building blocks
that you can use to make a file format
but if you just like someone tells you
oh it's XML you don't really know
anything about the file format you just
know that that's the building blocks
that they're set up on so there's a
bunch of application where there's a
bunch of higher higher layered
specifications that say well what do how
do we put these building blocks together
to make a contactless payment
application or a something to use that
the photocopier or something like that
EMV is what is the standard
specification or the base specification
for all payment protocols these are
master and different payment schemes
make their own and they basically define
make their own and they're based on EMV
though and they define specifics of how
terminals talk to the cards how ATMs
talk to the cards and things like that
so and finally there's a layer above
that and that's what we're at which is
which defines of how to interact with a
card from the outside and basically
there's it's a very small market these
people making these machines that
personalized cards but everybody thought
of their own way of doing things and at
one point they standardized it and
strangely enough they standardized on on
XML script to do that they also do they
also specify other things that are in
the card but this is only going to be
the scripting language so there's a bit
of it that there's an API that they that
they define and and we're seeing a lot
of the things that we saw
before like the t1 and t0 protocols for
the card the status word 1 status word
of the response there's a Sunday PD you
command to send bytes to the card
it also contains primitives to deal with
cryptography and especially in cases
like this that you you have hardware
security modules where all the keys are
stored in so you need to access those
one of the problematic things of dealing
with these with this sort of data though
and why why JavaScript really isn't a
too good of it all of this was just
bytes and that the PO at the point where
they were there that this was specified
into South 2003 there they roared there
were no WebGL buffers there were no node
buffers there was I'm not really sure
how common joyous deals with character
data so they made up a lot of their own
stuff and there are really heavily
influenced by Java they have two
different ways to deal with these byte
buffers are sort of like Java string
buffers and that you can't really do
anything with them but they're mutable
although what the purpose of having a
mutable data structure when you can't do
in when you can't change it around this
is sort of questionable and on the other
hand the immutable string type has all
these operations but that will keep on
creating new byte strings but that's
sort of the access into the bits and
bytes world there's another problem with
it that all this is there needs to be
XML in this because these are financial
some so they put their best man on on
the job for this and what they came out
up with is this I mean why you don't
really need a pesky function
keyword around and curly braces around
your your script you can just have much
more clear and succinct XML tags wrapped
around your your individual functions
and that makes everything a lot easier
to deal with and it's there's all it's
it's not very pretty
okay that is how far I wanted to go
because I think a lot of these things
that we can if people are interested in
this I think we can get we can we can
play around with these things later what
I was saying that I wanted to do a small
sort of demo this is in case somebody's
interested in trying this stuff out at
home this is the open source
implementation of the JavaScript part of
it and they have a fairly nice yeah do
you know a keyboard to mirror the
displays
[Music]
okay I'm gonna have to sort of scoot
around then I guess
okay I don't have the card reader
plugged in okay so
okay so it recognized the card reader I
can put in I can put in a card now and
[Music]
okay a card object selector
and then I
we sent that with a constant you can
either turn off the electricity and turn
it on again or or not do that we'll turn
it on and off again just for kicks cold
would be you actually cut off the
electricity to the card warmers you just
tell it to reset itself this is the ATR
actually the these bits here of the 3b
and 60 and and are the ATR and this is
sort of this describes the this
describes the card and now well I just
would like to do is what was in the demo
just to like the payment application and
just see how that works so we need to do
one of those five strings and that was
one page one and then you have the way
this works is now you tell it this is
hex or in this case it's not hex its
ASCII that I want the bites of and we
have those bytes again so per se the
length it's 14 that's right
and now I can just do cards and apdu
and that was the class by it is zero the
instruction is select I want to select
this file is a four I want to select it
by name so I do that and then the second
parameter is 0 and finally it has the
utility method it calculates the length
of the data I want to send I just have
to give us the data and I can send that
to it and this is the reply and response
this library takes care of the get
response part all in one go
and this contains more data about the
file than than my example did so what
the only about done the question is be
like what is the practical use of this
on the I guess the main thing is really
just play around with it to see you
canyou can use Java for other stuff I
could imagine having and if you're if
you're doing server-side JavaScript the
actually the only safe way to store SSL
Certificates as is on on smart cards so
this would be nice if and I'm sort of
working on that is that you have a small
FFI binding for for node or something
like that that you can that you can
access cards to store your your SSL
credentials or if you're doing some
local sort of things if you're doing
home banking and you have a local
component that does it that you can you
can sometimes in Germany at least you
need a smart card interaction in order
to authenticate to authenticate your
your your financial transactions that
you want to do and it's just sort of fun
to play around with and unless of course
you have a job doing it and then it's
fun to good so if there's any equal
uestions I think we're yeah
see there the money is not on your
credit card the money is resting in your
account that's the problem you could
break your card with it you can also you
can you can block your cart you can use
it to block your card if you want to do
that if you want to keep the money from
getting off out of your account and then
well in Germany there's a thing called a
guide card where the money is actually
on the on the chip but they say that's
safe and you couldn't ever
no this is not on the card at all this
is just on the side of the computer to
talk to the card but the the set of
commands the the EMB this EMV that they
define the language that's spoken by the
card and that's that's the same on every
card which enables you to you know go to
Saudi Arabia and get money from an ATM
there as well so unless you're in this
unless you go to the states where they
don't have chips it's it's the same
everywhere there's some subtleties it's
not quite true but and it's also the
same when you're doing NFC or
contactless payment then only the the
bottom the physical layer is exchanged
for RFID and everything above that these
apd use and and all of that stays the
same and you would be able to use this
library to talk with the contactless
credit card or an NFC based handy wallet
or something like cellphone wallet or
something like that
okay okay thanks