we are an interesting lot when you look
at the community as a whole we are a
ragtag group of developers designers
noobs and elites we have a sordid
history as one of the greatest
technological battles was played out
across our community and left us in a
wasteland of stagnation for years are
you six big vendors have looted and
plundered our community and we survived
it and some would say we came out even
better for it many of our original
heroes have been lost to legend or have
been scorned by the Dragons they sought
to slay we have seen new leaders rise
with vigor and innovation not seen in
other programming languages we are a
community of rejuvenation of rebuilding
of finding problems addressing them and
fixing them properly we are a community
of developers who prefer j/s but use a
variety of other languages technologies
and tools to accomplish our task we are
at a point of a huge renaissance of
interest excitement and energy and yet I
worry I feel as the drums of war from
the browser vendors continue to be
louder and louder and the rising tide of
interest sweeps back into our community
are we ready for it what will our
community be will we have built
something sustainable or made yet
another flash in the pan technology cult
the new generation of JavaScript you me
those of you at home just watching this
that was supposed to be really exciting
where we have learned from our past or
are we doomed to repeat the exact same
mistakes in the worst possible ways let
us not just begin a discussion today let
us trigger action implement change and
inspire our fellow developers
sustainability should be the most
important goal for the technology
community at large and yet it's never
discussed at a technology conference
tonight we will do more than discuss
chapter one education j/s is not a toy
language you all believe that otherwise
you wouldn't be here the reality that
reality is just now permeating the
general populace and their first
impressions of jas is absolutely abysmal
how many of you know what shows up when
you search for JavaScript and Google
here I'll show you look at the links
Wikipedia w3 schools which hasn't been
updated in a long time and download Java
maybe you're saying to yourself that
JavaScript just that term is too broad
nobody in their right mind when they're
learning a language would just type the
language name so let's you know what go
for something that they would type and
most of us probably have type quite
frequently JavaScript array yeah not
much better the first quality link on
this page is the MDC Doc's link eight
non-existent if you want me to take it a
step further that's actual let's
actually do a query that a first-time
developer would do learn JavaScript the
first link that actually presents proper
JavaScript learning is John Resig at
again position eight and the stuff
that's in there would blow their minds
so this is the first impression of
JavaScript
by the general masses who are coming to
this language and once you see this you
can see why people consider it a toy
language and you can understand why
there is so much horrible JavaScript
code out there and so much disdain for
this language that we've all come here
to talk about we have hidden our better
tutorials our learnings and our dock one
lay a one browser or maybe doesn't
really even execute all and they don't
know how to validate that but it becomes
a close approximation of runnable code
then they publish it back out to the
world proud of what they've done and
continue to perpetuate this plague of
horrible code we have failed our fellow
developers case you didn't notice that
was link 3 on array we have failed our
fellow developers and designers in the
sense we have made it almost impossible
to learn proper JavaScript a language
with both beauty and warts admittedly
some will say it is not our fault the
browser vendors they they should have
provided better API documentation for
their implementations or the standards
committee that's what they're there for
right I am calling on that
tonight I say it is up to us to invite
welcome and properly educate all the new
entrance to JavaScript we are the best
and brightest of this community we have
an obligation to help those who are
trying to learn and understand the
complexities of this language we are the
ones who will benefit the most from it
because you know what most of the people
entering the language right now they're
going to be the ones that are extending
morphing caring feeding and eventually
taking over whatever you're working on
right now regardless of library
framework and even programming language
if everyone knows proper JavaScript
a little bit better we all win period so
i challenge you to put down your library
or your framework preference and write
about some interesting facet about the
jas language describe how you find
attributes on objects describe what the
difference is between an object and
array and how you actually tell the two
apart anything and everything if you
seek fame and click traffic to your blog
right about the entry-level stuff you'll
have fifteen thousand hits in the next
week if you seek it if you seek respect
and deep dialogues right about the
difference between implementations and
methods and convey when do you convey
the wisdom when to use one over the
other if writing is too time-consuming
or your muse escapes you today I'm
announcing a new campaign promote j/s
com the goal of promote guess is this
through pirate technics and guerrilla
SEO we can change how search engines
present answers to common queries about
our language by driving traffic to the
proper documentation we can change
everything we can change and ensure that
people interested in jazz are connected
with the right educational resources the
first target for promote j/s yeah you
guessed it unseat w3schools and put the
proper mdn documentation on the first
hit
quickly I am openly saying to crowd hack
google and i'm giving you the code to do
it when you go to the site see that
little box you copy it in you paste it
on your blog it generates a highly
valuable high-quality SEO content button
that shows you support better
documentation for us by us you paste it
in everyone gets a unique one and it
provides an organic backlink to the
right documentation underneath the right
query strings you don't believe that
this can be done well there's the link
if you need to see it bigger you don't
believe this can be done look at what we
did in the day we took a zero byte vapor
JavaScript framework and we put into the
top of github imagine what we can do in
a week we need to be the voice of
education for our community we need to
promote the proper way of doing things
instead of just ignoring those who don't
get it or watering things down we need
to commit to educating our fellow
developers on Jas the language and in
doing so it helps all other frameworks
every library meetups conferences the
whole shebang promote j/s is a step in
the right direction but it is by no
means the end and we need to do more so
the more of this chapter is the more
people that learn proper jas the better
this community will be chapter to love
the pirate damn the privateers the
technology field has changed
tremendously in the last 20 years and
unfortunately it has become almost
entirely focused on profiteering and
fame we see companies running technology
conferences to profit
selling food in metric tons and
making zealots out of noobs con men
jumped from one hot tech to the next in
order to be the first to sell this
week's new hot deal it started with Java
and the marketing campaign behind it and
the engine that pushed it into the
limelight it thrived in the.net
ecosphere and came full circle with the
hackers in rails the world of software
development has seemed to shift from
developing for the betterment of mankind
to the slow but strong bleeding of us
developers this is not the way of
sustainable craftsmanship with in
computer science we must turn this trend
back we the crowd gathered here those
watching at home all of us we be
interested oui je s calm have a
responsibility to ourselves to change
things we are people who can identify
these con men the bad actors in our
community the manipulators we are the
ones who have to call them out yes it
won't be easy yes they won't go down
easy and they sure as hell will fight
but it or pirates so I raise the
colors thank you
from the beginning of jay's cough doing
what matters versus doing what makes
money has always been a core fundamental
to all of us involved on both sides of
the pond we are pirates we deeply
believe in the code that all ships rise
with the rising tide and that equality
for all makes for a proper ship we have
no problems addressing the issues in our
community opening and calling for a
change we must rattle the sabers and
shake out those who aren't committed and
we need to do it now because I fear to
tell you the establishment is at the
door once again and they are ready to
make money off of your work and thus I
say love the pirate damn the privateer
privateers for those of you who don't
know where people that posed as pirates
and would pillage other country ships
and other pirate ships at the best of a
monarchy or government they were little
more than hired guns paid to discredit
pirates and break up colonies they were
not in it for life they were not in it
for love and they were not in it for
friendship they were in it for money
pirates were in it for all three pirates
had a code though it might have differed
from ship to ship the general philosophy
of honesty and good faith amongst one
another was ever-present this was untrue
for the privateers we need to root out
those amongst us who are not here for
the reasons that the rest of us are we
need to bring out the people who present
themselves as great but provide little
to no example and reasoning as to how I
say show what you have done let others
determine your value not the other way
around anything else is privateering
many people think I'm someone important
in JavaScript but they've never once
seen my code
or use my code because trust me if they
had they sure as hell wouldn't think
that we need to pull down the
unfortunate cult of personality that now
permeates our world it is the only it is
only a device of the privateers of the
businessmen of the marketers of those
that would seek to just make a quick
buck off of us which is like quarter of
a Europe this is not true this is true
not just for this band of pirates
gathered here under this flag but for
all software developers out there we
must band together across programming
languages we must bring back
sustainability sanity love to our
profession Douglas Crockford this
morning showed a picture of grace hopper
it's unfortunate that not more people
knew who she was that was the golden era
of computer science we need to get back
to that in this I want to openly applaud
Rebecca Murphy for challenging those who
champion Enterprise jquery without
offering solutions or frank discussion
about these issues i also want to
applaud z shah for openly speaking out
about similar issues in other
communities our profession needs more
champions of character and less
and so I make this call to arms love the
Pirates damn the privateers with the
deepest sincerity luckily we are
starting out almost a new at this point
there is no more Ajax experience there
are a few of any publisher run
conferences in j/s right now we have a
developer driven development community
think about that for a second we have
the power we are a ship full of pirates
we have a beautiful open sea ahead of us
adhere to the code are
chapter 3 Sex Lies and comparing sides
j/s is not the greatest programming
language no program programming language
can ever be they are all at best close
approximations to something the computer
can understand every programming
language has its benefits and its
downfalls we need to get to the point
where we realize this and openly admit
the negatives along with the positives
we need to stop presenting each new
language and framework with zealot asst
oh my god this is the best ever
I have a legitimate or coming out
with ridiculous metrics that benchmark
two things that are not the same or
aren't actually benchmarking the
appropriate use cases this world is big
enough for all programming languages for
all frameworks and to be honest the
world needs all of them not more than a
year ago if you would say if you would
ask somebody is jas a serious contender
in the server space you would have been
laughed at probably would been pantsed
and feathered same with Ruby if you had
said Ruby 10 years ago you would have
been laughed at time changes needs shift
holding the single weapon makes you easy
to combat in a horrible pirate you have
no lasting power we are not JavaScript
errs we are not Python ESA's we are not
rubyists we are programmers we need to
improve ourselves in as many programming
languages as we can wrap our brains
around because every language you can
you can clap that out
every language forces you to view the
world in a slightly different way we
need to remove the trolls from our world
we need to stop comparing sizes we
need to be blatantly honest we are all
geeks we are not rock stars we are not
ninjas luckily though we are all friends
confession time I am NOT mr. J humph I
am NOT a leader and I'm really not that
good at programming on a good night I
can pull together something but it won't
win any awards or medals before I
started yes conf I was completely
unknown like many speakers at Jazz calm
for us and you after this I'm going to
return back to home work my full-time
job in a cubicle and then go home and I
enjoy the company of my family I bring
this up to make one thing very clear I
am nothing special I am just like every
one of you and honestly I don't want to
be anything special this is not false
modesty this is not self deprecation
this is honesty an honesty is what we
need to be to ourselves and to our
fellow programmers I am most worried
about this issue above all others that i
have since that i've previously
discussed it is pride and selfishness
that have turned programming from an art
into a cesspool it has to stop now we
have to be the ones to do it why why us
well simply put because we're an
interesting lot because we all come from
different programming languages from
different backgrounds from different
education from different countries we
span the entire sphere and that's what
jay has come
is we have a rare opportunity we have
the perfect mix of curiosity
intelligence and experience we are
sitting at the precipice of an amazing
time and we are an amazing people that
is why it is up to us to do this so let
this be the start of something great we
are going to improve our community we
are not going to let it become a ghetto
we are going to do this not for some
misguided blind love of a programming
language but because we embrace all
programming languages we have the power
and the knowledge to make these changes
to make the programming world a better
place and in turn make the entire world
a better place we are pirates we r je s