this dog is about conquering fears so
it's all one thing it's pretty scared to
be up here in front of all these people
but actually I'm not really afraid of
that many thing so I'm kind of I do a
lot of stupid basically I'd like my
mom would put it uh here's me in middle
school in a mosh pit at a metal show
here's me skydiving in California with
that guy's name is Rocco that's his real
name um yeah here's me and my family at
the CN tower in toronto girl leading off
of the tower we're all harnessed up it's
actually super safe but it's such a
crazy view of the city that's me on the
left and the rest of my family well we
all smile we you can't tell each other
apart it's like crazy so I was just on a
month-long trip in Mexico in a road trip
in a two-door car and we were there when
this hurricane was hitting and I was
like whatever it's gonna be fine
actually was fine it didn't really hit
us but it did really hit the west coast
really bad but thankfully did not damage
us um I swam through this cave thing
while I was there without a life vest
that was really stupid because I was so
tired at the end and here's me diving
off into another it's a kala signal day
it's like a natural body of water and I
really up that dive but I was
like you know just go for it you just go
for it and so we have a lot of fears I
don't have the only like crazy weird
irrational fear that I have is of
cockroaches I really hate them but the
other thing that really scares me is
code which sounds really weird because
we're at a JavaScript conference now and
I code for living but uh so we're going
to go back we got to talk about my life
we're going to talk about code and my
relationship with it over the years so
here's me as a child I just wanted to
show you that because I look super cute
and well we're going to go a little
further forward an elementary school I
was in a G&T program and they would take
us like during school for a couple hours
and we'd play with 10 grams but we also
did this thing called logo which you
basically learn how to program a turtle
move around best thing ever so fun and
like make it like rudimentary calculator
and things like that fast forward a
couple more years this is mean I think
this is fourth or fifth grade that's me
in the middle that is a dead Playboy
bunny shirt so weird I know and I went
to this camp called cty and oh my god we
have to talk later and so so this is a
summer camp and for three weeks you go
to a college campus and you stay in
dorms and you take a class monday to
friday for like us you know like a
regular workday but you go to a class
and you got a break in between and stuff
but it's basically school in the
summertime so i did that for five years
most like one of the most amazing
experiences in my life like super
formative and the first year of cty i
ended up taking a computer science class
but and we like I think was visual basic
that we learned how to do and learned
about computer science but then somehow
I just forgot like what that all the
things that learned in that class and I
didn't realize it was like programming
programming like as we know today fast
forward another couple years making
xanga layouts this is not my own i would
not make this but something equally
horrible so like learning how to like
copy paste HTML CSS and JavaScript I
didn't know like really what those
things meant i just copied and pasted
things and change things around and
that's what you do you kind of fiddle
with code and that's how you learn but I
wasn't really thinking about it s code I
was just thinking about how do i make my
site personnel to me my xanga writing
about my middle school life I know so
and I don't know if you remember this
font it was really popular it's like
super nice she's like if you're a middle
school and you were doing xanga layouts
like I feel like this was really popular
and some of these weird Photoshop
paintbrushes yeah pretty embarrassing
and of course there's myspace you can't
forget about that so now we fast forward
a couple more years I'm in college and
freshman year I have no idea what I'm
doing I just take a lot of random
classes like I'll be a psych major I'll
do american studies I'll maybe I'll be a
math major all I want to do
environmental biology because my entire
life I've wanted to be a marine
biologist but I never happened but
whatever maybe it's never too late maybe
i'll stop programming but so but
sophomore year I saw me I was like
trying to do a lot of different things
so I decided to take a pro intro to
computer science class am I talking
million miles a minute probably started
taking a programming class and I decided
oh this is what I've been doing all
these years like typing you know
characters and making things happen and
so I was really excited oh yeah I'm
gonna be programmer this is gonna be
awesome java doesn't look that much but
like I only know that now but then I was
like oh this is super cool I'm coding
and stuff like that so yeah so the
sophomore year for our first semester
and that course finished and I decided
to go to a hackathon just having taken
one programming class and what is
happening my stepping on something um so
this okay after this program in class I
just know how to like do some you know
make a blackjack game things like that
and I decided to go to my first
hackathon I didn't know anybody there I
didn't know any of my friends were going
and so I just kind of showed up and
expected the best to happen and you know
what it did it kind of turned out well I
actually had a mutual friend that was
there for a friend of a friend who was
there joined his team and we ended up
winning an API related prize and took
home some amazon gift cards which is
awesome and here's me but then also
looking back at all of my pictures from
like the years i looked the same exact
same in every single photo it's crazy so
for the hair so that happened and i was
really excited and i was on my way to
becoming a programmer i had internship
under my belt the summer after that and
another one after that the next summer
but
that's a junior year happened junior
year was a little crazy first semester I
had failed a class those artificial
intelligence really terrible experience
we had to ride in Lisp and I was like
all right trees and stuff I can't do
that because I really like doing
front-end development so that's kind of
like what I liked but all my programming
classes were like no learn this theory
and learn how to make decision trees
because you're going to be using that
again so I was like this in college was
kind of senior of beginning a senior I
was just kind of like burnt out just
doing this in the library at like five
in the morning and just not knowing what
to do with my life I was all I was so
effed I was freaking out failing my
classes feeling lost I was like what am
I going to do up to college like it
might going to be coding forever like
computer science doesn't feel like it's
the right fit for me so I just felt
all over so I had to make a
decision I was like do I continue in
this major and have a terrible senior
year or do i drop down to a
concentration which you can do i miss in
my school and still do computer science
like on my degree but still have a good
time because college is about having fun
also with the sites learning so yeah so
i ended up taking a bunch of fun classes
that i never would have taken if i
hadn't dropped down to concentration I
took a poetry class post modern poetry
class you don't really know what post
modern poetry is it's just like
postmodern like weird stuff I wrote this
really awesome gem of a line push
language to the edge of possibility I
have no idea what that means but you
know I went to college so it's super
sounds really really smart I know so but
like that semester I took ballet because
I really loved dancing i took this
awesome agile development class i had
taken this mobile HD I class where I met
Charlie and this poetry class was pretty
cool I had to write a lot of papers
which I wasn't really used to I was used
type in code not really writing real
words out into strings of words that
make sense together sort of sort of make
sense so this one poet shock me at the
beginning of the course his name is
Clark Coolidge
and he was a poet but he was also really
into rocks he was really into geology so
he would write poetry that kind of
related to his interest in geology this
is sort of like tangential this is a
poem that we read in this class you're
soaked it in you know ounce Code Orange
the home trilobite chawla bytes makes no
sense but there's a lot of context
behind it which is cool trilha bites are
these like prehistoric animals that are
like you know you can find fossils of
they look like that that kind of
scary-looking but yeah so this guy you
know he's a poet but he also loved
geology and so I was like why can't I
you know combine code with poetry and do
something cool with that so I went to my
last hackathon as a student I was pen
apps that was like 2014 cool oh my god
that was last year that is so crazy is
only last year and so these were kind of
my goals for the app that I wanted to
make um didn't end up really being like
that because I I'm a front-end developer
so like I don't want to really do back
in so kind of ignored that part so I
ended up making with a couple my friends
something called exquisite hues and the
idea behind the poetry that's written in
this app is that is this thing called
exquisite corpse and so basically
exquisite corpse is a method of you know
making art by which a collection of
words or images is collectively
assembled and every collaborator
basically follow some set of rules or
are only allowed to see only the end of
what the previous person wrote or
contributed per se because this is an
example of some surrealist painters of
jamming together to make this weird I
think it looks like pencil yeah so
really cool things come out of it it's
always kind of weird and almost doesn't
make sense but sometimes makes sense
sometimes another example of exquisite
corpse one of my favorite podcasts how
to do everything did this one episode
where I talk about the super bowl and
they're like let's make a super bowl dip
but everyone who contributes only knows
ingredient before them so like if you if
you don't know what I'm talking about
it's like a dip you know it's like
usually like five cheese's or like walk
and like nachos and stuff and so this is
what they came up with so they started
so if you yeah so there's strutted
chicken jalapenos cream cheese grape
jelly extra chunky peanut butter
marshmallow fluff graham crackers
pretzels and dark chocolate hot sauce I
don't know how that jump happen sour
cream ground beef guacamole spicy tomato
jam deep fried green beans jerk chicken
Satsuki Ken fried onions and topped a
pepperoni you've got this like crazy
frankenstein where there's like a lot of
sweet stuff in the middle and then spice
surrounding it I wouldn't eat that would
you would anyone eat that oh yeah oh
weird people in here who would like to
eat that um so yeah so that is the idea
behind exquisite corpse so the stack I
want it we kind of wanted to wear this
elaborate idea at the hackathon where we
would do some sentiment analysis on the
poetry that was written and like make
these Philips hue lights change color
but I didn't end up happening and also
ended up being like a completely funded
app that's a really cool thing about
firebase you can write it's a data store
and you can kind of query it on the
front end and it updates real time
things like that so we were able to
write it all in the front end and I
wrote some shitty angular code to go
along with that so after that project I
was just done I was like oh I'm done I
did the project it works and I can go
home now and I didn't sleep for 36 hours
whatever and so that's how I thought
about that but let's backtrack a little
bit so I said I met Charlie in one of my
classes we worked on a project together
and he introduced me to the whole
JavaScript scene like of the world I
guess at this point so so he told me
about Empire node I one tampon owed and
I met these two guys there that's John
John Kay Paul and jason rhoads they're
both awesome and I wish they were both
here so they both we met that weekend
and they were both like we you know
we've got along really well and they're
like Jane you have to give a talk I
might meet up it's like you're just
going to do it there's like no there's
no for an answer that you can't I won't
take no for an answer you're just going
to do it this is John Paulding my like
direct messages on Twitter he's just
like constantly picking me like hey
wanting to do this talk what are you the
stock wanting it in a stock and at this
point I wasn't really sure what I was
going to talk about I think and then I
kind of inkling it was going to be oh
there's Jed in there too if you this is
a tweet from a long long time ago so
people were asking me to talk and
because they thought like I don't know
I'm loud and obnoxious and like kind of
funny sometimes maybe so they're like
you should speak and I was you know
thinking about what I should speak and I
was thinking about this previous project
exquisite Hughes I was like okay I don't
feel great about that project cuz I
built it at a hackathon and it looks
pretty shitty so I did this again where
I freaked out and I was just kind of
putting myself down and shutting myself
like I can't do this like I have to
rewrite the app I was like building up
all these excuses why I couldn't do the
talk and I was supposed to speak at HTM
NYC html5 which is John Paul's meet up
and there was some hurricane also but I
also backed out and that's which is why
we had all those we've had that thread
of him keeping asking me to talk at his
meet up so uh but so I didn't end up
talking at that meet up but Jason
approached me and he said hey I would we
like metaphor tiny food and we decided
that I would speak at his meet up in
Baltimore at Charm City jeaious so I get
to that point and I had sort of started
tinkering around with the app because i
was kind of like half committed to doing
a talk and so I decided to rewrite it
and scrap so I changed from express too
happy Jessica had just gone to a node
another note was it I was TX Jas and I
got to do a node workshop there we
learned happy and I was like oh I kind
of understand middleware now so that's
awesome so I decided to rewrite it that
way and instead of using angular which I
didn't really know how to use and it was
kind of a lot
features for what I needed to do for
this app i switch to just doing vanilla
JavaScript which is what I'm most
comfortable with anyway and yeah I kind
of flip flops on the firebase thing
because I was like you know I didn't
like how I structured the data in the
first place and I was like okay maybe
i'll rewrite it and do it in Mongo
because you know well i was thinking
mean sack mentality even though when i
was using angular but I was like but I
don't want to rewrite that stuff so I'm
just going to keep it with firebase yeah
and no it's awesome I ended up doing
like encryption for the phone numbers
that were coming in you know and then
you can write everything in JavaScript
that's just amazing and we're a
JavaScript conference so that's perfect
this is one of the first poems that I
don't know what's up yeah Brooklyn is
right here so the first yeah so this is
a slide with the first poem that I wrote
on it it says hi the message stares back
no sleep no sleep no sleep and this is
at two in the morning of course and this
was like two days before I had to give
that talk but I like kind of get
everything done it was like an
adrenaline wash and so uh that's me ah
perfect that's me at Charm City j/s that
was my first ever talk and it was
awesome and yeah that's me and me so
meta it's like nested and here's me
speaking at the html5 talk can't meet up
dad finally happened and then I don't
have a picture of the Brooklyn jazz talk
that I did but Jen had one in his talk
so you saw it um so yes that's that I
was like oh god awesome i got to do a
talk I feel pretty good about myself
people like what I had to say cool and
so I for some reason I decide to submit
it today as calm cuz like why not why
not submit it to a conference and it
turns out i actually got selected which
was such I was just like blown away like
what and I was in Mexico at this point
and I was like oh god I didn't bring my
laptop and I was like I'm gonna have a
whole month where I like won't be able
to work on this and when I get back I
like start a new job and everything so I
was like freaking out again
I was definitely freaking out but I
couldn't really freaked out about on the
trip because I was so busy like
traveling but then I got back and I'm
faced with this task again where I have
to write a talk and and I was like my I
feel like my apps not good enough even
though I talked about it already i felt
i still felt like there was something
missing like my talk was not worth
listening to that nothing worth saying
to people and so and then i had
submitted the idea was conquering fears
like what what I do I don't know felt
like kind of weird about my talk idea
and I was like damn I'm i'm
really and i only have like a
week to pull this together um so but
then I just like decided no I'm gonna
get my together a sat down in front
of the computer and I just you know just
like that died that I you know I was
doing you know I I took a dive in class
in college too super fun and the teacher
was always like you stand up there too
long you're never going to do it and you
just have to jump and a lot of people
like did their first dives in that class
and it's really cool and so I started
from my computer and I was like
complaining all my friends I can't do
this i'm not worthy and nah and i just
sat down and it just did it so instead
of adding some features that i had
wanted to implement i ended up rewriting
the app again so uh i know a little bit
more after rewriting it the first time
and having like lived my life and
learned some stuff along the way at
meetups and conferences and stuff i
decided to go back to express a night
because i had added a bunch of happy
plugins that i didn't really know how it
worked and it they were just sitting
there and like I just didn't know how
anything worked but now I knew how
things worked it was awesome oh that's
that and then I also learned how to
deploy it digital ocean and like even
set up a back of and all this stuff and
save the droplet and made a snapshot
which you can do I didn't realize so I
had that all set up and I felt pretty
cool this is supposed to play that's
right that's like one of my favorite
gifts of all time this kid is so funny
so now we're going to go back so the
purpose of this whole thing was to do
all these things right a full stock app
do something creative
actually finish something for once and
it turns out like nothing's actually
ever finished because I keep working on
it and finding out that I know more
things that I learned more along the way
that you know I still always have this
fear of speaking but I just like if I
put myself there and I just make myself
just do it I'll just do it and that's
this is the attitude i have about lots
of things in my life I just like you
can't think about it too much if you
think about it too much you're gonna
freak out like i was doing before so
we're gonna go and do a demo sort of i
mean i'm just gonna show you what it is
because it's been up for a while let's
see we will go there awesome so if you
haven't checked it out yet this is
exquisite text oh this is the about page
but the rules are basically you
construct a poem through text messages
if you text so you can see the last line
on exquisite XCOM so right there or you
could text the word last two here to see
the last line and based on the last line
you're going to text it something new so
you guys are all probably gonna do it at
the same time and so they're all going
to be related to the line that's up
right now but that's cool that's like I
kind of like the serendipitous nature of
this app like you never know what's
going to come out especially you don't
know who's that the other end you don't
know who else is writing it so I kind of
like that aspect Oh super creative Hey
oh we go in in so yeah so it's this
still using firebase so updates
real-time on the front end and so yeah
I'm gonna show so the first poem was
this that I would speak talking about
no-sleep no-sleep no-sleep someone
during my first talk try to you know do
that at the end which is super cool but
nothing bad happened and they also
exploited the fact that I didn't strip
the casing on the word last so people
were texting the word last over and over
and over again with a capital L that was
cool I like this one because it rhymes
I'll read out for you but can't you just
not rhyme who has a time what's up
pretty boy the milk I drink prefers soy
the kind i drink as a boy I don't know
so that's like one of the earlier poems
this is back in August it was really
cool that emoji you just were
works and it was all this is August when
this was happening but the first line is
definitely so true um yeah and this one
is this a cool first line cuz it's like
very alliterative so I don't know how
many you guys actually like reading
poetry but I kind of nerd out about it
sometimes and there are some really
awesome poems in here some of them are
like some people really put their
emotions into what they write and it's
just one line of you know just one line
of English and they kind of sometimes is
not even English but it's just one line
of like how they're feeling at the time
or they are responding to the person
before them and they kind of have a
conversation like this last one or is it
there was one there's like a really like
long conversation between these two
people but I can't find it again um so
if you guys can give me a number betray
between I I miss something ok I missed
something but well you'll see in the
poem and then when the palm gets
completed you get link I don't know if
you got a you get a link to your poem so
that's is something that happens
sometimes so they give me a number from
1 to 10 50 we can read a random home 47
ok so so like I didn't really implement
like a search function very well so this
is just it that's very simple all right
fish swim oh I actually like this one
fish swim trees grow men yearn into a
state of unknowing childlike wonder
filled with color and dreams another one
we're just keep doing this until I have
the time out it's like so much fun I
actually last night I was like freaking
out about this talk but I started
reading all the poems that people wrote
and 149 actually I think I feel like we
already saw that one but oh no we didn't
oh nice the bacon is dripping shrug grab
a vacuum and clean and the unicorns are
actually horses so many jobs drink some
cheese and eat some wine all right we're
gonna wait time for one more poem number
127 All Right see how this goes she sold
her last seashell and boarded a toy boat
set sail for the moonrise kingdom it's
like cute it's so awesome and sometimes
though I read these poems and sometimes
the language is like very sad and
someone's like obviously going through
some and some relationship problems
and they're just pouring it out into
this poem and then somewhat somehow
someone else is responding they also
have relationship problems going on same
time so it's just like a long poem of
like why why why it's like pretty sad
but it's also kind of cool that they
using this as a fun way to express their
fins at the time so it's kind of like a
reflection of humankind at any point in
time I like to think it's kind of a
lofty description but yeah so that's
that and one more thing where am I so
okay so burping all for this idea I had
this other idea I know i was at i think
it was i think his empire node or Empire
j/s where a bunch of people from
portland were there and they gave these
awesome demos and talk about creative
code and that's also kind of why I was
still stuck on this poetry ideas like I
want to work on more things like that so
we try to start this like creative code
made up in New York because some are
happen nothing actually came to fruition
but we're going to try to meet again I
know you're not angry you're one of the
people and so this is like basically
just an idea that I had where you have
an exquisite corpse but with code so i
have this repo set up here you guys can
totally go to that and right now it's
just i think it's just the terminal like
spinning out a bunch console logging a
bunch of random numbers and so the idea
is to just build on top of that and see
where all of our collective coding
knowledge takes us so with that I want
to thank james Kalm so much for picking
me and my first JS comp was in May and
so I've had two days console one year
and I'm
so sad that I didn't get to go to all
the other ones but I wasn't a JavaScript
programmer then so but feeling really
blessed to be able to be here and to
speak in front of you all and yes this
is like me in the inside but I won't