so I made a bit of a silly application
really and there's a bit of a story
behind it and I've got a few practical
tips to share that might be useful if
you want to squeeze every single
millisecond out of your application a
couple of years ago I stumbled across
Matt Westcott's Jes Becky which was a
Sinclair spectrum emulator written in
JavaScript and I thought this was
awesome but I didn't really know any of
the spectrum games so I kind of wanted
to recreate it for one of my childhoods
consoles which was the Nintendo
Entertainment System and this was my
first big JavaScript project really
before I only done sort of little jQuery
hacks and you know done some closure sin
where you know I put millions of things
in the closures and I didn't really
understand how JavaScript really worked
but I suppose you've got to start
somewhere and I'd know how to make an
emulator so I thought I'd find an
existing one to pause or to at least get
some inspiration from unfortunately most
of the existing emulators are written in
C and they use loads of sort of pointer
magic to map bits of memory around now
this could be implemented in JavaScript
but it'd be incredibly inefficient so I
tried to look around for one that was in
a sort of higher level language luck
would have it someone had written one
and written in SML is written in Java
which was called Venus and it's
available at virtual maze comm where he
has a big library of games and it runs
inside the browser as an applet now the
nice thing about Java is that well the
syntax of Java is actually fairly
different but the semantics of the two
languages as in what the code actually
means is actually remarkably similar
and this makes translating Java to
JavaScript really straightforward for
example this is a class in Java with a
constructor function and this is
basically the same thing in JavaScript
we've just removed the remove the
constructor function and made it part of
the function which if you like is the
class this sort of thing which is a
class method I basically did this by
just writing a regex
it's really quite simple breathing as
Mike this sort of thing again thank you
this sort of thing which is class class
properties again it was basically a big
regex to go through and replace all the
sort of publicans with just VAR sorry
this dot because it's on a on a function
and there were a couple of semantic
differences like this sort of thing
where javascript doesn't have inter
digital division so you have to
explicitly say you wanted an integer
because in in java being just typecast
it as an integer now on top of this I
just had to write the pixel where the
pixel buffer to a canvas instead of some
Java applet thing and attach a few
keyboard events and add a set interval
to trigger the frame function sixty
times a second and that was pretty much
it I mean most of those bits I just
borrowed straight off Jess Becky because
it's the same kind of thing and within a
few days I had a working emulator now
Jeff spec he ran at full speed but from
the start I knew that the Menezes was
far more complicated for example the
spectrum doesn't have a dedicated
graphics chip but they the nez does to
generate sprites and stuff so I really
had no idea how fast it was going to run
and when I was writing it there was no
scientific process at all I was just
coding and praying say I've got it
running at the time I was developing on
Firefox 3 because at the time Firebug
was the best thing around and it kind of
works get married to move it kind of
works but it was a bit like Mario's on
the moon it wasn't really playable
this was supposed to be running at 60fps
and it was barely managing ten now
really interestingly actually it was
like this across all the browsers
although all the modern browsers at the
time anyway Safari and Chrome both ran
it about this feat and being just a
naive JavaScript developer I just
assumed that all JavaScript engines were
built equal and this was the fastest it
could run so I just sort of gave up I
actually didn't release it for six
months because I thought nobody would
want to play this but anyway so going
back in time a bit I first started this
in December 2008 and then I released it
onto the Internet in June last year and
then a few months later somebody I went
to uni with sent me a patch and all it
did was replaced this bit of code which
goes through every pixel in the buffer
and writes it to the canvas element and
see the screen is 256 by 240 pixels and
it replaced this with this which all
it's doing is exactly the same thing
except it remembers what the previous
buffer was and only writes pixels to the
buffer which have actually changed and
when you applied this patch and ran it
in Chrome it did this it was running at
full speed
and this is not the incredible bit I
mean this is with a frame limiter that
limits it to 60fps or almost 60 P FPS
anyway without the frame limiter on it
was always running double that speed I
had basically a ten times performance
increase just from this one tiny patch
and I mean initially I couldn't
understand what the hell was going on I
mean for starters my assumption that all
the JavaScript engines were built equal
was just wrong and not only that I
couldn't stand why chrome was the one
that when obscenely fast say with a
little help quite ironically from a
mozilla developer we basically found I'm
just gonna stop these we basically found
that chrome is just really really really
fast and at least at the time it was at
the time it was streets ahead of
everything else and the problem was that
chrome had a bug in writing stuff to the
canvas which is now fixed but
essentially by only changing what's
changed from the last buffer it was
minimizing the number of writes it made
to the canvas elements which essentially
worked around this bug that made the
canvas element really slow and let v8
just steam ahead and run at full speed
now these sort of micro optimize a these
sort of things are micro optimizations
so they usually don't really matter for
your applications but when you have
really really tight inner loops where
every optimization counts they really
make a big difference like for example
the nez runs at 60 frames a second and
for each frame it's emulating ten
thousands CPU instructions and you can
imagine how much that photo how many
times that function gets called almost
3/4 of a million times a second so that
function really has to be super
optimized now once it was actually
playable and it was aptly on the
internet it got a bit of attention on
Twitter and the blogosphere and stuff
like that and somebody from Apple came
along to try and figure out why it was
so slow in Safari
it turns out it was actually a really
simple problem safari had a problem
caching really large objects which Jess
knows was full of but I'm happy to say
that this is now fixed it's not quite as
fast as chrome but it's but it still
runs the emulator at full speed and a
few opera people have pointed out that
their browsers pretty fast too
but unfortunately Firefox is still
really slow and you saw how how fast it
ran in an old version earlier and it
isn't much better on a recent stable
version and it's basically a problem
with how Firefox traces code where it
tries to sort of tracing is where it
tries to figure out how a path of code
is going to run because with an emulator
there's so much branching where it
branches the different things for
different instructions you have what's
called I think it's a branching
explosion or something where it just
can't figure out what's going to happen
in these branches and then it just gives
up and falls back to interruption in the
instructions one by one that might be
wrong but that's the impression I got
but credit to them though they're trying
to fix this and on their jaegerman
creating the eager monkey engine this is
a recent build of it it actually at
least on my little laptop it's almost
full speed and I've heard it runs at
full speed on faster computers and
they've yet to improve on this I think
they're gonna merge two branches or
something to make it doubly fast but I'm
not sure what's going on but it's gonna
be really fast now I I did try it on
explorer 9 and it it did run but I left
it running for about an hour on my
benchmark and it just didn't do anything
so I'm not sure whether that's a problem
with Internet Explorer or my benchmark
can it be great to talk some people from
my class about this but in theory it
could work on in Explorer I'm just not
sure how fast it is now a useful perform
step which you probably already know
about
it's another micro optimization thing
which is using prototypes for example in
this top one every time that a new
instance of tile is braces it creates a
new render form
but this is in the second example it
always uses the same render function
from the prototype and this can be
significant faster when you're creating
loads and loads and loads of objects I
put this code up on the web sometime
afterwards if you want a copy and paste
code now when I was cleaning up my code
to put everything into prototypes I
stumbled on a really really annoying bug
in Chrome and this one took me days to
fix essentially as I sort of hangover
from the Java port I had a load of
variables declared in the constructor
like this and then I called a reset
function which actually assigned them a
value so I could reset the object
without having Theory instantiate it and
obviously this is a bit pointless
because I'm declaring those I'm defining
those properties anyway so surely I
might as well just take away those you
know properties that equal no and it'll
do exactly the same thing it doesn't at
all Chrome the forms in Chrome drops
around 20 fps just Chrome none of the
other browsers I mean even Safari ran at
full speed I'd somehow kill this bit of
magic that made chrome run really fast
because I was doing it as part of this
sort of big refactoring of the
prototypes I was convinced it was
something to do with this and I just
didn't like didn't consider removing
those nulls would actually do anything
and it turns out to do with how v8
represents objects objects in v8 are
backed by things called hidden classes
which are a bit like classes in Java
they essentially define what properties
are on an object so when you need to
look up a property in in from an
object's it knows the position of that
property from the start of the object in
memory and it can do a really fast
lookup like I think it's sort of three
lines of machine code or something but
Java scripts are dynamic language so you
can add remove properties any time so
when you add a property to an object in
v8 it takes away the hidden class that's
already on the object and a new hidden
class with that new property had it
so I'm guessing by not defining these
properties in the constructor it was
just sort of switching in and out hidden
classes and I had as I added extra
properties or maybe even wasn't using
hidden classes at all and just doing
slow lookups on the properties I don't
know but it was something to do that it
was something to do with Chrome's
hidden classes so the lesson is I
suppose always declare your properties
in the constructor otherwise Chrome
might do something weird you know
another neat thing which might be
helpful is a benchmark I wrote that it
essentially runs 50 frames of an open
source home Buriram and times it and
here are some completely unscientific
results that I put to get on the plane
here if some of the latest browsers you
can see Chrome on the left is really
really fast
I'm sorry slightly slower and they're
not pretend is about twice as slow as
Safari and then Firefox is a lot slower
but this is kind of unfair because
Firefox are going to improve their
engine a lot this is actually the latest
build the Egger monkey stuff but I think
they've yet to get this faster before
the actual official release of Firefox 4
this is available on my github account
and I think it's being used on the Yaga
magic monkey engine at the moment on
there are we fast yet calm or something
like that and if anybody else wants to
use it please see find me afterwards
because I'd love to make it you know
something that's useful one of the
things that was really really hard to
get right was accurate timing in Firefox
which is quite important for an emulator
originally I was just using a set
timeout that called the frame function
of like 60 times a second but this is
incredibly an accuracy and all the games
were just really jerky as the browser
you know sort of decided I'm going to
take up some more CPU time and the
emulator just sort of stalled for a
little bit the method I eventually
settled them after trying a few other
ones is using a set timeouts but making
it fire really early and then just
sitting in a while loop until
right time to display the function add
display the frame sorry it's really
really inefficient but it kind of works
it's incredibly accurate actually
essentially what it does is it renders
the frame and then waits until the right
time to actually display the frame then
writes it to the canvas and then
triggers the next frame sort of half the
time too early so it can render in the
next frame if somebody has a better
solution I'd really love to hear it
because I don't like the solution at all
one of the other shiny things I worked
on was sound and this is really cool for
a while you can write dynamically sound
dynamically generated sound to an audio
elements so I wrote a tiny little one
pixel flash application oh it's red a
buffer from JavaScript and then write it
and then wrote it out to the speakers
more recently Mozilla have developed
their audio data API which is only
supported in Firefox which is
frustrating but it lets you read and
write audio samples directly to the
audio elements as you do cool
visualizations and synthesizers and
stuff like that so I wrote this little
using the flash application I had
written before I wrote this little
library essentially it uses Firefox as
API if it's available but it falls back
to a flash little flash widget if it
needs to
so it's essentially backwards compatible
Baxter I haven't tested it back through
sort of Internet Explorer but it'll
probably work on really old versions and
that's pretty much it I suppose this
time the questions because Tobias can
make it
yep
oh right oh that's interesting yeah I
see
okay yeah cuz you could tell when you
were playing the game that it just sort
of sped up and then slowed down and sped
up and slowed down that becomes I heard
there's a hack where you could attach
something to the window objects to get
round set timeout zero not actually
being set timeout zero I don't know if
that works but not very interesting
thank you yes it didn't really make much
of a difference in my case because I
instantiate all the objects before I
started but I've run a few benchmarks in
that about that and it's about three or
four times faster I think so if on an
inner inner loop if you're creating
loads and loads of objects it's probably
worth it I just did it to make tidy code
but yeah that's yes
but there was who
oh yes
okay what should I use and said okay
yeah thanks for the tip anything else