okay so I went a little old-school with
my slides
there's no presentation it's like just
text pulled out the old-school ASCII art
there so I'm gonna be talking a little
bit a little bit about ext Jas and I
called this presentation UI morphing
just cuz it's like it's not really
anything animated or anything it's just
changing a UI a user interface after
you've already got it done so bring on
my browser I'm gonna damn well
so I threw together this fake UI and
using Exige EAS this is the this is the
schedule for Jay s comp just load it up
in a in four grids so the idea here is
that the you know the customer or
whatever has already like signed off on
this layout so you've built this this
project and you know you've got some
editable fields and all that cool stuff
and you've got like delete features and
add features and stuff like that all
built in the UI so with the Exige S you
can change all of that really easily so
that's what I'm are you talking about if
anybody wants to find me I'm on most
everywhere as Arnold Fox and I have the
code for today's presentation on github
as well
and I like bacon there wasn't any I was
kind of disappointed there was no bacon
I was actually gonna have a plate full
of bacon right up here I just it just
you know we got like quiche or something
so I I work with the xyg a lot I'm a a
committer on their their project and I
wrote the learning ext J's book that's
out right now so my first example I just
called it a that's the one we just
looked at this this is pretty standard
exg just features it's their grid
component their editor good component a
couple of things like json reader and
and just really standard stuff
so what I'm gonna do is pretend that the
client came and said you know I just
don't like that's layout anymore this
for side by side so let's let's make it
into tabs or something
so we'll put all the grids into their
own tab
so the difference between having four
grids side-by-side and four grids in
four separate tabs here's an example of
the diff between that so we're only
looking at you know two lines removed
and three lines added and all of our
features still work you can still edit
the fields you know you can still add
all this stuff still works the same as
when the panels are side-by-side now
that that's a pretty that's pretty
straightforward one so let's move on to
another example
all right so my next example is a
variation of the the first two basically
so it's going to be grid side by side
but they're in tabs as well
this is a pretty typical thing a climb I
do is come to you and say you know yeah
I don't want those in four tabs now I
just want him in two and put them
side-by-side again everything stays the
same all the editing still works all the
adding all that good stuff
so the difference there was just a
little bit more but a lot of it is
really just configurations and actually
a big chunk of it is just tabbing
because I tabbed everything out properly
oh there you yeah without the whitespace
see that's a lot less so you know it
doesn't lines and your UI is all change
now
see
okay so now we're gonna take this layout
and introduce and editor and editor on
the side so the editor is activated by
double-click this is a pretty standard
ext foreign panel so we can change text
in here it's save and it updates our
grid works with the track be great grid
as well so it's all tied together
so the difference between those two is
is pretty pretty minor because we're
really just there when I am screen do
that again so the difference there is
pretty minor because we're just adding
that editor panel on to the side
what did you use for a ski guard it's
like it's just a website where you go
and type in its like if you search her
ASCII text it'll be like the third hit
or something
all right so next thing we're adding is
abuse oh this is gonna be like to
preview the data so now I've got a
single click for my viewer down at the
lower right corner
my editor still works on a double click
the layouts been changed but
everything's still tied together
everything's still functions
everything's still like hooked up wired
up
so eniac see everything's built in like
components and and mostly for the UI
stuff they're built into what they call
panels like like right here we've got
three panels well roughly the two grids
count as panels too and these things can
be moved all over the page how's it
going so these things can be moved all
over the page and their interaction with
each other stays the same
so we've got you know our delete or edit
all that cool junky
single click you get the preview and I
changed it so that the edits on the left
this looks pretty awesome in this small
resolution but I change it so that the
previews on the on the right there the
edits on the left to double-click even
though we changed our layout
everything's still tied together
everything still works
so each of these components are
basically firing off events - you know -
to trigger these actions so they don't
they don't care where they are layout
just fire off an event and you listen
for it it does it
you want to see the diff between those
two it's probably pretty small too
so I think that's you know F yeah I mean
we're just moving things from from left
to right so it's only a couple lines of
code to change but the cool thing about
it is that all of our all of our
interaction stays the same
okay so the next one gets a little
better well that is not the right one
hold on
okay so our next one gets a little
better so now our edit and our preview
is gone but that's because we've we've
changed how they show up this time
they're in a window instead of in the
main panel so if I single click I get a
window for the view and if I double
click I get a window for the edit
somewhere oh wait I haven't done the
edit
hold on just doing the view first okay
so I'm just changing how the view works
how it how everything's displayed
everything's still tied together through
these events so these events fire off
and we just decide how to handle them so
let's see what are we on right all right
no it's been aged
so I set up these these events that
happen in the UI and then these are the
the the handlers that are taken the the
result of that event happening
you want to see the diff
pseudo god okay
so that was between F and G so that was
just oh that was the one where we moved
from the left to the right I think this
is hard to keep track of these letters
well sometime on I but I think I skip
some of the diffs okay so here's the
change that made the preview open in a
window instead of previewing in the
panel on the right side not many lines
and from the users standpoint that's
that's a pretty big change from the
end-user what they see
okay I wanna make sure I got the right
one here so it should be a single click
to view double click to edit I'm not
sure why my double clicks not working
though
was working earlier of course so let's
go to the very last one
all right JJ all right
there we go okay so this is uh this is
horrible in this tiny screen but all our
tabs are now windows they still interact
with themselves the same they still
they're still you know they're tied to a
preview you can go and click on these
different things we get we get the
preview and the double click to edit so
even though everything went from being
like kind of a flat interface where
everything's in panels all shown at once
to a window to interface all the
interactions still happen the same we
can change stuff and save it here and it
updates in the grid
and this is really because of these
these events that we've set up these
custom events so what I've done here is
set up just four events on a what EXT
calls in observable so which is just a
really simple component that you can you
can you know fire events through so I've
set up those four events and then down
later on to my code setup the handlers
for those those events so you I doesn't
care at all you know what it looks like
these events still fire and and act as
they they normally would so uh anybody
have any questions about that just gonna
the first year yep yeah she with it so
this is um this is what we started out
with
so just for grids side-by-side these
grids they all have this edit function
in this case you know it's built right
in it's an inline editor the delete
actions all work add all that kind of
stuff so from there the next step yeah
I've also got the source code up on
github if you want to look at it there's
to github repo for it
but I mean this is the this is the guts
over right here this is where the
applications all set up like I said it's
using ext4 all the UI work so we're
creating a bunch of exe components here
creating a manager that that you can
relay events through and tying them all
together so for instance here I've got
like my main grid this main grid the is
what ext calls an editor grid which is
right there I set up some basic stuff
for it like how to store the data how to
display the data so like the first thing
in there is is setting up a store that's
where all the data is stored comes in as
JSON and that the store normalizes it to
be used by ext so the data could come in
as XML or whatever wacky format like CSV
and and ext will normalize it so it can
be used anywhere in the XT components
these are some events that I'm kind of
relaying to make my own custom events
like I take the row select tonight I
relay it through my manager and call it
the view schedule item event double
click again relay it through the manager
edit you know the ad relays to an add
event the next item is the editor which
I think shows up in D
so that's the editor panel this is a
forum panel
what do you cause a forum panel
so this is almost like this is almost
boilerplate code you know it's really
just setting up configurations then I've
got a view panel
so my view panel is activated on the
single click down here and it's just
it's like some fragments of HTML and it
uses ext x 10 + to display the data so
actually this is kind of everything this
is a really neat thing in ext they have
these X templates and the the HTML this
used to render that little that little
section and the lower-right that
actually comes right out of the document
itself it's in this text area that's in
the body and it's got some you know
variables in there that are replaced
when it renders so that's the gist of it
you know if you want download the code
and play with it it's a it's you know it
would be like a good base if you're
starting out to build a ext app it would
be a good foundation to kind of build
off of so enjoy
oh yeah yeah you can find me on github
is vinyl fox vinyl fox