[Music]
hello let's break here
I think if you're investing time in an
open-source project
you shouldn't be obliged to also invest
money in showcasing it so I want to show
you some services you can use to yeah
going live to go live on a budget and
I'm also on a mission here I want you to
consider stop using github pages because
the feature set isn't that great and you
check in artifacts in your version
control system which is kind of strange
and there are better services out there
and in my opinion the best one is net if
I calm it gives you yeah a custom domain
for free or you can have a custom domain
with certificate for free you have
really good continuous deployment
integration even worse like Thomas 5 for
configuration for CDN and it's really
nice you have a preview for every
request you have you do it offers also
cloud functions and user management with
a free tier and yeah if you have a
node.js project
I recommend leech calm it's a little bit
like code pants so it has a nice
community around it and yeah I can have
a full-blown node.js application in the
browser on a glitch comm sub domain
which is really nice and yeah it also
has a editor if you have some difference
of a side project for example go I can
highly recommend our sides by this
company called site but to mix with the
newspaper it's great also for hosting a
static site you can have an author as
product there too and if you provided
akka fire they will start the docker
container whatever is inside and PS even
on glitch comm you can start a go server
when you define the NPM start in the
package Jason to like go whatever your
main go faster
so yeah if you have a open source
project shock hazard
they are great towards out there they
deserve your money and if you want to
pay you're invited to do so but if you
don't want to if you don't can I think
you don't you shouldn't be obliged to do
so yeah please