[Music]
all right we're here to talk about
Sencha touch hopefully you're in the
right place my name is Dave Canada that
is an awesome cartoon of me I so I wrote
about three years ago I wrote a plug-in
called JQ touch for jQuery it's a
plug-in that sort of makes you allows
you to create web pages that feel a
little bit more like iPhone apps or
mobile apps about a year and a half ago
I moved over to Sencha and we started to
kind of redo the same thing but based on
a JavaScript API and way way more
powerful so that's my twitter handle
that's the company's twitter handle if
you have any questions if I go too fast
I am gonna rush just shoot me a question
on Twitter and I'll try to answer it and
full speed ahead so since a touch is a
free JavaScript framework for building
rich mobile apps we are an
object-oriented framework so you know we
use the classical inheritance model we
have things like MVC we have things like
data I'll talk more about those in a
little bit but first I think it's
important that you just sort of get an
idea of what it can do so that being
said I'm going to show a couple apps
this first one is TravelMate so again
this is a web app this is built with
JavaScript you can see things we have
like we have things like a carousel this
one's a little translation tool we have
these sort of Pickers and again that's
all being done just in a web app this
next one is the schedule for a
conference I just went to a couple weeks
ago in Dallas the breaking development
conference anyone there anyway go there
yeah I know you and you can see we're
adding it to the home screen we get a
custom icon and when we launch it again
no browser bar custom startup screen
and it feels like a real native app
right we think we have things like the A
to Z controller on the right we have the
grouped headers in the list pull in some
tweets custom messaging little map
component I really like how recently
they added the ability within the Google
Maps so that you can actually do the
Street View directly in it and it works
great within the framework alright
that's pretty cool right and some basic
pages whatever and then this last one is
called irresistible this is done by a
friend of mine Nick he's sitting over
there this is for a food delivery
service in the UK Nick built this I
should have asked beforehand but I think
it took him about a week and I think he
said within the first weekend it
basically paid for the entire time he
spent developing the app because so many
people used it awesome little CSS
animation done with our CSS animator
tool but we're here to talk about since
you touch so and this is something new
so I wanted to try everybody's just
gonna be on their laptops the entire
time I figure anyway so you might as
well be checking out our stuff while you
do it
this is for a kitchen sink demo this
just is sort of like a big combination
of all our demos has some data features
in there but mostly shows off all the UI
so go ahead and pull it up it's got to
be in a webkit-based browser so open up
chrome check it out JMP slash touch sink
so the reason I think Sencha touch is
cool is details matter this was
something Brian fling friend of mine
said in Dallas a couple weeks ago and I
think it's true I think in terms of UX
in terms of usability when you're
looking at mobile apps the details the
way somebody interacts with the app is
important for example that TravelMate
app when you have two Pickers
side-by-side when you're converting
languages that's the best way really to
show off or to to get the user to switch
to languages right that would be a lot
harder to do and a lot less pleasant to
do with two select elements just the you
know microseconds matter to a user and
that being said I think such a touch is
sort of the sweet spot in mobile web app
design between web and native so you
know there are benefits to doing things
natively you have all of your UI all of
your apps sort of on the device and all
you're doing is requesting data that's a
really nice thing to do that speeds
stuff up a lot for your users everybody
here I assume knows the benefits of web
development better debugging lots of
developers they're cheaper it's fast
it's awesome it's cross-platform I don't
have to sell you guys on web right you
guys like the web
I hope devices we support iOS the only
thing I want to point out is that we do
support the iPad really well which is
something some other sort of players in
this field don't do at the moment we
have a very rich layout system and it
looks awesome on the iPad the iPad 2 is
insanely awesome blazing fast I can give
a demo later somebody wants then there's
the bajillion androids we support all
those the tablet again and the same
thing with blackberry tablet all these
things are just WebKit so basically
we're saying we support WebKit on mobile
I think we are getting ready to start
looking at Touch 2.0 and hopefully we
will look at some extra platforms and
things like that but I can't talk about
that now so what you get and this would
be a good time to open up that like sync
demo and just sort of play along because
these are the dry slide portion touch
events so at the very core of what we do
is sort of one of the base layers is
abstract all the touch events on the
device
by default you get four touch events
touch start touch end touch move and
touch cancel we go a step further than
that we abstract them all to the
document so that their performance so
you're not binding you no touch events
to every list item or things like that
it's all handled in the background for
you when you bind an event our way and
in doing so we actually get to add in a
whole bunch of sort of more sensible
default events so you get things like
tap DoubleTap pinch rotate stuff like
that stuff that makes sense stuff you
want to bind to the next thing we do on
top of the touch event is our own
scrolling layer how many people know
what I'm talking about when I say fake
scrolling on iOS mobile Safari
that is awesome this crowd rocks alright
so I'm just going to show it then cuz
you guys know what I'm talking about
it's so smooth right buttery smooth
we've spent months simply on this scroll
both in getting the right momentum the
right physics and then actually making
that performant on things like Android
and Blackberry which if you go out to do
on your own good luck then we have a
whole lot of components I won't bore you
with the whole list but you guys can
read and again play along JMP
touch sync you can try them all out in
Chrome or if you even have the you know
some sort of emulator throw them in that
try it out on the theming side of things
this is sort of my contribution my
brainchild to the framework this is my
favorite part all of our themes are
first of all of course based on css3
because we're targeting WebKit so you
get all of the awesome gradients text
shadows box shadows etc but then we've
actually taken it a step further and
abstracted that with sass and compass so
basically sass encompass give you the
ability to use things like variables and
mix-ins within your CSS and we've
created a whole framework on top of that
system including our own mix-ins our own
variables so you can actually take the
default since you touch
theme and change it pretty pretty
incredibly on-the-fly and hopefully if
we have time I will get to show that off
the other important thing to note is we
include a ton of icons by default icons
are important on mobile you can
optionally include them all in your app
they all come in basics before encoded
into your CSS which is great for latency
on mobile and then the last thing I want
to mention is there all
resolution-independent
so one big goal we've had from the
beginning of our theme is trying to get
it so that a button is the same physical
size regardless of the ppi of the device
across all the devices which is a
challenge so then this is something the
more techie audience might appreciate we
do include a full data package with
Sencha touch as well as our desktop
counterpart XJS this gives you things on
the client side like an ORM like client
side associations you get you know
validations field validations and then
we have a whole bunch of data stores
data proxies etc that make it really
easy to work with any sort of API
endpoint XML rest JSON whatever you want
and then we also actually have a proxy
set up specifically for offline storage
so you can easily take some data you get
online and take it offline and that
being said all of that sort of comes
together into a full application
architecture which is something that not
a lot of frameworks nowadays offer we
include things like MVC we include data
we include the theming as you saw some
others I didn't get to mention our
history support device detection
orientation events this is just kind of
become a catch-all for just random
things I don't talk about layout system
animations etc at any rate I encourage
you to play around with it
that being said we're very rich
framework we have a lot of features law
functionality so it's important to note
we have a lot of sort of support venues
for you we have the API Docs which are
getting an improvement very soon little
makeover you can check
an XJS 4 and then we have forums that
are super active we have over 200,000
active members of our forums and we have
a learn section which with a bunch of
tutorials getting started guides all
that kind of stuff and that's actually
getting a makeover soon as well I hope
and then lastly once you create your
awesome web app with Sencha touch how do
you distribute it like you saw in some
of the preview movies you can just
distribute it in the browser works great
you may want to wrap it up in something
like PhoneGap if you want device access
or you want to put it on the App Store
the Android Marketplace blackberry app
world I think so yeah thumb gap rocks
highly recommended works great with
Sencha touch and then lastly just sort
of looking ahead to the future some of
the things we're going to bring in in
Touch 2.0 we're still discussing
features so this isn't exactly the
feature list of what's coming in touch
2.0 this is just sort of the hard set
minimum we know what we're bringing in
we're going to improve the MVC system a
lot we are implementing a new build
system which will automatically create
an optimized javascript file and
optimize build for your app by literally
launching your app in the background
seeing its dependencies and then
automatically creating one minified
javascript file for you of your app and
taking out everything you don't use that
is awesome I'm just throwing that out
there now charting extension which is
sort of based off of our desktop
charting that we're doing right now a
dynamic loading system which sort of
goes along with the optimized builds and
improved history support the one more
thing referenced at the bottom of the
slide is our GUI and I apologize this is
a little but ugly right now but this is
way alpha prototype we are working on a
drag-and-drop system to put together
your views which will be awesome
how's this rate going for everyone too
fast too slow I think it's good yeah
should I had an extra shot of coffee
before I came up save two minutes I
think this is going to be really sweet
once we get this thing together so so
the concluding slides if you like some
of this stuff and you find it
interesting you like sort of recreating
native interfaces with web tech come
talk to me because we are hiring and
like crazy
we are growing an insane amount I think
I joined about a year and a half ago not
even I was the eighth person on the team
and I think just last week we did a
recount we've just hit 60 so come on
board we'll take you all right so that's
pretty much it
again our web site center comm my
twitter name I'm not done yet though I
am going to show you guys some code
because we actually did that in 14
minutes and 24 seconds round of applause
for the time come on that's usually an
hour presentation just throw that out
there you're like thank God because I
couldn't sit through that for an hour
all right I'm gonna go back to the
mirror
destroyed my desktop
lame
Twitter Shh nobody @reply me right now
okay it's okay you can keep them coming
all right so this is an app I did with
O'Reilly conferences for their
conferences schedule app you'll kind of
recognize the one we showed earlier that
orange one the breaking Devlin they kind
of pirate patch this one so again you
know we have a list you can see I'm
running it right in Frome right now I
have to do the whole drag to scroll
thing but other than that it's pretty
awesome right cool app cool app all
right you guys have seen it you're bored
so let's look at code is that readable
good awesome
well first I'm just gonna sort of
quickly look at this class for this app
keep in mind this whole app this whole
conference app which you saw is pretty
rich has a tab bar has tweets brings in
data all this kind of stuff it's about
600 lines of this JavaScript of
JavaScript that looks like this which is
pretty short for such a full app so just
to give you guys some idea you can see
we are creating a object called a
session list which extends a basic panel
ext dot panel we throw it some config
options like the layout card some custom
options I threw in there then within
that panel we throw a list which we just
create a new ext dot list again give it
some config options we have a quick
inline template for each of the rows in
that list for each session and basically
all we do is set up a data store against
a model and I'll show you real quick
those models are wacky easy and if any
of my colleagues saw me putting all of
my models in one class I would tell
get yelled at but uh or in one file
rather sorry but anyway there's my
proposal model you can see it has the
association with speakers and then I
just sort of say what the fields are
going to be I then pass that model into
the data store say that we're gonna sort
it by time the group string is going to
be a pretty time variable on that data
and then the proxy is basically just a
JSON one we say script tag coming from
this API endpoint we're not going to
cache it that's for my own purposes I
think I was debugging something and the
root node is proposals and then after
that it basically looks at that JSON
goes to the proposals note looks at that
array grabs all those objects matches up
the objects in there sorry the
attributes in there against this
template and then creates that list it's
pretty simple right louder no just I
don't care so we have a selection change
event when you tap on a list item so
this is cool when you when you click one
of those dates at the top so we have
these guys right all we're really doing
you know in the sort of jQuery mentality
and totally not bashing jQuery I love
them but you know you would be when you
click one of those dates you would be
clearing a Dom list you would be saying
grab this ul clear the Dom you know go
through my JSON re-inject it this way
here dealing with sort of an app
architecture dealing with data stores
data miles etc you can see we're really
simply just clearing a filter on the
datastore that's bound to that list and
then re filtering it on the date from
that button which is way simpler right
it's all about UI binding
and then I scroll to the top just cuz
I'm a sucker for details
so does that look cool to everybody so
that kind of makes sense that's kind of
all I'm gonna that was not nearly strong
enough a reaction to the cool part come
on no as long as you get it and
hopefully I can squeeze in like a few
questions just real quick I'm gonna show
off the theming system so this is what
the theme for this app looks like you
can tell it is a little custom we have
kind of like a pink thing going on right
now let's say we didn't want it to be
pink next year we're remaking this app
for the next conference but the next app
is actually green we could just throw
that in there this is actually getting
compiled behind the scenes with sass oh
no it's not so I can just run compass
watch that the folder where that files
living it's going to take a look at it
recompile the CSS whip that new color
change and now everything's green right
so we have about 50 to 60 variables in
touch you can see even the selected
state is green back buttons green it's
sort of taken over every possible place
it could again with about 50 or 60
variables you can get a lot more
granular with your control I'm just
changing base color because it is the
most sweeping change it's the most
noticeable some other sort of big ones
or we could say the overall base
gradient is glossy all right make sure
that fires and now everything's glossy
you guys see that
and as I mentioned we can get a lot more
granular so let's say we just want the
tab bar at the bottom to be glossy got
get a little more iOS feeling I guess it
only does the tabs yeah that's still
cool so that's it do we have some time
for questions
yeah let's say yes that would be
difficult the question was you know are
the is the scroller components or
separated enough that you could be used
outside the framework not in the same
way things like glove box and you know
touch scroll or I scroll whatever it's
not as componentized as that it does use
some of our other classes hypothetically
if we get the build system to the point
where we want it to be fine then don't
show the thank you sign oh did I kick it
then hopefully that will be possible at
a certain point yeah that's a good
question so the question is is it really
free yeah it's free so basically just to
sort of explain it a little bit we do
have a commercial license and a GPL
license they're both free sounds wacky
I know but basically we do it so that
you can't create a tool that creates
other sense of touch apps and then
distribute that and sell that and all
that kind of stuff but in general if you
just want to use it to like get you know
you have five apps that you want to put
on the App Store at the Android
Marketplace go for it free if you are a
school or a non-profit or you're doing
something open-source you do the GPL way
still free so yeah totally free we do
have paid support options stuff like
that but really the company rests a lot
more on the XJS side for the commercial
licenses such as just open we figure
it's a lot more consumer centric so we
just kind of want to get it out there
alright so I know I'm holding up the
next guy thank you guys a ton find me
afterwards okay