ah
who knows what the Raphael is raised you
can well it's actually pretty quickly
grew okay so you shouldn't talk at all i
think because i'm not going to say
anything you I suppose probably start
with demos right away
okay so the biggest problem of Raphael
is the fact that people usually have no
idea what to do is it before I say what
it is usually people's like oh it's a
nice toy it's nice it's cool good for
charts and then just think okay so what
could I do about just so I could show
you some examples i did recently so this
is a sketch like application i did with
Raphael I did as a side project at my
current job we have like a code review
tool and we would like to add something
like picture review so you could drop
some pictures and somebody could you
know come here and say like hey look at
this guy and then just oh like don't
look here and let's that's kind of nice
head another guy sorry I'm just need to
it's like this yeah tell this very
editable only semi-transparent and and
so on and so forth this is like one of
use cases how you could use this vector
graphic stuff so right Bailey's
protector graphics i forgot to say that
if you haven't heard about driverless
vector graphics now the animation what's
the vector graphics or graphics library
without good animation this actual demo
from this side so not really new if
you've already been on the website so
the idea that as soon as you create any
object in Raphael bead circle rectangle
or custom shape you could then change
the attributes and change it feel
changed stroke change it something else
there are lots of attributes i'll talk
about it later a bit and of course you
could change it instantly or you could
change it all the time so for example
you could change the coordinates of the
circle and feel all the time like this
it's pretty kind of cool thing and you
could change the rotation of the airlift
you could change rotation of the
rectangle you could change paths into
another path
so you could grab one part and animated
to another path along the time did I say
it works in a six it works in Isaac's
and n is seven here and I ate in 99 in
Safari Firefox Opera Chrome ok it's both
chrome anyway and well it's not real
morphing if you think that it's real
morphing instant real morphing it
depends where the coordinates studies it
just basically turns from one path into
another so for example in this rectangle
transforming to triangle centrally
nice-looking morphing animation this
looks much better here and the only
difference in bed with joseph triangle
drawn from the left top corner and the
bottom rectangle is drawn from the right
top corner to make things a bit more
smoother but if you put the points in
correct way on the path then animation
is really smooth like to this circle or
for this circle basically the first
circle has three points and the first
circle has four point that's why
animation so smooth if you have
different points it's not really a
smooth so it's great stupid animation
the way it could be used could be used
for example for the sort of charts and
to do the animation on the fly as soon
as you create a new object you'd control
any of these parameters and for example
you could when you create the curve you
could basically control the curve and
change it the way you wish and it's very
very dynamic and stuff now the other way
to use like this is something i saw on
best in project and see how that's a
cool idea should probably try to create
a demo which looks alike and i kinda
show this demo now homepage so when you
when you edit the page you could say
okay now I want to add the comment to
the page so you just click anywhere and
you have a menu pops up and you could
choose ok when I add comment and
something will happen or you say ok when
a favorite this page and pretty
page so again the difference between
based on canvas that this actually also
works in IE the same way you could use
the gradients in Rafael as well as
anything else there are some limitations
that we'll talk about it later okay
let's back to our presentation now when
I show it
right so this is raphael this is a
graphic library written in JavaScript
and you could use JavaScript to create
graphical stuff and Raphael provides you
the adapter to make it work across all
the browsers I'm aware off so how is it
done well first of all how it was
created a bit of history so it was
created because I'm stupid I was working
on the project for we have like a hag
day in atlassian the company i'm working
for and i need to create something to
impress java developers in the company
and because they're java developers they
have no idea about JavaScript so you
can't impress it with some just
something it should create something
visual you know so they could ask how
the did it so I think oh yeah who
create some chatting so I pick out the
dojo GFX and start kicking on dodgy GFX
trying to draw some stuff i spent one
hour and didn't succeed even to draw a
circle and i just had ok i'm just idiot
i can't find this call this API works i
just wrote myself whatever and i start
taking on with SVG and vml so basically
it's SVG i choose the SVG because I
first of all I was using SVG back in two
thousand one and I kind of like it and
su G school and SVG support is kind of
getting there the only one problem with
SVG of course and you know I wouldn't
say how much I hate Explorer because
it's kind of understandable but believe
me guys I hate it a bit more than you
because you probably most of you
probably never actually work with this
monster the BML is a grandfather SVG was
created by Microsoft's and visio guys to
probably as I assume so when you save to
web from Microsoft world or you
odds are you you know lines and curves
and shapes will also be saved and you
could view them in explorer so they come
with a standard for vector graphics
which is pretty good in the Indian idea
let submitted to w3c w3c rejected it but
they liked the idea so they create SVG
based on vml a Microsoft X will take
apart in the creating of SVG but for
some reason they decide not to put it
into their browser and come with their
proprietary standard which obviously
cooler here it's like G Remo we ml and
SVG share the same idea you could create
objects in the page just like you create
thieves you create circles rectangles
curves whatever and that's it that's as
simple as it is now we ml SVG just two
different api's to kinda the same sort
of engine vml api is a piece of
right it's smoking stinky piece of
but as soon as i use SVG in vml together
you could make all these guys happy and
they could all show you the same circle
kind of the same way not guaranteed
pixel perfect but depends how you wrote
it and please not mobile safari here so
SVG supported in touch whatever ipod
ipod ipad iphone since 2.2 software
update so basically everywhere now to
make this tooth these are things are way
different like really different
like totally different the API is so
different SVG in BML and the only way I
found to make them all together it's
JavaScript so I create a JavaScript
layer which detect the feature do you
support SVG the browser or support vml
and use the different methods to
creating the stuff now this is how it
looks like in the coverage of the
features the SVG is a bit bigger than
vml vml is a bit smaller now the Raphael
trying to cover something it could cover
everywhere so it doesn't cover all the
SVG and doesn't have all the vml but it
cover big enough chunk of functionality
to create something useful when people
complaining about hey guess what you had
this awesome feature like clipping path
could you put it in Raphael you could
put it in our fail it's open source
project as soon as you make it working
in explorer I'll be happy absolutely I
have no idea how the collision repair
how to make it working vml I mean if you
can awesome submit the page I will apply
G now Raphael is 20 kilobytes zipped
minified it's kind of small now as I say
can you do the charge is usual thing is
like people like oh yeah awesome i could
use it for charts yeah you can use it
for charge it's not only for charts you
just saw this protocol presentation like
another forty percent of a UI interface
elements could be done with Raphael like
all these attach it to the anchor so you
could do it with images but with images
it will be like okay you have like five
images five GTP request all these are
steep steep here k SVG it will be much
faster one javascript file right which
contains all the stuff and most of the
time actually the su g is smaller than
the image unless it's you know
photo of your wife or something like
that so wait where where it could be
used the first and obvious example is
Raphael Diaz home side I did the
redesign recently and I create all these
images for the icons I droid myself so I
don't need to pay anybody so I'm sorry
if it's ugly I draw these icons and I
make an amazing laga by SME cube but I
found that I have too much HTTP requests
and my flgs has about 2,000 hits per day
she's not big for some corporate website
but pretty big source library
which is special target so it has like
lots of hits so I decide okay I could
use surprise i'm smart i read the books
so i was i was using sprites and still
was like not good enough so i think oh
well it's this icons are pretty simple i
could draw them in Raphael I draw them
in vector in the beginning so I draw the
one in Raphael so now I cut another HTTP
request because it's just in my
JavaScript and it's actually smaller
than the images and for all this stuff
all this stuff out images this
screenshot contains no images at all
right so they are like three files HTML
CSS and JavaScript that's all well the
page down there has one image more but
this part doesn't have any how cool
ivette now I I'll quickly show you why
this matter actually this matter because
this is the page right this how it looks
now let's zoom it right because it's not
an image it do mean really nice and
you'll be surprised but it's printing
also very nice when you print it the
logo and the icons looks like it's not
from the page like it's come from PDF or
something if you bring it up by hand you
the print out you will never believe
it's printed from the web page because
it's vector in explore it work the same
way it's not just so size does matter
your icons or your logo like if you have
a log office of your company on the page
creating recreating the Lord of is
Raphael doesn't only make it smaller it
also makes it bring nicely and
particularly know about the guys who was
using Raphael for the application
because they have to print it and they
had to have a pie chart and because you
know he woke with a client and client
usually is not technical person which we
call just dumb right so he tastes like
our I pray it up it looks pixelated WTF
but because its image you know the DPI
of the screen is not actually as good as
DPI of the printer like what we can do
like I don't know it's pixelated make it
look nice so they pick up the Raphael
and draw the same pie chart with Raphael
bring it up everybody's happy looks
awesome in print so if you have any
icons new page look like icons on the
left is Raphael icons I can on the right
I images when you zoom them up the
difference is stunning and printing
could be very important could be really
a killer I remember when I was
developing their application and it
could be printed so I have to include
another huge chip file with the logger
and resided to make it small and hide it
with CSS and open with the print so it
who printed biggest image resume it out
so it will be nice on the print and I
always feel guilty because I put the
extra you know image
for the user to download just in case he
will print now you don't need to worry
about it just make it a bit Raphael it
works and it prints nicely the other
user like UI interface things you could
use ruffle for like for example for
something like base there is actually
life example from one of my current
project we have this pop-up appears on
the page and you know like in any middle
too big company we have a developer we
have a designer and we have a manager
and the manager says hey we need pop up
then I said awesome rounded corners so I
come to design say hey okay rounded
corners let's talk and do you really
need drownded corners like around the
corner sauce that you really really need
rounded first well okay I II could be
without on okay fine I make it with CSS
awesome now okay and now this little
pixie on the top will be also it's a fix
it to show where you okay Trixie okay
draw the image in Photoshop put it in
make it look like this awesome then it
was day of review so me manage and
design is it together and I show them
okay that's how it looks like like how
it looks pretty nice is it even the
frame too dark making make it lighter
okay yes give me like I don't know ten
minutes I have to redraw it and you know
photoshop the image you have to upload
it I have to build the package around
the application and doesn't come back
together and I will see could you just
play with fire but now I can't play with
Firebug sorry I could you change the
background I can change the background
like again doesn't come on so every time
I delete all this code and replace this
thing with Rafael the next review was so
much smoother when I change at ya wanna
can we make it a rounded corners a bit
bigger yea big smaller yeah that's it
work at explorer like this yeah it works
explore as it rounded corners in
exploring yeah it's rounded corners in
explorer the most complicated past part
was to draw shape like this
I should say it's not the most
complicated transcribe ahead so I
successfully achieve it so Raphael in a
UI for UI elements could make your UI
more flexible could make you God smaller
because if you have similar you are
elements with different color for
example you could easily achieve it
seeming the UI easily achievable you
don't need to create five different
images for gradient background for five
different themes what else you could do
let's risk game I started to develop but
i was too lazy to finish and make it
works will click on the on the country
it's crazy arrows where you want to talk
you click country when I talk they bump
to each other and but then you always
bore it and I just the rules are too
complicated the javascript is easy so
but you can't do stuff like that you can
do it with this this is very small and
if you look at the footprint of this
page it's tiny it's tiny because it has
no images again in just one javascript
file they another another another
unexpected usage for the Raphael we
found in our applications this page also
contain no images as it all right so
this shadow is real shadow
semi-transparent so it it's on grey
background you can't really appreciate
it but if you have text on the
background or anything it's
semi-transparent shadow the shadow done
with Raphael and shadow down with
gradients from black to transparent and
we were using the shadow now in our
products why because the size of images
to create the shadow is about 100
kilobyte the size of profile library 20
kilobyte which means even even if you
use Raphael just for the shadow nothing
else for the project it's already
worthwhile not mention the draw file is
again just one HTTP request and for
images you have like 18 HTTP requests
you can't really surprised them so let's
be win-win and yeah it works in explora
without you know dancing and shaking 96
I mean semi-transparent shadow another
small example it's the table which
exists in the results of some web
development sorry and the JavaScript
enhance the table by adding the charting
to it this HTML table and underneath of
HTML table with javascript is on
creating the chart using Raphael to make
it you know much bit easier readable
thing just an enhancement to existing
again it's very nicely when when people
need to print it it brings very nice you
have very nice printing output now as
soon as we are at geeky conference I can
talk about geeky stuff
ok
I was struggling his animation and then
I did animation first time I have the
problem after a while as noticed that if
you have like this this is in this test
they create like I don't know about 200
circles draw them in the in the line
with the cycle and then I decide okay
now all these circles anime to
particular X so they should all you know
come to the one line and then notice
that a because the it takes a while to
animate each circle then when you come
to the last circle the time is different
and the position is different so they're
not moving as a whole line but instead
they moving like Yogi and the worst is
browser the jaw gave it an explorer
they're just going like this and then
coming to the line at the end because
they just so they don't have the same
time each of them has a separate timer
and second because I say animated mist
which means I go through all of them and
say animate animated animated animate so
when I come to this guy in the middle I
say animate the start of animation is
different from the guy in the beginning
because some time has passed but I'd
country so you add another method
animate with and if you have objects in
the group and say animate they all anime
twist and never happens like you have a
frame you have a text you animate and
text goals you know following the frame
so this is a original video how it was
you can see how jog it is and then after
update its run very smooth it's very
rock solid line
a little bit proud of this ok I know I
know somebody will appreciate it one day
ok in any recent release people start
complaining that in explorer the quality
of the graphics of the shapes to beat
doji you can see the shapes on the left
well you can see they're not as good a
shape on right there are some problems
like here they're like some problem with
a dot with the question mark it's not
really there they're like one pixel
differences here and there it could be
very annoying why it happens because vml
is awesome API right in vml when you
specify the path you can specify you
could only specify integer values for
pixels in SVG you could specify you know
pixels for floating point numbers so for
vml they had to round them the problem
is rounding is of course sometimes one
pixel is not much but sometimes half
pixel is a lot this exact examples of
that if you have small shapes like this
32 by 32 icons you could see they are
dodgy on the left then really as smooth
so what I did at the end because vml can
draw with half pixels it's back sorry
engine just API is totally
so I draw the image when you create a
path i draw image like 10 times bigger
and then zoom it in with vml internal
features to zoom it down 10 times and
then I have precision not one pixel but
one tenth of pixel which is kinda enough
for everybody for so far if it will be
enough i will make it 100 times big and
and zoom 100 time but 10 times is good
enough and then on the right you could
see their icons i compare it with a like
firefox rendering in pretty much the
same so I'm pretty happy with that so
this is like in the latest arrival one
point three point two in Rafael one
point three point three is on my laptop
waiting for be released by the way the
whole Raphael was written on the train I
have very long connection from work from
home to work with one hour so it's like
wasting 12 hours today so i bought the
laptop and the whole Raphael Richie my
hundred percent was written on the train
on this particular device so and as I
said it works in iphone oh sorry on ipad
right it doesn't work on Android because
android guys doesn't include SVG support
in their web kid I would I wouldn't I
wouldn't comment on this just I don't
know I haven't write a line of code to
make Raphael box an iphone as soon as as
soon as OS 2.2 was released for iphone
r-fl just magically started working
there let's power web standards because
when it's about SVG Rafael relies on web
standards that's it when it's about vml
it relies on Microsoft implementation of
BML because don't be mistaken the vml
specification despite written totally
buy microsoft and vm i'll implementation
in turn
Laura are two different things like if
you read MSD and I think that's how
things are that's not housing though
right the lots of bugs in like Microsoft
lockbox I think they just love insects
in general it's likely they create the
API they don't command it and they're
like ah c'mon guys boring let's add some
bugs Nate somebody nobody starting from
implementing them totally because it's
like yeah I wrote it I implemented like
why should make box anyway anyway anyway
API I think API is most important part
of annual JavaScript library it's
probably why jquery so popular I don't
want to offend your career but I don't
think it's like the greatest library
ever but I think that API is very
sweet and that's why it's so
great not because it's great library I
mean it's good library but because API
is so good that's why it's so popular
that's why you know you can't compete
with chick very much so I spend a lot of
time of thinking about API and as soon
as I talk about jQuery I just you know
just steal it from jQuery I Chad this
John he's okay so how to create stuff in
Raphael so first of all when you want to
draw something you have to create canvas
not bathe canvas okay not html5 can I
like this right look we are smart people
okay why are we giving dump names to the
product the prototype JavaScript library
the closure JavaScript library the
canvas Jamie now I can talk about
cameras without confusing people it's
not canvas it's not html5 canvas it's
canvas canvas no cameras people drawing
on you know canvas I call it paper okay
so you need to create a paper to draw on
very simple there's three ways to create
the paper paper Jesus first where you
ride Raphael and put the pre parameters
the ID of placeholder some deep for
example and dimensions within height
second variant you put the actual Dom
element placeholder and within high and
the third very end you put top left
within hide depends what is more
suitable for you then as soon as you
create a paper you can draw on the paper
what you can draw you can draw
primitives of course you could draw a
circle you could draw rectangle and you
could roll ellipse this is primitive and
if your indifference to que no es api
actually include soccer function so be
thankful for the circle you specify
contents of the center and the radius
for the rectangle specify X&Y width and
height and optional radius of the
corners by the way in BML when you
specify the radius of the corner you
specified the value of radius is the
percentage from the shortest side of the
rectangle it's very convenient indeed
so it's not a big sale like if you
specify racine pixels and in SVG
specifying pixel and in raphael
specifying pixel in VN well it's
percentage of the shortest side of the
rectangle for whom ever it could be
convenient I have no idea so rough I'll
take care of this and fortunately not
only base and as soon as you create a
element and primitive in this case as
you see you I assign it to the to the
object to the variable then this object
the primitive is a roper object around
the actual representation as with govt
ml in the browser and you could access
the actual Dom element by saying so
cannot correct not i would recommend you
to do this only if you really know what
you're doing because SVG in vml are so
way different so if you decide to write
your poem cross-browser think twice
before accessing dot node but I give you
this option whatever each year each
element has a set of methods the thing
you can do with it so you could animate
you could animate along some path you
could animate on some path different
direction you could animate with another
element you could set attributes and the
attribute is probably the most useful
method so you could set and get
attributes from the element you can
attach event handlers like click on
mouse mouse down mouse move mouse out
and so far and so forth so and so go so
example we create a circle then it's a
circle dot attr and you specify the
object which have attributes for the
circle the attributes that just take
from su G specification so if you know
SVG it should be very clean for you what
to do if you don't know if you g you
could always read the SVG spec I mean
it's kind of self-explanatory the field
is fill and the stroke is stroke color
so as Raphael supports not only hex code
hexadecimal
representation of the color but also RGB
and I also include HSB now hue
saturation brightness because it's kind
of awesome to have and stroke width
could be Mariah it's also only pixels
and opacity is from 0 to 1 you also
could specify all the parameters like CX
CY and radios in fact you could create
circle without parameters at all you
could just say create circle with
bracket bracket and let's say I TTR and
put all the attribute there you could
grab attributes by specifying the string
and obviously you could animate when you
animate the first parameter is also the
same attribute object so this is
attributes where you wanna object half
after the animation not all attributes
are animatable it's kind of obvious and
you could have a millisecond you have
obviously called back and you could have
easy and you can create your own heating
if you don't like the existing easel so
the attributes exist on the all the
objects all the elements are base of
course some of them are only makes sense
for some elements like GRC have only
sense for images font only have sense
for text target the target make sense
for everything so you could add a href
for any element make it a hyperlink you
could add rotation the path only makes
sense for path so perfect hey this world
perfect how you English speaker
pronounces but it's it's when you you
could create different custom puffs and
that's the most powerful thing about
Rafael so the path in text is very
simple you say paper the path and put
the past ring easy there example of
pastoring
it's very simple I'm sorry it's right
for I try to mess with G so I like it's
like not rocket science really I said
I'll explain it to it it's actually much
simpler than it looks so it's all in SVG
spec and you could read it if you want
to write it by hand but basically their
whole string contains of Commons and
parameters for the columns so each
letter is a comment all the numbers
comma separated or space separated after
the letter our parameters of the common
as easy so this is a comment in this
case it's move so we move our hand to
the particular particular x and y this
is X this is and this is why so capital
letters means it's absolutely moving
lower case letters musn't relatively muy
so you have here you have moved to X Y
then draw a relative line to XY draw
another relative line to X Y and so on
so far nobody asked you to read them so
let let me show you some demo of
actually usage of pathways
I have this PDF file on the screen
because a very recognizable icon right
so let's open it with my favorite vector
driving problem this is vector icon for
of Firefox longer simplified just for
sake of this demo now let's save it as
SVG right
ok
now
this is a test HTML this is a small HTML
I wrote just for this demo so it's
basically just HTML which contains a
Raphael GS include and then some
javascript which and Lord draw Raphael
paper and then I will draw some pockets
here let's find this file this is 54
stupid right so you can see here this is
Frankie pocket already encoded here so
you don't need to write it by hands
unless you crazy I'll just like pain I
don't know but you could just grab it
from illustrator or inkscape or any
vector any vector tool it supports let's
support of SVG which is pretty much
everything so that I could add all the
information here so give me the field
color it could easily from this field
color here now I say this
that's what I got right how easy with
that so have this path right here it's
vector zooming you want to do something
cool about it okay let's do something
cool about it i don't know let's let's
animate it I don't know
something like this something you
probably can't do with the images right
so it's just a shot down over there so
like don't be scared by this path syntax
because most of the time you don't
really need to use them but sometimes
like when I draw the when even just need
to draw the little twig see not the
whole thing then drawing Trixie I could
draw it of course with the string
methods instead of creating in
Illustrator or something now obviously
it's good library need plugins and you
can create plugins for FL as well so
again I still the syntax from jQuery so
you can write ref held or the fan arrow
and that's mean that paper object will
have the arrow method now and inside the
arrow method this is actually paper
titled around in context of the paper
and you could draw some custom you know
custom shape here for example if you
need to use this arrow all the time you
just create a method and then just use
paper to arrow boom boom boom you could
also add customer methods to the
elements then you write our failed at l
and i create for example short card for
fuel and stroke instead of using ATT are
all the time that makes just your
development bit easier or you could
create some rappelling pub then off
he'll plugin in publish it there are
some plugins i really really want to
create a plugin page in refugees com I
just don't have a bloody time but i will
good talking about plugins the one of
the biggest plugins i wrote is the graph
i owe to graph is the charting plugin
for Rafael because everybody wants to
have charts from Raphael most of it
anything else so gravely charging
blogging let's take a peek
Oh
so this is the pie chart drawn by
Raphael nothing really exciting let's
make really appreciate it but you have
to look at the source code for this ok
right shot
so
so here it comes so basically they align
to create the pie chart of this you
create you specify the coordinate width
and height and radius well I mean x and
y and radius and then you put an array
of the values and it's great the pie
chart for you boring okay it's yeah it's
nice like it's nice to have a pie shop
but what you really want to do is to add
some you know events to the pie chart so
let's add event for the hawa so when I
hover the sector this function will fire
and this function will run in the
context of the object you have access to
the sector so I could say this dot
sector a GTR I know stroke black
one climate
let's do something useful okay what I
want I want to create a drop here so
graph a loss account not with just a
charging stuff with some helpful methods
like drop for example and when I say
drop I want to show like a small pop-up
with the value of this particular
segment so let's say okay I know the
coordinates of the center of this
segment in the context object with the
max and this store why and please dot
value it's really a bit more useful
right but not really totally correct so
let's hide it so almost out I want
actually to
remove it if it exists that's a bit bit
better right you could see what the
actual values for particular cases it's
a bit a bit not nice looking I mean it's
a bit boring looking things so let's I
actually know the angle I'm angle knows
the angle of the of the second segment
yeah that's better right make it a bit
more funky so you could make it as good
like there are lots of parameters there
are lots of different things you could
make it bigger if you wish to make it
more visible you could replace the drop
with I don't know pop up your pop
doesn't have angles will just give you
this something like this you can do more
because it's you control what's
happening in mouse or you could draw you
could draw pop up or you could actually
access the context of the page and draw
something using Raphael you know
highlight the whole Sigma and Rho our
arrow here draw something aloud
something change there he didn't input
field in the different corner of the
page you decide what to do you handle
the events it's done for developers not
for psyche users right
so this is graffeo all the things that
open source all the things are free I
forgot to mention that but if you wish
to give me money I always glad to heaven
I did it for my free time and I like to
do this more and everyone can draw with
Raphael nowadays right in all browsers
you don't need to use flash well you had
this flash when people saying Raphael is
a flash killer I really glad to hear
that not it's flash is not
about to be killed by Raphael or SVG or
html5 life has lots of things to compete
with but if you in depth what like if
you have small project if you have like
again like the Sprott corey google or
yahoo pipes have this you know Vybz
connecting the elements you want drag
and drop around yeah you can go with
flash you can write your own engine in
cannabis use X canvas which is totally
wrong approach well canvass are in BML
are very different things right or you
could use paper I fail for that and
don't invent the wheel but you could
invent everything which I invented find
all the rakes in the grass I found good
luck I mean yeah it's fun it's painful
but it's kind of fun or you could just
use whatever I wrote and it's open
source so you could contribute you could
make it better you could nobody
contributed so far much they woke up
alone leave a couple of patches but they
were pretty much small I'm working alone
so the Raphael team is bridging small
and tight but we working hard to deliver
the best results for you
and yeah you can draw if you go in
topped open your mind web is not
rectangle anymore okay make shapes make
it make it rocks thank you very much
any questions Jesus yeah is it possible
to us which one's the effects are
setting up the pages two possible resize
obtained from
resize the paper yes ha yeah yeah yeah I
just didn't go through all API because
it's yep Lori's yeah so I noticed on
some of the path you were giving a
floating point but a lot of significant
digits have you found like what the
trade-off it is where you can still have
an SVG image that scales pretty nicely
with a path well try to reduce the size
of it well what again your question so
you had some things where you're like go
to dis X and this wide and it was like
you know one point and then three digits
and so you had lots of minifigures can
you reduce that so your overall
pastoring would be smaller but you still
have a high quality image it depends it
depends how big is your path so if you
pass this 32 by 32 icon it could be
significant you could round it to
integers you could see problems if you
pass that big like 800 800 pixels you
could run to integer nobody will notice
a difference it depends on the path when
i create the map of Australia for real
estate agents you ask me and I have it
as a demo and that's very nice because
you know you know like you're going to
real estate agency and you have like in
your case probably US map and you say
like to state and covering and the
either use flash or image map or just
looks dumb right so with the Rafael you
could avoid using flash and make it
works on ipad or you could just make it
easier to implement because to use place
you have to have pledged developing
house if you have well awesome why why
bother with Rafael but if you have just
JavaScript developer in house and don't
have flash developer and you need to
create something vector e Raphael could
be a choice so in perth australia around
it to 11 number of the dr dot what's
good just integers was a bit dodgy on
the edges one number was a kid yes
it's called monitor and it's called
eurofurence it's two phones which comes
together very nice
yes
hey
well Raphael is basically it's two
scripts BML and SVG implementation they
are absolutely totally different and
don't share anything pretty much later
on generic functions like parts Cola
parse path but in general they were way
different a lot of things in SVG which I
would like to implement bike on because
BML has lots of limitations the
gradients is the best example in vml you
can't have radial gradient on anything
but Alex it's very useful and you can't
put it it's a bug when you add radial
gradients you have rectangular gradient
if you understand what I mean it's not
actually radio and even on the custom
path its rectangular I don't know work
around as soon as I found they will put
the page but so far I have no idea how
to work around it so this is limitation
of Raphael there are the limitation you
can't specify you could specify as many
colors ingredient but you only could
specify one ampacity at the end you can
specify multiple opacities in SE g you
can and in everywhere you can in vml you
can't it's just there no even way it's
not on the bug just API doesn't allow
you there no way why
I don't know maybe it's useful for some
you know Microsoft engineers maybe they
found it all this will be useful for
people so thank you very much for more