so my name is Hakeem shoot it's my
privilege today to bring you out of the
lunch coma back onto track B I'll be
talking about technology called HJs
which allows you to run node.js and that
net framework called code in one process
so when you write an application today
you have a choice of many languages each
of them has its own strengths and
weaknesses if you choose not yes as your
back-end solution that these are some of
the challenges you have to deal with so
first of all no js' is not really cut
for doing CPU bound work and by CPU
bound I don't necessarily mean weather
prediction but even something as simple
as you know calculating a fibonacci
sequence if you do in a CPU bound work
in node.js you will effectively block
the node.js event loop and prevent your
web from serving subsequent HTTP
requests it is it is very infrequent
then you're developing an application a
new application in a complete vacuum
typically you'd have some ecosystem of
other subsystems or components that you
would want to either reuse or integrate
with and chances are these components
are not implemented in ondrea's but with
some other technology like JVM based or
or CLR based and lastly you know
javascript is not really cut for many
tasks out there and and far superior
implementations exist implemented in
other technologies and to write a really
good application you really have to have
a hybrid technology stack and be able to
reuse the components that do something
better
so a common solution to all these
problems in in no js' when you're
writing that hybrid application
consisting of many technologies is to
move the computation that is using other
technology to a different process so
you're introducing a process boundary
within your application establish some
form of inter process communication to
exchange data between the node Reyes
component and let's say Java or.net
component and this this approach
generally has two big disadvantages one
is the added complexity now you have two
processes instead of one you have to
deal with process lifetime management
many more kind of failure ingles of the
entire system and also you have added
latency arguably any inter-process
communication mechanism is going to have
higher latency than any in process call
within the same address address space so
there has to be a better way of solving
that hybrid application problem and in
case of CLR I believe the solution could
look like this
so MJS is a node.js module when you pull
that module into node.js application
what happens is that from the node.js
perspective it appears to be a native
module however the first thing it does
is actually spins up a CLR virtual
machine within the note process itself
so at that point you are running v8
which underpins nodejs and CLR which
allows you to run any of the CLR
languages within the same processes here
node.js code executes in addition to
that the add module provide a single
function called func the function takes
CLR code in a variety of representations
so we'll be talking about soon and
creates a JavaScript wrapper around that
call so in here we are basically we have
a async lambda expression in c-sharp
which accepts an input parameter and
returns a string there is a
concatenation of dotnet welcomes and
that input parameter C realized the
string
H fact creates a JavaScript proxy around
the c-sharp code and that proxy is
called hello the proxy is actually a
script function so next we are calling
it passing node.js is that single
parameter
and as is the case with the typical
async pattern in not is that hello
function accepts input parameter in the
callback function in the callback we are
basically displaying the result
generated by the by the seashore code so
let's let's take it for a spin
that's probably way too small something
happened with the retina see if I can
quickly fix this so this is our function
that you just a minute ago on the slide
if I run it basically it prints out that
net welcomes new Jaso at that point
we've been running the node process
I wasn't spinning any external processes
I was running that CLR code inside of
node
Xin windows and of course that this was
to be expected as Windows that are three
more runs on Windows but you can do the
same on a Mac as well so we have the
same problem here and I can run it on
the Mac on market is using a Shimano
instead of dotnet framework and you can
do the very same thing on the bun to
welcomes ingest so this is a
cross-platform capability to of
scripting CLR inside of a node.js
application so if scenes run on windows
on mark and on linux there have been
several attempts prior to address to
provide support for interurban CLR and
no js' most of these attempts were
trying to solve a very general problem
of allowing not dress code to call any
api in that net or any managed library
this is problematic because there is a
fundamental discrepancy between the
basic design of node.js and CL
no js' a single-threaded in even the
base see that is multi-threaded and
effectively by being multi-threaded it
also allows the number of synchronous
blocking calls and that meant framework
is actually it provides many blocking
calls that that if called from no js' on
the v8 singleton threat would directly
block the node.js event loop so edge is
takes a much more prescriptive approach
to the Interop and says that any code
that you want to invoke from not Jes
must be wrapped in an async delegate the
shape of the racing the delegate is
frank object task object which means
that the code you are calling from not
Jes in CLR must accept one parameter
which is of type type object it may be a
complex type and the returns a task
typed with an object a task is a the
sila concept that is a moral equivalent
of a Java future or a JavaScript promise
which is basically encapsulates a
concept of an asynchronous call that
will complete sometime in the future
with either a result or an error and
that concept of a promise can be very
easily mapped into the basic
asynchronous pattern of calling
functions in node.js which is basically
a function that accepts a parameter and
a callback method and the callback
method accepts an error an optional
error in a result and this is how how
this for these concepts map onto each
other
so what address gives you is basically
the ability to run a silicon
CLR virtual machine and v8 virtual
machine inside of a single process it
provides the capability to marshal data
between v8 and CLR reconcile the
threading models between not a threaded
CLR and simulated v8 and provides that
all within that framework of this very
prescriptive
interrupt pattern so why is this a
better way than spinning to processes
first of all because you don't have two
processes now you have just one and it
is definitely simpler to deploy simpler
to manage and simpler to think about and
second of all that is
but faster than any inter process
communication mechanisms that will be
required if you had multiple processes
to integrate a hybrid an application
consisting of hybrid technologies
specifically I've done some measurements
around providing the same application
logic where the dotnet process was
running separately from los Reyes and
there was an HTTP communication between
these two versus using address 2 to
perform the same functionality within
the scope of a single node.js process
and the latter approach the single
process approach was 30 times 32 times
faster and this is the similarly result
that you get across the three platforms
so CLR is you know c-sharp is largely
perceived as the kind of primary
language that CLR supports but just like
JVM see that support multiple languages
so address actually allows you to script
not only c-sharp but many other
languages so in here you can see an
async workflow expression in F sharp
there is integrated inside of a node.js
application this is Python using
ironpython implementation in top of CLR
this is power shell which is a scripting
language that only works in Windows and
lastly you can you can actually go and
implement your own languages or DSL
using the edge reyes extensibility
mechanism in this particular case I'm
actually scripting T sequel directly
from not Reyes the the baking
implementation is that that T sequel is
translated into a second extraction that
is passed to a do dotnet and that way
you can basically communicate with MS
sequel and fetch data from MS sequel in
a very easy way and arguably this is
actually the vastly superior way of
accessing a mythical data from not less
than any of the alternatives simply
because a do dotnet has been around for
over a decade
so predates anything that had been
created for not Reyes so the stable
tested and this is the de facto standard
of accessing I'm a sequel data from that
net
there are several ways you can pull in
CLR code into your knowledge race
application this is the kind of basic
primary mechanisms you pre-compiled your
sealer code into a minute assembly just
like you do a regular class library and
you call the h frank function and
provide assembly name type name and
method name that method of course must
have that prescriptive pattern that a
J's requires which is func object task
object but but from their own address
can basically create a JavaScript wrap
around that function call it the second
way is to actually provide a literal
code and there are three ways you can
provide that code either as a string
which is function of one you can do also
do a multi-line string the multi-line
string is a little hack I would say
because JavaScript definitely support
multi-line strings very well what I'm
doing here is I'm providing the edge
func function with an anonymous function
with a body that consists of a comment
it turns out that in v8 in particular if
you serialize such a function you'll
also get the body's he realized the
string so afterwards I'm I'm running a
simple regular expression to extract
that string compile it on the flight
when in memory CLR assembly and from
there own and three that wrapper the
JavaScript wrapper and F 3 you can
simply store your sealer coat in an
external cs5 and basically loaded up and
running
generally speaking CLR is a strongly
typed environment you'd expect all your
types to be to be declared upfront and
you'd have a class person with members
and so on however CLR also has a concept
of dynamics which allow you a way of
accessing data in a very similar way
that you'll be used to from loosely
typed environment like JavaScript so in
here we are constructing an input object
in JavaScript that has some nested
properties we are passing that input
object to the hello function which is
created via edge that funk and when you
look at how the data is accessed
within that async lambda expression is
actually with a simple dot dot dot line
and no types were required upfront you
can just dot your way into this data
structure using dynamics if you need to
write code that goes beyond a very
simple hello world you'll frequently
need to pull in extra assemblies or
namespaces so I borrowed some of the
syntax from Rosalie in the new C shop
compiler to allow you to actually plug
in by reference new new assemblies like
system data DLL if you want to use ad or
dotnet and using statements that are
kind of out of bound of a class I would
say so you know these these declarations
can be directly followed by an async
lambda expression without that markup
surrounding a class you can pass pretty
much any kind of data from JavaScript to
CLR a J's takes care of marshaling all
the basic data datatypes from ins
boolean strings to objects arrays and
buffer similarly you can pass very
similar data structures from CLR back to
not JSON returning the value all
civilization or isolation on marshalling
between the eight and CLR is done by
value so the moment you call that
function or the moment you return from
that function a copy of the data is
created either in v8 heap or CLR heap
and from there on the data lives in the
independently it has independent
lifetime so if you go and manipulate the
value of an array that you have passed
from one side to the other it won't have
any effect on the value of that array in
the other environment another the most
exciting marshalling feature that
address provides is actually the ability
to marshal functions so in addition to
marshaling basic data types you can also
marshal back a function as long as it
corresponds to the basic interrupt
pattern that address requires so in here
we can see an async lambda expression
that return
another async lambda expression back to
no js' when cold so when we are calling
that Creed hello function which
corresponds to the outer async lambda
expression it returns a low function
that we can later call now the reason
this is interesting is that it actually
allows you to manipulate manipulate
durable CLR state if you look at this
example we have a create counter
function this is the outer isn't lambda
expression and we are calling it
providing a value of 12 as an input
parameter the first thing it does is
actually storing that value of 12 in a
local Kay variable and then it is
returning an async lambda expression
which is implemented as a closure over
that local state and as you see the
implementation of that closure we are
basically increasing that local value of
K so we have just created a counter and
whenever we call that counter method
which is switch corresponds to that
inner function the value of K on the CLR
sight will get increased despite the
fact that that variable is not directly
exposed to no js' so you can extend that
concept really exposing entire object
hierarchies from CLR to Drai's but K
could this will be an instance of a
person with many methods on it and what
you could return from that outer async
lambda expression is an anonymous object
with a number of functions that perform
a variety of tasks over that person is
nice so similarly to exporting a
function from CLR to not jsut can also
export a function from not rest to CLR
so in here we basically construct a
payload object that contains two basic
atomic data entries as well as a
property which is a function i call it x
two because all it does it takes an
input and multiplies it by two and cause
the callback without value so later on
when you pass that payload object to the
function created around some c-sharp
code you can extract the dot time
- method and cast it to that funk object
ask object delegate that a J's has
created around it so this is just again
a proxy around a JavaScript function
that lives in v8 and you can since this
is the the return type that function is
task object you can call it using the
very convenient a weight keyword in the
net framework which is basically like
yield from in Python which basically
doesn't block the the current thread and
still allows you to write asynchronous
programs that have the look and feel of
a synchronous application one other
exciting feature of edge is is the
ability to tap onto multi-threading in
CLR so the moment you call a function in
via AJ as a function in CLR you are
still executing on a v8 thread so if you
do anything blocking there you are not
race event loop will be blocked
however in CLR you have the option to
actually spin up a new CLR a thread pool
thread and perform some long-running
operation there so the equivalent of
that long-running operation here is a
task delay we are basically waiting for
five seconds but since we are doing that
waiting on a CLR thread pool thread the
single don't be it threat remains
unblocked and you're not jeaious event
loop is capable of accepting subsequent
processing subsequent requests I was
supposed to be an outbreak but we're out
of time so what we can build with this
zip compression zip compression is an
example we kind of lightweight CPU bound
operation you can't do that very easily
right now with node.js you have to spin
up an external process with a Jas you
can do it in process literally with a
single line of code because dotnet
framework support zip compression
they're very kind of usable API same
thing with image conversion dotnet has a
very rich
image processing capabilities you can
convert images between PNG and JPEG with
a literally a single API call but again
this is a CPU bound operation so you
would normally do it from from within
your node.js application even if you had
an API for it with edge you can run that
logic on a silver thread pool thread
without blocking the
dress event loop you can skip the sequel
we've been talking about it if you want
to go beyond the basic crud crud
capability David knew has actually
created a great article showing how to
call like stored procedures use
transactions around a sequel using edge
and a do dotnet similarly you can this
is a very interesting concept that's
kind of pushing it you can have an
express race application that subdivides
the URL space were part of that space is
handled by nodejs and part is handled by
dotnet that not actually defines an
interface very similar conceptually to
WS di in Python which called Owen which
allows you to write applications the
kind of web applications that are
abstracted away from the underlying
server and Bruno bias created an
extension of a Jas that allows you to
take these applications that and
applications and plug them into the edge
the Express Reyes pipeline you can also
call legacy job services there isn't
really a very good library in Andres for
calling soap simply because that
technology largely predates the
development of node that meant framework
has a very rich sub capabilities in the
form of windows communication foundation
so you can use that legacy services and
lastly I wanted to mention something
completely different if you if you
recall the basic interrupt pattern
between nod Reyes and CLR it is very
much symmetric it basically allows you
to call functions from one side to the
other export functions both ways and so
on so just as you can scrape the CLR
from node Reyes you can also script
node.js from CLR so so basically this
actually required compiling node.js as a
shared library rather than an executable
which is a standard distribution
mechanism but at this point you can
basically take no js' with a 70,000 NPM
modules and you know do things like run
connect middle word inside of asp net
around expressjs rendering engines in
asp net 2 and this is it so high level
basically address does it run
CLR a no dress code in one process
it is faster than having to processes it