awesome thanks a lot guys
um so money my name is Pete LePage and I
gotta say I'm a little bit intimidated
to have go on after the last session and
and this next session that's coming up
sounds pretty intense so I'm gonna try
and just sort of give you guys a good
overview of what we've done with
Internet Explorer 9 with the new
JavaScript engine and some of the ways
that we're making the browser run a lot
faster be a lot more efficient much more
standards compliant um I'm gonna say
this now I'm sorry for i6 at this point
like ie6 is a 10 year old browser we
need your help
getting everybody off of it getting them
onto IE 7 getting them on to IE 8 and as
I nine ships getting them onto IE 9
right we're working as hard as we can
but we need your help anytime you go in
and have cases where folks are using
Isaac's encourage them talk to them get
them off of ie6 onto i7 or IE 8
so this morning I was sitting in the the
opening session with Ben and Dion and I
gotta say those guys stole my two
opening slides now the slides look a
little bit different but the concepts
are the same when I kind of looked back
at how the web was and in the early 2000
timeframe and many many years ago it was
all about going and consuming content
there wasn't any interactivity to it and
as the web has progressed and has gotten
better and more interactive we've gotten
to a place where today things like
Netflix or Facebook give us really great
interactive experiences that allow us to
share information to be able to be able
to get stuff share things with our
friends and not have to just consume and
you know I think as the web progresses
and gets further we're gonna see a lot
more interesting applications people are
going to be able to start building
applications that sort of feel native on
their desktop they feel just like
they're running a desktop application
but without feeling it it's in their
browser this is the screenshot of the
IMDB panorama that we did as part of the
IE test drive site right it gives you
full video support panning and zooming
all sorts of really cool stuff and where
it comes down to as we started working
on i9 we sort of came up with three main
pillars that were work we worked on and
I'm going to talk about two of those
pillars today we took we started excuse
me we started around the all-around fast
the browser just has to be fast
whether that's JavaScript whether that's
rendering whether that's opening a new
tab whatever that is the entire browsing
experience has to feel fast we need to
take away the the feeling that some
folks have that things aren't as fast as
they should be
we need the browser to be clean with a
focus on your sites
get rid of all of that great amount of
space that takes up and try and get the
browser so that it gets out of your way
you can do what you want quickly
easily and interoperable right html5
css3 HTML for JavaScript just has to
work you don't want to write your code I
don't want to write my code I spend a
reasonable bit of time writing websites
and that I don't want to have to write
my website multiple times for multiple
browsers so let's take a look at what we
mean by all-around fast as we started to
build that out one of the things that we
looked at and the way we try and build
the browser is really based on data so
what are people doing how are they using
it and so one of the things we did is we
went and we took a whole bunch of news
sites and we sort of I mean autumn eyes
these down to news site one through five
because I don't want to pick on certain
web sites because you'll see why in a
moment
but we anonymize these pop popular five
news sites down and we looked at where
they spent different time in the
different components of the rent of the
browser so we came up with sites one
through five you can see you know the
total file size new site one three Meg's
to download and look at that web page
right like that home page is three Meg's
to download that whereas new site number
three 300k it's nothing like it's
completely significantly smaller than
the other one so we looked at what
they're using how they're going about
using the different rendering engine
components and the different components
of the browser and you know I talked
about the size difference right
huge huge differences in size lines of
JavaScript code right 3,000 lines of
JavaScript code versus 20,000 lines of
JavaScript code for a new site right
think about in any news site you go to
today they're all doing about the same
thing they're showing you the news but
one's got twenty thousand lines of code
one's got three thousand lines of code
then you look at the number of
JavaScript libraries that they're using
how many of you guys when you're
building out your sites are you
more than one javascript library yeah
okay I'm seeing a couple of hands go up
all of those things are going to affect
the performance of your website so we
looked at how all this stuff goes
together and I'm kind of curious which
one do you think loads the fastest now
if you think it's number one put your
hand up number two okay a couple people
for number two number three okay a lot
of people for number three number four
all right anybody for number five number
three smallest site fastest to load most
of you because it's not pulling down a
lot of stuff you're not executing a lot
of JavaScript all right which one's the
fats are sorry slowest to load all right
number one who thinks number one is
slowest to load okay
good chunk of people number two number
three well I guess we kind of limited it
eliminated and number three didn't we
number four number five number four not
that much bigger but because of all the
JavaScript that it's going through and
executing it's running a lot more slowly
so as we built out all of this
infrastructure to really understand
what's going on how these sites are
using this stuff we came to a really
interesting conclusion because of all
these sites using different components
at different times in different amounts
that it's not just about the JavaScript
so as we built out i9 we needed to make
sure that we built i9 to be faster
across all of the subsystems if we made
the JavaScript engine faster but nothing
else well okay we've we've made it
significant improvement but we didn't
fix all of the things that we could fix
so for us it was important to fix all of
the things that we could fix to try and
make the browser as fast as possible all
up in fact when you when you average
these out here's the average for the new
sites right so just over a quarter of
the time on the average new site is
spent in JavaScript how do you think
that changes for an Ajax
Hevy website so something like facebook
or any application that does a lot of
JavaScript does it go up or does it go
down if you think it goes up put your
hand up okay if you think it goes down
put your hand up alright if you think it
does nothing keep your hands down right
alright I have a have a highly active
audience okay in fact it goes down but
the amount of time you spend in
rendering because you keep changing
things with JavaScript your going and
manipulating the Dom you're manipulating
the content that's on the page you spend
more time so that was an important a
sort of piece of data for us to realize
and start building on so let's actually
jump into the JavaScript engine so in
ie8 we have this javascript engine and
the JavaScript engine will go it would
start downloading your file and it will
go and it would start interpreting right
off the bat right and that works not
terribly fast but it works in IE 9 we
built a brand new javascript engine
called chakra alright basically we wrote
it from scratch to be mount standards
compliant with expert 5 to run a lot
faster in fact I'll pull these our
principles up so principle number one
needs to be fast for real-world websites
today and tomorrow all right
yes I'll skip to the third one I checked
today it has full support for vapor Jas
awesome all right but the second one is
modern JavaScript language support we
have full support for the atma script
five language specification with one
exception all right so we've gone and
done a ton of stuff to make sure that
javascript is standards-compliant
works with the same markup does the same
thing across all the browsers and is a
lot faster so how did we do that
this is where I think we get some into
some cool stuff so by default as we
start pulling down our code all right we
start interpreting it right off the bat
because if we start to try and compile
it as soon as we pull it down while we
have to wait for it to compile but as we
start pulling it down and waiting for it
and start interpreting it as soon as we
have it all on our system we go and we
compile it all right and that means that
it's running compiled code runs that
much faster once it's done now the cool
thing I think at least to me is we're
compiling this in the background we're
optimizing for your whole PC for people
who are coming in on a Windows PC one of
the things that we know again through
some of the data that we've been able to
collect is that most pcs today have more
than one core so if you're got one more
if you have more than one core might as
well go and use that core for other
things like compiling in the background
as soon as we've got the native code we
switch over to that and we run through
that it means that your code runs
compiled and that much faster than
having to interpret every single line
all right so I meant I talked about
doing that the compilation and
interpreting we do that via some
heuristics so we're not going to go and
compile every single bit of code on your
page we're not going to interpret every
single bit we look at what
best way to have a very fast experience
on this is and in fact we tried this
using amazon.com website to find out how
they want run and when you run Amazon in
a completely interpreted mode we're four
percent faster with the new JavaScript
engine if you go and I guess I'm missing
a word that know so if it's compiled you
have to go and compile that code means
you're gonna end up being about 20%
slower so using the heuristics to go
through and understand how much faster
your code is running gives you a really
great opportunity to be able to make
sure that everything runs faster much
more efficient so I'm gonna pop over and
I'm gonna bring up a little demo here
and bring this guy over here how many
people have actually checked out the
platform preview or ie 9 beta all right
a bunch of folks that's awesome you can
download it um there's there's two
things that are available there's AI 9
beta which is what I've got up here all
right
the ie9 beta allows you to update your
ie installation gives you the full ie
experience the other option is to
install the platform preview the
platform previews are the things that
we've been releasing every eight weeks
through the IE test drive site and if
they install side by side with your
current ie installation the platform
previews give you an ability to see what
we're doing with the web platform
alright so you don't get all the sort of
look and feel the the browser frame or
anything like that but you get the still
html5 you get the css3 you can see
what's going on
we're gonna keep releasing these as we
move forward so if you go and file a bug
on connect and say hey this doesn't work
or you have have find an issue you'll be
able to see those get updated as we move
along so I'm gonna bring up this flying
images guy
and as this comes up hopefully we'll get
a little bit more Network so we get all
our pictures here so this is Internet
Explorer 9 this is just some simple
JavaScript HTML 4 and CSS 2 there's
nothing magic about this this is not and
a canvas demo this is not a Silverlight
demo but you get a fast rendering like
you've not gotten before all right you
can try this in other browsers and I
encourage you to go try it and other
browsers I'm actually gonna go back and
I want to print out the fishtank demo
because I really like actually you know
what I'm gonna bring up fishtank over
here first so I'm gonna bring up Chrome
and we'll have a quick look at the
fishtank demo in chrome so again this
particular demo is some canvas SVG html5
running on the page so in I airing
Chrome I'm getting what about 20 frames
or 20 fish with 11 frames per second I
can go and I can increase that if I want
to have 50 fish oh
my frame rate goes down alright
so because Internet Explorer 9 is using
the faster JavaScript engine and using
GPU acceleration to get those guys
rendered on the screen you get a much
faster you get a fairly slow experience
in Chrome because they're not using the
GPU acceleration I'm going to get out of
this so that we have a similar
experience let's try this the fish tank
over here and we'll let this guy load
because you get the faster experience
we're gonna get a much higher frames per
second rate in Internet Explorer 9 as
long as we get in that connection all
right come on fish
all right there we go so 20 fish I'm
running at 50 frames per second all
right
so between the JavaScript and the new
the hardware acceleration we're able to
run much faster so I'm gonna get rid of
these guys all right so if you think
back to the spinning images what's going
on there and in Internet Explorer 8 for
that for one sort of animation to run so
that's just moving the images one little
bit we spent over a tenth of a second in
the JavaScript engine so going through
and running through the JavaScript this
purple part here this is doing the Dom
manipulation this is saying hey go grab
this element move this from here to here
and then the yellow part is the actual
rendering so it took us about half a
second to do one iteration that's why ie
eight if you try this today and I ate
you get such a low speed in IE 9 because
we're compiling the JavaScript and the
hardware acceleration you get an entire
revolution an entire animation in less
than a tenth of a second all right so
you get a much faster experience now I
think it's really also important to have
a look at you know I we talked about
some of the the pillars that we had for
i-9 and for the all up fast we do look
at some of the benchmark scores all
right and ie8 we were up at around 3500
milliseconds
all right so we were slow to put it
mildly and I ate for the SunSpider
benchmark we've been working to bring
that number down at PDC back it was
pretty much this time last year we were
up at over at about 750 milliseconds
today in ie9 were the difference between
us and
Chrome nightly is seventy-seven
milliseconds all right now for the most
part if you can see 77 milliseconds and
a test that takes as long as this does
to run that's pretty impressive
all right so it's there's a lot of work
that we're doing to make sure that our
JavaScript engine runs much faster and
much more efficiently and we're still
not done there's still lots of work to
go here and we're working to get that
number down so that one of the things
that's interesting and looking at the
the SunSpider numbers is when you look
at any of the the performance tests and
I encourage all of you guys to go have a
look at the IE blog there's a couple of
blog posts up there but there's one
that's really interesting that goes in
and does a really good analysis of some
of the different JavaScript performance
tests out there and the SunSpider test
is just one of them on there but the
SunSpider tests because it runs things
so often in so many times it runs the
same test multiple times combined doing
JIT compiling makes a huge difference
all right but it doesn't count the
compile time in there so it's really
important to look at how those tests are
being used and what they're doing so
when you're looking to compare browsers
look at how they're doing not just
particular benchmarks but how they're
doing for your site all up so let's talk
about some of the new things we've added
some of the things we've done and
changed this is not an exhaustive list
and I'm not gonna bother reading them
all out because I think you guys can
read them all yourself but we kind of
fixed a couple of big ones like oh say
get element by ID yep that one actually
probably works full Ekman script five
support I put almost in there I
mentioned that there was one thing that
we don't have and that strictmode
but we've got everything else in there
still opportunities to go through and
try them and play with them so I really
encourage you to do that
we have full Dom level 2 and level 3
event support which means
add eventlistener finally works you
don't need to go back and write multiple
lines of code to make things work and
ie9 actually that's a sort of I'll
sidestep a sec and just mention as you
start playing with testing your browsers
or testing your applications and other
browsers just give me nine the same code
that you give Chrome Firefox Safari or
opera and I will be willing to bet that
you will find that it works without any
problems compared to other things are
compared to other versions of ie now we
are still in beta right so there are
still bugs in our stuff but we're
getting there and we're going out and
we're fixing those things um there's
also a bunch of other technical things
that we we sort of did a little bit
deeper there's a new object type system
for those of you who are looking at some
of the type stuff because the new
JavaScript engine is written from
scratch and is actually written in
native code and lives inside ie now I'll
talk about what that means in a sec but
we now have to deal with numbers in a
little bit of a different way or
different parent variables in a
different way so it means we've got a
much faster way of dealing with that
we've got new regular expression engines
which go and heuristic aliy decide which
one you want to use so that you've got a
faster experience and then the other
thing is we're being super conscientious
about hey backwards compatibility is
important right you want your sites to
work that you wrote today and whatever
browser comes out so if you're using any
of the X you a compatible switches or if
you're using anything that throws IE
into one of the previous rendering
engines that's gonna still work and in
fact we've versioned the JavaScript
engine you get the speed performance but
get the IE 8 or IE 7 or quirks mode
behavior so I mentioned that we're doing
a bit of work around moving the
JavaScript engine
into the browser in the past if you
wanted to go and make a call from the
Dom or through JavaScript to the Dom to
move an element you had to go through
this rather complex comm chain and it
was a real you didn't see it as web
developers thankfully but the browser
dealt with it and it was a fairly
expensive process that's over there on
the right you had to go through the comm
elements well now in IE 9 you don't have
to do that anymore javascript the chakra
engine is built into the Internet
Explorer 9 in engine making things run a
lot faster and a lot more smoothly how
many folks are familiar with the the NS
performance stuff okay one pant so one
of the things that I find fascinating is
that we've been working with the
standards bodies the w3c in order to
find ways to make it easier for you to
profile and look at the code that you're
running to understand what's going on to
understand how things are working so
that you can go okay well I'm running
into problems here here this is what's
going this is what's going on so there's
a new window object called MS
performance now it's called MS
performance right now because the spec
for it in the w3c is still under
development we haven't locked it yet
with the w3c chrome has gone and
implemented it and I believe they've got
chromium dot performance so you can get
an idea that this is something that
we're all building together within the
w3c to actually build a set of
performance api's to go and be able to
measure those things I've just got some
some real simple code there but you can
say hey var nav start WMS performance
timing that navigation start which will
go and give you the number of sec Dix
after a particular time and then you can
go and convert that so you can actually
see hey this is when my page starts
rendering this is when it stops
rendering you can understand how we're
weskit made what are happening within
your requests so in addition to the new
JavaScript stuff some of the other
things that are happening are the
hardware acceleration and Ben and Deon
sort of talked a little bit about this
this morning but by using the power of
your whole PC using the GPU that's in
there to accelerate your your markup
you're not just accelerating canvas
you're accelerating your entire markup
so whether that's HTML 4 and CSS 2 or
whether that's canvas and and SVG html5
video with GPU powered HTML you're
actually accelerating the entire
experience it's gonna mean that things
get rendered on to the screen much more
quickly and in a much better experience
than ever before so at the same time
that sort of leads into making sure that
we do great ja a great job implementing
the html5 and css3 stuff so that sort of
leads me right to interoperability and
interoperability that's defining the
same markup is a really important thing
right we want to make sure that the code
you write works the same across all the
browsers we want to make sure that the
JavaScript is fast that it's
interoperable and when you go and write
code that you're not having to write
things for different browsers and
different experiences so with Internet
Explorer 9 we're spending a lot of time
we're really going through to understand
what's going on and make sure that we
have that documented and we've got a
good set of tests right this is a
rendering this was grabbed probably
about a month ago so there may be a few
minor changes on this but I last I
checked there aren't you know this is
using the border-radius css3 property I
9s got rounded corners the borders look
about right but as you try and look at
all the other browsers what you're
getting is you're not always getting the
same
thing so as we build this out and
understand what's going on we want to
make sure that we're building out html5
and css3 and the way that you're using
it and so to do that we actually went
through and and we looked at the top
seven thousand websites and we said hey
what are the API is the JavaScript API
so you guys are using all right and so
this is just some of the data and you
can see how quickly that graph drops off
for the number of for wit API is are
using index of dot index of used as sort
of as the number one API across all of
those top 7,000 sites used a 94% of of
sites the first one that we didn't
support we had to get to number 27 add
eventlistener we've gone and added that
so we want to make sure that as we build
out our standards we build them out in a
way that's interoperable that works so
that we can test them and that they're
things that you're using to build the
sites you need today and the stuff that
you'll need tomorrow and we're doing
this with working through the w3c with
ACMA who's the standards body that
creates the javascript spec the
javascript spec for Ekman script 5 was
just ratified this past December and was
a really great opportunity of all of the
browser vendors working together to
create a spec and a standard that works
for all of us and part of that is
creating a test suite that we all agree
to and sets the standard for the web and
sets the standard so that when you write
your code things just work
in the iaea timeframe one of the things
that we did for CSS 2.1 was we actually
went and took our CSS 2.1 test suite and
we donated it back to the w3c because we
kind of looked and realized that the CSS
2.1 test suite that the w3c had had
about a hundred tests all right now you
guys know what CSS 2.1 looks like it's
not exactly a small spec so we're doing
that same thing with HTML 5 with css3
and in fact we're doing it with
JavaScript so we have just donated over
2,200 tests back to a test conformance
suite with the ECMO task or with the
ECMO standards body to go and create a
test suite that actually tests a chart
sorry
tests the JavaScript spec in a way that
is interoperable so that we can go and
all agree that hey when you call this
API with this parameter you get this if
you call it with a with an invalid
parameter you get the same behavior
across all of the different browsers
because if you don't do that you end up
with the experience that we kind of have
today where things don't exactly work so
this is something to me that's really
great and is going to help make our
lives as developers much easier and work
much better because we're going to be
able to write the same markup and have
it work across all our browsers one of
the other things that we've gone and
done some new developer tools the f12
developer tools they're built into the
browser they're there by default just
hit f12 brings them up those f12
developer tools we now have a network
inspection tool if you've ever tried
using Fidler before well that's built
into the browser doesn't sit there as a
proxy we've got I we've taken the
console tab and made it into its own tab
so you've got access to that can change
the UA string just by going and doing uh
basically tool
change you a string tried to make this
stuff easier for you for me to go and
write the site's that we want so I kind
of moved through things quickly because
I wanted to leave some time for
questions but you can see where I was
where we sort of started with Internet
Explorer 9 JavaScript engine new
hardware acceleration is gonna make
things run a lot faster all right
getting the browser to be cleaner and
more streamlined so that folks can get
to your sites easier that your site's
stand out instead of the browser being
the center of everything and that things
that are interoperable the mark-up that
you write just works whether you're an
i-9 or in any other browser so the beta
is available today you can download it
at IE test drive or a beauty of the web
com you can get the platform preview at
IE test drive and that installs side by
side so you're not gonna go and nuke
your IE installation it does need
Windows 7 or Vista to install because of
the hardware acceleration stuff but it's
super easy to install I'm and I noticed
that there are a lot of silver colored
laptops instead of my black colored
laptop up today just install a VM you
can get the same experience you don't
get the hardware acceleration but you
still get the ie9 experience and you can
test your website play with your website
see how the browser works see some of
the new things like hardware accelerated
canvas and video so with that I'll open
it up to questions and oh yes so if you
didn't get one of these lanyards I think
they're kind of cool I was only showing
these today because you pull this off
and there's a nice two gig USB stick
here so quick easy way to be able to
share stuff and I'm not using it as
bribery to go download the bits but the
bits are on here too so if you want to
go try the bits you don't even have to
download it so with that all Papa
any questions you guys have yes Oh Doug
so we haven't at this point figured out
whether we're going to get we haven't
said much about strict mode so we're
gonna you're just gonna have to sort of
keep an eye out there to see what
happens I'm not sure what what the
decision has been made yet
okay so I'll make sure that I update
those slides to make sure they they
include that fair fair point and the
goal is to get there so that we have
worked with the same markup work well
standards compliant so yeah yep
so I'll repeat the question and please
just make sure that I got it correct
just so that everybody can hear but what
are the options to contribute back to
the test suite because if it's just one
vendor doing a test suite you end up
with you know a slightly biased test
suite and there anybody can participate
in the test suite creation for ACMA
script right now the stuff is sitting on
our site because we're moving those over
and we're giving them to for the html5
and CSS stuff those have to go through
the w3c they have a process in place I
believe that there is this a similar
process in place for the Ekman script
Task Force in order for those guys to
get the tests in there all right there's
one at the way of the back
so the question was what's the release
date we haven't announced a release date
we want to make sure that we'd get the
browser built really well so that the
same markup just works so that we're not
going and shipping you know a browser
with a broken implementation of any
particular thing we want to make sure we
get it right
so roughly don't have a rough date for
you I wish I did but I don't have one
for you and then we're going to go
through and we'll look at how we we sort
of encourage users to upgrade we will be
working as hard as we can to get users
upgraded as quickly as we can
so take one last question up here and
then I'll call it good if that works
so the question was what's my personal
take on what is the browser is it just
sort of another GUI IO with a network
stack built-in that set a fair
representation you know I think the
browser is a really awesome platform for
us as developers to build applications
that enable our customers and our
friends and our family to do really cool
stuff and for us to show off the stuff
that we like to do so as it is but it's
not such a platform and that to me the
web is about the platform it allows you
to go for us to go and build stuff that
we haven't been able to before
especially now with the Internet
Explorer 9 with with and with html5 and