Oh how's it going everybody who has been
to reject jazz before that's so cool
I wouldn't like take a look around here
this was the Jas conf venue - was it
three years ago three years ago can you
believe that can you believe that the
Jas Kampf
satellite conference the satellite
conference for jazz comp is in the Jas
come venue two years later is that not
just nuts so like I mean that's
definitely a round of applause moment
[Applause]
yes and I've also been to all five Jas
comps so I'm a super Jas conf reject Jas
fanboy was I think I was at the I was at
the first one as well that's where I met
all right okay cool so that's my real
signature man so all right so who was
here last year
cool last year I brought a ukulele and I
played some stuff and I played two songs
it was we are the rejects which I wrote
for the first year and played that and I
played like a two little boys medley so
this year I've got three songs is that
okay this is gonna be gonna work all
right
so yeah let's get going so this the
first song I went to node confer who's
anybody at node coffin in California
well that's great okay cool so I was
gonna say if anybody was feel free to
leave so how we gonna make this what's
the situation
all right cool all right so this is a
sorry that that week in in San Francisco
I went to this dinner on the the night
before the week before node conf and I
wasn't gonna write the song but I sort
of just had to it was it was just too
unbelievably ripe for writing a song
about so let's see how it goes
so what I do at this
oh I prepared okay
oh yeah
[Music]
San Francisco
got an invite from a guy who knows a guy
that I follow
[Music]
got a snazzy suit my new cards are
printed spend my last $10 on an uber but
it's okay I'm gonna be minted I'm going
to it - she did are gonna get messed up
so I'm gonna be your winner within my
app takes hold I need a rock star or a
ninja oh I need somebody to code it
doesn't matter what they use as long as
it's Unicode are you ready to sell your
heart sell your soul have you raised
your series a whole
[Music]
long nights in my bedroom crying I'm
drying my eyes I'm ready to innovate
optimize an alliance I'm going to a
douchey dinner gonna get busted soul
I'm gonna be a winner when my app takes
hold I need a rock star or a ninja who I
need somebody to code
they use as long as it's Google go
[Music]
I'm going to it to shetan I'm gonna get
my startup so I'm gonna be a winner when
my aunt takes all I need a rock star or
a ninja were lucky
body to code it doesn't matter what they
use to as long as it's compatible with
Windows 98 millennium Edition server
[Music]
[Applause]
all right let's do a test there how's
that you'll hear it
[Music]
so if anybody knows the words to this
one feel free to sing along
Robin Manor and Jelena
came together in their own backyard to
put on a JavaScript conference to give
the developers confidence they didn't
get accepted to the warning
only j/s comfy you Robin and Yan had
ideas to put on a show with some talks
and beers we are the region we are the
region this wasn't the conference we
want that's why we sing this song Mac
McKenna's from Australia I didn't know
they had computers they're web
components alive Jim Bob all set
callback pyramids to died Tobias
animator with bonsai Jas holy the
body did with just CSS and Dre knows you
love fun and profit so go make piles of
money Chloe Mario in JavaScript we are
the we are the region
this wasn't the conference we want
that's why we sing this song staff
should adaptive wear design
and when to use a hyper media API docker
in our pocket wit aku and a stroke but
Bottari in the browser well that's cool
Yan did musical experimenting he's
totally controlling me
from behind the screen he took the J has
gone so entered into no God so we other
we are the retest this wise him the
conference we want that's why we sing
this song golden axe golden axe
golden axe golden axe
golden axe golden axe we either
[Music]
we are the rejects
we are we
[Applause]
this wasn't the conference we want
that's why we sing this
[Music]
[Applause]
do you want one more
[Music]
so the first reject was the Berlin Jas
right and so that was the night that I
just realized that I met gen Schmidt
which is incredible so I would like to
the the guy who's actually controlling
the screen was standing over here and it
was Jed so I'd like to invite him up to
join me for the final number no no so
this song is extra special so Jed and I
have been attempting to write some songs
of late and maybe someday you will but
this song was born out of our
frustrations of trying to write a song
and just leaving it all right yeah
[Music]
I got invited about six months ago to
give a talk at a conference to put on a
special show but there was so much to do
[Music]
I got invited about six months ago to
give a talk at a conference put on a
special show with so much time to
prepare I plan to surprise and delight
but I ended up working on keynote
throughout the night before
[Music]
back when I was in college I had to
write a dissertation but there were so
many other things to do during the
preparation he's supposed to be reading
about Arthur Schopenhauer but in the end
I ended up playing Super Star Wars on my
stairs emulator I'm a procrastinator
I got job to write a web application
something about the social graph
combined with geolocation but the geoip
module I downloaded was a piece of lame
work so I decided to write my own geoip
framework I ran out of memory I started
to melt the CPU my code was so sloppy
and I didn't know what to do I got some
inspiration in the shower while I was
for washing my face it'd only take a day
or two to implement my own database yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah crash
[Music]
[Laughter]
I'm the only one around here who cares
that the server's about to die nobody
seems to give a damn that we are not
compliant with PCI in the meantime I've
replaced biased you well and replace it
with Mongo
but everybody's standing around arguing
about the logo
[Music]
someone round here really needs to think
about some new infrastructure it's gonna
take more this time than just a simple
refactor this tiny VPS can't handle all
the incoming requests but everybody
seems to be on there
[Music]
[Laughter]
[Applause]
[Music]
[Laughter]
[Applause]
procrastinate
[Music]