how quick can we be data visualization
techniques for engineers so who are we
um a lease actually unfortunately
couldn't be here today she is in New
York and and she was not able to make it
unfortunately but she is a front-end
engine I'm sorry she is an injured
senior engineer at on Google's crisis
response team which uses software to
respond to humanitarian crisis real time
around the world and prior to that she
was on the maps team working as a
backend engineer I'm of knee and I'm a
senior front-end engineer for Yahoo's
tiger team and we actually go around
every three to six months on different
projects depending on on company
priority and I've been in front and
engineer for the past two years and
before that I was actually a database
back to web developer so I'm coming from
data the database world and this is us
at the last random acts of kindness
where we're very sleep-deprived trying
to get our hacks done so I want to first
explain how we came to speaking about
data visualization so Elise and I are
extremely passionate about open source
technologies and bringing women into
computing at the Grace Hopper conference
in october which if you don't know it's
the largest technical women's conference
in the world we both participated on the
open source for good panel and the panel
was hoping to motivate women there who
were very new to open source to become
involved in humanitarian free and open
source projects and at least had a
spur-of-the-moment idea to challenge the
women at Grace Hopper to attend the next
random acts of kindness event and the
random acts of kindness or our hawk is a
community of developers around the world
working to develop software solutions
that respond to challenges facing
humanity today and twice a year the are
hot core team where both of our
companies are founding partners hold
hack events around the world and it just
so happened that there was an R hoc
event happening in December about two
months after Grace Hopper and another
issue was like at previous our Hawk
events there were only about two or
three women attending at each location
so usually the number of women in a
technical community or work environment
is very few right and the number has
actually been declining over the last 20
years so we decided we would set the
challenge to an ambitious twenty percent
we would aim to get the goal of having
twenty percent of the participants be
female at each of the 21 locations
around the world and we announced the
challenge at Grace Hopper and promoted
it via Facebook Twitter Linkedin the
usual methods and also a scholarship for
one female participant and after the
event we wanted to see well how many of
the locations actually reach twenty
percent so in several locations we were
quite successful for example the Chicago
location where we hit thirty one percent
the winning the winning hack was
actually comprised for a four-fifths
female which was pretty awesome so we
also wanted to represent this data we
collected in an easy to comprehend
manner the data from our Hawk the are
Hawk event made it very clear that we're
really far from getting to 5050 in terms
of gender ratio so we wanted to present
this data so people actually feel
shocked when they see it and our perhaps
compelled to raise awareness and take
action regarding the gender disparity in
open source and in computer science in
general so data visualization is not
something either at least or I are
experts at or do every day and we have
like due to our day jobs we have like a
limited amount of time to explore but we
wanted to see what we could do with the
the data we had and we talked to
colleagues and found out that this is
actually an interesting problem right a
lot of Engineers even front-end
engineers don't think data visualization
is easy and we wanted to see if this was
true so we gave ourselves a challenge to
explore data visualization techniques
and the idea of the talk began to form
so I want to first show you the raw data
we had so um so as I mentioned the the
challenge that we put out was a
spur-of-the-moment idea and we didn't
have a data collection process in place
when we made the challenge we kind of
just did it so we had like an online
event registration system but each of
the locations people just wrote down
their names when they came in so we
didn't have an online record of who came
to see who came to each hack or the
gender of the people who attended so
this is a snapshot of the original data
and we have one row per participant and
but we yeah we didn't have their gender
so our lease and I went through like
1500 rose and manually entered in the
gender for each location and we
contacted colleagues around the world
like asking like is this mailer is this
female and we removed like as we learned
today there are names like Jan which are
both male and female so we had to remove
that data so we still ended up with over
1300 name valid names though with gender
so we thought that's a good set of data
and now that we had all this data though
we wanted to figure out a way to present
it in a manner where that is easily
digestible by the public and by the our
hot core team so we first aggregated the
data so we could see how each location
fared using spreadsheet formulas to help
us and we then wanted to start looking
at okay different tools to help us
visualize the data and we decided on the
following process we would start with a
set of tools to evaluate we would take
10 minutes to see if the tools of viable
option and if we found the tool to be
viable we would explore the tool further
to reach our desired goals with our
goals being one to plot the number of
people at each location to to plot the
percentage of women at each location and
three be able to plot both one and two
on the same chart from four clearly show
the gender disparity and five be able to
use this tool to easily visualize data
for future are Hawks because we want to
continue the challenge and hopefully
slowly increase the goal percentage as
more and more women at 10 and we also
decided that we would take like one hour
with each tool so if we could reach this
metric of success so the first tool we
started with was open heat map so open
heat map is it's an open source project
implemented by Pete worden ER and it
uses the OpenStreetMap tiles to draw the
maps and the service is designed to make
it easy for non-specialists to create
maps for communicating information and
we're like oh wow that's us right
non-specialist this could be a dream
tool so for developers there's a jquery
plugin that makes it easy to create an
open source mapping component on any web
page
so I want to show you a quick demo of us
actually using the tool with our
aggregated data so you can see how easy
it is to use
so I love my mouth where'd it go
mmm do you guys see it completely lost
it okay try again huh okay all right
here it is yay thanks so um let me make
it larger so you can easily come here
and you can upload a CSV so we uploaded
our abrogated data set and then
basically if it thinks the data is valid
what it will do is basically say okay
your data is loaded click here to view
the map so then you can view your map
right away and right away it gave us a
heat map of the data that that we had I
can hover over the markers to see any
specific data points so I can see the
percentage of women at each location on
the the large blue circle is Colombia
there and it's actually a really big
anomaly and we removed it from later
examples we did because Colombia was a
satellite location and it happened to
have it had one person there I know it
was a female so that's why it looks so
big but you can come in here you can
customize at the bottom you can
customize certain parameters you can
customize the title the color it has a
few color schemes the size of the
circles and you can also show other you
don't have to use circles you can use
blobs and some standard images so then
when you get your finalize what you want
you can save in view and while I you got
your map with the parameters that you
set this is nice big this part is nice
because it actually shows a nice legend
based on the data you have and we
actually learned a lot of tools don't
even the programmatic ones don't come
out of the box with a legend it does
have this weird thing I don't know if
you can see but it came up with the
weird name it's like do die Onision whew
I mean it came up with a weird name for
the the URL and there's no way to
actually change that so that was that
was kind of unfortunate so but as you
can see the tool is very easy to use
that was completely real time and you
just go to it's at open heat map calm
and I like that this map made it very
clear which were the high percentage
women areas like I can look in this map
Colombia has been removed here but I can
look at this map and easily see okay
northeastern United States a lot of
women attending surprisingly the one
data point I was really surprised about
was the Zambia data point in Africa
because I was like I didn't know there
were a lot of women programmers in
Africa but there were close to thirty
percent and we later learned there's
actually a blog post on our Hawk right
now on the our hawk website about this
but there's a women's group in Africa
based in Kenya carrot chicks which
actually encouraged women to go to the
hacks and I mean I thought that was
pretty powerful that if you have the
support team there that you actually do
have women participating so so far this
seems like a dream tool but then we
realized some limitations once you
create your he map and you left the Edit
window you can't go back and change the
parameters so I couldn't go back like
I'd first plotted it based on percentage
I couldn't go back and change it based
on number so there was no way for me to
edit it would have to create a whole new
map also since we used a CSV to upload
the data there's no way we can edit the
raw data so we could there was no way we
could edit the numbers like I couldn't
remove the data the Columbia data point
which is kind of annoying you can create
a map directly from data in a Google
spreadsheet it will as long as your
spreadsheet this public and then your
map actually does get updates
automatically if your if your data in
your spreadsheet updates and as we saw
the generated URL is predefined with
some arbitrary name so the solution
which gives you more flexibility though
is to use the jQuery plug-in right to
host the the heat map on your site using
the the heat map API how are we try to
use the API and we use the same data
file but it's it you actually couldn't
you had to understand you had to geocode
your data manually and you had to be
familiar with the OpenStreetMap the
OpenStreetMap tiles to understand how to
the API the documentation is not very
clear about that so we decided to move
on Pete the author he's like really
responsive on to github messages so it's
something worth checking out if you want
to look into it more so we realized at
this point the tools can be broken up
into two paths we would have the non
programmatic ones and the programmatic
ones and so we thought we'd look at
several tools of each type for non
programmatic tools we decided to look at
open heat map which you just saw Google
Fusion Tables Google charts socata
charts been in factual charts been
turned out to not be a good option
because it doesn't allow you to upload
your own data like it has some
interesting data sets up there but I
couldn't upload anything of my own and
factual was not a good option either
because it doesn't provide a map view of
our data so it wasn't a good use case
for us now the programmatic tools that
we looked at where the Google Maps
JavaScript API the Yahoo Maps Web
Services the Bing Maps Ajax control and
the Google charts the Google charts
tools using the visualization API so I'm
going to talk a little bit about both
i'm going to start first with a non
programmatic ones but i will get to the
programmatic ones at the end and the one
I thought this is probably like the
coolest find for me at least which was
Google Fusion Tables like at least
already knew about this but I want to
show you a demo also so you can see how
powerful Fusion Tables is
okay so i can come here let me get
larger again i just go to the fusion
table site i say i want to create a new
I knew I want to import data from a new
spreadsheet I select the spreadsheet i
want to import from and i can easily do
that the one so we're using our
aggregated data set again one thing that
and i'll explain this in a minute why
but we did have to add a column for
country that just had the country and
i'll show you in a second why I'm you
can give it a name and some parameters
and then right away it gives you a table
right and it automatically detects now
this was just spreadsheet data raw data
automatically detects that my two
columns location and country are
location-based and it highlights them so
when I go to create my first simple map
I go to the visualize field and I say I
want a map out of it it automatically
starts geocoding based on one of those
columns that chose location which is
what we wanted by default and right away
I get data points so this shows me
easily this shows me quickly all the
locations where the hack took place and
if I click on one of the locations then
I can see details about it can see the
total number of people that attended the
percent female now this is great but
it's not ideal right because I can't
just look at the map and see which ones
have the largest number of women or
which ones had the most attendance so
Fusion Tables also offers what they call
an intensity map and this is pretty cool
because right away what it does is it
basically takes the data I have and then
color codes countries by default and I
can hover over and I can see the total
number of people now the one thing that
was odd though is um it actually like
you can see here for Canada it's okay
because we only had one location in
Canada and the total number was 80 so
that was correct but if you go down to
the US it's only showing seattle's
numbers like there were way more than 25
people attending the the hacks in the
United States so that's where we had
that country column came into place and
Fusion Tables actually has an aggregate
option where you can select ok you want
to sum or over us
field and we want a son by country and
were able to see we're able to see the
aggregate data now the problem is like
there was some glitch so I actually had
to go to another value and then come
back and then it showed the correct data
so now i can see okay 377 people
attended in the US so that's actually
correct and it's aggregated by country
there's also a few other neat things you
can do you can see which one do I do
next you can actually view markers so
with the data not aggravated I can view
markers and then it plots points the
problem with this this is great right so
this is going to be the same thing open
heat map did but this shows the number
of people that attended but I can't see
the percentage of women so it's only one
it's again one-dimensional it's only one
set of data that it's able to handle at
a time if i go back to regions i can
narrow in on a certain area also so if i
wanted to narrow in on the United States
it has a you know a search assist and I
can see for each region how many people
attended I can also add a filter so I
know that our goal was twenty percent so
we have six locations in the US i want
to see how many actually reached the
twenty percent and i can see okay great
four of the locations did so it's so
this was this is actually being done
pretty much real time actually this is
all real time the earlier import i did
speed up a little bit okay now if i go
back to maps I can also do custom
markers here so this is like a great
playground for if I just and seeing what
I can do with the data so if you like I
think Fusion Tables is great like if you
want to like if you don't know what you
want out of your data but you just want
to play around with it see what's
possible you can use it to do that and
then actually maybe when you decide what
you want then use a programmatic version
like use JavaScript to build your final
version
so here I'm just I decided to break my
data into buckets and i'm saying i'm
going to have green pins for greater
than twenty percent yellow for between
10 and 20 and then read for less than 10
alright so this shows me pretty quickly
that the u.s. was at least above ten
percent in all their locations which is
pretty cool now this is again one
dimensional so Fusion Tables does all
the one you can plot two dimensions of
data with scatter plots and here I'm
plotting the total number versus
percentage right and this actually shows
me pretty quickly that as x axis is
number of people so the more people that
attend the higher the more likely I am
to get towards the twenty percent the I
was at least above 10 the there was one
exception which is Argentina which was
nine percent but I thought that was
pretty cool the scatter plot actually
info window didn't show the the location
so it only shows you in the info into
what the x and y value is that was kind
of a limitation here the pie chart and
the line chart I can easily see which
location has the most number I can
obviously India had the most number of
flat people the the problem is that or
Bangalore location had the most people I
think the problem is again it's only one
one dimension of data
okay so here again is the chart where
we're using the aggregated counts to
show the number of people in each
country and in Google charts there is a
heat map gadget you can use to plot data
and this is a heat map of the number of
women who attended aggregated by country
and you can actually access this
functionality directly from google
spreadsheets there was a little bit of
difficulty plotting the data you need I
so country code and it has to be done
manually and you also need aggregation
count so your aggregation count had to
be done manually also it wasn't like
Fusion Tables where it actually
calculated it for you um so for non
programmatic tools for heat maps it's
like Fusion Tables is much more powerful
than Google charts the Google charts
does have some interesting things that
I'll talk about a little bit later the
next tool want to talk about is sick
rata so Tsikata is a company working on
open open data sources services for
government and it provides a platform to
help you share data with others so it's
used by the City of Seattle you can go
to data gov for examples and they have a
they have a way dogs to also upload your
data and visualize them using various
maps api s it's a little bit less
trivial than open heat map and it seems
that cicadas main use case is to quickly
allow visualization of existing data on
the platform so you can choose between
ging Google and Bing and esri maps like
the upper-left hat is a Google
visualization and the lower right is
ESRI and three minutes we were able to
create an account and upload a CSV to
plot the heat map of the country however
however like if you want to plot data
that's in a location other than country
or a US state you are required to
actually geocode your points and it is a
little bit slow to render so it's a
great way to visualize existing data
sets but it's probably not a perfect
tool for just one time data use okay so
then we moved on to the Google Maps API
and we created a map ski to use in our
application and we found it pretty quick
we found out like pretty quickly that we
could plot individual markers of data
using our aggregated data set so much
like what Fusion Tables had we were able
to come up with the same same with the
google map
api so it's very easy to take our
summary data points plot them on a map
and open up a window with the number of
people and the percentage of women in
that info window so we first initialized
the map we centered around Chicago I
think here and then i set the map
options and i chose a road map to use i
created a new instance of the map in my
map canvas div and the data the
locations data was a simple array right
with the columns being location latitude
longitude number of people and
percentage so i plotted the map I let's
see so we just loop through the data we
create new marker for each location and
we add a call to set markers in the
initialize function so then to add the
info window we basically have a little
bit of script which builds the the
content in the info window itself
pulling the data from the array passes
the the data to the marker and then adds
a listener to so that when a user clicks
on the map you get the info window you
and add a new instance of the info
window in the initialized method and you
get the map we looked at before the data
points like as i mentioned still don't
make you very clear from one view the
number and the percentage right i can
click on a point but it's not the same
as if i was able to see at once so we
kept looking and we came upon marker
cluster so Margaret cluster is an
extension to the Google Maps API written
by Frank woo and this is a plot of the
number of women that attended each
location using the extension so if I
know that over 1300 people attended the
hacks I can quickly see with this map
that women make up a small part of the
total attendees and I love the graphics
but this chart still doesn't show me the
ratio of men to women so it's difficult
to grasp the disparity and to use if you
want to use marker cluster though all
you had to do was include one file the
data did have to be one row per person
though and what it does we had one rope
for each woman that attended is like a
JSON object and the marker cluster would
then actually cluster the data for you
so if you had 30 woman in one location
you would have 30 data
points and then the marker cluster would
cluster all those points and make one
marker for it we loop through each of
the data points and created a new new
cluster marker marker and then we added
the layer to our existing map the other
another weakness we found for marker
cluster is that there was no way for the
tool to use different data like we
couldn't use like the female or the
percentages or it basically used the
number of data points you had in your
data so and there was no way to use a
field that you designated say okay the
number i want to appear in my map is is
based on this field and as we saw this
was a result so the cluster uses both
the size of the marker and the number
inside and the color to plot the same
data right so it would be really cool it
would be a really cool extension if we
could say that the size of the marker
represents the number of people that
attended and then the number inside
represents the percentage of women or
something something like that so you can
see two sets of data on one map one nice
feature about the marker cluster though
is the drill down capability it provides
so when I was looking here I was looking
at a zoomed out view so showing me only
numbers per country when i zoom in on
the map it automatically I'm zooming in
the u.s. here it automatically shows me
the numbers in the u.s. so we feel like
we're making some progress but there's
still like not clear visualization which
shows the number of people who attended
versus the percentage of women so we
continued exploring and we came across
layers in the Google Maps API and found
a layer for the fusion table heat maps
so we saw the possibility of integrating
our fusion tables with the Google Maps
API using the fusion table layers class
and we're like oh cool you know we can
use the Fusion Tables we have we don't
have to you know create export to CSV or
anything and create a heat map with the
Google Maps API and plot markers on it
and we'll have what we want so we
started looking and then we found this
is an example Google Maps API with
fusion table heat maps and it's plotting
beaches in Brazil and what it's actually
doing is plotting a single point for
each location so much like
what cluster marker had you have to have
one row for each data set and so this
wouldn't work with our aggregated data
where we only had one point per location
so the integration of fusion table and
Google Maps API to generate the heat map
didn't fit our use case it might have
been possible to do with individual data
but i think the the heat point still
came out really really small so we've
got to multiply it by a lot to get
anything really visible on a map if you
want to do it though here's how you do
it and it might be valuable it's it's
valuable if you want to use your data
directly from fusion table so here I'm
just accessing my that's the first
parameter to the Fusion Tables layer
instance is my fusion table ID so as
long as its public I can access it and I
can pass an option to set heat map to
true and then I can add the layer to my
map so heat map is heat map the heat map
option is probably not suited for
aggregated data though so we then came
across the circle class in the Google
Maps API we started with an initial
basic map with plots of all the cities
and we use the same data set that we had
in the basic map we first plotted
circles where the size was based on
attendance so you can see here Argentina
India Zambia and the Northeast US had
probably the most number of people
attending so creating circles was really
easy we just we basically used we passed
the circle options where we indicated
the color of the circle the opacity and
the radius which we did still have to
multiply by three thousand to get
significant size circles but we passed
the sorry the number of people that
attended which was our fourth data point
in the array and we passed that to an
instance of a circle so that was easy
and they were like okay well that was
easy why can't we just do different
color circles based on the percentage
the value of percentage right so we can
do the buckets again so we did that
pretty quickly so we use the the fifth
data point to say okay if the percentage
is less than 10 color is
um read if it's greater than 20 it's
green else it's yellow and then we
passed the color to the circle options
to get this so now again different sizes
are based on the size the circle is
based on attendance but now the circle
color is based on percentage so it's
easy to view which places had a lot of
people and also to gauge the relative
percentage of women and if you remember
like when we did the open heat map
screencast it was Columbia was really
big but here now it's saying Columbia
only has one person so you can you can't
barely see it on the map which i think
is more accurate representation so it
shows you it shows you both sets of data
now if I want to get more detail about
each one I can add back in a call to set
markers and info window and now I can
click on each point to get more detailed
information about each map and you can
actually also tie the info window to the
circles themselves so you don't need
them the marker points and then and the
actual we have a blog post up on our
Hawk right now which has has this map up
without the you can actually click on
the circles directly I'm another thing
is the circles automatically scale to
your zoom level which is pretty cool
okay so then we looked at Yahoo Maps web
services and also Bing and this is the
first map we created with the Yahoo Maps
API so we had explored the google maps
api extensively and we wanted to see
what Yahoo and Bing also had to offer
and it turns out the api's are all very
similar in structure the function names
are different but the structure is the
same so um you create a map you plot the
markers at event listeners for the click
to get the info windows one thing I
didn't like about the Yahoo Maps was the
default marker so i went ahead and i
found a class to you that the custom to
add your own custom icon and used the
same icon that Google Maps has um for my
yahoo map and I came up with this and so
I like this a little bit better now all
the api's offer the ability to use
custom icons and it's done in a pretty
smudge similar mantle manner so you just
create a new image set the source set
the size
and for Yahoo Maps it does offer an
option to actually move your marker move
your window around like offset your
window based on your marker and then you
make sure to pass the icon to your
marker now when we and when we looked at
the Bing Maps this was the map and when
we looked at the Bing Maps HS control it
turns out that their API is also very
similar in structure so um this is a
street view but and one advantage that
Google Maps does have is the street view
so street views avail I think I'm sure
almost everybody knows about it but it's
available by default when you create
your own map using the Maps API and we
thought maybe this will be useful in the
next hour hawk because to use before the
event so that people can actually find
locations of hacks because you're
usually going to a new new place this is
actually the where we had the Chicago
hack in December is the cna Insurance
Building in downtown Chicago okay so
next we looked at the Google charts
tools which uses the visualization API
and you can use it to embed an
interactive chart graph or other
graphics on to your web page and the
visualizations are interactive and also
expose events such as user mouse clicks
enable you to write code to create great
effects on your page so you can embed a
visualization either using javascript or
an embedded gadget and when what we did
earlier was a gadget but you can also
use the API to build your own and host
it yourself now if you use j/s there's
still the same limitations we
encountered when building the gadget you
need to you need iso country code and it
has to be done manually and you have to
add aggregate the data yourself and that
also has to be done manually and you
can't plot cities which is kind of
limitation it does provide a pretty good
legend but google charts is a great way
to plot like multiple charts
synchronized with each other on the same
page so if you have multiple charts and
you want two things happening to the
charts at the same time it's a great
option and there's also it offers a
large variety of options like table bar
line and some interesting custom ones I
actually saw some speedometers and their
examples which looked pretty cool so
they're constantly improving so it's
definitely something to look at also so
in conclusion if we take a
look at all the tools together and their
capabilities when we first started out
like the goals that you saw at the
beginning we really weren't sure what we
wanted but those goals like we came up
with those at the end and there's
criteria that you see across the top we
kind of came up with those after we had
done all the research because we weren't
really sure but realized what we really
wanted was to be able to visualize two
sets of data we wanted to see if it
required coding or not we would like
have liked it to be easy to make a
legend we also evaluated on how easy it
was to create the first map and do we
get full control or not and you can see
from this that the more control you have
the I guess the more control you have it
gives you the power to visualize two
sets of data right because you can
really build what you want on the map
whereas if you have less control it's
you're not able to visualize the two
sets of data I think the other thing is
as I mentioned earlier like Fusion
Tables was really powerful like if
you're just exploring data but if you
know what you want then maybe then using
like a programmatic tool such as Google
or Yahoo might be what you want so some
more conclusions it's very easy to plot
flat numbers with most tools plotting
multiple sets of data without code
though is not trivial and flash graphics
still are ahead of JavaScript graphics
with respect to data visualization and I
forgot to mention this but Fusion Tables
actually inputs your data into a flash
object to produce those maps whereas the
google maps api is all JavaScript most
map and charting tools need better
overall legend support the Maps API
products are very similar in structure
Yahoo is actually coming out with their
at 3i think they're at version 3.9 right
now but they're coming out with the
version for which people on my team are
working on Budish and it's using the
Nokia the the OV backend so I'm really
excited to see with what they have there
we've Justin covered the tip in terms of
data visualization there's there's a lot
of options
there and that you know that one hour
limit we had set for ourselves we I mean
we were not able to adhere to that at
all because there's just so much
information and it took us a while to go
through everything and figure out how to
get what we want and our visualize data
showed us that the more people that
attended the event the more likely we
were to meet the twenty percent
challenge we do need to improve an
automator data collection process as
much as possible for the June our hawk
we're using a vamp right and we're
hoping to scan people in as they come
and we're also collecting gender so it
should make it a lot easier we
definitely need more women hacker still
and when women do participate like they
did in Chicago if they win okay that's
it questions so in what way was /
superior ajs um well it's easier to get
maps where you can actually color in the
whole region like if I was coloring in
the the state or as coloring in the
whole country that was much easier to do
I think Google Maps actually provides
somebody has built out where they
actually plot those specific regions but
it's not you have to actually use that
extension it doesn't come built in okay
any other questions okay that's it
Laura did you remember to load the bacon