Trans Eye for the Cis Ally: Ensuring an Inclusive
Community
Julien Fitzpatrick
>> I'm kidding\h I do\h I love that song.
I know all of the words to that song.
So, I don't know if I'll be able to do karaoke
tonight because it's really late for me because
it's like three hours later inside of my body
than it is here.
So, but if I can, I will sing that song in
karaoke, I promise.
Yes.
All right.
So, I am extremely, extremely excited for
our next presenter.
This is a topic that is very near and dear
to my heart.
I am always trying to be a better ally.
And I think it really speaks volumes about
this community and the values that this community
holds that we have a talk like this interspersed
with all of the amazing cool, wow tech stuff.
So, Julien Fitzpatrick is gonna be teaching
us about how to be a trans ally and build
more inclusive spaces.
So, give it up for them.
Are you ready?
Yeah.
Give it up for Julien.
[ Applause ]
JULIEN: Hello, what's up, everybody?
Welcome to trans eye for the cis ally.
My name is Julien, I use they/them pro nouns.
I used to be a cartoonist, now a software
engineer.
I have been working as a programmer for the
last four and a half years or so.
I work at a company called Artemis.
This is an indoor agriculture management platform.
We are hiring, of course.
So feel free to talk to me later.
In my spare time, I enjoy power lifting, hanging
out with my really cute dog.
His name JPEG.
That always gets a really big laugh from programming
conferences.
I like to obsessively read about Freddie Mercury's
life.
And finally, I'm like kind of a Queer Eye
super fan.
So, what is Queer Eye?
Before we get to the actual topic of the talk,
I feel like I should give a little background
regarding Queer Eye just so we're all on the
same page.
Queer Eye is a show on Netflix, currently,
that on its surface is a makeover show.
Five gay guys take one person each episode,
make over their hair, clothes, their house,
their cooking ability, but most importantly,
their feelings.
Usually it's someone who's had kind of a hard
time in their life and they've struggled and
the fab five, as they're called, come together
to help them get their whole life together.
Almost every episode of the show ends up being
pretty emotional.
So, if you've never watched it before and
you really to want watch a feel good kind
of tearjerker show, I would recommend it.
I should also mention that before I go on,
even though I'm definitely a super fan of
the show, I don't think it's perfect.
There have been a lot of really valid critiques
about aspects of the show.
Even though I'm not going to talk about those
things right now, I'm happy to talk about
various critiques of Queer Eye in the hall
or on Twitter.
If you want to do that, let me know.
So, moving on, what does this have to do with
what we're talking about right now?
This talk is called trans eye for the cis
ally.
Which is after the original Queer Eye, called
Queer Eye for the Straight Guy.
I've never watched the original.
Don't talk to me about it.
I don't know that much about it at all.
It's honestly pretty different from what I've
heard from the modern one.
In this case, I'm the trans eye and you're
probably the cis ally.
If you're here, you are likely interested
in making your workplaces and events more
inclusive for trans people.
Which is great.
The truth is, there are so many small things
and some larger things that you can do to
not only give your existing trans coworkers
and community members a good experience, but
also to make sure that even if you don't currently
have any trans coworkers or community members,
you're providing a space and experience that
will be welcoming in the future.
So, let's start with the basics.
Not even the basics, but like the basics of
the basics.
So, what is trans?
What is cis?
The simple answer is that trans means you
don't identify\h or transgender means you
don't identify with the gender you were assigned
at birth.
That's it.
Not everybody who feels this way ends up identifying
with or using the word trans to identify themselves.
But the word is there if they want to use
it.
For example, a trans man was assigned female
at birth and figured out later that he was
male.
And a trans woman would be someone who is
assigned male at birth and later realized
that she was female.
It's not that complicated.
Yeah.
Cis just means you do identify as the gender
you were assigned at birth.
That's most people.
If the doctor said it's a boy when you were
born, and you're a boy, congratulations, you're
cis.
Not hard.
Transgender and cis\h people can't be transgendered
and cis gendered.
We jokingly say this, I trans'd you.
But you can't do that.
If you want to be respectful, use the words
correctly.
And non binary, you're somewhere outside of
the male/female binary.
There's a few common misconceptions about
what non binary means.
It doesn't mean gender neutral or androgynous.
Or assigned female at birth and leans masculine.
Non binary, it could mean that for some people.
There's not one way to be non binary or two
or three ways.
It means you don't fit into the binary and
this is the word you have chosen to describe
yourself.
Technically, it falls under the trans umbrella.
So, some non binary people don't consider
themselves trans.
This is fine.
If someone tells you they're non binary and
they're not trans, just say cool.
Serve different.
It's okay if you don't understand.
Something really important that cis people
don't get is it's okay for you to not understand
trans people in order to respect us and treat
us with dignity.
I don't know what it's like to be cis or straight.
It doesn't stop me from being able to respect
others.
You don't have to totally understand what
it's like to be someone in order to respect
someone.
Pronouns are a really good example.
So, when someone first comes out as trans
or you meet a trans person.
They might want to use different pronouns.
To you, they might not look like someone who
uses the pronouns.
Or maybe they/them pronouns and you have never
done that before.
Try.
All you have to do is try, you don't have
to get it.
If you mess up, just quickly apologize, correct
yourself, don't make a big deal out of it
and eventually it will be second nature to
you.
So, while we're talking about pronouns, I
should mention as an aside that a person's
pronouns are just a person's pronouns.
My pronouns are they/them.
It's become common for people to say preferred
pronouns.
But only when they're talking about trans
people.
Everybody has pronouns.
They're not preferred, they're just pronouns.
Also worth mentioning, some people have done
this in my life in the past.
Some people think they can use they/them for
everyone because it's a simple solution to
having to remember the pronouns for everybody.
This is not great.
If you have a trans person using he/him pronouns,
and you call him they, you're still mis gendering
him.
Think of it this way.
You have to think of different names for everyone
you know.
There's probably three different gender pronouns
that you have to learn.
Compared to learning all those names, it's
honestly not that hard.
So, now that we've discussed some basics,
let's move on to the next level and talk about
what you can actually do right now to make
things better and more welcoming for trans
and non binary people at your company or your
event or your meetup group or whatever.
So, back to pronouns.
For me, as a non binary, it's impossible for
someone to guess what my pronouns are just
by looking at me.
My life is a series of awkward situations
in which I have to figure out how to tell
a single person or a few people or a whole
room of people they use they/them pronouns.
This is the case for binary trans people too.
Just because I have to do it all the time
doesn't mean I'm good at it.
Or that I'm used to it.
I kind of hate it.
So, a really simple way to mitigate this is
just be proactive and make sure that people
are given every opportunity state their pronouns.
At the beginning of a meeting when a new person
is interesting introduced to the company or
whatever, just have whoever is running the
meeting start by being, like, my name is so
and so.
My pronouns are, you know, they/them or he/him.
And just have all the employees just kind
of be an example.
Make it a normal thing.
If you have an employee page on your website,
you can have people include their pronouns.
This also helps prospective employees know
that you tend to be a trans inclusive space.
It's something I look at when I'm looking
at people's job pages.
If they have pronouns, cool.
Honestly the bar\h it's slightly above the
worst.
That's great.
So, same goes for events.
Anywhere a person's name is listed, if they
want to include their pronouns you can include
their pronouns as well.
You can offer pronoun stickers or pins like
we have here.
Or just have a way people can write their
pronouns on their badges large enough that
people can see them easily.
Something I really like about these pins actually.
I have been to a lot of conferences with a
lot of pronoun things and I like this because
you can read it easily, it's large.
You can put it anywhere you want.
You can make is visible.
I think that's the best solution.
Even if you're cis, put the pin on and whatever,
write your pronouns.
Because you can encourage other people to
do the same.
Just make sure like when you introduce yourself
to people you say your pronouns.
Just, you know, that sort of thing.
So, this picture of pronoun stickers is from
a meetup where I live in Portland.
That's called Donut.JS, which is pretty great.
Yeah, make sure people know if they're interviewing
candidates to introduce themselves with their
name and pronouns and ask if the candidates
want to do the same.
Your company or event has a Slack, make sure
everyone know they can include their pronouns
or have the leaders include their pronouns
in the profile.
Make it a thing not only the trans people
have to deal with.
It kinds of sucks.
And also something I haven't written in my
notes.
I'm going ad lib, whoa.
Something people talked about and mentioned
a few times is you shouldn't force people
to share their pronouns.
That's also a thing.
Like, it's great to be really encouraging
about it, but some people are in the closet
and it sucks.
Even though it's totally understandable.
I'm going to refer to you with a third person
pronoun.
Tell me what you want to use.
It's so stressful for people in the closet
to have to think about it and put the wrong
one up.
I've had people tell me that before when I
talk about pronouns.
I wanted to mention that.
Don't force people.
But, you know, encouraging and if you know
you're cis, put your pronoun on.
So, on that note, you might to want consider
if you do have a trans employee or a co worker,
you might to want ask them what, if anything,
they want you to do if another employee mis
genders them.
Don't assume everyone is bold enough to correct
other people, especially if they're new.
And on the same token, don't assume they want
you to say or do anything.
Leave it up to them.
But find out in advance.
I can say\h depending on the person, it could
happen constant lily for them and it's gonna
come up.
So, you want to know the right response ahead
of time.
On that note, if you've hired a trans person
or someone has just come out to you as trans
and you're wondering if something is okay,
you should not assume.
You should ask.
So, for example, you have a non binary employee.
This is actually a thing that happen to me
at my old job when I came out.
So, usually when you go to conferences you
have like\h so, in our case we previously
had an even split of male and female employees
and we would share hotel rooms at conferences.
But instead of just assuming which person
I wanted to room with, my boss was like, hey,
how do you feel about this?
Which person do you want to room with?
Do you want your own room?
That sort of thing.
Yeah, don't assume what people want.
Just ask.
But also sometimes don't ask.
So\h so, like, stuff like that, yeah.
You should ask.
But there's a ton of thing that is you should
never ask.
Luckily this is, I think, really easy to figure
out.
But it still happens all the time.
So, think like before you ask somebody a question,
ask yourself if it would be okay to ask a
cis employee.
It's not okay to ask a trans employee if it's
not okay to ask a cis employee.
So, don't ask if they've had the surgery.
Like, the surgery is like some abstract concept
that is not real.
So, just\h it's ridiculous.
Anyway.
Don't ask literally any question that has
to do with their body.
But especially their genitals.
Like, you know?
Don't ask invasive medical questions.
You might think that these things are obvious.
But it happens all the time.
It's extremely common as a trans person to
have people you barely know casually asking
you about what's in your pants.
So, don't do that.
It's not appropriate.
Health insurance.
So, don't wait until a trans person is interviewing
for a job at your company to find out if you
have trans inclusive health insurance.
You should find out today.
Most insurance companies these days have like
a section in their literature specifically
about what is and what is not covered with
regards to trans health care.
So, just take some time and familiarize yourself
with it so when they ask, you can answer.
Bathrooms come up a lot.
You probably don't put a lot of thought into
them yourself.
And for a lot of trans people, it's a minefield.
And it's important that you know and understand
the extent to which we fret and worry and
stress out about them so that you can come
to it from a place of empathy.
So, one of the reasons I love working remote,
personally, is I never have to worry about
the drama of using a gendered office bathroom.
In the best scenario, feeling an.
Sometimes I waited until all the men left
and went to a meeting and then go to the men's
room.
Especially if I didn't know all of them.
Sometimes I even left an office to use a gender
neutral bathroom in a basement or a coffee
shop nearby.
If I'm at an event like a conference or a
meetup if I don't know the bathroom situation
beforehand, sometimes I will stop drinking
liquids hours ahead of time even if I'm thirsty
or I won't eat even if I'm hungry to avoid
having to use the bathroom because I don't
know what the deal is.
Unless I know there's at least one gender
neutral restroom available.
Then I'm not worried.
So, what I'm saying is for some trans people,
not all of us, mind you, but definitely a
lot of us, we put a lot more thought into
bathrooms than you might think.
So, what are some ways that you can deal with
this?
The best case scenario is that you have single
stall gender neutral restrooms.
This is the holy grail of the trans restroom
experience.
It's the least anxiety inducing experience.
Just degender gendered bathrooms.
There's no reason for a single stall bathroom
with a door that closes to have a gender.
And maybe you have bathrooms in several locations.
Is it possible that you could put signs up
on one and make that gender neutral?
Sometimes events like this event we're at
together, sometimes they put up temporary
signs over one set of bathroom to make them
gender neutral for that one event.
So, if you do have gender neutral bathrooms,
but they're hard to find, that also happens
a lot.
I have called myself a truffle pig for gender
neutral restrooms.
I will find it.
I've had people at conferences be like, where's
the\h brought you a map.
Yeah.
Put up signage.
This is helpful if it's somewhere else.
Put signage by the gendered bathrooms so people
know where to find the gender neutral ones.
It's worth a thought if you're hosting a company
event or an offsite that's a little more casual
like a small group.
It would be great if they could do recon on
the bathroom situation in advance so that
the trans people can know if there's, you
know, what's the situation?
Where I live in Portland, it's common, a lot
of bars and restaurants now have gender neutral
restrooms.
But it's not like to when I go to company
offsite.
Anyway, this might be a little bit of an unusual
tip.
And also might be totally unnecessary depending
on your company.
But personally, if I'm in a situation where
I have to use gendered bathrooms, like in
a sports bar or someplace that's really like
just men.
I\h sometimes I like to have a bathroom buddy
who will go in first for me and will be like
there is, you know, this many stalls.
The stalls are full.
There's three urinals or whatever.
Tell me what's going on in there so that I
can know ahead of time.
Yeah.
Occasionally I like my friend to go in with
me if it's really bad.
But that's pretty rare.
Year, I wrote this, already said it.
It come up in really masculine bars, sports
bars.
You don't have to do anything huge.
If you have a good friendship and they use
the same bathroom, it's worth privately at
these events, if you want someone to come
with you, I'll go with you.
But not everyone wants this.
So, as I said, it depends on the kind of relationship
that you have with your co worker.
I've had friends do it for me and it's been
really helpful.
It really sucks to be out at a bar with your
coworkers and you feel like you have to leave
early or you have to miss out on things because
you don't want to use the bathroom there.
And sometimes depending on the event and who
is there, it can be like you're missing out
on actually a really important networking
opportunity.
So, it's worth keeping in mind when planning
events or off sites.
But again, it's like don't just approach any
co worker like this.
Like you should know that you're really good
friends.
Otherwise it's really weird.
So, speaking of company off sites and events.
Sometimes you\h sometimes you might find yourself
traveling to and from an airport with a trans
co worker.
You probably know how terrible TSA is.
Like, have you heard?
But you might not be aware of like how awful
it can be for some trans people.
So, unfortunately there's not a whole lot
you can personally do.
But there's like ways you can be supportive.
So, you might not be aware of this, but the
scanners they put you through at the airport
require the operator on the other side to
decide over the course of about a second whether
to put you through as male or female.
So, the way the scanner scans your body for
bombs or whatever is that it sort of compares
your body to what it expects a male or a female
body to look like.
So, for example, before I had surgery but
after I was on testosterone, I was stopped
and frisked every single time for chest abnormalities.
And I still sometimes get stopped and frisked
for groin abnormalities.
But I had to get into the habit of stepping
into the machine, this is a thing I did when
I had boobs.
I would step into the machine lean out and
say, hey!
I have boobs!
Hey!
Usually they would be like\h uh?
What do you want me to do about it?
Just press the female button.
Press the female button and then it would
be fine.
But, yeah, it's not for everybody.
So, sometimes yeah.
Literally depending on the mood of the TSA
agent and how trans phobic they are, it can
go extremely poorly and result in a humiliating
experience if you're trans.
If you're in the cis person in the situation,
you don't have to do a lot.
Make sure you're nearby in the security line.
Pay attention to how the TSA is treating your
co worker.
This is rare.
But just be prepared to serve as a witness
if things go bad.
Consider having your phone ready to record
if something goes really bad and you have
proof.
if they are going to move them, step in and
say, hey, can I go with you?
Most of the time, it's just slightly awkward.
But things can and do go bad for trans people
moving through TSA.
It's important because this could happen to
a co worker or friend.
Being traumatized by TSA is a pretty bad start
to the work trip.
There was an article in The New York Times,
flying while trans that you can read.
It goes over a specific bad experience that
one person went through.
So, one thing you might not have considered
is how much more trans friendly your workplace
becomes when you let people work remote.
Even if you have a primarily real life office,
if you let people work remote, as much or
as little as they like without having to explain,
I'm working remote today.
You unintentionally solve a lot of problems
that trans people have in offices.
And some have days or weeks or months where
their dysphoria is really bad.
It can be really debilitating if you have
it bad.
Sometimes it's easier to be remote.
You don't have to manage your dysphoria in
an office setting where there's triggers.
I don't get much anymore.
But when I wore a binder, the ways that my
clothes fit would be a huge trigger.
On one occasion I had a panic attack at an
event because of that and I had to go home.
Yeah.
It just sucks.
So, sometimes if\h when I used to wear a binder.
It's really uncomfortable, restricts your
breathing.
Makes your chest hurt.
You're not supposed to wear it more than eight
hours if I had to go somewhere after work,
wear it for eight hours and go somewhere else
and be in incredible pain.
You're not supposed to do that.
You can literally break a rib.
Yeah, working remote means that you don't
have to do that.
If you want to go to an event later, you don't
have to wear the binder all day.
That sort of thing.
So, struggs to func.
It really goes for any marginalized group,
but you might not be aware, trans people's
rights are on the line constantly.
We have become a popular target of public
discussion in the news and a large variety
of other media.
If you're trans, it's almost impossible to
ignore.
And hard to deal with.
Because I heard that the Supreme Court is
going to decide whether I should be protected
from discrimination in the workplace.
Great.
Yeah, there's also the talk about rolling
back health care protections.
Yeah.
So, it's really stressful and terrifying and
it's hard to not let this kind of news affect
you when it has to do with your day to day
life.
Especially when sometimes it feels like nobody
even cares.
So, what can you do?
I strongly recommend reading this blog post
by Lara Hogan from 2018 called Managering
in Terrible Times that makes a lot of good
suggestions.
Personally I like seeing a show of public
support for coworkers.
Seeing them Tweet support is great.
At the last job, my boss put these trans flags
everywhere during pride.
It was really cute.
So, wonderful.
In recent years, I've noticed a trend among
meetups and conferences and stuff that used
to be for women in tech that are trying to
rename themselves to be more inclusive.
But unfortunately it often seems like they're
not really sure who they want to be inclusive
of.
They end up naming themselves women and non
binary or women and femmes.
And nobody knows what it means.
Womxn.
This is a truly well meaning way of organizers
to be inclusive of women, but maybe not trans
men.
There's a lot of confusion about who they
want to be inclusive of, what the best wording
is based on who they want to include.
If you're confused, I don't blame you.
It's confusing.
So, let's see what we can do about this.
First of all, I'm gonna assume whatever event
we're going to be talking about, it probably
started as something for women because women
are still an underrepresented gender in tech
and they're still a marginalized group.
Many women experience misogyny and discrimination
in the workplace.
And many were raised to particular personality
traits, not rocking the boat, not speaking
up, and this is a male dominated field.
Most men were raised to be the opposite of
the traits.
It can be exceptionally hard for women to
forge a path.
It makes sense that groups have popped up
so women in tech can organize.
In recent years women's spaces have, you know,
they've decided that they want to be more
inclusive of trans women, which is great.
As people have become more aware of the existence
of trans women and their collective need to
be accepted in women's spaces, and become
aware of others, usually non binary.
Usually they become aware of non binary people
because someone in the group who formerly
was in the group comes out as non binary.
And they don't to want exclude that person,
so they call themselves women and non binary.
This causes issues because non binary means
a lot of things, and femme means way more
than people think it does.
The messaging is confused.
Non binary people are assigned male, there's
people like me who were assigned female and
for lack of a better phrase now look like
men to most people.
Even though we're all non binary.
A lot of us wouldn't feel comfortable going
to the event, women and non binary, or women
and femmes.
Not to mention trans men who are often ignored
or forgotten.
They're still a large group who might have
experienced many or all of the situation or
problems as women in tech and they're completely
excluded.
So, what should you call it?
Yeah.
I just want to get it out of the way that
it's absolutely fine and okay to have something
that's just for women.
You're under no obligation to include other
genders.
And think about the mission, who you're including
and excluding and why.
I especially ask that you give serious consideration
to why you would exclude trans men because
you probably are.
Most but not all of the time these groups
and events with actually mean to include everyone
who is not a cis men.
Everyone assigned female at birth, male at
birth, non binary people, trans women, some
intersex people.
If you have taken the time to thick the mission
of your group or event, think, I want to include
all genders.
Strongly encourage you changing the name and
mission and call it marginalized genders.
It avoids describing your group in opposition
to something that it's not and instead describes
who it is for.
You can put an asterisk next to the name and
be more descriptive or put not cis men in
the space.
Or be sure you're accurately naming your group.
There's consulting you can hire to help out
with that.
I'm running out of time.
But my last tip is not to like\h if someone
in your office is trans and you want to look
something up on the Internet, like, don't
do that.
Don't look them up on the Internet in front
of everybody because you can unwittingly show
their birth name and all other information
that they would rather not show you unwittingly.
Anyway.
In closing, I want to reiterate that there
are things you should think about today.
Don't wait, you know.
Do it now.
I'm also happy to speak in more detail about
any of this stuff afterwards.
So, feel free to come up to me or Tweet at
me or whatever.
There's a lot of things I didn't get to speak
in as much detail as I wanted.
I'm happy to talk more.
If you have a really complex concern, I will
refer you to someone who does that for a living.
Not me.
I'm just a regular person.
But for most basic questions, I'm happy to
answer them.
Finally, I feel bad that all of my Queer Eye
GIFs, Bobby has been underrepresented.
here is one of the few Bobby GIFs I could
find.
Hopefully you can see why I wasn't able toll
find a place for it.
That's it.
I'm Julien.
You should talk to me.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
KATIE: Oh my gosh, thank you, Julien.
I learned so much.
I really appreciate you sharing your experience
with all of us.
If anyone needs a good name for their formerly
women and non binary people group at work,
at Etsy we've recently renamed to magic, which
is short for marginalized gender identity
community.
So, you are free to take Magic and use it
in your own company if you want to have a
group that encompasses all genders.
anyways.
We're going to take a little break.
Come back at 2:15.
Sara Fecadu is going to be talking about how
music gets from your computer out into the
speakers or something like that.
Anyways, it's going to be really cool.
I'll see you back here at 2:15.