hi welcome to Berlin evrim and that look
like an here myself everyone that
doesn't live here everyone that does I
see on a most viewed work with you all
my name's Ben green and welcome to the
most deliberately low-tech presentation
with Jess conf I'm really happy to be
here I work on a bunch of web projects
javascript-based and others and not
talking about those maybe next year if
they go well I work in Berlin for nokia
on a great big mapping application and
i'm not going to be talking about that
either if you wanted anything about that
andreas talk tomorrow is going to be
brilliant take your hangovers and enjoy
that so and then green but you can call
me anything you like Sideshow Bob is a
quite a common one and the title of my
talk is how to be better it's how to be
better how to get better and how to
decide how good you want to be how to
argue with jas lint but if anything it's
a celebration of core JavaScript so a
little bit peculiar coming straight
after Sammy's talk about frameworks
because this isn't frameworks it's
called JavaScript first question then I
suppose that needs to be answered is is
what is getting better mean the original
rubric for this talk said that it was
one mediocre JavaScript developers
tedious and ongoing attempts to become
slightly less mediocre that's me the big
shots of JavaScript to hear fortunately
no matter how ur embarrassed and nervous
I am I don't think I can be Brendan
Ike's nervousness and embarrassment this
morning when that a very nice young lady
sang to him so that's ok be the big
shots of JavaScript to hear I am NOT a
JavaScript demigod I'm not sitting on a
cloud saying hey I'll give you a hand up
this is how this is how you get here I'm
struggling to get there just exactly the
same as everybody else the second part
of it i suppose is when did javascript
get hard it is hard
about it there's a lot to learn when I
started on the internet when the
distinction between the internet and the
world wide web was still important and
relevant the internet at the time was
all particle physics and tributes to
Jerry Garcia if you don't know Jerry
Garcia was to see me after class and
light bulb jokes and Klingon jokes this
is an unsustainable ecosystem as soon as
the ultimate mashup of the internet
happened which was how many Klingons it
take to change a light bulb that was the
end of that he was doomed and we needed
something else new thing of course came
along thanks Tim was was the world wide
web and things started to get difficult
straight away in the in in the start it
was dead easy everyone wanted to get
their their documents their brochures
they wanted to get the math in in the
electronic space and this was by no
means programming there was nothing
about this that we would recognize his
programming today but at the time back
then no one could touch type computers
were still sufficiently intimidating for
a profession to grow up out of this then
those are nice folks at Microsoft and
then to invent it away where you could
change already you had free access to
the SRC property of an image for example
something we could change images and we
call this D HTML and then the again it
was Microsoft again they invented this
thing called Ajax and the job boards
went mental with we want people who can
you can speak Ajax so you looked it up
on the world wide web which we now call
the Internet where this time you looked
up and you found it was to new things
you need to learn one new xhr request
activex component thing and
onreadystatechange look this instead
excellent like into ajax and at this
point things started to get interesting
and we started the game called a mystery
a mastery buzzword bingo d HTML became
ajax ajax became object orientation
object orientation became behavioral
driven development don't know what the
next big thing is that we're going to
have to do is BDDs already about six
months old so in internet time table 2
certainly a little bit
but it's fear it's the paper scissors
rock Spock of JavaScript mastery bdd
beat 00 beat say Jack say Jack sweets
DHL DHL beats flash I supposed and the
it's about halfway through this list
some moved in a Jets an object object
orientation but things got interesting
and when it got interesting then we
could do more with it and when we start
being able to do more with it it
attracted a better a better caliber of
developer and better developers come in
why don't I do make it more difficult
for the rest of us the more difficult it
gets the better quality developers it
attracts the more the pay goes up I mean
it keeps getting harder and harder but
the great thing is all of this stuff was
there in in the in the original spectral
earring Douglas Crockford invented
invented Jason but it was already there
it was it was already part of JavaScript
I mean obviously harmony is going to do
great things about this and it's going
to it's going to make it all it's going
to throw away the rulebook an agency
it's going to come to a real proper
stuff so the question is if Java scripts
getting harder or subtracting better
developers and what are you going to do
about it and the original rubric I wrote
for this talk the one that thanks guys
got me the talk in the first place I'm
said something along the lines of you've
ripped yeah I'm missing a slide I'm very
gay just keep talking to each other okay
I'm missing a slide actually it looks
like that hey you can't say hey probably
probably turn up somewhere a little bit
later on in the image I this is low tech
as I said and the original the original
description of this talk said okay so
you've read the definitive guide you
flick through Dec my standard and you've
joined your local user group what are
you going to do now how do you take the
next step I spoke to a bunch of friends
of mine JavaScript developers of a love
and respect and think great things off
it turned out that none of them had read
the definitive guide and very few of
them a flick through the standard and
none
join local user group so I wish this was
on the on the on the screen HD cuz it's
a good one it's got takes this is this
is what I say is that the first step
this is this not what I want to talk
about today these are the first step so
going back in and look at these things
and of course it doesn't have to be the
definitive guide and the guy downstairs
talking in a minute is written in one of
the very greatest books on JavaScript
there is in my opinion and I don't know
why you're not all down there he's
wonderful you don't need to read easy ma
standard of course you can read Dimitri
shot and coughs explanation of it which
is just like the easy ma standard but
it's explained and it's got its got
getting a mission much much far fewer
square brackets in it which certainly
play with my head and you don't need to
join your JavaScript local user group
join a user group where you can talk to
other developers about coding about
writing stuff the things I want to talk
about today so just to go back and those
three things at the start they're not
the path the path I want to talk that
has these three strands on it our
purpose autonomy and mastery the talks
how to get better clearly we're at James
Caan forget me talking like JavaScript
we're going to be using javascript
examples but it's about getting better
this might not be the best talk here but
it's the only one that tells you it's
going to make you happier and healthier
and better person very good first often
the purpose what is the purpose of what
we're doing first up purpose is the
product that you're working on do you
love the product I'm lucky and working
for a team that really really gets me
gets me quite excited as a nine-year-old
kid the only thing that I thought was
really important in the world was maps
those are the maps and computers and
make care of the work down the chip shop
put them never got anywhere with a one
out of three of those so maps and
sausage million-match aspect and none of
us are feeding the world or curing it
evades unless any of you are in which
case comes me I'll give you a donation
afterwards good work but that doesn't
mean we can't engage with the products
that we're creating me I'm working on
maps Nokia Maps as I'm going to make a
big song and dance about it but the
purpose for the product
there are more important things in the
world and maps but I really love it
number two in purpose is your users your
personal experience on this one of
course of in freelancing for many years
now and working full time with the
product that I'm currently working on
it's in beta we don't have any users and
we have be two testers but you can't
trust them because they're all fanboys
which takes us on to the some familiar
not be nice about it either but there we
go which takes us onto the team the
question about the team is possibly the
one that's hardest to address and you
have to get on with your colleagues and
clearly if you don't then do something
about it if you're alone JavaScript
developer you're probably not going to
get any better it's going to be really
difficult for you try and get yourself
into a team clearly if you are Elaine
JavaScript developer if you're a jobbing
freelance and you're having fun
absolutely fantastic there are plenty of
talks at this conference that will help
you with your jobs in your day-to-day
work this talk is that how to get better
and it did say that you need to decide
how much you really want to do the
question that's relevant with your team
though about you getting better is are
you the best JavaScript developer on the
team if the answer's hell no that's fine
if you want is absolutely yes then it
probably isn't the important answer is
long ago yeah well not quite sure and if
you're in this position then you're not
going to learn as much from your team as
someone who's more junior so you now
have to you have to find out something
else to do so if you love your products
and you love helping your users but you
sort of may be top dog in your team it's
about time to start giving swing back
you got to mentor the juniors you got to
teach the world start a blog why not
there are loads of good blogs out there
but there's always room for another one
there's always a new angle and or you
can quit I've done it I've quit more
jobs than that I've had hot milk you
learn quickly as a freelancer jump
between jobs you will learn stuff from
people because you're meeting awful lot
of people you'll get exposed to a lot of
stuff it won't all be good you'll see
stuff that you go oh my god that's
terrible I did that last week and
you'll stop doing it you can learn from
negatives as well as positive and
but for my money the best way to learn
once you're getting good when she coming
somewhere close to mastery is long-term
development on full on multiple life
cycles of the product let's look at the
next one in purpose autonomy and
mastering mastery this is probably the
one that's sort of most interesting and
when I spoke to the organizers they said
I hope you're going to show us lots of
tricks and great little things that will
make you a better JavaScript development
i said course I am and there aren't any
it's as simple as that there's nothing I
can say do this and you will be a better
JavaScript developer understand
JavaScript you'll be about a JavaScript
developer but there's nothing I can say
there's nothing I can give you to take
away that if you start doing you'll get
better however we can say some stuff
what's mastery there is a definition of
mastery in a dictionary can't run which
one it was the ability of power to use
control or dispose of something so we
all use JavaScript this is good we're
all here because we use JavaScript but
do we control it or does it control us
control is deliberate and careful
construction really glad to see Sam eat
on that construction we're constructing
stuff are we constructing JavaScript or
are we checking it all together in in a
pile like a rubbish bin outside the
restaurant are we making it go beyond
what it what we think it can do what we
think they can naturally natively do to
dispose to dispose of something the
meaning of disposes to throw away is a
fairly modern meaning really what it
generally means what what it's always
used to mean was to deal with finally
and conclusively so to achieve mastery
in something is to use something
deliberately and conclusively are we
using our JavaScript like this an
example maybe is the best JavaScript
developers I know right the best unit
tests okay we don't need to open a
conversation on unit tests we all right
then we walk one hundred percent
coverage we all run them for every
commit go sweetie especially me they're
our team members of mine here they're
the ones laughing hardest I think I can
feel it and
the best JavaScript Phillips I know
right best unit tests this isn't an
accident it's because they're writing
tests which there aren't a code excuse
me which they control which they
natively understand there's nothing
strange about it there's a famous
golfing quote that's variously
attributed to arnold palmer and gary
player but it was an actual fact neither
of these after shooting extremely long
and difficult part on the 17th green no
error and syncing it some some wise
commentator said you know Arnold Oh Gary
or whoever it was you're really lucky
the answer was I know it's amazing and
the more I practice the luckier I get
it's the same with writing unit tests if
you're in control of your code your
tests will be easier it's a good it's a
good mark of if you're if you're winning
if your unit tests are getting easier to
liberals inconclusive means there are no
wtf's in JavaScript here's my favorite
one okay I'm sure you've all seen it
it's so it's not completely unheard of
its it's not particularly new it does
matter it's still my favorite even
though it's old I have two expressions
the first one has an empty array
equivalent false the second one has not
an empty array equivalent false
presumably only one of these expressions
can possibly evaluate to true the other
one must be false question announcers
are boring I'm not gonna not going to
say your hands up or anything but these
want the folks here encapsulate pretty
much all JavaScript WTF so at least all
the easy ones foxy values type coercion
and operator precedence they're both
true the first one is simply a statement
of fact the foxy values in javascript
need to know them do we all know them
faulty values and Java scripts are right
there if you have an empty array it
equates default however the truthiness
of an empty array you stick a stick of
bank before it and you no longer looking
at the mt array you're looking at the
truthiness of an empty array eraser
objects objects are always truthfully
objects aren't in that list so the
truthiness of an empty object of an
empty array negated false both of those
statements are true and when i first
started designing this talk i thought
about starting with foxy values and then
the phone
sizing and and we're all way beyond that
and then a couple of days later and I
genuinely do work with some of the best
JavaScript developers I've ever met I
found a wrong falsely value someone had
got something on so learn the small
stuff first I know you all know this you
all know there are six foxy values not
five and not seven in you can you can
you can read all them all off on the top
of your head off the top of your head
but first thing is learn the easy stuff
secondly it's learned more difficult
stuff again this is patronizing leeez
I'm not attempting to show anyone
anything new here two ways of making an
array one is using new word over the
array constructor and the second one is
the the literal construction of it okay
my suggestion isn't that this is really
new and exciting it's just a nice card
to show what I actually want to say
which is there a 21 native methods of
arrays his little game for you to play
afterwards mix up with pairs or threes
or fours sperling it's swinging when
none of us might after the talk grant
paper and a pencil and see if you can
write down all of the 21 native arrays
native methods of a raise my betting is
very few of us would be able to do it
I'll give you a clue there are seven
mutators seven excesses and say seven
iterators but you know if you don't know
this stuff and you're not was that so
that's what someone's directing me which
is entirely possible i love accumulating
these i'm a twitcher a twitter in
english is a birdwatcher I almost keep a
little book by the cert of my desk and
every time I use a new array method I
noted down with the date and feel
extremely proud of myself this one I
don't actually clearly there'd be far
too nerdy and I got to use a raise some
for the first time this week and that
made me extremely happy then there's one
of your iterators by the way that's som
e honest lee seun doesn't exist if it
did i guess you'd use array reduce
there's another one there's two
iterators some and reduce just fine for
those together and so when your erase
learn your foxy 840 values start simple
around 40 values we build up strings are
easy there's not so much to learn about
those coercion but stringz usually win
that race learn objects learn how to
tell a raisin objects part
something that was in my talk earlier
but speaking to Morgan sitting at the
front a friend of mine and named quite a
velocity something that came up there
just this morning was know the
difference between global variables and
properties of the window object they
look exactly the same but they're not
these are the things that mastery
requires and power it requires power and
mastery and so there are two more things
aren't say about JavaScript I've got no
idea how I'm doing for time I'm probably
speaking Farsi fast and nearly finished
the first thing I want to say I musingly
coming straight after also learn css3
transitions there's the slide won't help
you with your JavaScript but it'll make
you a better developer I promise you
learn them they're really awesome but
let's flip over them and it'll mean you
lose use a lot less jQuery helpers then
we are allowed to use things to help us
to learn core java script this is fine
I'm not too too harsh on this one he
says help is part one then his
frameworks and we've just seen fantastic
fantastic talk about frameworks by a guy
who knows an awful lot more about in
than ID our frameworks are good faint
frameworks fill the holes in JavaScript
implementations and browses the shins
and they even out accesses to things
that are difficult it's ridiculous that
the event model is still kind of hard to
get to and not completely constant
across all browsers it helps us with
repetitive tasks helps us do stuff that
we would find difficult to do otherwise
my question is why they say damn big and
why do they do so much stuff um there's
a whole bunch of them and clearly know
some of them some of them you don't for
example those ones as the ones i wrote
you never heard them because i never
released them if you if you need the
shins and you're traveling from job to
job let's get rid of those because
you'll just focus on them I used to
carry these things around on a floppy
disk which became a CD which became a
pen drive which broke and I've got a
backup somewhere I'm sure you carry
around the functions that you really
need
all of a sudden you put the frame that
you put functions you really need on a
floppy disk and you've got yourself
framework one impeachment one beseech
Minh please do not put them on get there
are enough there already use them to
Sammy said use them to fix the problems
in your application in other words write
them for your application no doubt about
it you will code faster using a
framework you will knock stuff out more
quickly but I'm not interested in what
your freelancer day rate is I'm
interested in making us better call
javascript developers and one word is if
you use a framework even when the
awesome ones i read you will not become
a better called JavaScript developer i
also have an interlude very nice a
couple of things about helpers this is a
help as interlude we're on the subject
of both get and helpers here are some
things to consider as a JavaScript
developer using vile vin drinking energy
drinks using now using get all of these
will make you a better call javascript
developer in exactly the same way that
riding a fixie makes you a better
JavaScript developer I don't care what
ide what takes 30 to use I don't care
what you drink club parties disgusting
whatever I don't care if you're on git
or svn or if you're on sneaker sneaker
whatever it is it doesn't matter it's a
it's what you do and not particularly
the tools you use to have you there I
told you use to do it I'm we spring this
on to help us part 2 as I'd like a
Bering a lot of fist fight after this we
better move away from the get in the air
and the the club Marty conversation and
move swiftly on help us part 2 could
also be called coffeescript vs jayus
lind best way to look at these are
spaced best introduction is to look at
some quotes best quote I over heard
about coffee script was actually from a
boss of mine is that everyone gets bored
of writing braces sooner or later and if
you're using it on coding on a german
keyboard you're going to get bored of
them even sooner it's a real finger
that anyway this quote I honestly don't
remember who is
there was from one of the gods in es
discuss it might be market smell it
might have been half an hour ago I knew
the other person it might have been the
better JavaScript rewrite excuse me the
better your coffee script will be seized
me dry up the better JavaScript you
write the better your Papa script will
be coffee script doesn't improve your
JavaScript it writes your JavaScript for
you it's sugar it makes things easier if
we're attempting to be on the path to
perfection the path of mastery the path
of getting better if you're committed to
this road of improvement you do not want
to be making things easier for yourself
you want to me making them more
difficult for yourself improvement comes
from overcoming hurdles from bettering
your knowledge not from bypassing them
and taking shortcuts j/s link will hurt
your feelings it's the only quote about
Jazlyn that really matters it's from
Crockford himself everybody knows it by
gun does James Lind hurt my feelings it
puts boulders in my path but then sort
of that sort of boulders that I like but
my rules for Jay Iceland you can only
stop using it when you can effectively
argue with it I've seen some arguments
against Jazlyn that I do not understand
at all if I don't understand those
arguments then I don't feel that I'm
that I'm allowed to use them well you
can do those you can look at the options
one bar with white reg 81 violent forces
hoisting stick variable at the top with
says we're not allowed to use it whiting
forces whitespace rules and regs kills
records basically that's southern bottom
you don't have to be able to argue with
the whole of jazz Lind but you can only
start turning options off when you can
argue with those options reg ex really
easy to argue with the rules for reg ex
ganja in jail in break almonds
nationalization
personally I've fair dealing in
internationalized stuff can I turn that
off nice and easy white space does an
argument that says code consistency is
good there's an argument that says why
are you telling me to use white space
it's a little bit trickier to argue it
with for example and the guy currently
talking downstairs won the JavaScript 1k
competition this year I don't have seen
this little canvas jumpy gaming house it
fantastic crack open the code have a
look at it it's amazing it relies
extremely heavily on with other than
that with is generally dangerous it's
generally bad if your code is good
enough to win the JavaScript 1k
competition don't use with other than
that it's probably considered bad 1-var
if anyone can find an argument for not
doing this buy me a drink now by your
jigger and buy you out by your case of
drinks there's nothing you can argue it
about one where at all so James min term
bits off a my mind I again turn bits off
hey when you can argue convincingly with
them which leads us to a graph this is
the graph of J's link vs coffeescript
usage percentage you're allowed to use
them plotted against your own personal
JavaScript skills ors CoffeeScript makes
things easy jobs could make things hard
as you get better you can start using
one more than the other
then we'll note on that javascript makes
you think CoffeeScript makes you fast
we're good if you need to think then you
shouldn't be speeding up so we called
tell me alone when I'm good if you need
to think you don't need to be speeding
up coffeescript is not a shortcut to
mastery it's not a short cuts getting
better it's the reward you get at the
end for being that damn good it's the
Karate Kid apprenticeship comes before
mastery if you can't wax on wax off
you're not allowed in the ring couple
more things to say not very much nearly
there at the end probably a bit too
early being speaking too fast one of the
most important things and Sammy touched
on this as well is the styles change
about a year ago dis looked horrendous
this looked terrible to everyone that
saw it I still know some people who
argue with it I think it's really cute
and really neat and it's not new and
we've all seen it yeah assignment by
what is it son by some sort of boolean
check first I think that's absolutely
fantastic be prepared for be prepared
for styles changing and adapt your stars
to them be aware of when they're
changing as well this one here's a
little more controversial maybe if you
go to google and you type in javascript
assignment in conditional you get 15
pages of java developers saying this is
so bad don't do it don't do it again i
disagree i think this is this is really
quite elegant and it saves a line and i
think it's a thing it's gonna start
getting used an awful lot more last
thing on mastery and I was gonna say
quite a bit about garbage collection and
making things faster but I think a lot
of you were just downstairs and most of
what I was going to say I was going to
Nick from his talk so if you've seen all
that there's no point be going over it
and Sony we're going to skip everyone
and pretend that wasn't there there was
a mistake in it several mistakes in it
high-end mastery then we've done the
easy stuff done false values done
strings with an object's have done
window objects we know all the methods
of all the natives high-end mastery then
is about garbage collection if you've
mastering if you're mastering the
intermediate then move on to the
the real hard stuff the only thing I
really want to say about garbage
collection is objects are not data dumps
the most I remember one step forward
that I took was when I was passing a
single parameter into a function and
suddenly I needed to pass too and as I
crap how am I gonna do this because I
really couldn't modify anything in the
code and guy sitting next to me I was
much younger obviously guy sitting next
to me they passed an object in I thought
this is actually fantastic you got two
parameters for the price of one really
really useful these days they my opinion
is that you should never ever use an
object as a data dump never just keep
willfully extending an object it's
really really bad the key word is keep
your object shaped object shapes the
same and I'm afraid I don't have a card
for this but if two objects have exactly
the same structure then as you'll have
heard from downstairs I expect you
mentioned it the comparisons getting
something like absolutely blindingly
fast so tidy up your objects for me this
is the one that I'm at at the minute and
I still extend objects absolutely
willy-nilly I spoke to a colleague of
mine about this and he said yeah it's
dead easy always use constructors for
objects great advice it's long that I'm
going to be trying to go for our next to
the final thing then in achieving
greatness is autonomy autonomy is what
happens when you have enough space and
enough time to think about stuff the
fable urban myth by Brendan rising j/s
in 10 days it wasn't that he sat down a
rated in 10 days it's that he was given
10 days of free time in which to write
it a 10 days of free time is not a whole
lot but these 10 clear days without any
molestation when he could bring together
everything he knew about Netscape and
small talk and hyper card and all the
other things in you and he was allowed
this creative splurge and if in your
workplace you are not given free time to
do some of your own stuff I'd change it
I mean change it is actually relatively
straightforward getting there get
yourself research days and research
weeks if you're really lucky allow slack
in your in your agile planning because
we're all doing our job clearly allows
slacking you're planning to do extra
stuff just to sit and think if that's
all it takes and you need space and
time and privacy I supposed to combine
new ideas and autonomy leads to
inspiration inspiration is ideas having
sex inspiration leads to genius genius I
told you don't say that and so talk
about purpose how to get greater
JavaScript need purpose you need to
understand your product and you use as a
new team and you need to know that
they're all working for you mastery do
the easy stuff first don't assume you
know all the easy stuff because you
probably don't the intermediate stuff
has anyone come up with the 21 array
methods yet let me know first onto it
i'll buy them a beer as well issouf on a
beer and the stuff you don't know the
real difficult stuff go over there as
well autonomy allow yourself the room to
breathe and room to think be the author
of your own ambition decide how far you
want to take it and most importantly
keep it to yourself don't tell everyone
what your ambition is they won't help
you necessarily with it thank you very
much that's the end apart from the
course the final slide I know there's
only one reason you've stayed at the end
you want to know how many Klingons it
takes to change a light bulb well the
answer is Klingons are not afraid of the