so this is going to be a little bit of a
crazy talk I've had seven espressos this
morning if I can get my hands stop
jittering it'll be even better all right
so uh fuck cyberspace let's do it live
this is seriously the live part of the
live action because it's live I just did
the slides up there two minutes ago this
is going to be live I have a cow to
prove that it is actually alive see this
for all those who weren't listening only
in Portland does that happen so in order
to get you acquainted with what I'm
about to talk about I need everyone to
close their eyes and think back to their
days back in the early 90s everyone
please just close your eyes please don't
put your fork into your mouth when you
close your eyes but just close your eyes
come on do it do it try it try
how many of you grew up to those
beautiful beautiful beautiful sounds how
many of you secretly at night maybe put
it on just to go to bed good i see some
like-minded individuals here so i'm here
to make a proposition that not a lot of
people are gonna like it's that the
internet sucks all of its parallel
computations concurrency all this other
stuff happening all the same time forget
that that stuff sucks I mean we're all
at no DJ s nothing happens all at the
same time right no okay I do want to
make a comment on that hit when mono
multi and Tyler are crawling on rooftops
that's when the Internet's awesome let's
give them a round of applause really
quick but seriously though I do miss AOL
I miss those days when we had PBS's and
you know you always get that wing sock
dll error at the wrong time i talked to
a lot of people nowadays and and it's
funny some of the means that lived and
existed like hey man what's your baud
rate I've got 5,600 on this oh I'm
rocking the hard speed of a 56k modem
whoo we need to bring those days back
and it's actually unfortunate that a lot
of people don't know how to utilize a
serial port I mean how many of you have
eight how many of you have a serial port
on your computer right now raise your
hand point moving what do you think the
S&C r USB is it's for cereal all right
so we have all these serial connections
we don't use them as developers and what
I'm here to tell you about is that you
can use them as developers and you can
use them just as easily as if you were
to write a socket i/o client and that's
why I decided to write a library for it
to help people build the Death Star do
you guys know what the Death Star is let
me show you
continue with the operation you may fire
when ready
that's right you know it never works
when you want it to
so the Death Star was a very very
complicated machine that was designed
for a single purpose of destroying stars
so obviously with that intent you would
need five different buttons to hit in
order to get the laser to work this is
very much how serial port code works and
that's part of the reason why most
people don't write serial port code
anymore you have to deal with things
like software flow control hardware flow
control baud rates retries potentially
if you're going out of further wire what
happens if the packet gets messed up
it's also why a lot of people don't
write tcp code at low levels but you
know what I like writing code at low
levels I think Ryan also likes writing
code at low levels sometimes so let's
get back to the slides and I took it
down so what I'm here to say is don't
call this a comeback people have been
doing this stuff for decades and decades
and they're still doing it in back
offices in the basement and you know
it's fun it's a lot of fun in fact right
now is a great time to be doing this I
don't know if you've been upstairs yet
we have the cool little arduino starter
kits up there they allow people like us
who may or may not have had a lot of
hardware formal training to do things
with hardware but in order to get access
to these you have to do serial code and
up until now nodejs developers are not
JavaScript developers web people have
not had access to that communication I
built the library that allows you to
talk directly to these devices through
nodejs so please oh the one this is the
one person who is used it let's give him
a round of applause I built it
personally not for arduino although that
wasn't nice side effect that I didn't
plan on I built it for other things like
x10 z-wave zigbee these are things that
you can put around the house and I was
going to turn off all the lights but we
were afraid we might not get them back
on it if you don't know what those
protocols are go home and research them
they are awesome what you get is you get
a little USB stick you can use the
serial port code to push down
information like turn all my house
lights on wind door opens shut dogs door
when a car comes in turn on no lights in
house it's a beautiful
full thing Nikolai are you here the
dream is alive in Portland Nikolai had
this theory of taking jquery style
syntax and saying instead of a document
object make it a house object and then
flow down from there with this code you
can do that other things like rack
server monitoring your car with this you
can actually program your car in
JavaScript I might be the only one who
gets giddy about that but I'm kind of
excited and mobile devices the the
beauty of a mobile device is everyone
talks about how advanced they are they
still run on serial ports so here's
where the package is go play with enjoy
and if you want you can go upstairs and
we can play with it together it's a
great great thing it's a fun fun world
and everything just happens one after