Thanks as an insurance policy in case my
demo doesn't work today I brought it out
last night I was working at all today so
there are some people who actually did
see it work so let's see if the demo
gods are nice to me
so everybody loves robots right ow
Jason Huggins co-creator of the selenium
project and co-founder CTO sauce labs
you should follow me on Twitter all
right so this is for the next three
slides and only the next or two or three
slides is a repeat after me thing so
everybody get your vocal cords warmed up
repeat after me
testing let's try that again testing is
not cool let's try that again oh I won't
I'll just let you do it you don't really
believe it I don't I don't believe it
anyway you're wrong by the way you can
stop repeating so here is a nice little
philosophy thought process here robots
are cool robots can test their for
testing with robots is cool tada
so this project really is I've been in
this whole testing thing I'm kind of you
start as a developer fell into software
testing by accident it's actually really
interesting intellectual problem for me
and I think if you don't care about
testing it means you don't have an app
with any users or that makes any money
right which sounds like an insult but
actually if you're like a stealth
startup it's more important to you know
if you're two guys in a garage two girls
in a garage
the more important thing is to ship
anything something that's relevant that
people care about and so at the very
beginning yeah testing is actually not
important but once you do have users
once you do have revenue what it comes
down to is once you're at 3 a.m. and you
get a page that something is broken
you're gonna want to fix that problem
and then want to start doing testing so
you never have to do that again of
course it's you know it's harder than
that but testing it testing is important
anyway so today the the the thing I've
been doing all these last years is doing
all the software stuff and this project
I call it it's made of this building
material called bit beams so that kind
of the home for this project is called
bit beam gorg
and I'm really kind of taking the
software out of the computer and making
a test in the real life so it's kind of
like if you remember Tron the movie you
know he falls in the computer this is
kind of like the reverse Tron I'm taking
the selenium the software robot out out
into the real world so let me tell you
briefly a little bit like where this
story came from or where this where this
kind of crazy thing came from
so a long time ago Sony came out this
thing called the robot dog and I've
actually always been interested in
robots ever since I was a kid and then
the late 90s Tony came out with this
thing is like oh my gosh the robot
revolution is on which is also weird
robot revolution is also on now it seems
like it kind of goes in waves like every
10 years there's like a new revolution
anyway back then robot dogs so I had
this idea to you know long story but I
was gonna do robot fish right why not
right and so I started to make these 3d
simulations of house fish swam I bought
books I went to aquariums and I learned
this crazy thing that fish swim in a
sine wave if you kind of look at it
especially like an eel it's it's very
much a perfect sine wave thing so I
started doing 3d simulations and on the
software not on this thing but I had
this thing called pin arts I hope
everyone's gonna seen this not everyone
knows that it's called pin art but
everyone knows what I'm talking about I
had this kind of this thing was sitting
on my desk and yet I was doing 3d
simulation of swimming fish and sine
waves and stuff like that on my desktop
and I thought wow it's ironic I really
want to see this 3d animation but it's
trapped on this 2d piece of glass so
this is kind of you know not talking
about software robots but this is kind
of like this art project hobby thing
that I've had going for a while this
motorized pen art idea is something I'm
still I want to have existed in the
world um so I started again just this
hobby not related to testing not a job
related thing I didn't know what to call
my motorized pen art thing so I called
it pin thing and I've got a demo here
the
think about this I guess in the room I
don't I haven't met mr. doob yet is he
here or is he around anyway but this is
3j s on on the software and then I'm
using the RAM Remy's console and so the
idea for this little art project is to
you know if I want an array of pins I
can do all kinds of animations but to
kind of start simple I think maybe if I
get four of these I could do a clock and
you know the whole point of the really
this project is like I want to get into
robotics and mechanics and all kinds of
fun stuff again still not related to
testing not related to anything j-job
related but this pin thing I want to
exist and while I was still working on
this project actually I'll switch
forward
I was prototyping in Lego I have to
figure out what the actuator is for each
one of those pins and I did a first
version in Lego and then I realized okay
now that I have that working there
here's the clicker the linear actuator
but if I scale this out to thousands of
pins wow this is going to be really
really expensive so then I so I could
kind of put the project on hold for a
little bit I then went to a Maker Faire
and discovered this project called grid
beam this is for making for like
standing desks and tables and beds and
all kinds of crazy things this is one of
the co-inventors Richard Jorgensen he
lives in Northern California and yeah
this is a standing desk I'm kicking in
the shins like yeah they should this is
a really cool building material it's
like life-size like a rector set kind of
stuff anyway so I I knew of this project
and so like wait a second Lego is cool I
like the geometry but it's expensive so
I had this crazy idea it's like combine
Lego the geometry of it with grid beam
basically report Lego geometry to
different you know cheaper materials and
now I've got this thing again this thing
is meant to be vertically vertically
aligned for my pin thing project but
then as I was walking around the house
with this and you know I actually you
know held it upside down and kind of
noticed actually you know it could be a
pin simulation thing but it also is kind
of like a glorified button clicker you
know and realizing that's kind of what
selenium that's what testing really is
that's actually what makes testing
uncool as people that you pay probably
offshore somewhere and just they just
pay to click buttons all day
it's like wait a second this potentially
could be a button clicker and this is
where it became not so much an art
project but potentially related to the
day job so I designed this this robot
basically the first version of it around
around this clicker and so now I have
got that this is actually generation 2
we see over here bit bean BOTS
and of course you know testing you know
selenium and apps that I tested
originally you know time expense apps
very boring makes for very boring demo
but so trying to go for the most
ridiculous thing I could think of I was
like well if I can make it play Angry
Birds it can do anything right so that
that was that was the mission make this
robot clicker thing play Angry Birds and
so there's there's kind of the thing
I've realized in building ground of
robots that's really kind of like a
triathlon of things you need the
electronics the mechanics and the
software most of the stuff I think in
this room we're mostly really geeking
out on the Arduino and and the software
side so the demo I have thanks to Chris
Williams at the johnny-five and Fermata
you know upskilled my software it was
the latest node stuff the thing that
struggle that I struggled with the most
is all of our robots need skeletons so
like the node copter stuff is cool but
that's kind of an off-the-shelf
proprietary thing and so for me to I
want to do robots I want it to be a
completely open source stack all the way
down so the mechanics was I think I
really stumbled I stumbled on but now
that I've created basically an
open-source Lego I now can do the
software the electronics and the
mechanics all open source so that I
guess that's the way I called the bit
beam project it's you know Linux is to
Microsoft as bit beam is to Lego my only
problem though is no one hates Lego I
hope I picked a really bad enemy there
but they do sue people they do that
patents thankfully most of them all of
them I hope most of them have expired so
I I mean it is public domain they're
expired to expire patents at least so I
can kind of a they don't they might sue
me anyway but we'll see you know so that
there's this idea this this again I've
said this before but you know selenium
and starting from that it's a software
based robot it's really just a glorified
button clicker you know so you know
could we make a robot that does that
does this
thing so long a dream for this then is
to have the selenium API where and I
don't have that today but you know at
some point you can say you know I want
to drive Firefox I want to drive Chrome
Safari or I want to drive an iPad in a
robot and as far as you're concerned the
API is the same so I'm still driving
towards that vision right now it's
there's kind of low-level API is yes
let's switch to a demo so I'm using a
photobooth it's inverted to the the
screen here so let's get my windows all
set up so the first thing that you want
to do when you want to have a robot the
plaything Angry Birds you need to select
the app right right so I'm in the app
and I know I will get to be the frontier
right yes so one of the things this is
this generation 2 of this robot this is
actually called a Delta robot you could
perhaps see it here if I can kind of a
shall do a little tour of the robot here
there's three arms that's why it's
called a delta it was invented I can't
forget his name but it's actually a
Swiss engineer in the 80s and no joke he
he designed you know the disc delta
robot design too from Switzerland of
course it was conveyor belts of
chocolates coming off the conveyor belt
and they're trying to get chocolates
into packages and they were noticing and
that everything was automated except
that last parts where the chocolates
were being picked up by humans and
putting in boxes like all could we do
that so they needed as the conveyor belt
was going pretty fast they need a very
fast robot designed so as I was
embarking on this video game robot thing
it needs to be fast
someone saw my first version of it so
like wow that's really slow you should
check out a delta robot thankfully the
patent has expired so hey I can I'm
legally allowed to to build a delta so
anyway there's this thing so yeah it's
it's kind of its kind of creepy cool
right yeah
so keep going on with the demo here
now for the big point actually hybrid
manual testing right okay so uh I have
to get into position I wonder if this is
actually work oh yeah sure
famous last words
[Applause]
okay now once is just luck right so
let's see if I can do it again wants I'm
lucky - I'm good let's see I improve my
score I think that was one star how many
stars do you think it is one - I think
that was one if you hit that if you hit
right that corner you get three only one
Sara okay so I've got I've got a room
for improvement right so so let me
actually show you a little bit actually
one of the things I just got working
today there's this really robotics is
ultimately very simple but they use if
you study robotics classes they've used
all these big words so you can sound
very smart at a cocktail party but it's
very simple stuff one thing is to tell a
robot to go to a point it's very simple
like you don't even think about it as a
human you just like oh I want to pick up
the glass boom that is a that fancy
phrase and robotics is called inverse
kinematics and I have an inverse
kinematics library I'll put on github
after the talk and there's really kind
of there's two things in robotic lands
there's inverse kinematics basically
saying like there's an XYZ point in the
universe I want to get to it that's what
you have to do is like your robot
doesn't know about anything about
geometry in the world but it knows that
it's got a motor that can go 180 degrees
and this motor can go this and so what
you have to do the inverse kinematics is
this is to say given an XYZ point in the
universe what are the angles for all of
the motors to get to that location so
I've I've had this robot actually for
you know a couple months now but I've
had a very low level API I granted all
these go commands that's pretty low
level but it's higher than it was a
couple hours ago what I can do then is
just give it a particular location and
then it figures out this very fancy
algorithm translates that to what the
server's need to go to so if I can I can
do some simple things now again it's X Y
Z so
so the origin is in the sensor and I'll
see you naked 1 120 that's in the z-axis
and I can kind of go there and if I want
to go down I can kind of keep doing that
that the surface or the tablets right
around 150 I'll so I'll just keep it to
keep it safe there's that so you can
kind of see the input go is X Y Z and
the output is going to be the angles
that the servos need to be when it's on
the origin they're effectively all the
same but if I go you know often in
Cartesian on a Keynesian adventure
that's negative 50 X and that's plus 50
X or I can do that's why and then
negative Y so now I have like anywhere
in the X Y Z plane I've got I've got the
that I've got the power right also
because of the kinematics the
calculating forward it's a little bit
opposite of what I would think would be
but so you got inverse kinematics
forward kinematics means I am here tell
me what the position of my servos or
what my angles are so I could do the
count the forward kinematics and I'll
just say it's what 1.5 41 41 that was
roughly the the output from the last
function and it should inverse it yeah
roughly zero 50 negative 20 anyway
rounding errors right but you can go
forward and back for me I needed it's
really important to have the XYZ thing
so so future steps for this project if
you kind of noticed some people are
saying like well how do I know where to
tell this robot this is a another thing
in robot lands this is an open-loop
right which means I'm telling it to go
somewhere and it really doesn't know
anything it's not very smart there is no
feedback mechanism from the robots to
back to the computer to say like oh you
told me to go here but I'm actually here
and
let's course-correct to get to the right
spot so one of the things I'm also
working on is then using Peter Braden's
OpenCV bindings for node and that's
where things get really cool with an
iPad 2 and up and and the iPhone 4s and
up you can get a VGA adapter and get a
mirror to get a video signal out of of
the iPad once I have that actually use a
device called prosaically named VGA to
USB right so it takes the VGA signal and
then I plug it into my laptop so now I
actually can grab like JPEG frames of of
this of the iPad screen once I have that
I can use open a CV and I have a little
thumbnail picture where I can find the
bird on that screen open computer vision
algorithms can can translate this bird
to a particular XYZ coordinate on the
screen once I have that XYZ coordinate I
can then feed it into this inverse
kinematics function and then and then go
so the other dream for this is I can sit
back and then watch it completely you
know play by itself and then on top of
that then once we have a robot that's
kind of sort of autonomous and
course-correcting we can then start
having competitions about Angry Birds
playing robot you know efficiency and
you know find the pig find the bird
figure out the angle you know how far to
throw so I envision Angry Birds robot
contests in the future like is make it
as ridiculous as possible but yeah
there's lots of things there's lots of
things that we can do with this and one
thing I think after after my talk I'm
gonna go back back to the coffee spots
but I need I need to help I need you
might I need your help implementing the
tweet function so I want you know by the
end of it today get this robot to just
you know say hello
J s conf and then the key thing is a
sent for my robot so that's that yeah
that's coming coming very soon but yeah
anyway so the inverse kinematics and all
that all this robot stuff there are some
really good classes at Stanford they put
them all online
iTunes University and I thought I was
really interested in robotics you know
like a long time ago but because I
didn't have a project to do something it
was very dry very
boring material I think this is one of
those lessons learned of college because
I didn't have a project to work on I
couldn't even I couldn't survive the
first class but now I now I need these
functions I now I now get it but don't
get scared by the science and the
vocabulary just realize a lot of this
stuff is very simple
I mean robots are ridiculously stupid
even at this level they're not very
smart and so the things that we're
trying them to do to get them to do it's
it's just geometry and and thankfully
lots of other people's you can kind of
uh grab people's algorithms and run them
in your stuff and get them to work but
so at this point actually I think I
would like to open it to questions yeah
[Applause]
there yeah oh holy cow I forgots
thank you so much yeah Chris Williams
actually implemented this last night the
dancing robots and then let's see if you
want to like take a break and chill
right I just stopped was that dance Oh
oh shoot right can't see it there you go
thank you
let's try that again
[Applause]
so Chris also if he he got the the week
controller we got it working so we can
actually can kind of play the video game
you know abstracted through throw all
this so you can show that to see the
demo later
any other questions what was that is the
code for this I just went to the get the
bit beam repo but that's for the yeah
for this demo right now I'll put that up
right after thank you right I want to
see it it's Johnny 5 stuff Johnny 5
right it's okay Johnny 5 is the robot is
the node library and then Fermata is on
the arduino side yeah how much does this
thing cost approximately oh right so
it's a lot cheaper that you're gonna do
it in Lego and also the other thing is
Lego doesn't make parts like this long
so it's actually about a hundred dollars
and most of it actually is the Arduino
their Arduino in the in a prototyping
board that's like 30 or 40 the servos
each hurt 10 apiece so just in
electronics actually 2/3 the cost is
just the electronics the wood and the
bolts are probably like maybe 10 15
dollars or so and that little iPad
stylus I overpaid and got it at Best Buy
or something like that I could I could
make my own dirt cheap there's actually
one I did put this project up on there's
a website called tindy TI n di e.com
it's kind of like an electronics version
of Etsy where you can kind of put your
project up there
granted it's it's for sale but I don't
want you to buy it because I'm really
it's a manual process to make this right
so what I need to do next is to make the
robots that can make this robot so I
need a conveyor belts and any more bit
beams that can I can shake the bolts
onto the conveyor belt I can find the
bolts put them in a kit so I haven't
done that yet so that's there but yeah
so the you know plans are out there I've
documented like a whole Flickr set
for all the construction steps for this
and yeah it's about $100 I laser cut the
wood at TechShop San Francisco so if you
have it if you have access to an
epilogue laser cutter you can kind of
you know buy the wood at a and this is
actually just two foot lengths of
basswood for like ninety nine cents and
learn how to laser cut and and do it the
thing though I think the laser cutting
is also to to manual to labor intensive
the better idea is to download the the
bit beam file from the Thingiverse so I
have the cool thing about open source
and the thing I think of versus all
these things I uploaded the the 2d DXF
laser cut files and within an hour of
being on Thingiverse someone uploaded
the the 3d version that can is RepRap
printable and so this was this is ABS
plastic on the same as Lego and anyways
pretty cool so I think actually the the
best way to if you're gonna make your
own is you know get the electronics from
wherever the Arduino and the servos
that's kind of been known how to do that
spark fun or something but I would
recommend getting a 3d printer getting
the bit beam files and then just
printing a bunch of them so that yeah
that the dream I think is you know
besides robots they actually can you
know be the equivalent of selenium and
test all your software the other one is
to kind of imagine a toy company that's
it's kind of like a modern company
instead of a factory in some country
where I make stuff for you and send it
to you for a ridiculously high price
imagine there are just 3 D printers
everywhere and so there's you know
building up a community of people to
putting kits up on the website and then
that has the instructions on how you can
print it and so you can send an entire
you know bill of materials to your
printer and just say you know in the
morning you now have your own kind of
Lego kit and didn't have to you know
wait for shipping and handling for that
kind of stuff so yeah that's kind of the
dream so you can make it yourself or at
some point once they have the whole
robot assembly line I'll go - yep
so can you tell us about controlling
that with like a Wii controller maybe
later later the Wii controller yeah
because that was pretty cool
yeah all probably going to I'll go into
that I'll go into yeah I'll let fly me
laughter yes yes any other questions
okay thank you thanks