um my name is Thomas Tyner um you can
see my contact details on the slide and
today I want to talk about how you can
pirate the semantic web using javascript
very quick introduction of my person I
work as a research scientist at Google
Hamburg left a google before in a
different role um maybe some of you have
seen me at the google developer days
i've toured all around europe in 2008
and the google developer dies will come
back this year in munich so if you're
interested in joining the google
developer days speak to me after the
talk again in the invitation code so
yeah the chance is high that you get in
with them yeah what I do at Google will
I'm research scientists working on a PhD
around the Semantic Web multimedia
semantics so currently I've submitted a
paper for the I eswc conference in
Shanghai represent a JavaScript
application that is able of yeah finding
objects and entities in YouTube videos
and yeah I want to present this in
Shanghai so myself I won't be at the
Google developer day in Munich because I
will be in Shanghai then but not you
will meet multi-day so yet another
reason to attend yeah and about all I'm
showing here today is bleeding edge
research so this is really something you
and about this talk to sponsor talk but
no fear this won't be marketing blah
blah but please do use google chrome so
that's about the only marketing message
I'm sending out today and yeah this type
is scheduled in the unthankful yes to
start as i as i call it and so please
don't sleep please don't fall asleep
please stay awake we have new stuff that
you will learn today hopefully
um I got a couple of free the great
comments in this top and best of all i
got this surprise prize back so um
staying awake is really a good
motivation because you will have this
great surprise day at their back with a
little bit of luck so let's get started
hiding the web so not this meant to be a
Semantic Web hiring the web things you
can pirate on the web I give me a little
bit of time to read the comics because
here it's actually one of my favorite
thanks you can parent on the web audio
books hands if you have read the comic
all right let's write a little bit more
all right so um if you want to have a
collection tired them or I think that's
really important phrase down there
demand your M free stuff so if you hire
an mp3's you're actually downloading
communism so a lot of people have seen
this is really old comics but still I
really like them another thing that you
can part on on the web movies yeah and
one of the things I really love or XKCD
is you see the comic but on what some
people don't know if your mouse over you
can also see a message and yeah like
next book that's particular funny can i
flip to the next side alright thanks
again paired on the web images but this
is really alingo um you can see this is
from getty images um I went there
yesterday it's lukas podolski prints
poorly as we call him in germany great
football player or soccer player as the
Americans say
I think you can see it on the slides but
I have maybe you can see there's a
watermark in the image this is really
highly illegal but it did here I've
tired it this image so now we come into
the interesting part how can the
Semantic Web help not tired things but
you know making sure that you don't
pirate things so easily so I want to
start with a bit of an interaction what
is the Semantic Web so um I assume most
of you have a very wake level of
knowledge so I'm really going into the
details but not too deep just deep
enough that you can follow the talk so
first of all bonus web well the web is
the web as you know what it's document
it slings it you know JavaScript me this
kind of things the Semantic Web however
is there a set of techniques that you
can apply to the web as we know it today
and basically on the you need the cable
hey you go yeah that's a problem so um
using the Semantic Web and we can enable
giving meaning to things and I will show
you how this looks like in a second here
in this slide you can see two phrases
one is I love internet and the second
one is I hard the internet so the
meaning of this phrase is exactly the
same the thing is the syntax has changed
that semantics still are the same so in
the Semantic Web it's all about giving
meaning to things html5 defines a
computer-readable syntax so yeah it's
you know image of a bunny with a pancake
on its head and you can see image blah
blah jpg but there's no meaning it's
just an image um you don't know what is
on the image or in the image so yeah
it's
meaningless more or less and now on
semantic web you can apply a meaning to
it so you can say this is an image and
on that image you got a funny man funny
bunny with a pancake on his head and if
you're browsing whatever search engine
that you prefer search for oolong if you
love this money you will find a couple
of really interesting photos approved
for all audiences so no worries yeah so
getting meaning to things saying well
this is an image but on this image I
have runny with a pancake on his head in
the romantic web it's all about triples
triples are basically a subject
predicate object object sorry so
javascript has good part who of you
agrees with that okay that's a good
question to ask you this conference that
was kept as bad part stop as Crawford in
here because people will not necessarily
agree on the bad parts but whatever so
this is just an example triple
javascript has good part so now let's go
a bit a little bit into real-world usage
you can see the object in this case is
yet another XKCD comic I give you a bit
of time to read the comic before I
continue it's probably pretty small but
it was released I think on on friday
night i finished few slides on friday
night for am so yeah this was just the
latest XKCD back then so yeah you can
see well this is an image you can see
the predicate is well it has a license
and then you can see the object which is
in this case the Creative Commons 2.5
what's the exact name I'm not really
sure so share remix attribution and
non-commercial license so basically this
license says well let you get this image
you can share
which I'm doing today and you can remix
it which i would do if i added a pixel
somewhere here if you attribute it this
is what i did here so i said well it's
not mine i have not created it this is
the URL but very where you can get it
and yeah you may not use it commercially
so I'm not paid for being mia so I guess
this qualifies as non-commercial we use
of this image so I said real world so
let's have a look at the HTML code that
generated this image this is really
coming from side so don't get scared by
the yeah text this is basically the
mouse over text for this image and you
can see well it's an image tag it has a
source tag it has a title it has an alt
attribute and then you can see we get a
link down there that says well it's
linked to a license with the relation of
license so this is already good the
problem is well this license does it
apply to the side where the images
contain so basically it does it apply to
let's go back here does it apply to XKCD
com / blah blah so 797 or does it apply
to just the image itself we don't know
so let's see how using semantic web
technologies and in this case I'm only
talking about rdfa and you can do this
so you've probably seen it I've added a
little bit let's highlight it so now
with this about attribute you can see
well we get images XKCD com blah blah
about and then you can see well this is
a license that applies to exactly this
image so you can see this is not really
magic this is just yet another attribute
that gets added to the HTML code
and yeah this is basically all what
already if a is about so RDF move us has
heard of RDF okay yeah this roars
description framework a lot of people
turn away by if XML is one serialization
but for the web people multi-tech use
RDF a which is yeah putting things
putting the but the triple information
into attributes that's a 4 that's what
the a stands for all ready fa you can
see about in this case it was as easy as
just adding one about attribute to this
tag and here you go now we have exactly
defined well this is the license for the
image not the page but for the image
which in this case could be added to the
side but yeah a lot of people currently
if they use license information have
this kind of license which is which is
already great so basically they say
about it you may use the side and by the
side most people think of the side and
its components which means the images
inside of the site but it starts getting
messy so this kind of technology as soon
as you have a compilation of images from
jas code for example imagine I would
want I wanted to generate a page of all
the images that i found on flickr from
people that have taken photographs at
jas conf probably you have decided to
use CC whatever license we have decided
to keep all your images your own so copy
art by you and some personal a show last
row might have decided well they put
their images under GPL or whatever crazy
license a similar to start putting this
page at these images together on one
page it starts really getting messy so
rdfa so using a technology like this is
a great way of yeah making busy that you
give the right license to the right
images if you're into like doing things
whatever I said right now
compounding images and putting them
together on one side mark Berbick his
website is we backplane com has
introduced some nice techniques how you
can do with such such things for example
compiling five images that have the same
license and not using this about tech on
all of them but just on a container
around these images so a search whatever
search engine you want to search on mark
birbeck rdf rdf a image license and it's
the first link on at least our surgeon
alright so another thing about our EF is
tripled and well triple visualization so
this is what you will probably see if
you read a bit about raf a great
document that you can read is from w3c
w3c hard word if we start if you search
for rdf primer you will find a lot of
images like this so you can see well
this is the image again and you can see
it has a cc colon license and I can see
Creative Commons blah blah the URI to to
the to the license so in the Semantic
Web it's all about your eyes because
your eye is unique so it has a unique
identifier on the world and well we as
human beings can interpret what is
behind you rise so it is recommended
recommended to add information add your
eyes that human beings can read can
understand so in this case if I go to
this uri i can read the license and i
can interpret and make sense of it and
well see that this license is about
though i may share i may use it blah
blah but i may not use it commercially
in this kind of things so yeah your eyes
and putting information that is that
makes sense for human beings bhai
these your eyes yeah so this about this
and now well finally we are there
finally we are at javascript London
grade if he could access these turtles
right from within JavaScript so having
things like document dot get elements by
property and say give me all the
elements that are at CC license and then
filter may be on all the CC license
elements that are under GPL for example
you can see the second example here how
about about getting all the triples that
are about a certain subject about this
image wouldn't it be great and well the
rdf a API working group at the w3c is
currently working on a draft for such a
future standards so probably or maybe or
hopefully however you want to put it if
we talk about this again in I don't know
say 2012 2015 2011 I don't know maybe
then this will be real all right already
so that you can use document dot
whatever get elements blah blah yeah so
this is currently in draft status so
it's still really early in the in the in
the development phase but yeah you can
already make fun stuff with it like for
example right a Chrome extension that
would add lasers to all the RT to all
the creative commons licensed element
and yeah this is exactly what I did so
let's go to the next slide and demo it
with this great XKCD comic this is
really awesome and will give you a
little bit of time to read it I have you
can read it in the last rose my favorite
all-time favorite XKCD
the title of this image is I'm an idiot
all right so now let's jump to the demo
of this chrome extension rub I open the
page and you can see well yeah this is
the page let's check the mouse over so
it says sadly this is a true story at
least I learned about the OSX a command
so this is great fun command if you're
on ssh and your acid etching into I
don't know your girlfriend's computer
make it say something great effect a lot
of fun stuff that you can do with it so
yeah let's crawl down a bit to the
actual license and you can see whoa we
got lasers and this is directly stolen
from the Jays comp site but mine is
fading out and fading in so really
awesome I think and you can see this
work is licensed under creative commons
attribution noncommercial 2.5 license
and you can see license information is
fading in and fading out with a laser
effect so this is a lot of fun of course
this is just a demo and just for fun but
you can see here a small CC gets about
you can see the mouse cursor probably a
small CC gets added to the how do we
call this tuesday is it magic bar how do
we call the address bar in chrome the
sorry i don't get an arm
harmony bar Carter said well you
understood it I didn't well the our
address bar um but why did I say it's
really hard to understand omni bar okay
right so on the Omni bar you can see it
has added a little CC which means that
on this page my chrome extension has
found license information and if you
click it you can see that at the moment
it doesn't do anything at all but you
could imagine well you could put in
there a list of all the images and
something like a very easy copy and
paste mechanism that would be licensed
aware so you could imagine having
something like you copy the image plus
the license information which would
enable things like let's jump back to
hear like adding this small corporate
caption that you can see on our my slide
automatically now it's a pain because
you have to create a small text area
copy and paste to license so wouldn't be
great if this would be more or less an
automatic process I'm releasing my
chrome extension after the talk so
whoever wants to have a copy and paste
licenses or sorry license a better copy
and paste feel free to play with the ex
engine and add a lot of awesomeness to
it um so whoops I'm going to quickly
jump back to here so this really works
and I've seen a fun side that you can
test it on which is classic car show
calm and it has just well this website
is about classic car ism I have no
interest at all in plastic cards I just
happened to find this page and if you
open whatever image you can see lasers
so
it's here the problem is these guys
don't really do it exactly right they
don't apply what we've seen before in
this example they have the license
information within the image but they
haven't done it correctly so whoops if
you happen to know the guys behind
what's the car what's the name classic
car show calm please tell them to fix
their RAF but still it's already great
stuff and this works on whatever random
page you want to test it and this is
technology so like adding licenses to
images today that you can test on for
example our search engine if you search
for Jas conf images you can see a lot of
fun jas kana images and then you can see
I then can go to advanced search and
filter by license label for commercial
reuse with modification hit Search and
then you can see well this is the images
that we may legally reuse for commercial
purposes around Jas conf this is enabled
by this technology because with this
info with this details we have so let's
open the dojo guys yeah this is fun so
let's go to the actual website look so
you can see somewhere here yet some
rights reserved so if I open this you
can see well this is under a Creative
Commons license even if on this page
yeah this is just a static HTML page
because it's the old license so you
don't see lasers so hopefully if you go
to the new version
no well this is just static HTML so here
we don't have license information but um
if let's go here and this is my private
blog nothing really interesting but at
the very end you can see well lasers and
if I click on this link your bra you're
you're brought to this page and you can
see well this is kind of what I'm aiming
at you can get automatically created
this is a diff that you should add to
any content coming from my website that
has yeah the license information
embedded and you can see here well I'm
on this website but this website
suddenly looks like dynamic because it
uses the information that comes from the
HTTP referer and because we know that
well on my website I have placed this
special markup that says I'm the owner
please use this in this license for my
content all right so let's jump back to
the presentation you can get they get
this extension if you go to bit ly / rdf
a laser yeah so you can download it um
the source code comes with the
applicable with 3x engine and if you
don't know how to extract the source
code from a Chrome extension search the
search engine of your choice for
extracting the source code of a Chrome
extension or ask me so I said I'm a PhD
student which means I rate a lot of
papers and one of the papers i really
recommend if you're interested in this
kind of things with a relatively
practical application case go to VIP fee
j/s cons paper nice paper on yep what's
the title of the
quickly open it yeah policy of our
content reuse on the web going back here
and so this is the URLs again rdf a
laser have fun with the extension and
yeah as I said please please please do
make a lot of a lot more out of it and
now we're at the fun part um this
surprise that can be yours if you know
the answer to this question how automag
can you change the volume and tell me
the first response and we got the
awesome awesome awesome streaming client
from mounted right open here and the
first person that will add reply me the
right response will have this awesome
surfer a surprise back so this is 3 me
real time so let's see who will get the
first surprise bag so I believe this
open in the background rub and basically
this is my top so I have no idea what
you're talking about so here's an image
from the binding with a baffle in his
head um any questions on this tas or any
questions on RTI for whatever semantic
web stuff yes please
my dominance
yeah so the question was and why why do
I need a specific dome API the thing is
in my in my library that has implemented
this this API I'm actually using xpath
for for accessing but other the element
the thing is there's a lot more behind
because what my API does or what my API
implementation to us is it can retrieve
the elements but it is not by default
triple aware so it doesn't really get
this this idea of having triplets on the
page it kind of does by simply brute
forcing running over all the notes and
checking well where r triples but by
having this so remember this is
something that we want about that that
people in in this community want to head
to meet native in web browsers so this
is something that can really be
implemented by a safe Firefox a chrome
say what kid so that it would run a
level deeper so not on JavaScript level
but yeah right within the browser and be
really really fast so don't think of it
as being something like a Dom API my
implementation just implements the API
and it's not implemented to be fast it's
not implemented to be something yet that
the end user can use it's more like a
demo of what could be possible with this
API let me show you very quickly
so this was one of the answers let's see
if someone else on streaming I guess
Thomas dumb care is the winner so I
think I don't have to sudo though but
this is the right response so YouTube
loss for Thomas
Thanks so sorry you were a little bit
too late yeah that's some fun gadgets in
there nothing really too fancy but yeah
it's not a new film it's not a new
android phone sorry for that so yeah I
wanted to show you here we go I wanted
to show you the source code of this
chrome extension so who of you has ever
built a Chrome extension a couple of
hands so hopefully after today and after
having seen these slides you will see
that it's not magic it's just JavaScript
this is just my JavaScript so it's
really bad job
so really need JavaScript freaks guards
like you will do a better job on this
but yeah even someone like like me can
do it so this is the concept of the
background page where you have the
actual website and then you add with the
chrome extension the concept of a
background page to it which is something
like a virtual page it runs in a
background that holds the application
logic for the chrome extension and you
can see here all that this extension
does is while it waits for a follow
request and if a request happens the
callback function gets gets fired and
you can see well basically it's really
really low-tech if the request thought
show element contains I can I will show
the icon and if not I won't show the
icons so the thing is well what where
the surah guys come from and then we
have to jump into the content script and
if you know grease monkey this is more
or less the same thing so you inject a
script into the actual page and you can
see here this is my API so its name
spaced link oops sorry its name spaced
link data a link data API so think of
this as document dot but for my really
simple implementation yeah I have names
vested link data API and then well let's
very quickly see what this does it's at
it sets a namespace mapping so basically
all it does here is it says CC should be
the namespace of Creative Commons blah
blah the URI and then you see the
problem this case it's the DOMA
operations link data API get elements by
property license and then restore it in
this in this variable
the next step is well some people use
the namespace others don't so we have to
run basically the same thing again but
this time this time with the namespace
and then we put the two together so we
can't get the two arrays and well then
if there are elements that are a CC
license then we basically just fire a
request to the background page and all
this does is it shows the small icon
here so this is the i can i'm talking
about and yeah then you can add whatever
i say before then you could add a lot of
logic here if you click here it opens
what we call the pop-up page of the
chrome extension so background page is
the concept of the application logic
pop-up page is the concept of what
happens inside of this speech bubble and
content script is well the greasemonkey
script that gets injected into the page
so let's jump back to the source code
sorry okay yeah well all that happens
here is well I just add the magic lasers
that's it more or less so it's just a
couple of lines of JavaScript and Bob
this is just the look and feel of it the
lasers the actual chrome extension is
like I know 10 15 lines of JavaScript
code maybe and well my library runs in
the background so it is let's see boobs
this was at the beginning so yeah with
the application with the extension
manifest you have to include this
library and then it can make use of it I
think yeah I'm running over time thank
you very much ping me if you have
questions I'm around here and thank you
very much for being here for listening