alright so I wanted to talk about the
recent use of JavaScript and some
industries that we might be less
familiar with so by old line I mean
industries that aren't using the world
wide web as part as essential to their
operation on a day-to-day basis so semi
conductor is one that immediately comes
to mind aerospace lots of industries in
manufacturing biology pharmaceuticals
plastics lots of companies sort of
outside of our world of kind of the
World Wide Web so here's one example of
a company in the south bay that does on
genomic sequencing for medical purposes
and I love seeing this job posts because
I would imagine they'd be hiring like a
PLC programmer or a c-sharp programmer
or a C++ programmer but they're hiring
an angular programmer to make dashboards
which i think is something that we've
only started to see in like the past
three or four years like these these
types of companies weren't really
looking for JavaScript programmers three
or four years ago so like why is that
why why is javascript suddenly coming on
the scene in these other you know these
other classes of companies so I used to
work at this solar cell plant and that's
actually where i learned javascript and
i was making internal websites that
never that were never seen by the world
wide web
we had we were collecting all this data
from the manufacturing line and it was
going into a my sequel database and we
had to present all that information to
the engineers and the factory workers so
everyone could easily see what was going
on and I had never done anything like
this before and being you know I guess a
millennial the natural the way that
seemed most natural to display that
information was using a browser so we we
built this sort of dashboarding system
using javascript and kind of the tools
you know people here are really familiar
with but if people if people in these
industries aren't using javascript and
websites to display this kind of
information and what what are they using
what have people been using you know for
the past 50 years in these kinds of like
old line manufacturing industries and
one on one program that's really common
that some of you guys might have heard
of if you had fewer in grad school or
you worked in a lab and college is
LabVIEW so like a really typical
paradigm believe it or not for these
companies where their labs or
manufacturing lines is you'll have one
computer that's like the dashboard
computer and if you want to go and check
what's going on in the lab you like put
on your bunny suit you go into the lab
and then you check the dashboard and
you're like okay great everything's okay
and you go back out out of the lab and
into the office or you might have some
kind of like remote desktop system so
that if you're at home you can check in
on the lab computer which it's which
sounds so ridiculous when you could just
use a browser but a lot of companies
still sort of work this way the
the company that makes lab views a
billion-dollar company just to sort of
like show the extent of how much these
kind of desktop dashboard programs are
still in use so dashboarding i think is
in my mind kind of the entry point or
has been the entry point for javascript
coming onto the scene and some of these
more some of these older school
industries and that's that's really
thanks to a lot of a lot of like the
easy and nice plotting tools that are
available now like d3 the Google charts
API digraphs it's just really it's
really easy to spin up charts in a
browser now and all those tools are free
so versus paying a few thousand dollars
for a program like LabVIEW there's been
a lot of kind of recent interest in
figuring out how to in sort of
scientists that don't have any
programming or JavaScript background to
learn enough to be able to make to make
dashboards and displays like these so
you know dashboarding to me is kind of
the entry point for these types of
industries but I think there are maybe
other future uses of JavaScript in these
sort of scientific and older school
engineering industries and one that I
think is really interesting is technical
computing like the the very early days
of technical computing were in C and
then there was Fortran and then there is
matlab and a lot of people use Python
now and now there are people working on
julia and technical computing is you
know it's like a it's a it's a branch of
programming that's really needed to
solve to solve math program math
problems that you know we can't solve
analytically and we need a
you to resolve and there are some people
that are you know starting to do the
groundwork for that would be needed to
do technical computing in JavaScript hmm
one person is this fellow McCollough
who's starting to do a lot of sort of
basic work and like how how do we store
matrices in javascript in an efficient
way just kind of like a lot of the
really fundamental work that would be
necessary to solve these types of
problems in JavaScript then another you
know potential future JavaScript
application in these industries that we
don't really see now but who knows 5-10
years could become commonplace is
instrumentation so there's this company
in berkeley tehsil that's making these
microcontrollers that you can program in
java script which which is something new
and cool and this is really just you
know for fruit insurers and hobbyists so
far but you know maybe in the future
this is sort of like a typical plc
programmable logic controller display
that would control some some type of
machinery in a factory and they're
typically program using c sharp or some
kind of graphical programming languages
but you know maybe in 5-10 years
javascript will change enough and so
many people will know javascript that
you know it won't be uncommon that you
program something like a programmable
logic controller in javascript and then
i work for a company called plot lee and
we really focus on sort of this the
scientific plotting part of what
javascript has to offer to the
scientific community in these types of
industries and the nice thing that you
get out of plotting and javis
it is there are all these great tools
like d3 and you get interactivity so
these chart on these charts you can
hover and you can zoom and you can pan
around and if you compare that to MATLAB
or LabVIEW or kind of other common
scientific software right now you don't
get that kind of interactivity so it's
it's hard to imagine going back from
that so you know there are a lot of
people in the scientific community that
think javascript is here to stay at
least for for visualizing data because
the upsides you get in interactivity
then finally I just wanted to mention
that potli has a node API so if any of
you guys are working on node projects
where you want to plot some data are our
API is on NPM and it's free and supports
pretty much any any type of chart so