there's mac bit more on the lead
engineer so if the tables um a little
bit about us a little bit about this
slide right here in going about this
talk mom one of the things that I
realize is that for a lot of people
remote work means that everyone in the
office is remote for this talk I'm
really talking about remote employees at
like a very centralized company on so as
social tables were a pretty flat
organization we are doing tons of like
quick one on one's full hand meetings
we're all in an office in DC but my wife
is in international development um this
is made my wife in Swaziland and so thus
from time to time she's gone for like
months on end in foreign countries not
the third world because that's the
Soviet error term the developing world
and Swaziland is actually really safe
but um it's internet connectivity does
really suffer this is who I am um MC
whittemore on github and twitter follow
me what is social tables social tables
event planning software um we are
somehow involved in the planning of this
event not really sure I just got told up
earlier today so we make software that
plans these kinds of events um I'm going
to Swaziland so why do land as a country
in southern Africa it's not the one
inside of South Africa it's the one
between Mozambique and South Africa um
it's the highest aids rate in the world
um
arguably that's because there are more
honest people than other people's that's
a little bit swaziland and that's why my
wife is there here is where on the
continent of Africa you can find
Swaziland and today swaziland looks much
more like this than like our straw on
Shaq I saw you a couple seconds ago
which by the way that door is like this
height and so you have to like crawl in
and so that if someone was trying to
steal in your house you could just mount
them over the head cool swaziland fact
so I've spent nine months of my life now
working remotely um first six of it I
quit my job because of it it was
absolutely horrible again I worked for a
very like centralized team at that time
in Atlanta and while we talked about how
to interact with people we never really
worked on it um so on coming to social
tables and knowing that this was in my
future we started talking about a lot
how do you introduce something some way
for an entity to help the communication
process right because if every day of
your life is about interacting with a
person at your office and then suddenly
that person isn't there and there is
nobody else working remotely your
default behavior isn't go get on google
hangouts and have a meeting your default
behavior is talked to the next guy talk
to the next gal and so we we came up
with this concept called I Matthew in
which we literally turned myself into a
robot um it is this I Matthew not iphone
Matthew and so for the next three months
I was him I was a robot at our company
um this is me in some meeting it looks
like I'm leading it but that's just
because that's where they had to put me
I'm not leading it this is me hanging
out with one of our sales people um and
then this is me at our weekly weekly All
Hands so again like here you see me this
is the metaphysics part like literally
being a robot I can't walk around the
office so someone has to drag me around
the off
um we didn't we like thought of this
like two days before i left so we like
had all these crazy ideas about using
Johnny Five and like whipping up
something to make me able to move around
but that didn't happen so you are
suddenly a quadriplegic for all
intensive purposes inside the office I
which really raised some interesting
problems for me after about three months
um because I can't like just have that
meeting people still um still thought of
me as that entity he still came to me as
that entity but I couldn't come to them
um so slight little downfall about this
way it'll eventually make the person
feel I mean like their robot so we're
going to talk about these five things um
but first I want to just quickly talk
about why people should work remotely
because I actually as much as I've
struggled with it I think it's a really
it's a thing especially in our field
that we can take advantage of there's
the whole argument about productivity
I'll get into that I think we live in an
amazing world and we can work anywhere
for the most part and I know so many
people on who feel bound to their small
you know worlds wherever they live no
matter how large or small the city and
it's just not true anymore so the fun
pictures of lions and tigers and bears
these are the reasons why you should
work remotely there are only six hundred
wild dogs in the world about and I got
to see one actually a lot there are lots
of crocodiles um drafts baboons on and
of course the obvious one which is
work-life balance um yeah there's you
know going to remote parts of the world
and seeing things that you know only
small parts of humanity sees but there's
also raising your kids I'm not yet to
but will be two in the next couple of
years um and I mean my wife works
remotely in foreign countries so
it's gonna fall more on me um and like
we should be figuring out how to do that
better so sort of meetings what does it
take to be a robot in a meeting um we're
going to go through these basically as
problems and then quasi solutions
because I haven't really found solutions
number one problem with being a robot in
the meeting is that microphones aren't
ears I mean vol probably seeing this
with conference calls like you start
talking over each other but again if
you're the only robot in the meeting no
one else realizes that you can't hear so
if you're working with remote workers
remember they can't focus on you and so
if we're having a conversation and
someone else is trying to talk I'm
hearing all three of you talking at the
same as the same person so how we sort
of dealt with trying to solve that
problem is we introduced rip chat so we
actually do a lot of our started doing a
lot more of our communication over chat
we've used shat traditionally but in
much more like siloed ways and with
HipChat not to like give that lassie in
like PR but with HipChat you can just
like open random rooms and just start
dialogues um so meetings would often
have chat rooms brainstorming the next
big problem um I think especially for me
at least I'm a white border I'm assuming
and a raise of people in this room who
loves the whiteboard yeah so like there
aren't great white boarding solutions
they're definitely aren't great white
boarding solutions over 3g internet and
boarding solutions over a 3g internet
which is what there is in Swaziland when
everyone gets out of work and starts
using their cell phones and so what we
ended up doing on sometimes was having a
whiteboard and having like a camera
pointed yeah my robot pointed at the
whiteboard and I would be like oh yeah
you should draw the Box bigger and like
that's the kind of conversations um so
white boarding is definitely a problem
um the best solution I think that we
came up with was just straight up using
Google Docs
um again this is you know obviously just
trying to recreate a whiteboard um but
i'm i'm warming google drive like being
able to just type and like putting ideas
down so solution sort of obviously not
as good as a whiteboard so focusing
distractions on one of the reasons i
think that we like to think remote work
is great is that there's a lot of
research that says that engineers are
productive when they're not distracted
and that in the office you get
distracted all the time there's this
book that i just found out about my
research that I want to read called why
programmers work at night I know there's
Georgia Tech has done a bunch of
research on this and it like the amount
of time that it takes an engineer oh it
takes really any creative worker to get
back to where they were is ridiculous
and so we talk about remote work as this
great sort of way of solving this
problem um but I think we often forget
that at least in the case of swaziland
there are like chickens that decide to
sleep in your coop I mean in your house
as their coop so like one day I woke up
and this chicken just wouldn't leave my
house um yeah it was fun um in Swaziland
there are also all my slides oh there
are also monkeys that decided your
avocados and at least for the first
couple of weeks that I was there I was
just like this is a monkey in my
backyard eating my avocados and every
time I were here now just be like monkey
get the camera go take a picture which
actually only happened once and this is
not from that because that pictures
really blurry um so I mean there's
things the thing about when you're
working remotely on that like obviously
you don't have your boss walking in or
you know somebody else walking in and
asking you a question but I mean you do
still have people interrupting you and
when you're working six hours ahead of
schedule um as I was in Swaziland your
co-workers become an interesting
interruption because they all get into
work at say your 4pm which is at least
traditionally for me my most productive
time and is traditionally for them their
least productive time and so chats
explode like emails start getting sent
out and like these ideas that I've been
working on in like my siloed little
universe in swaziland just suddenly gets
smashed on fun things though you do
learn when all of your co-workers wake
up on and if they check their email when
they get out of bed um when you're
working that far ahead um for instance
dawn who's our CEO gets up like three
hours ahead of most people and add who's
actually in the room that's up read
about the time he gets to work so um
lastly um for just general thing some
motivation I think is really hard when
you're this kind of remote worker um and
this is this is one that actually i
think really kind of hits home for me we
we're we're sitting alone um you're like
working on this great product you know
you can think of sort of like those
entrepreneurs who are like just starting
something and that's like that's great
but when you start to get a little bit
bigger you have this you know we're
working on this together and once you
get siloed into a foreign cotton like a
continent far far away you can no longer
have that interaction in the lack of
forth and like the motivation to make
your code better to like iterate on your
product to you know be a good employee
starts to the mesh um so the thing that
I think we found worked best was sort of
going back to more of that like early
stage startup that early like there's
only one or two of you working on this
product and like saying you own this so
that when i woke up at two a.m. eastern
standard time and got to work like I had
my work and like this is what I was
doing um so that you know obviously that
that's I loathe you more and there are
problems with that metaphysical fun
problems with that but it also does let
you own something and I think ownership
is really key task management is really
hard unless you have someone who's
really really far
head of their scheduling um because
sometimes I would just like get through
like 10 stories and then all of the work
that was scheduled would be done and it
would be like 38 you know 5am in the
East Coast and no one's waking up which
is why eventually we moved to more of an
oriented um like ownership oriented
structure that said like I really think
the problem with this single remote
worker is that we don't think about it
we sort of use this picture as an
analogy think work is work we think a
road is a road we think they're like
every time it's the same and especially
in the United States I think we define
work is coming into the office and
typing on and letting our managers or
our co-workers or whoever we have peer
pressure from CES typing I mean
obviously like we think it is a lot more
than that but if we define it down to
like the bare minimums I think that's
what we think work is but once like work
is completely remote once work is you
know not possible to be you in a room
typing I think we have to start really
getting down to like what is work and
like what that means what that means in
your company so we you know we spent
some time and we created this I Matthew
concept we actually have a new remote
worker who she's just moved out on to
Colorado and so we have an I Claire now
and and it's definitely something that
works on definitely something that helps
but I think if you're ever in a place
where you're thinking about siloing
yourself remote working yourself you
know large not even large just like in a
centralized company on a non distributed
company it's something that that really
needs to be thought of because if
everyone on the team is not completely
about trying to solve this work problem
your remote worker will be a
inated no matter how much you don't want
that to be true and eventually like what
happened to me before they'll just leave
like it's really easy especially if
they're in the United States to
interview while your remote working
really easy so things the thing about um
that said i would love questions answers
and discussions there's a sweet small
group so like stories about an auction
or where we are in time but some
questions if anyone has them but you can
also look at more fun pictures of
swaziland um that said baboons by the
way or like my least favorite animal um
well it doesn't help that i was there
during a boon mating season um but like
they would just like throw like random
seeds at us like we were like so if you
look at this this picture the end of the
presentation you can actually this like
it's called the comb be this like van
thing he's what we were in the whole
time because you don't want to be not in
the van thing when these guys are around
um but like the baboons are just like on
the treat like this tons of animals are
just like on the street like this oh and
the baboons are more or less okay with
you unless they're not okay with you and
then they just like start throwing
things they're very territorial um when
I was in Honduras briefly and I had
black baboons chase us because we
accidentally walked through their
territory but you should check out wild
dogs I didn't know about this at all by
the way but kruger national park which
is where all these pictures are from is
in south africa and there are 600 might
be a little bit low balling it but they
are like a completely dying thing um and
they're really rare to see they'd never
stopped moving and this one is injured
actually just sad but cool because I got
to see thing that barely exists i don't
know how i feel about that um yeah um
any questions comments wisecracks
it's my ninth grade teacher used to say
um no we we well we started profiling a
bunch of things like a couple of days
before and so yeah um it is there's a
bunch of them any bought and then it
might pull this off the top of his head
better there's a couple of them that do
look really cool have you ever used any
butter
yeah Nick
haha I don't know um Romney how did you
feel about me being like hey call people
for me oh so rally was was generally the
person who he was the one who got
hangouts cuz there's a couple of people
that would struggle with hangouts for
some reason um and so I would just be
like Rami called this person and he
became like quickly the default person
um I think really it does it just comes
down to everyone owning it I mean like
this like make this your own like your
company can't have remote workers and
this not be part of your culture like
you just can't do that like you will
lose the employee like that's the bottom
line um and so yeah like I mean if their
remote for a couple of weeks or a couple
of days or you know it's not gonna be
part of your culture on though I think
if you're thinking about people being
remote it's probably better to think
about it now and like make people use
this any but you know make people cart
am a vcard around um or else seriously
guys like it it can get really bad um so