[Music]
hello yeah so networking my name is
vinicius I come my way from Brazil to
Berlin and I want to share with you
today how I mean how I made my journey
from Brazil to Berlin and how the
community helped me to do so so to do it
I will walk through my kind of short
career and try to explain you what to
give you some context and how things
went and how all the committee helped me
to do so
so our first short story my career I
have just four years career so it's
really short in the beginning from 15 to
17 I basically work as a stock developer
and mainly javascript no frameworks a
lot of stress and then 18 I went as a
back-end big data developer I shift my
career because of some stress prizes on
the year before and it all happened on
the same very same company back in my
hometown in Brazil so in 2019 I moved to
Germany to Berlin actually to work in a
front-end engineer that doesn't have
that much relation with my previous job
and how did it happen in the beginning
of my career like in the first years our
walls up was I used Khalid are ordinary
developers so I just used to work go
home study and do things that were good
just for the company and not for myself
over something else I didn't know what
conference me top open-source and so on
I was just like working every day going
home and that was it
so how the community helped me in the
past two years so basically it helped me
to not be just an ordinary developer and
do something else above the company
interests work on so how do you help me
to move to another continent so
basically in the beginning I basically
didn't have any reason to keep studying
and putting effort and frontend anymore
once I moved to like back-end and so on
and in fact my last boss
it was jockeyed weird but he told me
that I was wasting my time losing focus
going to meetups conference organized
meetups and so on and that it should
focus on something that really matter
and he said it if I want to do so I
should make money from it I respect his
opinion and so on but I didn't agree
with him and so it all started back in
my first contact I started going to
meetups conference blog and speaking and
organizing meetups and so on and since
my first like year having all this
contact I felt really welcome so my
first meetup I felt welcome first
conference welcome blog post welcome
talk conference welcome so I felt
welcome from every single place I have
been and 18 I kept doing it I fell in
love basically for it
and basically the committee helped me to
push me forward on studying things that
I wasn't even working on touching on
anymore basically JavaScript and voj yes
that I have never had a professional
experience before and so after that
period I didn't consider myself an
ordinary developer anymore and okay
that's all nice but how did I get into
it I mean I was just a kind of a guy
that went to work back home and how it
all changed so the reason to be here
today it show my gratitude means to to
show my gratitude to a person that
invited me to be part of all that thing
the guy that invited me actually to my
first meet I have my hometown the guy
that convinced me to travel more than a
thousand kilometers in Brazil to go to
my first conference yes Brazil quite
weak to travel that help me do my tips
to start my first meetup that invite him
to organize my first meetup and helping
me to organize with him also like a
conference back home so all we know I
want to say thank you to someone that's
not here today is in Brazil as one of
the main reasons that why I am here
today so I want to thank you all and
take your this guide yogam already for
being here thank you
[Applause]