I've been the working on a framework for
the last year and a half called fuse Jas
and over the course of that time I've
learned several things and so my
presentation today is basically what I
learned creating fuse Jas and so I'm
going to go into performance selector
engines and then a thing called sandbox
natives so let's get into it alright so
the first part of performance is
reducing abstraction basically
simplifying things down to vanilla
JavaScript so things run faster so in
this example here we have a function
called times that takes a method and a
context and executed a number of times
and in this example you see that there's
the the range and then a dot each and so
that's that's where it's getting
abstracted so we're going to go and just
remove that and just use a regular while
loop here and it does cost a little bit
of extra code but what you end up
getting is better performance and so if
you do this in like say your entire
framework you end up getting better
performance overall because there's less
of less complexity and less function
calls so there's reducing abstraction
the next one is method forking method
forking basically whenever you have
browser capabilities you want to do some
kind of feature detection for them in
this case this is a weak object
inference basically saying that if this
is true the-- then it assumes it can do
all of these things and same for this
one than that one but what this is doing
is this is for every execution it's
going through and checking it every
single time and so what method forking
does is is instead of checking it every
time you check it at the definition of
the the function so you save on these
checks every
so I'm going to walk through that okay
so first we need a way to do a feature
test for the various methods and because
these are host objects host objects are
things that aren't native and so dom is
a host object so what we do is when you
access these these properties and these
methods on host objects their
implementation dependent so they can
throw errors for example element that
offset parent on a detached element will
throw an error so the best way to do
that is by a type of check and so
basically what this is is this is host
object just checks to see that it's not
a boolean it's not a number of string or
an undefined value and not know and it
does so without doing like a 4 in or
just a regular property access so it
avoids throwing errors when checking for
da melt so that's that okay so this is
just stepping down through the code
alright so this is the the fall back for
the contains method basically just
straight j/s without without having to
use any particular Dom API so this is
what you always want to have as a
fallback method whenever you do method
forking so in case the browser doesn't
have any of these new fancy methods you
can at least fall back on a on a regular
j/s approach so there's that one and you
notice it's when it's checking it its
defining the method here you can see
that
okay and now this is basically checking
to see that it's got the compare
document position method and it's it's
it's using it now for this instead and
that's the only thing it is doing so now
whenever you execute it it's not
checking every single line it's just
going straight to the meat of the
functionality and then the last one
there it does it for if the method
element contains exists so that's that's
a method for you can also take it a step
further and do things like lacy
definition and what that means is
whenever you define a method you don't
actually fork until the first execution
of that method and that's good for
things like event wrappers because you
don't have an event object to start off
with and does the spin up for all of
that just requires even more testing so
it's best to do it for something like
that so what that would do is for lazy
definition is on the first execution it
then it then defines it rewrites the
method and defines it again so that's
Method forking all right the next one is
memorizing and basically it's just fancy
word for caching and what this is is you
just create a closure create yourself a
private variable and use that as your
cash and so for example in this camel
case method you can then this is a weak
example but you can then use it to
instead of having to calculate and
create the camel case every time for a
given strength you can cash that so the
next time it comes through you can then
access the cash instead of doing the
computation on that so that would be
cashing I wanted to just do a little bit
on the performance the rest of it is on
selectors and sandbox natives but I
wanted to at least get that through all
right so my next talk is on CSS selector
engines you know everyone knows if
sizzle it's part of jQuery prototypes
using it now machi kid and there's
there's various other engines
to it gets into some of the obscure ones
over here but today I'm going to talk
about two of them and compare it to an
original one and this is because
whenever I was creating fuse Jas I had
to choose a selector engine because I
didn't want to create my own and I kind
of wanted a black box solution to throw
in there unfortunately as I started
going along I got sucked into it and so
now I know more than I ever wanted to
about selector engines so I'm going to
go ahead and narrow it down so we're
going to narrow it down to NW matter
which is used by my framework as a
default and prototype as a secondary and
then sizzle which is used by the other
ones so here we go ok so when looking
for support i'm using prototype as an
example because it had to make the
similar decision whenever it was
choosing which selector engine to to use
and so a big thing to do is look at
browser support and browser
compatibility and so you can see its
prototype one point six point one this
is its browser supported browsers and
then you can see that NW matter supports
as far back as fire 2 point 0 plus and
then sizzle supports Safari 3 which is
inconsistent with prototypes previous
support so that means when they upgrade
they're going to lose compatibility and
so so that's that's a that's an
important thing to know firefox to i
tested it it worked but it's it's it's a
it's a difference between firefox 1.5 so
it may be something to be aware of
whenever you're making decisions about
select your engines
okay another thing to look at is the
supported selectors per engine you can
see that the legacy has has quite a lot
of supported selectors the the gray here
means it's not supported and then sizzle
you see loses support for some of these
so when users upgrade they're going to
lose support for these selectors and if
they had applications built off of them
their applications are going to break so
that is something to note and it gets
really important whenever you go into
browsers that don't have query selector
all because those are the ones that need
support for these query selector all
likes kind of even things up there and
then you can see NW match or has all of
those plus some all right speaking of
query selector all there's some bugs in
query selector all and this is important
because some frameworks we'll just dump
to query selector all as a as a quick go
to because they assume it's it's working
and consistent across browsers and that
isn't the case there's there's lots of
query selector all bugs and there's
actually more than is covered here
there's there's a lot more ie bugs out
there too so this is just an overview of
which bugs each engine supports and
fixes and so you can see that they both
have some kind of class name case
sensitivity bug and then there's these
all these other bugs that are covered
under NW measure
okay now this is testing for CSS
selector css3 select your test basically
rules that the spec defines on tests and
or this test is test the rules for that
for those and so basically it's an
unimportant I'll give you links to the
examples of these but as you mouse over
it tells you what's failing from the
spec and so you can see here there's a
few inconsistencies between browsers but
not not many and so this is right now
this is the legacy so this is ie8
compatibility mode IE eight safari three
our safari for chrome for firefox 3.6
and opera 10.5 plus so so that's the
compatibility for prototypes old engine
so now
now I'll do sizzle okay so here's sizzle
and here's the you can see the tests
that it's failing its failing quite a
few more but to be fair it doesn't have
support for a lot of those those other
selectors that I'm sure this thing is
testing so keep that in mind whenever
you're looking at this that this could
be quite a lot of the selectors a dozen
some point so that's this is sizzle
through the same browser range there and
there's there's slightly different
results from mode to mode but you can
test this out to whenever you go to the
test looks and then here is NW matter so
in css3 compliance and so this is this
is its engine basically the only problem
it has is ie bugs with one where ie
strips out certain attributes that they
have default values or empty values so
it actually removes it from the source
it removes it from the attribute method
so there's no way to detect it the other
one is text nodes and how it strips out
new lines and things like that and that
will cause issues with like the empty
selector so this is NW match through all
this now I'm going to get to let's see
now I'm going to get to matching
basically selector engines can be used
in matching can be used for event
delegation so whenever you trigger an
event you check to see if an element
matches the selector and then you're
able to proceed on and so the speed of
your match method is important because
that affects the speed of a bit
delegation so this is a charge to show
the matching speed of the various
engines and so you can see the further
over the faster it is and so you have
prototype and sizzle and then NW matcher
this also test some of the native
methods that have been introduced in
late in the the newest versions of
WebKit and and Firefox that because they
have their own matching methods now too
and so you can see like Firefox is
native
matching method is insanely fast but web
kits you know isn't isn't as fast in
fact regular jjs engines can can beat it
so that's the breakdown here I don't
know if you can see this is uh this is
opera that's actually 10.5 for some
reason that the browser string says nine
and then it that's 3.6 for Firefox this
is IE 8 this is ie6 this is safari 4 and
chrome for now for regular performance
this is a modified form of slick speed
that talents executions in a given
amount of time instead of just three or
four executions so the higher the number
the better and the number isn't
representative of the executions it's
actually divided by 100 or so just to
make it a pretty number else it would
they would all be thousands of execution
so we don't want to see that all right
and so zoomed in view you can see NW
matter has 914 sizzle has to 96 and then
prototype has to 92 for their old engine
and then you can see because prototype
supports both NW match your and sizzle
you can see that what there's new speeds
are whenever they're running under the
new engines which is 917 and 293
okay so if you're if you're running
prototype and you want to switch to NW
matcher you have to rake it and select
your engine and so this will allow you
to choose NW metric ok the next talk is
on sandbox natives basically sandbox
natives our way to grab array string
number all of these Native objects and
constructors off of a different
environment and import them in and this
is because you have issues with for
example when you extend an array and you
then do a 4 in on that array you end up
getting the contents of the array plus
the new method that you've added to
prototype of that array and then this
this goes into explaining but in
technical jargon what it's doing but you
also have problems with frameworks for
example framework X defines a method and
then later framework why it defines
their own method paving over them and so
when you define when you extend natives
like a ray and string and function and
all of these you run the risk of
colliding into other frameworks and
other projects that extend the same
natives so that's that's a problem and
for example this is this is a real world
case where this is prototype and this is
EXT j/s they both do this they really
extend the same thing all right in this
case we have a problem where a framework
defines a method or let's say your own
code defines a method extending the
array and then later on a different
method if the same name gets added to
the spec ECMAScript and so then you get
issues where your implementation which
paves the other or may not is different
than the official one and so you get
different results and so this is an
example of what else can happen wrong if
you are extending natives directly on
the window
okay the solution is sandbox natives I'm
going to go into a just a brief example
of sandbox natives and talk a little bit
of how they're created I have a series
of video casts that talk about the the
whole process of sandbox natives and
things and all the link to it was in the
beginning and I'll probably court back
to it at the end basically I create
sandbox natives in three ways I use
either an iframe I use an activex object
called activex or HTML file or I use the
the proto property which is the
underscore underscore proto underscore
underscore property and using those
three ways and I feed your test for them
so they don't there's no browser
sniffing they're using those three
things I'm able to grab the Constructors
or modify their their prototype
prototypical inheritance to 22 new
objects so therefore you're able to
extend these and create real number
objects real real array objects real
string objects and you're able to extend
them without affecting the global array
or a number or string or object or any
of those and so this is an example of
doing that you can see we're fused array
dot prototype sighs I'm extending a real
array and then I'm returning a real
array and it has that method but then
the window does not have that because it
doesn't touch the window so that means I
can then play with other third-party
code that does and it's not going to
affect you okay the browser's tested for
this these techniques are listed here
it's quite a lot of browsers and also
the various JavaScript engines because
it supports the proto property a lot of
these engines also support that property
and so you can actually run sandbox
natives on the server side as well so
you can avoid extending the natives
there as well so this is the browser
supported there
okay and this is the list of supported
natives that I'm able to sandbox I could
probably do others but this seemed to be
a good number of them so its array
boolean date function number object reg
ex and string and so that means you can
extend these all and it won't affecting
all right so here's some usage of
sandbox natives you can create the
string but you notice that the string is
not type of string its type of object
because it's not a primitive because if
it was a primitive it would be a
primitive of primary document and then
it you wouldn't be able to have the
sugar associated with the method so what
it is is it's just like calling new
string it returns the string instance
and so type of is object and you can say
it's just like the new string where the
instance is an object but what's neat is
that it still has the internal class of
string so all the the frameworks that do
is string or is array they all check the
class property and so it's always going
to return string or array or function
and then you can also chain because
chaining works which which required a
little bit of tweaking so you can you
can use it just like you use your normal
natives whenever you're extending
natives okay so what's cool about this
most people when they think of sandbox
natives or something will think wow I
can use this for a raise subclassing
arrays because that's that's a pretty
hot thing so this shows an example of
creating multiple fuse multiple sand
boxes or fuse boxes as as it's called on
the name space to do different things
one has just regular array methods but
the other ones used for like a jQuery
syntax and you can see where querying
returns an instance of node list which
has methods on it like AG class name or
show and so you can just chain all the
way through
okay so now I'm going to talk a little
bit about fuse Jas and what it has to
offer fuse Jas is a fork of prototype
JSI started with prototype and have been
shifting it over for the last year and a
half so I'm going to just point out some
of the unique things that views Jas has
all right fuse Jas is tested in ie6 plus
Firefox 1.5 plus chrome Conqueror opera
and Safari 2.00 so it supports the older
set of browsers that prototype used to
support in their previous version some
of the neat things our sandbox natives
which allow for better third party and
browser support because of the issues
that I described I don't have any of
those issues because I run run them in
their own sandbox performance what I've
done is I've reduced the abstraction
I've used method forking by browser
features to boost the performance of the
engine because it's not having to go
through everything another big thing is
zero browser sniffs I use feature
detection feature testing an object
inference to to do this and basically
the difference between feature testing
and feature detection is feature testing
is like is sorry feature detection is
like a proper object inference object
inference usually implies that you're
testing for a property X in assuming
function y so feature testing is is
testing for the existence of property or
method X because you're about to use
method X so and then feature testing is
actually executing the method trying it
seeing if you get the outcome that you
would expect and then another neat thing
is that fuse jas will support framework
emulation which means that few GS will
be able to run as for example prototype
so all you would do is delete prototype
jas from your project then drop infuse
jas then plus the emulation j/s and it
will run as if it is
prototype so your code doesn't have to
change but you get the benefit of
increased performance increased browser
support feature testing and new features
so so that's that's a pretty neat thing
and then as we go along will support
other frameworks and then another neat
thing is that it's it's debug friendly
which means i use function expressions
or yeah function expressions to create
readable names whenever you debug into
console so whenever you for example put
this method in the console it's going to
spit back the name of the method and the
arguments accepts and so whenever you do
things like profile on your site or use
the Firebug profile instead of having
like anonymous function pop up all over
the place you're going to actually have
the full method there so you can see
them other features are its going to be
modular so because there's less
abstraction there's less dependency
between files and functionality so you
can build because you can create custom
builds that say don't have array
extensions or don't have the template or
the range or the Ajax or any of these
things because there's there's no
dependency on either one for the other
to operate and then select your engines
I support seven selector engines because
i like giving developers a choice and so
I support dojos acne EXT jss Dom query
NW matcher peppy sizzle slick which is
mootools new selector engine and then
sly which is a variation of that i'll
also be supporting quirks mode for
dimensions and positioning code which is
something that some browsers are some
frameworks actually don't support so
like jQuery I think dropped dropped it
recently prototypes had problems with it
so I'm going to make sure that I support
some quirks mode there other things is
our I up I do dham wrappers and I do
event wrappers for things so I'm not
extending the Dom either so I don't run
into the conflicts of names or
issues where things aren't being
extended properly because of ie bug X or
Firefox bug why so I have that and
another another neat thing is that when
I have Dom rappers you can still have
the functionality of extending things
per element so like in prototype you
could give just input elements a method
like get value and then this way too
because this mimics the the Dom classes
you can just give input elements a
method or just give image is a method to
refresh or something like that so that's
neat I also support cross frame or cross
iframe communication so the method will
still work on the iframe document even
though the iframe document does not have
the framework loaded in it and that's
because I avoid references to document
or the global and I resolve it by the
element owner document and so I'm able
to resolve the the iframes document in
these methods something else I do
differently is I in first I enforce
first in first out of in order when
you're observing events and a lot of
frameworks are doing this now and it
makes sense because I e is the only one
that really goes against the grain and
has a random event order execution but
whenever you're absorbing events a lot
of times you want you want your first
observer to execute before your second
and so on it so you expect that order
and so I make that consistent something
else I do is I preserve backward forward
cash which means I don't have a non
unload handler to clean up the memory
issues with ie because I avoid the
memory issues with ie in the first place
and so because of that I don't have to
break backward forward cash and so
whenever you flip between pages the
framework will continue to the state of
the page will still be preserved and so
that's that's what that's actually a
pretty pretty cool thing there something
else I do is I don't have any expand
owes on IE elements expand those effects
screen redraw and things like that and I
found a way to avoid any of them on IE
so you don't get that performance
penalty
on ie or other issues like whenever you
clone nodes and things like that
something else need is I have method
generics which means if any of you have
used or gone to mozillas MDC site you'll
you'll see that they have like a ray
slice or a push or these generics that
are on the constructor instead of on the
instance and so I have all of my methods
support generics as well so anything
that's on like the element prototype is
also on the elements generic form too
and then something else I do is I do
separation of Dom properties and
attributes and this is this is an
interesting thing as you get into a
framework you'll see that a lot of times
they mix up Dom properties like element
da checked and Dom attributes like
element get attribute checked and which
is there's a difference there because
attributes are source attributes which
means how they are when the page is
rendered their properties are live so
like the attribute value of an input
element is what it originally was
whenever the page loaded the live value
is the element value which is the
current input and so I make a kippah
separation there and I keep it
consistent in the end the method so
there's none of the confusion that goes
along with okay this is going to be some
performance tests with fuse j s alpha
you can see right now in its early stage
it runs about as fast as jquery 1.4 2
and is right around what dojo 1.4 is as
well or 1.4 or maybe one there so that
it's doing pretty good for itself at the
time you can see prototypes is is a
little slower there so that's fuse JSE's
performance
now i'm going to show you fuse jss
performance in ie8 and compared two
prototypes performance in ie8 and in
this case less is more because this is
task speed so you can see here that this
is 2,000 something and this is 11,000
something so the speed difference is
pretty big for ie8 and then last but not
least i mentioned that fuse will support
framework emulation and i wanted to show
that i'm closer to prototype support now
because you can see i'm getting proto
used to yes to run as prototype and you
can see the performance differences
right there this is a 2180 and this is
almost almost 3000 so the the difference
in speed is quite noticeable you'll have
additional features and that is fuse j/s
cool any questions yes i just want to
make sure i understand if you're saying
you emulate for the text messages
okay yes anything else there's got to be
a drama well the the the issue is on
performance is how they're designed
prototype has a lot of abstraction in
there because they like to use their own
methods over and over and at the
beginning I showed reducing abstraction
and so what I do is infuse I have
everything as vanilla Jas and so
everything is stripped down to the gist
the fundamentals so that's what runs
faster also I do things like forking the
methods to create faster execution and
so when all of that's combined you get
faster an entirely faster framework
another benefit is is because I don't
extend the elements I don't have a
penalty for let's say ie6 or ie7 that
doesn't have the element that prototype
and so that's another way to be faster
and so might the idea is is that as I go
along I'll keep optimizing and then when
I support other frameworks I'll still be
able to run as fast as them the reason
I'm able to run its prototype is because
I have all of my dom methods are this
generic the little this keyword generic
and that allows me to run as a node list
like jQuery syntax or I can then run as
as just a single element rapper like
they get the element by ID and then it
has the rapper or I can then dump that
back on to the element dot prototype to
run as prototype and the method still
works because it's this generic it
doesn't care that it's a rapper or an
element it just works and so it makes
the very little overhead to actually
create the emulation layer yes so huge
is including the default NW masters
ah how big is that compared to some of
the other popular frameworks like jQuery
there the goal is to get it to be around
30 kilobytes currently in the alpha
stage everything is inflated because
I've got the debug code in there and
I've got other things but the goal is to
be right around 30 kilobytes or so and
the size can actually change because you
can create custom builds so you can take
out the things you don't want like
template or range if you never use those
and just throw them out and so it allows
you to create a smaller more focused
file size also i have debugging built
the debug friendly function names those
those debug friendly function names
actually create an increase in file size
and so before you minify there's going
to be a pre process that you can run on
the custom build thing and it will strip
out the named expressions and cleanup
and so that helps reduce the size and
keep it at a manageable limit anything
else yes
okay in the optimal condition I either
use the ActiveX object or the proto
because proto supported by everything
almost and the ActiveX object avoids
issues with like domain a document
domain settings with iframes and it also
avoids issues in Firefox with some
iframe issues I had by removing and
inserting and then the I fall back to
the last resort is the iframe now in the
iframe I should mention that Dean
Edwards created a technique in 2006 to
do basically the same thing with the
iframe but what he did was he left the
iframe in the document and that affects
your window dot frames collection and so
I found a way to to insert the iframe
grab the natives and take the iframe out
and cash it so it doesn't get garbage
collected and so that allows me to use
it without affecting the window frames
collection so I guess the order would be
proto activex then I fer cool anything
else I'm getting the clap alright