I'm Kyle Simpson and I go by getify you
probably know me better by that way so
this title
JSU I not only was it because I like the
matrix but also this has kind of a
hidden meeting what we're going to talk
about today this JavaScript UI
architecture stuff it is it exists in
every single web application but it's
kind of hidden most people don't think
about it we don't give it a name we
don't talk about it but it is oftentimes
the biggest pain point in in application
so that's kind of the backstory
come on now you were just working a
second ago still working all right well
I guess I'm not gonna be able to use it
all right so dude where's my you re
architecture that's the title of today's
talk so what the heck is UI architecture
I mean all the stuff that it takes to
process package deliver get together
your presentation layer and get it up to
the browser from the server this
involves things like templating URL
routing data validation data formatting
Ajax even stuff like caching I didn't
put that on the slide all those things
are part of what I call the middle end
so this is in between the front end and
the back end so let's take a look at
existing web application architecture
diagram I just kind of whip this
together this is by no means definitive
but this is kind of representative of
how a lot of web application
architectures work so some things to
point out here real quick we've got the
client browser over here with the
javascript in the application and it's
very very separate and very very siloed
from the rest of what's going on in the
web application the typical pattern here
is that this JSF Legation re implements
to some degree and sometimes to a great
degree the stuff that's going on down
here so we've got two different views of
what our application are it's what's
happening in the browser and what's
happening on the server this is kind of
a way to visualize the typical MVC stack
we've got a web server layer sitting on
top
as I is this is Apache Ingenix even if
you're really clever this is no js' and
then we've got some control or an
application logic stuff if you're using
net Java whatever platform you can
insert this is entirely agnostic of
which technology you're choosing
but this layer is the one that sits
there it intercepts the request from the
web server and it controls everything
that's going to happen then down here at
the bottom we have the view the
templating engine the things that put
together what we're going to see the
presentation layer and sitting in
between them the model and it
communicates with our database so what
is my motivation for mucking with this
because this pattern has been around for
a long time
number one performance I'm a huge
performance geek a lot of my projects
are about that lab j/s and other things
like that so my biggest concern is that
I go to companies companies that I work
out or companies that have asked me to
consult on these topics and I try to
convince them that what they need to do
is just do something crazy like optimize
the mark-up that their application sends
out to the browser not too complicated
right and what's the universal response
I get back oh I can't change that markup
there's some compiled widget way down
deep inside of my architecture that does
that for me and I would never dream of
changing the way that grid control works
it surely is in control of that markup
this sucks
this really really sucks even simple
things like hey can you put a different
doctype on your page so that you can
have some standards to your web
application no I can't control that
stuff so performance sucks when you have
no control over what's happening
we need more control so that's the first
motivation the second one MVC now I'm
gonna pick on MVC a little bit but as
you'll see at the end I'm not really
telling you that MVC is wrong I'm just
trying to kind of evolve some of these
concepts a little bit so this is an
example I'm going to pick on PHP but
this kind of code happens in every
platform so some things to look at here
we're obviously we're inside of a view
we're in an HTML page or a PHP page in
this case we're in a view and what we've
got is we want to conditionally show
some link to some page we only want to
show that when some condition is true of
our back-end logic in this case we got
really clever we've got an
object-oriented model we've got a user
and that model has a function on it
called is logged in that's kind of
opaque we're not exactly sure what is
logged in means but it's probably
checking for a login session maybe some
credentials and then over here we've got
the permissions based side of things
that not only are they logged in but
there's a particular permission or set
of permissions that we have a
arbitrarily decided means that they can
publish and if both of those conditions
are true then we want to show this link
now this is perfectly valid logic the
problem is this is terrible to put in
your templates because as soon as you
write this code three weeks later
somebody's in your biz dev side of your
company is going to come along and tell
you well actually can publish is not
really the whole world we need one more
condition on top of can publish we need
this or we need that or or you're gonna
have back in developers that are going
to go through and refactor your model
and these function names are gonna
change or the meaning of what they do is
going to get overloaded and all of a
sudden your templates and your back-end
application architecture are terribly
intertwined this is exactly what MVC
tells us to get away from to have loose
you know mixture between our views and
our in our models and things like that
but unfortunately this just happens all
the time so my third motivation is dry
do not repeat yourself I am such a lazy
developer and I'm just gonna go right
out there and say it I do not like to
write code more than once I really I
want that utopia where I can write code
once and it's gonna freak and run
anywhere I want it to run and I don't
have to worry about it
and the last thing is we all wear a lot
of different hats
some people are get to get the privilege
of specializing in the front end or
specializing in the back end many times
people are having to wear multiple hats
they're having to do some front end back
some front end development some back in
development and the problem is that when
you are doing back in development you're
thinking like a back-end developer
that's a good thing but it's a terrible
thing for the front-end because system
architecture is entirely different so
very much orthogonal and opposite in
ways to front-end development and the
concerns of the front end and the
reverse is also true so when you have to
these hats you have to keep context
switching and thinking of entirely
different worlds and this is what leads
to the crap of I've got a widget that
you know builds out my markup and
because I'm a back-end developer I don't
want to worry about the box model and
CSS and markup standards and all of that
crap so I'm going to bury that deep down
inside of my java code so I never have
to worry about it again but then I have
lost complete control so my motivation
here is that we need to allow when you
are a front-end developer when you're
wearing that hat you need to be able to
stay inside of that core skillset and
get your job done fast and get it done
efficiently and get it done right when
you're back and developer the same is
true so we need a different view on this
and I am proposing what I call a new
pattern it's not exactly a replacement
of MVC but we're going to talk about
some differences I call it c b c stands
for client's views controllers or client
view controller so this is a slightly
different view of the world we're going
to talk about cbc UI architecture here
for a moment so this is a UI focused
architecture and it separates out the
tears it creates an explicit middle-end
UI architecture layer that you may or
may not be very familiar with seeing so
the first thing that i want you to
recognize here is that down here at the
bottom everything that was in that prior
diagram that was all over here and all
intermixed becomes this black box this
is our application and now our
application doesn't know anything at all
about how things are going to be
presented it is 100% an API based
application all it is is a state machine
all it is is concerned with dealing with
state with managing your login sessions
with connecting to the database and
doing whatever magic that system
backends do we stick a simple JSON
serializing API on top of that and the
whole rest of the world becomes
beautiful for the UI engineer JSON is an
awesome representation of data it's the
only representation of data that's truly
native recognizable in all of our other
tiers and every application is able to
serialize down to JSON then what we have
over here the most important thing is
that what now is in control of what's
going on on
server is that what I call the UI
controllers and I am implementing these
in JavaScript this is why I'm talking
about it at a JavaScript conference so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
write everything that the middle end is
in JavaScript all of this and then the
cool part is this thing over here this
templating engine and even some of these
things they can work over here in the
browser the exact same code I don't have
to write different code things like data
validation I can write that once and run
it in both places instead of having to
have you know some something that auto
generates JavaScript for me so I just
want to switch back to this one for just
a moment and then back so that you see
the differences we're making a UI
focused architecture here I'm not
telling you what you need to do with
this black box other than stop having
this thing do crappy presentation
whatever platform you're working on I
really don't care it could be Perl I
feel bad for you but it could be
whatever you want it to be all I'm
telling you is that your presentation
layer and your middle end probably sucks
right now and maybe you should rethink
it so let's talk about what CVC means
clients everything is a client of
everything else
they're decoupled they're modular and
they're scalable that means at any point
in the flow everything is able to talk
to everything else and it uses JSON the
views their templating they're portable
they're dry they're platform agnostic
and they use the core web technology
that UI engineers are most familiar with
the JavaScript HTML and CSS the
controllers are all these little tiny
things that make all this stuff work
this is the thing that takes a request
and translates it into an execution of
the View engine and grabs the JSON data
from the application and pumps it in and
packages all the stuff up it caches
things those are what the UI controllers
are doing they're small independent and
powerful they're also in JavaScript so
what I'm not suggesting is that we need
another framework so this is actually
the anti framework presentation none of
what I am doing is going to
automatically build you some UI we just
heard a talk on the ext j/s and they do
a phenomenal job of packaging all that
stuff
and making it so that you don't really
have to think about it much I actually
want to do the reverse I want you to
have to think about it so you can build
on top of this pattern whatever kind of
presentation layer is cool with you you
can use jQuery ext dojo whatever you
want to do but make sure that you use a
templating system that can run in both
places I'm not telling you to ditch your
whole architecture as I said you can go
and you can go back to your company
you know Monday morning and you can tell
them hey I just want to change the views
I don't have to change the entire
platform architecture and I'm also not
saying that MBC is inherently wrong or
that it's weak or something like that
I'm just simply saying that in our world
of web 2.0 and with the role separations
and specialties that we all are falling
into and our jobs it's time that we
rethink this a little bit and I'm
suggesting an extension to that pattern
CBC is an alternate pattern for thinking
about UI architecture and it is okay to
rethink you do not have to accept the
status quo because you've always been a
dotnet shop and you've never been given
the option of doing anything other than
that it's okay to go back and rethink
things so how are we going to do this
well we're gonna use Java Script which
is awesome and it's going to be on the
server primarily there's going to be
some in the in the browser as well
sometimes JavaScript on the server can
feel a little bit out of the wall out of
a fish out of water kind of a thing in
today's day and age we're really pushing
things and you're seeing some awesome
stuff from nodejs and narwhal and rhino
and all these awesome things and we're
trying to get them to kind of all work
together commonjs is doing a great job
of giving us some standards for how all
of these things work the problem is that
we haven't progressed very far yet so
you've got something awesome like nodejs
and they've gone and done like 18 or 20
different api's for all these awesome
things and only two or three of them are
things that everybody's kind of agreed
on in the common Jas world so that's why
you're seeing so much API that's
changing with node and it's and it's
also a problem narwhals a little bit
more mature but it's also a problem
there so and the world of server-side
javascript is still kind of a wild wild
west and we've got some issues to work
through there but I believe hole
hardly in JavaScript on the server and I
think it's the answer to a lot of our
problems so I'm prepared to be on that
forefront and we're gonna we're gonna
stub our toe a few times it's going to
suck but we're gonna eventually come to
something that is freakin amazing so I'm
gonna propose I've written some code
that I call bike Ching Jas this is a
much more simplified view of what
server-side JavaScript would be it is
not at all intended to replace or
compete with nodejs
but I needed something simple and a
little bit more kind of tangible to work
with when I'm demoing and kind of
developing some of these ideas so this
just wraps around v8 it's a single
engine file it's a single compilable it
creates a very simple straightforward
server-side javascript environment and
it uses the module approach that the
others are familiar with using I talked
extensively with Chris Cole and some of
the others from the common Jas world I
wanted to make sure that what I
implemented was as close as possible to
what the common Jas world is wanting to
agree on and because all I needed were
things like file i/o system i/o and a
few process execution things those are
the things that everybody's kind of
agreed on so that's the good news the
bad news is you're not going to be able
to use bike change has to do commet
servers and all kinds of freaking
amazing stuff but I actually don't think
that that's necessary for most of the
web's
UI architecture so bike chain Jas is
really just kind of a temporary stopgap
hopefully it'll evolve kind of in
parallel with some of the others and
it's a good synchronous simple
environment to get started and then you
can graduate to running this code and
something more sophisticated like node
or normal CVC plus javascript is the
power of the UI architecture put in the
hands of the people that need it most
the front-end engineers instead of
relying on your system architect who has
no clue what it actually means to
optimize markup and CSS and Ajax
communication you put it in the hands of
those who work with that every single
day and you give them the control to
make things better
my templating engine I call handlebar J
s this is actually patterned
significantly inspired by mustache J s
so I'm going to give full credit to them
they really were some pioneers in this
this is a primarily HTML text-based
templating approach uses a very simple
wrapper around that a very simple small
DSL for templating my basic idea was I
need the bare minimum that it takes to
get templating done I don't need to
bring a huge machine gun to a knife
fight so I'm not going to give the full
power of JavaScript to the templating
engine that's going to what's going to
let lead to that spaghetti code we dealt
with before so handlebar J s is very
stripped-down and simple and it uses
only JSON data for the input so we're
not dealing with inexorable
communication between our model and the
way our model works in the way the
front-end works if you've ever dealt
with this I deal with this all the time
you know for whatever reason the backend
architecture they want to do things as a
keyed hash and when I get it in the
front end and I want to iterate over it
it needs to be an array because I need
it to be ordered for whatever
presentational reason this sucks that we
have to have those two be the same thing
and the problem is that we're trying to
replicate the model that the backend
guys use in the front-end and that's not
how things work in the front-end so if
we serialize things down to JSON it
makes things a lot simpler we can agree
upon that serialization and then it's
kind of like creating an interface for
your data that interface doesn't have to
change no matter what the backend guys
do and if you need a little bit of a
tweak to that in your front-end you're
in control of tweaking that
serialization so the details this is
100% JavaScript runs both in browser the
server it only accepts JSON data not
models and behavior the application
state this is an arbitrary string value
that represents the state of your
application that's the state that that
black box is currently in that's going
to what's going to select which template
to use and finally for performance
reasons one step that I've already built
into handlebar j/s even though it's kind
of young and immature one step that I've
built into it is that it compiles your
text template so and it does all of this
you know complicated and expensive
regular expression parsing on text a lot
of these template engines are
just-in-time compilers and they do that
over and over and over again and
handlebar jeaious can run in
just-in-time but it also will
cache the results of that into
executable JavaScript so you can run
that as a build process so you can still
maintain your templates in HTML all the
way it ought to be but you get the
performance benefit of being able to run
optimized JavaScript so let's take a
look at a demo if you want to go and
check out J s content get a fine calm
that is this page I will tell you that
at the bottom of this there are two
links there you can't see the second one
there's a demo comments thread that's
what we're gonna look at in just a
moment then right below that there's a
slides link this is substantially the
same presentation that I gave last month
itself by Southwest Interactive and so
my slide set from that is up still on
SlideShare so you're gonna see most of
the same slides here if you want to
check out my slides let's go over and
take a look at this demo this is a very
simple demo and I encourage all of you
to be participating in this demo it'll
be cooler if more of you are logging in
and doing things so basically the setup
of this demo is I've got this image and
I've got 10 different randomly selected
images that come from Flickr and I can
just change those that will what I'm
doing actually is I'm using handlebar
jeaious handlebar jeaious was used to
build this page on the server when I
first requested it and then when I click
this change image I'm doing an ajax
request and i'm saying giving some json
back that tells me what's the new image
that's been randomly selected from the
server the details its source and alts
and all of that stuff and then i'm
rebuilding that markup using the
template on the front end so it's very
simple but you can see that it's going
quick so whichever image you happen to
have picked when you type in your name
and you type in some URL and you click
login it's gonna create a login session
for you and you can type in a comment so
i'm gonna say hey nice bench and submit
that comment all that that it's
happening here is using that handlebar
jeaious I'm going to show you some code
here in just a moment but everything
that just happened there that were Ajax
requests that were going back and forth
but they were only sending JSON back and
forth the mark-up was actually being
built on the fly using the same template
again j'en in the browser
is what I use on the server so if I were
to refresh this page the exact same
process of querying the application for
that data would happen and the
server-side templating engine would be
responsible for building this page so if
several of you have already added
comments which I'm guessing probably you
have if I use if i refresh this page so
now I know that several of you have
already made comments that request
happened on the server so I can do
templating in both places using exactly
the same templates I can also do data
validation in both places because I know
for a fact that I have a rule that if I
type in a really short comment like this
it's going to do some data validation
now what's cool about this is that data
validation code which I'll show in just
a moment if I have time that deadly
validation code very simple it just
looked at the minimum length of my text
field that ran in the browser gave me an
immediate request but that same code can
also run on the server because we know
we can't trust the javascript in the
browser so I did not have to write that
rule twice I only wrote it once so it
needs to be at least 5 characters so
then when I resubmit everything's going
to work fine all right so let's take a
look at some code first of all using
handlebar j/s this is intended to be
very simple a lot of this stuff is
wrapped up inside of the code so here
you can see that all I'm doing is I'm
calling handlebar and I'm calling a
function called process state I'm giving
it that arbitrary string value which
represents the state of the application
in this case I know there's a login
error so I know what that state is and
I'm passing it a JSON data structure and
then I'm using this fancy thing called
promises server-side defers things like
that so it's not really particularly
important exactly how this happens but
basically this can be an asynchronous
operation or synchronous depending on
the environment and what's happening and
so all I really want to know is either
immediately or later if necessary I want
to do something after this completes so
after I've processed that state then I'm
going to get passed to me the value the
results of that templating process and
so I'm just going to use some very
simple jQuery to replace the existing
form with what the results of my
templating engine were it doesn't get
any more complicated than that I use
that template engine as an engine to
grab me the markup and combine it with
that data
and it used the optimized precompiled
javascript version of the template
alright so handlebar j/s just to show a
couple of things this is just there's
actually several JavaScript files but of
course you can combine them all together
it's really nothing more than a bunch of
fancy you know regular expressions and
processing and things but I'm
essentially generating my JavaScript
right here that's what I'm doing is I'm
just building up strings of JavaScript
that represent the optimized output of
your text templates let's take a look at
what some of those templates might look
like so if you're interested in my
particular approach to templating so
this is a master template file you can
see here at the top that I declare a
template section that's what this dollar
sign colon is and I give it a name I use
kind of the CSS approach here so IDs
have the pound and then I have my
doctype here and of course I know that
ie bug have got no whitespace before my
dog died but then I just sum
substantially doing HTML and then here
I'm gonna drop in a sub template a style
sub template that's what the @ symbol
does down later you see in the body I've
got dropping in the content and footer
sub templates so this is my master
template for every page on this side of
course there's only one right now but my
individual template template done index
dot HTML by the way filenames doesn't
matter you can have whatever you wanted
to be but here I'm basically saying well
I'm going to extend sort of simple
object-oriented extension if you will
I'm extending that master template and
I'm going to basically here declare some
some values that are going to happen at
runtime when this sub template is called
but all these do are going to select
other sub templates so there's no
mathematics going on or data formatting
or any other logic that you don't want
to have here the only logic that happens
is presentational logic deciding which
templates need to happen so for instance
when I'm logged in I'm going to show a
different set of or when there's
comments I'm going to show a different
template than when there's not comments
I wanted to show you real quick I'm kind
of running short a little short in time
but I want to show you real quick a
couple of other pieces of code so this
is that validation code that I was
talking about this
is very very simple I just wrote some
some functions that that I can run in
both places you can do whatever
validation you want as long as it's not
you know tied to there being a Dom as
long as it deals with JSON data valleys
and then you can run it in both places
here I just have a different one for the
full name property and the URL property
and I can apply rules that will in this
code to run in both places same is true
of formatting I didn't really Express
that much but when I'm for when I'm
getting data back from a from an ajax
request i need to format that on-the-fly
need to make sure that HTML characters
are properly escaped and things like
that so that's another thing that you
the URL or the UI architecture does
usually for you and that you have full
control over this now you can pass it
into a formatting function and replace
your characters and all of those things
and you can do that either in the
browser on the server last thing full
disclosure the back end of this
application the black box of this
application is a PHP file when I gave
this demo at South by Southwest that
actually crashed and then I went back
and I was like man that sucks why did it
crash halfway through my demo some of it
worked and then it didn't and as I
discovered it was the PHP that crashed
so all the JavaScript was awesome and it
worked and it was the PHP that sucked so
full disclosure there's some PHP going
on but this is only doing the crappy
stuff of you know managing my sessions
and all that other crap but the last
line is the important one it just
encodes it to JSON and spits it out and
the rest of the world is beautiful junk
for javascript last thing on full
disclosure is to say that at the moment
I'm still experimenting with the jump
between a web request and an execution
context for JavaScript this is called
the the gateway interface it goes by jsg
I in the JavaScript world there are J
SGI things like v8 cgi that can do this
automatically for you
i'm trying to evaluate the best way to
do this it's basically how do you
translate a set of HTTP headers into an
execution context for javascript so at
the moment I have some really terrible
ugly PHP that's doing it but that's the
only part that's actually happening in
the stack that's PHP and very soon this
crap is going to go
and basically all this is doing again
for full disclosure is I'm simply
executing my JavaScript here I'm calling
my engine and passing it a JavaScript
file so that's really all the PHP is
doing but I took advantage of the fact
that PHP is pretty good about giving me
those headers and session management all
those things so we've got like one or
two minutes left and I think that's
substantially what I wanted to show for
the presentation are there any last
questions so I'm a huge fan of
server-side JavaScript and there's a lot
of different ways to take it it's gonna
make sense for some companies to go with
that architecture some of them it's not
for instance if you're in the dotnet
world you really want the smallest
footprint of change to that architecture
as possible because it's really hard to
adapt things in that world so for them
it wouldn't make sense to go with a
really complex you know CouchDB and
nodejs kind of thing because they're
gonna have to rethink their entire world
but if you can just tell them run some
synchronous JavaScript in this small
little sandbox give that control to your
front-end developers and let the
back-end developers only worry about
data and session management things I
think can prove a little bit I think
there's certainly a use case for some
more forward thinking or more
experimental companies that want to go
full fledge totally JavaScript on the
server and all of this code should work
exactly perfectly in that type of
environment good question
anybody else awesome go forth and
rethink in your eye architecture there
is a middle end it's time to give it a
name so thanks a lot