nothing has been sacred since I was 11
years old when I first began to question
all assumptions including reality itself
and that locked me in a metaphysical
conundrum that led to the brain in the
box and as we evaporate away we have
nothing left but that of nothingness so
naturally I turned to science to study
the smallest primitives of the universe
in order to figure out if they could
provide an answer to metaphysics and
reality naturally that be the atom and
the orbital States and electron and
consequently quantum mechanics so in
that process I'd like to kind of give a
quick snaps asst of quantum mechanics we
have an electron at orbital state 5 and
it jumps to orbital state to you can
jump back and forth and the interesting
thing here that you might have heard is
that it actually teleports from these
two states it doesn't move in between it
doesn't move between the space it
teleports right so the difference
between those two states is negative
three from five to two you have a delta
difference of negative 3 that is
quantifiable and literally that is where
quantum mechanics comes into play
quantum mechanics is the quantifiable
difference between these orbital States
that's the world of quantum mechanics
however further further you get into
quantum physics with Schrodinger's cat
multi worlds theorem wave particle
duality kind of discover that it doesn't
really hold any good answers for
materialistic kind of existence or
giving you a basis for understanding
reality so with that I decided I needed
to go even further down the rabbit hole
of questioning assumptions
beyond science down to logic itself now
naturally logic corresponds a lot to
computer programming so when I was 16
after using logic for about seven years
I developed a metaphysical proof for
reality but once I had done that I no
longer you know was just sitting around
all day all night trying to figure out
whether you know I exist whether this
hand is real and one side done that
right I had a bunch of spare time in my
hands so if I'd already gotten into kind
of the logic side of the equation
computers might as well learn how to do
HTML and CSS since that was the natural
path I wanted to be able to take my
metaphysical theory which would be about
six hours of Socratic dialogue in order
for me to explain but I want to go to
present it to everybody I want to be
able to explain my concepts so of course
naturally go to the best publishing
platform in the world the web which
requires learning HTML and CSS let's
just say that CSS would not make for a
good metaphysical framework because it
is incredibly inconsistent unless you
wanted a reality that was completely
fractured take this left side CSS and
this right side CSS these two pages are
exactly the same with only one
difference which is the overflow
attribute now the overflow attribute of
CSS does something really simple at
least how it's described if you have a
container and you have content inside of
the container the content overflows the
limits of the container you got a couple
options either the box will scroll it'll
clip it so you can't see it or the
content will just flow past it and it's
visible now if you notice that my
containers just have a content of a and
B so they're not the content isn't big
enough to trigger an overflow so you
should think according to CSS that well
you know these will render exactly the
same because the overflow actually ok
nope what overflow does is it
consequently changes the
the entire rendering layout engine it
affects how the actual boxes are
displayed on screen and this isn't just
like a chrome quirk this is like across
all browsers so CSS o miserable and I'm
glad we had CSS college because I did
learn some tricks like vertical
centering now yay so that puts us back
in the black box right what are we going
to do to answer to solve for these
problems so I decided okay if CSS and
HTML can't handle it I should actually
pick up the logic side of the equation
javascript i could probably fairly easy
create a javascript library tool in
order to create a uniform CSS that would
give me a consistent reality or at least
a consistent web page and so when I was
16 actually one is 18 I created Excel
sir an XL sir is a tool that using a
whole bunch of JavaScript using
turing-complete logic and I kinda want
to zoom out here and say that
programming for the most part is just
three things it's data it's manipulation
of that data and it is communication and
with inside of JavaScript you you know
those categories break down where we
have your primitives you have loops you
have if statements with these eight
basic primitives you can essentially
build everything you can build minecraft
and minecraft is turning complete and
inside minecraft you could implement a
JavaScript interpreter which then
interprets Ruby which interprets
JavaScript so on so these are the tools
that you want to use they are the lowest
level things that you can build anything
that you want on top of now with that I
was able to do something really cool CSS
and HTML I built this tool excel so as I
mentioned that allowed me to change the
background color that allow me to change
the margin the box shadow the border
radius you know all this stuff as I'm
interacting with it right inside of the
web browser so kind of my ultimate web
designer tool that's running in
the browser and gives me kind of I can
actually use the keyboard kind of like a
video game i can i can push on the
keyboard every individual CSS and HTML
property is bound to some key on the
keyboard so it's give me a really fast
way to not only prototype the HTML and
CSS and see it as I react with it but
more importantly is giving me that
instant feedback that I could then
iterate on top of and it's flexible
because I'm trying to just build it on
top of the already existing kind of CSS
HTML not do too many assumptions on top
keeping things flexible so naturally I
wanted to get that you know CSS HTML as
updating as I manipulating it I wanted
every single person that came to my
website to see that in real time okay so
I wanted all these changes to propagate
out toward to everybody those on the
website and in that sense I'm generating
a lot of data i'm generating a lot of
deltas okay and i needed to store that
data someplace and unfortunately you
know as i mentioned there's the data
manipulation communication manipulation
of communication in JavaScript it's a
little wonky but it does the job but the
data aspect okay there's not really
JavaScript database well okay now we
actually have a bunch of JavaScript
databases like that and a pretty much
quarter of the people I met first day
we're working on JavaScript database but
regardless of whether as JavaScript or
not we really had two ways to express
data which is in a table sequel or as a
tree a document based storage such as
MongoDB but I don't know about you night
data isn't really that cool it looks
more like this my data trying to kind of
Express reality is a bunch of
intricately interconnected just massive
blobs of messy junk I don't even know
exactly what it is but it's it's there
right so trying to express this in a
clean way and a table or in a tree it's
just kind of unrealistic so
just one aspect of the data side right
which is I needed it to be graph-based
to handle the complexity of intricately
related data I also needed it to be
distributed decentralized okay because
if I have two people that are editing
the same page collaborative landed on
the other side of the world or the you
know the network goes out I needed to be
able to still work so i started gun and
gun is a distributed javascript database
now as soon as you get into
decentralized stuff distributed stuff
you encounter what quote the experts of
database say is hard and complicated
concurrency control and paxos and master
slave replication and quorum and all
this stuff but i want to kind of d
thrown the experts and say if we spent
more time actually describing what's
happening and bringing more people into
the field and looking at the fresh kind
of perspective that they have on the
data and on the problems will be able to
make more progress than simply being
dismissive of a stuff and things get
difficult because of the problem of time
okay so other illustration let's go into
nonlinear time by raising hands in the
audience just very simple question who
would say that these two cars are
different yeah all right cool yeah that
ones blue ones read the different cars
right but if we reframe this from a time
perspective right we get something a
little bit interesting now that you've
seen this time series of mutable data
right where you have the car and my
stick figure comes along and paints it
to be blue how many of you guys would
now say that this car is different okay
good good very very good a lot of people
though however might think this car is
the same because as a consequence of
change over time it's still the original
car but this poses a problem that's
answered more by our purse up
okay and i don't mean perception in some
like hindu mysticism type way i mean it
in the sense of quantum mechanics right
when the photon comes from the car of
the red or blue car and it hits our
eyeball one of the atoms in our eyeball
you know reacts to that photon it goes
from the orbital state of let's say to
and it absorbs the photon and jumps up
to the orbital state of five whatever it
may be the Delta difference so
perception or observation is measurement
okay and when we measure something we're
fundamentally affecting or changing its
nature we are mutating it it is mutable
data so again as I stated right we have
the difference the quantifiable Delta
from the two orbital States now this
kind of gets interesting because I want
to talk about house plants you're
innocent docile cute little house plant
well I have some bad news it's actually
a man-in-the-middle attack your house
plant is actually a malicious pier in
your kind of network topology because
what is doing is this taking the the
source of the light right which is kind
of you could say bouncing it's not
really bouncing off the plant but the
plant is absorbing the information from
the light it is absorbing all the
spectrum of light and it's corrupting
the data it's filtering out all the data
except for green and then it's sending
its real aying back to you this color of
green so you receive it on your eyeballs
and you see that the plant is green in
reality or let's say metaphysics the
plant is everything but green because it
absorbed all the other energy levels
except for green greens only one that
sent back to you because it's trying to
kind of screw with your mind it screw
with your perception it is a
man-in-the-middle attack ok but this
leads to some interesting questions like
why we we like that plants are green now
are we going to suddenly ban all plants
from our network because all of our
house plants from our network because
you know it's doing this man in the
middle attack the very kind of struck
of the plant is how it is changing and
corrupting the data again it comes back
to the perceptual component however the
brain is doing something similar and I
can express this by an interesting
factoid you may may or may not know as
neurosurgeons have removed half of a
patient's brain okay and you think that
if you removed half of your brain you
would like die right or you know not be
able to walk or you'd lose your memories
or your your personality your psychology
would change but no we've found that if
you remove half of somebody's brain for
the most part if you do it appropriately
they survive and not only do they
survive but they have all their memories
still intact that's that's incredible
their personality doesn't change they
still have the memories so the brain
itself is working as a distributed
system and storing your memories
replicated across the graph of your
neurons so if only our database could do
this right somehow if we could have the
same sort of consistency and replication
that our brain does and if we lose one
server you know it's fault-tolerant you
know that's the whole point sharding etc
etc master-slave replication but I
actually want to reframe this again a
little bit more put it in the black box
and say this seems familiar all the
stuff now looks like well Adams right in
order to have this appropriately we have
to have idempotent data transformations
and that's fancy words but all really
means is that when I have the orbital
state change a mutation in state and
that gets emitted out to these other
atoms or maybe I should pseudo
scientifically say like let's let's look
at these things as servers right and so
as I submitted out replicated that that
photon that delta that quantifiable
change is then absorbed by these other
atoms and the electron goes from a lower
overall state to the higher orbital
state but what's interesting is that end
servers we want some sort of guarantee
of
the message being rebroadcast it okay so
each server let's say rebroadcast the
message that it gets separate from how
it processes the data and as a result
this guy down here let's just call him
Carl gets the message twice so it's
important that Carl D duplicates that
message that he doesn't process the
message in the same way and what's
exciting about this is we actually kind
of see this in light you might have
heard that light doesn't really act as a
particle it doesn't even really act as a
wave it acts more like probability a
photon can travel in any possible path
it can spin around do loops and come
back around to you and we actually kind
of see this with the the rebroadcast
innocence of our servers if we have
multiple servers interconnected with
each other there's multiple paths that
the information can take so to express
this in a more salient human perspective
let's say sadly that Carl's mother has
died okay but he doesn't know it Alice
knows it so Alice tries to contact carl
directly Carl picks up and Alice tells
him that his mother has died Carl reacts
quite strongly with emotional trial of
hearing that his mother has died but
let's rewind a little bit let's say
Alice was not able to communicate with
Carl directly so Alice kind of calls up
Bob and tells Bob the news hoping that
Bob may somehow get a connection to Carl
and then Bob relays the news to Carl and
remember Carl hasn't heard about this
yet so when Carl here's the news from
Bob he reacts strongly because this is
the first time you sort the news it's
it's a traumatic experience but now
let's rewind again ok Alice has heard of
the news and rather than doing one or
the other Alice does both ok and as a
result Carl is going to get the news of
his mother's death the trauma twice now
the important yet sad part of this is
that Carl's reaction is what's called
idempotent when he hears the news the
first time that's where he has the
reaction of trauma the second time here
is that of course it's sad but he
already knows the information right it
doesn't affect his state per se ok and
so
from that perspective is we can take any
multiple paths when we want to
communicate to a server or something and
the data will all resolve and and the
fastest path is going to be the
probabilistic one the one in which it
has the lowest latency the closest
connection so kind of this represents a
lot of my research with gun and I
actually have it's not just all theory
and metaphysics and stuff I actually
have this working and I would love to
have you guys all try it out in payments
tall I'm just getting started have an
MVP and I'm excited to announce i just
got funding this week so if anybody
wants to work on distributed javascript
systems for fun or for pay please let me
know but i want to go back to something
that I started with right which is we
have our mind and I want to end with
this which is our mind is perceiving the
world around us but how do we know that
that's real the metaphysics of it and as
I was studying these things I started to
go a little crazy because you know I'm
starting to hallucinate that there's
this computer in front of me that I'm
typing code in that I have this body on
me right and slowly as i realized that
data itself in the sense of the
replication the item potent
transformation of data is being
broadcasted is actually a way that i can
look at metaphysics right this the stand
right here a thousand years ago was not
in that locality it's not in that
position and so I should just be at a
you know wipe my hand through it but
well you know that didn't work but
that's because the stand and me share a
common state relative to each other and
that is kind of the transformation that
data through these atoms or through
these servers but I want to go a little
bit further and maybe propose something
a tad too side of pseudo-scientific
which is what if our minds themselves
our perception or operating that same
what if mental illnesses such as
schizophrenia or dissociative identity
disorder are simply a person who has a
conflict resolution algar
a synchronization algorithm a
replication log that doesn't work the
same way that we do so take a sketch of
inec he sees things that aren't actually
there he hears things that aren't
actually there but what if that's just
because in the same way where you had
the example of the Alice and the Bob and
the mother dying that kind of
replication log in his brain is simply
operating at a different synchronization
algorithm the rest of us so they're
perceiving a reality at a fundamentally
different state in the context compared
to what we are now that's probably
pushing a little bit too far but I'm
just jokingly suggest that maybe the
grand unifying theory of existence is
data replication data synchronization
and with that I'd like to end nothing is
sacred question all things and in that
process you will only learn a ton but
you might discover really interesting