whoo that's it come on come on all right
test oh that's loud welcome everybody my
name is Justin Meyer and today I'm going
to talk about done Jas which is new
JavaScript framework we built be going
over why we built it and what I think it
does really well and why you might want
to leave here right now abandon all your
angular and react apps and start
building done Jas if you don't feel that
way please talk to me afterwards I'm
really wanting to learn how to I really
believe in the product I hopefully will
convince you to too but if not come talk
to me because I want to argue it out so
a few things because I've given this
talk once before some fa cues that
everybody has in the back of their mind
the whole time I'm talking it's a
JavaScript framework it's open source
it's really for the front end the it's
back in agnostic so you can write you
can use it on top of your Python Ruby on
Rails application it's built on these
technologies it does have used node to
do things like server-side rendering and
and it's build system but like again you
can use it on anything you want it
supports ie8 works on every you know
major operating system we're just about
we've got a the pre version 6 has note
for note 3 support which should be
product production ready in about two
weeks and it's not a new framework we
recycle so this is part of the
JavaScript MVC anybody heard of
JavaScript MVC here you a few people
good so this is the rebirth of
JavaScript MVC so I work from a Toby
we're a JavaScript consulting company
and we built some of the biggest
high-profile ecommerce sites there are
not the biggest butt
whew in in the top 10 and even using our
own technology we would constantly find
how much other stuff had to be done to
build like these big powerful
sophisticated client apps um a list of a
lot of the things here um and it was so
much beyond what JavaScript MVC did and
we wanted to make it possible for
everybody to do everything to build that
modern web app that can compete in you
know today's JavaScript world so we
added a bunch of things and kind of
totally rewrote JavaScript MVC to
include things like real-time data
caching these are the ones I'm gonna
talk about today it includes all of
these but the one's going to focus on
today or how it does real-time data
caching progressive loading with CBN
deploys server-side rendering think and
hot and show off its hot module swapping
um and to do it I'm going to show
building a the hello world of real-time
applications a real-time chat
application and before I start building
this I think it's quickly it's useful to
quickly talk about the performance
features of done j/s and how important
they are when you're building a single
page application because when people
traditionally build a single page
application they build it like this it's
a skeleton HTML page that they just send
back to the user that downloads all the
JavaScript and once the javascript is is
there it makes a jest request to get the
data and it finally draws the view to
present that to the user how many people
have built a single page application
like that yeah we've we've all done it
right the reasons why we do that is
because building apps this way is
awesome you your front-end team doesn't
have to really talk to the backend team
there's a lot of good good
maintainability advantages but there's a
lot of performance problems so i'm going
to quickly break them down the big
problem with this is yes you when the
user goes to the page it's going to send
back that
HTML skeleton and then if you're lucky
you'll see a loading screen maybe a
little bit more as the just CSS and the
JavaScript down download for the page
now a big problem is that a lot of
people don't aren't doing or what what's
wrong at first when they're building
application is their site is downloading
too much JavaScript and CSS to slowly
but it's too much javascript because in
a single page application a lot of
people will bundle their entire app into
one big JavaScript and CSS file and then
it's too slow because they're not using
a CDN to distribute their files to make
downloading more local and therefore
faster and then once JavaScript and CSS
have loaded well now you need to get the
data for your page so you still might
see spinners while the page is loading
data and then finally the data comes
back and you render the page now what we
want and hopefully everybody here wants
is a much faster user experience where
the user sees right away what they want
to look at and then eventually and then
shortly after the page becomes
interactive and this is how done j/s
works it works by when the user goes to
the page it packages up it totally
server-side renders the single page
application sends that back but also is
able to identify what data that page is
loading and will package that up with
the page response so that when
javascript and CSS download fast and
just the right amount when javascript
becomes alive it'll say okay i'm going
to start making my ajax request but
we'll trap that and use the data that
was sent back with the initial page
response so the result of this is a much
much better user experience and I think
everybody is talk forever about how
performance is one of those things that
just drives you know makes users very
happy so that was a big part of the goal
for done Jas and with that i'm going to
show how to actually build that real
time application so the app is actually
two pages it's a home page that has just
this little
idiot and a link to the chat page and
the chat page just lists messages allows
people to create it and works real time
so this is going to show off a subset of
dung jss features and I think it's going
to show off a lot like some of the most
important and unique features which are
the ones under lined up here the steps
to build the application we're going to
set up the app we're going just kind of
set up a new done jas application i'm
going to add bootstrap and just show off
that hot module swapping is working and
server-side rendered i'm going to add
routing that routes between two
different pages and then i'll finish the
actual message isn't home page ad real
time to the messages page and then i'll
build and deploy it to a CDN and then
launch it so step one setting up a
dungeon hopefully you all can read that
but it's really easy it's the standard
way of installing every CLI ever which
is npm install done j/s once you do that
I'm going to create a project what's my
video runs ok so I'm going to create a
folder and then I'm just going to run I
can actually can't see the video here
but I can't up there I'm gonna run done
Jason it and this is just the standard
yeoman generator that will ask me a few
questions about my project install all
of its dependencies so here i'ma call it
Dungey has chat say I want all my main
source files in that source folder and
everything else is just the standard
fare it generated this file structure so
once and installed the dependencies
which takes a while there's a lot of
dependencies and this is actually like
double time so I don't have a very fast
internet connection alright so once all
the dependencies are installed it
creates a development server that hosts
the static files sets up server-side
rendering does little hot module
swapping pretty much everything you know
you want in an application its bundle so
I'm setting it up I'm starting the
development server and I'm going to go
to and it just sets up the very basic
hello world so with the hello world i'm
going to add bootstrap and then i'll
show that hot module swapping and
server-side rendering or working so to
add bootstrap to this page is actually
very simple so dont je s comes with
steel je s which is kind of like web
pack if you've used that dependency
management solution it you can load
modules in any format from NPM oh and
also sorry one thing I forgot to mention
our index that's ash here this is the
template that the page is rendered with
so the server-side rendering renders
this it's also sent to the client but
here I'll just show up live reload
working so I forgot them doing that
first so this is actually hot module
swapping but you can see me just
changing it updates the page without
having a refresh or anything and now I'm
going to install bootstrap and you'll
notice those can imports that will
become important in a second
oh so like I said steel can and done Jes
using steel can load pretty much
anything from anywhere including from
nvm so I just have to install bootstrap
into my dungeons project and save it to
its package that Jason and then I can
use those can imports which are kind of
like HTML imports but can import modules
with any JavaScript or CSS any kind of
module so I'm just going to add a can
import for bootstrap and bootstraps less
file
and then I'm going to change the HTML at
the right here to actually use bootstrap
to say hello world and when I save this
you'll see the page automatically update
to a hello world that uses bootstrap
sponsored yeah yay live reload so once
I've done that now I'm going to show off
server-side rendering so I'm just going
to open up the devtools show the page
response and just kind of prove that
this template is actually being
server-side render that's being sent
back so if we scroll the bottom now you
can see that hello world now I can talk
for hours about how good our server side
rendering solution is I highly encourage
people to look it up on Sanjay's calm
but it solves like every conceivable
problem of you know if you're loading
styles and it was to move those that up
at the top so there's no flash of
unstyled content it knows how to wait
for all your Ajax requests to finish
before rendering the entire page if
there's any set time outs we can track
those and it's pretty nifty solution I
say so myself and I am biased okay so
next step I'm going to add routing so in
the dungeon different pages are
represented by custom elements so I'm
going to have a chat home custom element
that represents the home page and a chat
messages custom element that represents
the messages page and I'm going to route
between these two so the first one I'm
going to build is the home I need to
build a home custom element and what to
do this with done j/s there's two ways
of creating custom elements Beaufort
custom elements are built as components
but there's two ways of building
components one is for very lightweight
components which are in done in these
opponent files that look very much like
a web component file so that's the first
one to create I'm gonna create our home
page as a single home component module
and I just ran the generator to do that
and you can see what it made here so
this is kind of a self-contained
description of a custom element it has
you know the name the tag name it has
styles for this custom element and as a
template that gets rendered inside this
custom element it has a view model that
controls the behavior of this custom
element and this doesn't need a
viewmodel so I'm going to get rid of it
all it really needs to do is show a
image that says done j/s chat and then a
link from this page to the chat messages
page so here I'm just creating that link
or the image
and now i'm going to create the link so
rowdy works a little different in in
done Jas versus other frameworks it's
two-way routing rules so what you say is
I want a URL that will set the page
property of the applications view model
to chat so this will figure out the best
routing rule for studying that state of
the application and will actually write
a / chat in this case so that's how you
create a it's all state-based you set
your which is what the state you want
and it will figure out what the URL
needs to look like and I'm just gonna
add some style just so things look right
so this is our home page and now i'm
going to create the chat messages page
i'm just going to I'm going to create a
dummy one so we can switch back and
forth between two pages so this I'm
going to add a component where every
single like its styles its template
everything split out into its own file
that's how we generally develop stuff we
call it the mod lit a folder structure
and on a file structure how we organize
things so we have a folder with
everything inside of it so this
generated the tests documentation
everything start like starter everything
for what a module should be so in this
case I'm just going to change the
template for my custom element to have a
link back to the homepage eventually I'm
going to come and make it lists all the
messages
so here I just want the state when
someone clicks on this link of the
applications view model to be page home
we're going to use this in a second to
switch between these two different
custom elements now one final thing I
want to do is make a pretty routing rule
that I talked about so this is how i
create those pretty routing rules that
map a certain state to a certain URL so
i want to say if the URL ever looks like
/ word that's the page and i want a
default page value of home
so with that when I want to check the
applications view models page state at
page property and if it's i think i'm
going to do if it's chat so if the page
property is chat what i want to do is
progressively load the chat module so
i'm going to use a can import and this
is to me the coolest stuff that done Jas
does or nobody else does this i can say
i want to progressively import that chat
messages module and inside that custom
element it's rendered with the promise
of that module loading so i can check
all that module is being progressively
loaded i want to write to the user
loading and then once it's resolved once
we actually have that module in the page
i want to write i can actually use the
chat custom element i can put it in the
page so i'll close the tag and i'm going
to do something very gonna assume if the
page for this app isn't chat it's going
to be the home page and i'm just gonna
kind of copy and paste this code
one really cool thing about done j/s is
that it's build system actually picks up
on these and we'll build individual
modules for every single different page
because it can actually see these and
identify oh I need to build a separate
bundle for messages in a separate bundle
for everything home component loads so
with that now I can go back and forth
between these two pages and it's
progressive loading just what's needed
when it's needed so now I'm going to
finish the messages page so we can
actually create messages so this is what
we want to be able to type a message and
actually get it foot in the page oh
sorry I should have to replay that sorry
forgot the vid it's not letting me
unfortunately control the video in here
I'm not sure why maybe because it's
screen sharing so the way to do this is
you create a model with what we call
super model because done Jessa's models
andale real time automatically they
handle have a fall through cash that
hits local storage which is really cool
technique if you've never used it but
I'm not gonna have time to go into it
today is I'm going to generate a super
message supermodel and I'm going to save
the I have a restful end point I wanted
to connect to and give it the unique ID
of the data type and I'll generate some
tests and the fixture so we can simulate
without a service if we didn't have one
but we do have one and it generates a
file like this can j has kind of split
its model logic into the connection part
and actually the type definition so
that's why there's a type definition on
top and a connection below where we
connect that data type to a to a URL and
finally see this tag this custom tag
message model that's actually make a
custom element called message model that
we can
choose to retrieve data so I'm going to
actually use that custom element to get
a list of all messages on the server
first to do that I'd actually need to
import that module into my template
again we can't import so i'll use that
message model custom element that's
using our supermodel behind the scenes
to get a list of all data and that class
is there just for bootstrap make sure
everything looks nice for bootstrap and
the content of this element is rendered
with a promise that represents the data
that's being resolved and I could do
that is pending is resolved is rejected
but I'm not instead I'm just once the
value there is a value that's resolved
I'm gonna go through every item and i'm
just going to list each message so each
message has a name and a body so I'm
just listing each name body and then if
there are no messages i'm just going to
do an else case and say there no
messages so with this that's everything
we needed to actually be able to list
messages from the server which is cool
no javascript is HTML that we had a
right so the next thing i want to make
the form actually able to create
messages so i'm gonna create a form with
a three in two inputs one for the name
one for the body and one for a submit
button and i'm just going to add all the
bootstrap stuff around it so make sure
bootstrap lines up everything nicely and
I'm going to two-way bind my inputs
value to my view model which we'll see
in a second view model of this templates
its name property so this is what to a
bindings look like in done Jes and if
you if you hate to a bindings because
you're a big fan of react you can not do
it with two-way bindings you can do the
exact same kind of architectural stuff
if you want to waste your time so here's
the here's the two-way binding for the
input binding to the body and here's a
submit button and the final thing I need
is that when we actually submit the form
i need to call a method on my view model
so i'm going to call this how you listen
to events on submit you want to call
send with the event so that we can
prevent the foul tip so this is what my
view model looks like and my component
which kind of connects the view model to
the template and i'm just going to
create that send message and this isn't
raining es6 so the first thing I'm gonna
do is prevent default then what my form
submitted and then i'm going to import
my my supermodel my message is model
so that I can use that to actually
create data and persist it to the
restful service so here I just create a
new message and I'll create a message
with a name and body that come from the
view model but read things from the new
model use just I happen and then I'll
save this to the server and then when
the server has successfully responded i
will i'll just update the body remove
the text of the body so the user can
enter another message
and with that you can create messages so
a really good observer would be very
surprised by what just happened right
there somehow with no code that new
message got put into the list of
messages how I didn't write any code
that did that well it's with set logic
and I might have time to explain it i
don't think i will actually um so i'm
gonna show it i do real time real quick
which is really easy so to do real time
you set logic to kind of automatically
manage the list that you've loaded and
know how to add things and remove them
but it's really easy to integrate with
i'm gonna install steel socket i/o but
it's really just socket i/o with a
rapper that makes it not run when you're
doing server-side rendering you can use
the normal socket i/o you just have to
make sure you have ifs to make sure
don't do this on when you're running all
this code on the server but if you don't
want to do that you could just use steel
socket i/o and all you have to do is
especially if you forevers here on the
last talk you know that like there can
be a lot of different ways to update a
client cool thing about done Jes is it
doesn't matter how what mechanism you're
using to actually update the client
socket i/o anything as long as you can
call the connect message connection and
tell it when something is updated
deleted or created we will update all
the lists for you automatically so
that's what I'm doing he right here I've
created my socket connection I'm
listening on when it's messages are
created and I'm just calling message
connection create instance with raw data
and the system handles everything else
so when message is created i'm going to
create messages are updated i'm an
update and when messages are removed i'm
at all destroy instance and i can open
up to browser windows and have them chat
I'll just going to skip this just take
well it'll show it but I so want you to
talk about everything
work school so this works with real-time
behavior I don't have time to really go
into it but the short answer is
essentially we store only when necessary
we know what parameters were used to
request data and we know and we can look
at when new data comes in or is
destroyed and we can see which lists it
belongs to based on the parameters used
to retrieve those lists it's pretty I
think innovative way of getting real
time for free don't have time to really
show how it works right now so next I'm
going to finish the homepage and I'm
actually going to skip that too because
of time which I just going to add a chat
widget to but not important now I'm
going to show how to build this actually
so when done j/s apps okay I'm actually
to skip the build just done GS is able
to do this thing where it figures out
your dependencies and or your which
pages are loading like I already talked
about and build highly optimized bundles
for each page now some people might be
thinking like web pack already does this
it doesn't do what this does we're able
to like balance caching versus
dependency or number of scripts that
have to load with this cool waste
function but another talk for another
day let's say we got our build to work
which is one step just done JS build you
want to push that to a CDN don't chase
makes this really easy i'm going to use
firebase as an example if you sign up
for firebase
you can create a new firebase account
and in a container for your application
so this is solving me your code
downloading your coat you want to
download your code faster you want your
users to download code from a CDN this
is how easy it is with done j/s create a
new container on firebase and then all
you have to do is specify the Dungey has
to get the fill out the Dungey has
deployed configuration
so this is what the configuration for
firebase looks like it's kind of not
something you could come up with on your
own but they're documented so I just
give the name of my app and then there's
one other piece of configuration you
have to change which is when you're
doing server-side rendering you need to
make sure that all the JavaScript of the
script tags instead of pointing like
from localhost or whatever whatever the
current server is they need a point at
Heroku so you give you change the base
URL for when you're in that one mode so
this is one nice feature done jess's how
it helps manage you through like
development to production life cycles
and with that you just run your build
and this is that high performance build
where it kind of figures out every page
and try some bundle things perfectly so
you just downloading what you need but
not a million scripts and then I ran the
Dungey has deploy and that just pushed
everything to firebase I can start my
done GS server in development first our
introduction and Rhys load my page and
now we get nine combined CSS image and
script requests and you can see they're
all loading from firebase cool ok so at
this point we have that very fast app
that server-side rendered has hot model
swapping all the cool stuff something to
be very proud of but there's two other
things done j/s does it can build to iOS
and Android and build to desktop so I'm
going to show that off real quick and
then I'm done so to build to iOS to take
this application and build at iOS I'm
going to install the iOS simulator so
you guys can actually see it work
and this is using cordova and then i'm
going to run npm ad chord on Jas ad
cordova so this will just add cordova
but it'll also rewrite the build script
so it knows how to bundle up all those
JavaScript files and put them in a
Cordova applications and I'll ask you
some questions at cordova once so we
want to build for iOS because i'm on a
mac you can build to any of the other
platforms provide you have the right
computer
and then you just run Dungey as build
and it changed the build script so if
you write Dungey has build Cordova it
will build your whatever Cordova you
configured to build so it's going to run
the build again and then ship that off
to Cordova and actually launch the
simulator so you can see it running cool
I'm going to skip over showing the two
things chatting because now i just want
to show desktop and why did it too fast
desktop is even easier i'm going to i'm
using n wjs to build a desktop app so
I'm going to add done GS add NW this
will rewrite the build script again
install some of NWS dependencies again
all this stuff works on linux mac and
windows a lot of testing there so the
only thing you have to be wary of with
NW is not all of their versions support
every version of mac and like two ppl
actually build a mac app so that's why i
put in 0 1 2 3 because their latest
version doesn't actually support
building come back at least not at the
time where i'm in this video which is
like two weeks ago so i wrote the
platform's i want to support in the
height of our application and now having
done that I just run done j/s build and
W then NW is really cool that it only
the first time you run it it downloads a
lot of its dependencies which is really
nice so if you're not having to not
everybody on your team who's not built
if they're not building NW app they
don't have to like install it when
they're just trying to work on some the
jet with a web part
so then I'm just going to made those
builds those executables I'm going to
open them and I get my desktop app and
then I can pull up the web app and the
iOS app and then I can have them all
chatting together
one big steps up to one big Capitan
so we have enough so part of the reason
why we built like I said built on jess's
like I wanted an application like a one
of the framework we could take you
through everything that you needed to do
so we have a more comprehensive guide
that actually walks through setting up
tests documentation like continuous
integration continuous deploys really
good to look at for more information
there's so much in done Jes that I could
spend hours on it but it's all actually
pretty well documented the features and
why they're important you can go to the
website I'm doing like free trainings
all across the u.s. that's it thank you