you
so this is 40 to the project when I came
here with like oh my god and he's going
to fill it with babes some super happy
to win this estate so as anjali say I'm
to happen at least say I'm working I'm
not syllabi day so I'm an absent genere
make-ups help people make apps but by
night I'm super solid so that's when I
get to make noises and like blue of my
neighbors so what we're going to see
today is first I'll just give you a
little bit of background so you know
where I came from then I'll see what I
build and then I'm going to blow up your
minds or your ears do you never know so
you know when you go in a plane and you
hit brace brace and the save you hit
brace brace discoveries so if you hear
that run because it's like it's growing
up and it's going to die materials so as
you might have understood I love music
and one of the first gifts i got when i
was a child was have blue vinyl like we
i thought i was like something like this
tall and i just couldn't stop listening
to that it was like one of those
horrible child bands he was like but i
just couldn't stop me so I was like can
I listen to die again and they were like
oh it was a turntable you couldn't just
put it in a loop like an itunes you had
to go put the needle back so it was like
this tall and the turntables here so it
was like trying to return it was like my
early Charlie and then the eighties were
good times so we had tea selector poop
maybe video games and Casio keyboard
amazing so this was mine it was like six
knots polyphony six or eight instruments
and serious it was like kind of limited
and from recording you had to record to
a tape which was an ideal but he was
fine and the 90s came about that man was
multimedia which was like oh my god see
the wrong players and stuff and truckers
and then you've heard about truckers
it's like a sample-based music program
so I could do lots of music and I got
into the demoscene as well which is like
graphics bit cubes everything all at the
same time and
Vijay which is like the same but with
realtor and I got who to go to live gigs
and I got someone to play some visuals
where I was playing music which was
pretty exciting but it's hard to connect
with people especially if your friends
live in another country like I like it
was this case um so I got like
introverted and got to software
synthesis and I start to building my own
since I self with C and C++ and I met
wait when instruments which is like a
technology so you can have synthesizers
with cubase or any other kind of so
we're probably that is that is hard to
distribute because can pilot part of the
SDK is proprietary so you can't
redistribute that and instructions for
building that are really confusing
because you had to say well this this
part you can use it but then you had to
go to cubase download something that I
can distribute because it's closer so it
was hard to get it to work for more
people than me even though some people
distributed that in line of
distributions which is pretty amazing
like it's so Harvard still people maybe
effort so that was exciting and then
he's like I yeah this is my time any God
wave Aldean shake yes well absolutely
and now she is and I could be a
one-woman westridge like I don't need
anyone else I can do everything myself
so I wanted all in below output and old
harbour input and I could do everything
with nodejs so I got this thing it's a
cuny harbor controller which is for
hackers um it's good pressure sensitive
part with le lives you can't really say
that because it's really right but there
are ladies here and it's a small oops um
the nice thing is that it uses GDP
either you've heard about GDP but it's
like a obviously you're fair about d I
mean obviously Oh opens how control it's
like a protocol you can use for
connecting between different instruments
and controllers everything it's like
maybe but modern like the will be big
brother of of midi so this thing comes
with something called oh you see Bree
which converts your USB data into
something that Oh any other internet
award program like nose candy chest um
so with a knife module that someone
already have made I could just read
whatever these things sends me and I can
also send things to that so for example
if I fabrice here it's just listening
the touch events i'm sending some just
getting messages here and then i can
also send messages here so i can control
the colors that you can't really see
again because it's very bright and then
that's for the input but what do we do
in in the browser because we want to
make it sound so so can you that's
evident um and then the way this works
is with open side control you kind of
subscribe to addresses it's like silence
it's like like URLs you can match things
with Richard recruit regular expressions
like these things so for example when I
press about I get sent a message with
data structure and again say I'm
interested only in present parts I'm
just describing to that I'm filtering
everything else and with socket i/o I'm
sending everything through from UDP to
this thing to the browser and just
listen to whatever i'm interested in and
then i can send messages again you can
see that but each part has like four
leds and i can control the red and the
green values so again i can turn the
whole thing red hold clean green or
somewhere in between and then that's for
the pub obviously had to do something
that might sound so previously i used to
build my old thing like total ignoring
all the opposition's using the script
notes I was like everything like it was
like if it was a still c++ but then i
thought that could do this with proper
web audio using only api from the audio
and make it very modular like i can
include one things and the other and
reuse as much as possible so the problem
with that is that the
very very native where all your stuff is
very very native and it's very very
limited so you had to write lots of
rubbers and for example the oscillators
when whatever our bow is just stops
playing it just disappears into the user
so you need to make something so that
you can detect okay this node has
finished you need to regenerate that so
you need to go making lots of little
things like that they are not very
difficult but they are not as intuitive
and they seem to be finding people by
surprise a lot and another thing that I
think it's interesting is I made a
little envelope I don't know if you know
about the envelopes it's basically if
you got an instrument and you pay always
in the same volume it's boring it's like
you need to give a little for expression
the way of doing that is having volume
changes so you can do love with
envelopes and develop is basically
attack decay sustain release so I build
that which kind of automates the way you
can change parameters we will audio
which is something like setvalue time
set parameter time that's given motor
blood all the time so you just automate
that with a class so that was for the
basic things but sometimes there were
times I didn't have enough things like
for example I wanted to multiply the
output of two nodes but I don't think
there's anything we roll it up that's it
so you can just shame it with a custom
node which is pretty good and obviously
you want to change things I'm a degree
and this is this is using this is
attached to whatever I created so it's
based on web component I don't know
about that thing so if it's very low
it's fine if it's not exactly shame
everything away and I just don't worry
about that so the way worse i create
instances with that and then i attach
them to real virtual instruments I
creative because has even faced whether
i do in the degree just reflect on the
instruments so i could be changed
the relief time and he should be
changing so it's longer release or sure
do so and if you change that
programmatically it would changes as
well but and I'm not going to life
program here so the first thing I wrote
was the bajo drone which is a funny Kim
howarth with the Spanish and English so
it's like based on and some more funny
multi voice in you unisonic bus lane so
it makes that it only plays one note
multi voices because it's got more than
one see later and unisonic is because
there are playing in different octaves
and its baseline so this is that and
then it made the coach inator which is
like it's like a pup pad a tour because
Colton in Spanish is a pub I just like
to make funny names for things so bill I
accepted her will likely you something
so i just took instances of the previous
instrument i put them inside these
things I've got like multi polyphonic
instrument just with the previous one
for this I had to create what they call
a voice allocation unit so you can
decide ok I've got three voices and
you're sending me four notes so the
first one is out so you need to
implement some sort of criteria for
building this thing and then it is porum
poem which is like drum machine because
prom poem in spanish is a way to kind of
represent the sound of a drum from pump
so it's just playing samples it's like
an 808 or 909 something like this and
then river I don't even know how to
process riverfront is I'm an impulse buy
uber model which I included off inside
the culture later because it what is
this thing you can see here actually the
the way for the river patrol is inside
the way for the other thing everything's
inside like the matrix or inception or
something so you can i'm using web audio
rebirth things so it's using samples for
representing how the reverb
be behaving it not sure it seemed very
well well basically they go to our room
my name to rule and put some mics
somewhere and they'd record and that's
what I'm because I'm that's one using
that's how they trigger the way they
sound reacts to different environments
so the nice thing is I'm whenever the
new bar is loaded I just load it and
draw it with canvas it's pretty amazing
I'm just throwing an OGG file here it's
like yeah I love this thing um so yeah
just back to the other thing um and
obviously you need something because
otherwise I can't be a one-woman
orchestra so I made something to go with
the music and that's of course where
jail by three hjs and the thing is that
I think this is something that many
people find confusing how do you render
many times of using only one renderer
it's very easy actually um I spent later
and i'm not going to complicate it with
these things because another 3d artist I
just made some cubes and stuff they look
kind of simple and minimal so that
should be fine so yeah the trick it's a
very simple trick you create the render
like this you say please don't delete
whatever when you're done and then don't
auto clear and then you want your render
you say it when there are clear ones and
then repeat primary for it's a scene you
want to render that should we do you
don't need anything else that's it and
for playing life obviously you can't be
doing everything at the same time so I I
don't know give her about renoise has
anyone used green ice or any trucker
ever now I can believe that okay so
basically now she's like a moderate
tracker and it's like any other
sequencer you basically prepare a song
with this thing um it's a tracker in the
future I will likely have my own web
editor but that would be like maybe 10
years sign when I
time enough for that so in the meantime
I just made the song with a newer
software like I'm not reinventing this
wheel this time so the good thing about
this editor is that the song for
Mattie's XML so but I don't want to use
XML so I sporty to Jason and there
wasn't any model for that so I made a no
they are not module for this and the
thing about tracker consider every like
way more than reason or qas or anything
is that it's got these concepts of
utterance tracks and roll and some
people say that it's like Excel because
it's like one page of data and its
numbers that's how you sequence that
it's very hard like so because it's like
pages of things and yes I place this
page in this order and pay this page
again and paste so it's like very easy
to know what's playing and when and
which row it is and everything so you
can make very recently with that and so
once you've got the orderlies which is
like this page and this page on this
page on this page you just what I'm
doing is I'm just creating a list of
events so i can know what to do when i
play life and this is kind of sabine
circuit like not own the node number
timestamp and then the order pattern
room does the thing that you can get
from the trackers and then instrument
volume less obvious so this is we show
you don't know what's playing and why do
you want to keep the order pattern on
the road because imagine you're playing
any sort of song and you want to keep
track of which bar door and so you can
make interesting tips with that so
that's why and you need to solve a time
stone axe ascending timestamp because
you need to schedule a all the events at
precise time so we say you're not going
to be trialled in india right at the
time because it's going to like mel your
browser so you want to make it like
prepared as much as possible before you
start doing the heavy thing so you
schedule everything a precise times but
the progress we've all the events that
you can't cancel them so you can just
prepare everything and send everything
to browser because if you
stop it or post it it's going to keep
playing you don't want to do that so
what you need to do is request audition
frame this is something I made up maybe
it's not the best thing but it kind of
works so well it does is periodically it
goes and looks at the list of events and
say okay so this buffer is this length
what can I fit in here okay so i'm just
going to dispatch things like play this
note and stop this thing and launch this
envelope and that kind of thing but the
promise that sometimes it can be off but
you need to be aware of what's going I
mean most of the people don't really
notice but again people don't even
notice one picture from pix elated and
say that it might be just curious like
me but is there and how do you make the
most of no data so the tracker gives me
this c4 things and you can convert into
me the node numbers and then because
it's numbers you can use maths which is
pretty ways amazing with music so for
example with maths you can say this note
for getting the higher take you just up
12 to the number so you can do this kind
of funny things like building chords or
our pages which is like Brewer and it's
all done with numbers so you just use
the note okay you complain things but
not the same thing and yeah why bother
wasn't residence the in Serge's like I
could just hope this thing to the output
and that should be enough but the
promise that for examples I've got a
bass drum like with you like and then
I've got a base and they both play in
the same frequency is hard for the
insert to say this is this is the drum
or this is the base so they can retail
so that way you still have you can still
have their 50 you want but you can also
know what's actually playing and which
node is it actually playing so that's
why I splain um yeah if you just answer
you need to deal with thresholds dark
indicate
and you know it's very different than he
can change from Santa song so it's not
true for all the songs so good chess
careful be very careful this is why I
warned you like sometimes these clips I
hope it doesn't but the first thing I
made they were I was like adding many
voices at the same time he was like I
just had to take my headphones off it
was like killing my ears so you need to
be very very aware of possibilities of
clipping so the solution for days that
you have limiters and compressors as
much as you can origin8 so that nothing
can go over 1 or minus 1 and the other
promise that it can break because it's
changing the I mean we've all the things
changing a lot especially for example
with nightly every day there are new
things happening changing improving up
until two days ago this was leaking like
heavily and you could close chrome he
was still playing and really why is it
playing there's nothing here yes close
the window but the window was a cinder
somewhere I don't know where but it was
there it didn't even show you an
activity monitor I don't know we're but
I guess it's part of the fun we are here
for having fun and breaking things and
joy in that so right ok good so let's
see if it breaks yeah remember about
this thing
you
right
ok
I'm sorry
I think we're done right yeah awesome
can we get a round of applause awesome
to have a presentation that is worthy of
this set I feel like I'm a Eurovision do
we have any questions you have to raise
your hands we have a weave angeline on
Mike back there so even if you're back
there it's totally cool yes hi um so you
were playing like something with one
hand and and changing the settings with
the other yeah right would it be
possible to connect some kind of
controller so that you don't have to use
your mouse yeah I just need time ok
sorry theory you've got this thing where
you can have I mean this is like the
whole point of the sliders but I i
wanted to map it like instead of
pressing the mouse I could map this
thing but time I thought that was very