i well we have a confession to make
where hackers for thieves for criminals
we've been stealing code for years in
order to protect our identity I'm sorry
Todd but I'm sorry but this is way too
hot well I said we have to protect I
mean it's crazy hard to say it and
forget it she Minds fine we have to
protect our identity did yours itchy no
oh can we trade no oh well can I take
mine off no we have to sector identities
but I'm sorry I gotta take this off it's
killing me is a lot better now everybody
knows who we are then we steal code well
so everybody does it no no they don't
otherwise everybody in this room
everybody in our community we'd all be
wearing masks oh yeah they kind of do
steal code github isn't stealing code of
course it is you browse into somebody's
code you look at how they did it then
maybe you take it and write it yourself
or worse yet you cut and paste it well
sure but well how about this I bet every
single person in this room has gotten to
this site copied some snippet of code
and paste it into your project that's
not stealing code it's the entire point
of stack overflow really because they're
copyright policy specifically says they
own everything oh except not every site
is stack overflow how about jeaious bins
policy if you put it out there it's free
to use I see remedy in the back he's the
one that created it
yeah it's open tools like these that
make it possible for sharing so sure
jazz Ben is super awesome we're all
thankful for it but the majority of
other sites out there so you're saying
we're all criminals not just that but
we've been doing it for years that's
that's some serious traffic was it 19
billion global views in six years a lot
of stealing that's it's years and years
of stealing sure people we know people
in this very room admitted to stealing
code even some of the speakers you're
going to hear this weekend like Rachel
and Remy and Pam even one of the
founders of NPM admit to stealing code
we've all been stealing code for years
decades even really decades sure before
get up there was sourceforge all right
right I before that we would go into the
forums right you guys remember digging
through all the PHP forums just to
figure out how to write a blog well sure
except picked yeah PHP completely sucks
come on man so what were you doing
before you troll the forums um well i
first learned java script using view
source in the 90s all right view source
let's that's great what was the last
time you needed that I mean browser dev
tools today are amazing well even before
that we had all these these magazines
with code in them right so you would
open the magazine sit down and then like
type the code from the magazine into
your computer but that's that's not
stealing oh I was just using those
magazines to figure out how how to do it
well it still sounds fundamentally like
a cut-and-paste job well how did you
start programming well I started on one
of these sweet Commodore pets
but how did you start programming it
well I just leaned over to the kid next
to me and asked him what up today and he
showed you what well he showed me his
coat and you copied it well we didn't
have cut and paste back then but you
typed it in well yeah he told me what
the time thus you stole his code but
what did you do next well I started
changing things I started trying things
out you made it your own exactly instead
of an asterisk chasing a pound side I
made it chase a dog so you took his idea
and you subverted it in your own manner
well but does it be active changing
something make it mine and not his like
I guess I I don't think you could
copyright an idea after all you just
copy write the expression of the idea so
you're telling me we're not criminals I
think so you're suggesting that the act
of changing what we steal makes it legit
well I think it's a little more
complicated than that you know while
you're though well but what about the
what about the fair use clause well what
about when your client comes to you and
they say they want a parallax site and
you've never even heard what a parallax
site is does the research aspect come
into play when you cut and paste from
stack overflow well again I'm not a
lawyer no no you're not but I do think
there's a good kind of code stealing
good stealing sure otherwise all these
people are in a lot of trouble so how do
you know what is good stealing and what
is bad stealing oh I think it comes down
to intent intent sure why are you
stealing the code is it to take money
away from the copyright owner or are you
just trying to finish the customer's
request so you can go home to your wife
and kids or are you just trying to learn
how to do it for yourself so you think
it's okay if our intent is to learn
right it has to be again otherwise the
whole industry is in trouble how's that
well think back to your days using view
source copying the code
code that you saw there well I didn't
copy it per se of course you did but you
changed it right well yeah I wanted to
see how it worked and then you change
this some more sure and so on your
learning through the change yeah that's
how I work right well that's my point we
have an entire industry of canker it's
baked into what we do okay I see we
steal the code to learn and then we
learn by tinkering right well my
daughter does the exact same thing
really watch this she's pretty cute this
is true but my point is that she's
learning by exploring she's trying new
things she's gaining experienced or
experimentation or as they say in this
slide here the bottom two lines the
practice by doing and immediate use
right actually when you think about it
it's the primary way that people learned
we replicate we change we observe and
then we understand the except when we
fail no well failing as part of the
process well fail often fail fast and
learn always the goal of experimentation
whether successful or not is
understanding so I steal code but in a
good way to experiment on it and
ultimately gain new understanding and
then build on that build on that sure
once you understand something you can
use it to understand the next thing up
the chain the bigger understanding but
if that's how we learn why did I spend
all those years or more importantly all
that money doing this okay you bring up
a great point me I did the other
approach is rote learning where the
understanding is dictated to you and
you're supposed to accept it as fact
well but again as we see here the
retention rate from lecture based
learning is really really low well
exactly there's no chance to explore
what you learned
it's all memorization but you're working
from the top down lectures reading
presentations there isn't a chance to do
anything right it's a different tactic
they give you the understanding and then
they let you figure out how to prove it
but the stealing way you're figuring out
how something works and then you can't
understanding yes so that's great news
because school sucks okay I'm not saying
that there's a place for both well
except the bottom-up approach is more
how we work we've already admitted to
all these people that were stealing code
and tinkering on it well maybe that's
the problem with how we're teaching our
next generation so too much
book-learning not enough experimentation
it's almost too rigid we end up with
college graduates who don't understand
the why the things why things work the
way they do they often lack the tools to
figure it out so how do they get those
tools how does a person that's been
shorted the ability to tinker learn to
take her how do we teach people to steal
it a good way well it's a really
interesting topic but for now we're
going to take a little detour alright
lets out this is the Mona Lisa oh it's
by DaVinci right but do you know how to
Vinci learn to paint I'm very sure that
he didn't take cs3 11 exactly he was an
apprentice to a painter and sculptor
Andrea del Verrocchio he taught DaVinci
all sorts of things like metallurgy
sculpting and painting in fact they
painted this together it said that when
they finished Verrocchio was so taken
away by da Vinci's work that he put down
his paintbrush never to paint again well
that's great but what does it have to do
with stealing code my point is that in
the old visit olden days disciplines
were taught through apprenticeship da
Vinci was an apprentice to Pharrell geo
and in turn apprentice some of his own
even including Raphael who painted this
oh those look really similar right an
apprentice learns to the process of
mimicking his masters technique okay but
we're not in the older days anymore it's
all about educating its scale how we're
mass communicated
but for our field like da Vinci's maybe
it's better for us to get our hands
dirty well now you lost me the goal of
an apprenticeship is to learn how your
master does things but you start small
doing the little work your master and
oil no longer has time to do oh right
the Scott work like writing tests right
but over time you row to do more and
more evolved work build all on all that
scut work you did initially so what
you're saying is maybe we need to teach
computer programming like we're teaching
art in an art class you get the theory
in history but ultimately you're
exploring your ideas from day one in
your studio work and well most CS
classes are theory and formulas but you
really don't get a chance to explore
until your senior level stuff possibly
even grad school so what you're saying
sounds like it really comes down to
where the opportunity to create lies
exactly art classes have you creating
from day one but CS classes don't have
you creating until the end so what we
just said that we steal code to
understand it to take it apart to make
it our own doesn't that sound more like
the art class example then the CS class
example all right yeah kinda and
actually the apprenticeship paradigm
isn't just about art lots of other
fields use it like music I mean the
voice is basically a show about landing
an apprenticeship and in architecture
and design Walter Gropius who was the
founder of the Bauhaus School said the
best kind of practical teaching is the
old system of free apprenticeship to a
master craftsman which was void of any
scholastic tape and even in physics
Einstein said the only source of
knowledge is experience taught oh sorry
let's get back on topic oh right I was
going to say that while you while I
agree with you we don't really do
apprenticeships anymore they went out
with the Industrial Revolution let's say
50 100 150 years ago well yes and no no
what we have apprentices now we just
call them entry-level developers or
interns that's that's that's where you
learn that almost everything they just
taught you in college is worthless
yeah that's that's pretty unfortunate
but wouldn't it be better of entry-level
devs started with the knowledge they
really need to know to do their job like
how to Google stack overflow for answers
well actually yes points for Glen
remember when we said we were stealing
code to tinker so that we can learn well
it's our topic okay right what wouldn't
it be great if the entry-level dev
showed up on day one and knew how to do
that yeah but I don't think that's about
to change anytime soon I know it's not
so maybe it's on us to teach the new
employees yeah so what are the ways that
we do that no well there's there's pair
programming sure pairing is a learning
technique this perfect example for this
it's codes dealing with a friend
in a good in a good pair one person's
writing the code while the other is
constantly copying stuff off a stack
overflow okay let's not get really
carried away here but but you do get
what I'm saying right right one person
is hands on the keyboard the other
person is thinking the bigger thoughts
well but I feel with pair program it's
really easy to begin nit picking on each
other oh it's not a perfect system oh
and speaking of nitpicking what about a
code reviews yes it's another way to
teach when it's done right I've been on
far too many code reviews well people
will use it as a way to show superiority
that's unfortunate if you lay out some
sensible ground rules a code review can
be an incredibly powerful teaching tool
so I guess that's then it's about it
comes down to the personalities and
their adherence to the rules yeah so
what else do we do with new developers
to help them learn the lay of the land
well you can use your workflow to teach
how do you mean like teaching a pull
request workflow for code reviews yeah
I'm still not following okay you use
your workflow process to automate things
to encourage conversation with a pull
request you can assign it to a specific
person to get their feedback provides
you with the initial opportunity to
start a teaching moment so instead of
leaving your people out there on their
own you're usually the process to
encourage communication exactly it's
especially useful for a newer person to
assign a pull request to someone more
knowledgeable oh so they're actively
asking for learn to learn by creating a
conversation but about what you're doing
okay but I feel like that becomes really
dependent on the process well yeah a
good process is everything it really all
depends on your company having a culture
of learning the process that fosters
learning okay but that that has to come
from the top the management has to
create and nurture a great culture well
so I would argue that the first person
in a company to help new people needs to
be the managers they need to be very
active in making sure the new hires
don't just learn the best way to code
but they learn the best way to
well it's an interesting argument but I
think a lot of managers would disagree
they're always too busy if they didn't
want to manage people maybe they should
it be managers well I'm a manager do you
manage people I do so do you practice
what you preach well I'm a firm believer
in being in the trenches so to speak
rolling up my sleeves working with my
employees working side by side so that's
another way that we mentor on the job
through a nurturing environment sure and
by actively participating I'm not just
helping the new person that public
myself but more importantly I'm helping
the keep your helping the culture
through mentoring precisely and it goes
beyond the workplace okay it does sure I
also mentor outside work okay now we're
getting somewhere tell us all about it
right so I work with Baltimore node
school and help others learn JavaScript
no diva the fundamentals of program
actually there is a node school event
running right this very second that I'm
missing to be here with all of you we do
have a pool and the beach but I'm really
sorry that you're missing it no school
sounds awesome I enjoy it and more
importantly it's getting us back to the
subject at hand of how we can give
people who haven't had the chance to
learn to steal code the skills to learn
to steal code all right can we agree to
stop calling the stealing code what do
you want to call it tinkering hijacking
pass um creative borrowing all right all
right I like it it's teaching people how
to creatively borrow okay how so well
known school works by asking you to
solve a problem and give you vague ideas
of where to find help to solve that
problem live events take it a step
further by pairing people together
encouraging them to learn together well
this sounds perfect for what we're
talking about well absolutely but let's
not spend a lot of time on it how about
some other programs do you know any
um no you hear about all these hack days
and training things let's get more
specific okay uh hack reactor hack
reactor is an interesting example but
it's one you pay for let's let's focus
on some free ones alright I work with a
lot of rails devs they tell me about
railsbridge it's the rails version in
that's cool okay I was in a coffee shop
the other day and a guy told me about
hacker hours so this is really
interesting it's where you show up you
code you throw up your hand if you have
a question the organizers will give you
some help even if they don't know the
language they'll find a way to get you
help a source for your creative
borrowing they're literally teaching you
how to tinker at its basis form that's
pretty sweet i especially like that
their date is an epic time so what else
you got for us okay there's also the
women who code this is a national
organization they host events all over
the place all the time helping women get
into tinkering cool but you notice what
you've done here what did i do well
you've moved from talking about
mentoring to talking about communities
interesting well maybe that's the answer
to the question through community well
communities that mentor communities that
nurture new people specifically well
like lemon code Oh notes cool and hacker
hours and a dozen different
organizations well this year at ember
comp they started women helping women
this is specifically a mentorship
program for women in tech not just for
coding and code reviews but for
leadership and getting people to speak
and for blogs there's also global day of
code retreat and this is starting with a
specific problem conway's game of life
and you show up and you hack on whatever
language you want you get help and
people pair and and switch off all day
long there's also international node bad
day I mean I actually learned about this
at the last J has come um I mean I'm
sure a ton of people here do robots and
love JavaScript so it's a full day of
that oh my company big nerd ranch
gratuitous plug we host a number of hack
nights and we have we're working in
languages like Android and iOS front end
in JavaScript and we do a lot of
hardware stuff and design but its
communities like these that make it
possible for everybody to get involved
and that's the important thing well but
it's more than just teaching people how
to borrow creatively yeah sure it's
about teaching people how to see from
different points of view as well okay
now I'm not following you okay well
consider our initial problem I going to
stack overflow or wherever and cut and
paste some code right yeah borrow it
creatively sure but then I changed thus
preventing you from doing any hard time
right but how do I know to change it
well it's code it's the nature of it
sure right but if I only ever knew about
one thing say oranges for example how
could I ever imagined a banana okay
you're talking about our ability to see
beyond what we already know about using
our imagination well partially but I'm
also talking about a thing called them
integral philosophy right where our
understanding of all that comes before
helps us build what comes after so
imagining a banana is only possible
because you know about oranges right and
the next step beyond that is only
possible because you know about oranges
and bananas it's cumulative well it's
comprehensive it's integrated exactly
but how does that apply to communities
well the more we consider a different
points of view and the more we let
different voices into our community the
greater our ability to comprehend that
which the way greater our ability to
comprehend stuff beyond what we know
that's what these communities are doing
women who code notes cool they give us a
chance to participate in the community
out ideas the diversity of human
experience and teach not just how to
really tinker but to also understand
well understand code well in people so
is that it we admit to being thieves but
we're all fees and we're all created
borrowers and that's not a bad thing
that's a good thing because
that's how we work well there's just one
more thing yeah well it's all yours well
it's on us to make sure that the people
coming into this field the newbies if
you will have the ability and the
opportunity to learn that to understand
it to use it to build something better
by which you mean well community is
great but it has to start somewhere it
has to be led by someone so it'd be
great if we were at some sort of I don't
know let's call it a conference where we
could tell a bunch people this so yeah
all you sitting out there we're trying
to tell you that being a great developer
isn't just about knowing how to tinker
or knowing how to creatively borrow from
Stack Overflow being a great developer
is about being willing to help others
learn to be great developers to learn to
tinker and to grow and to understand
we're trying to tell you that just
watching a community from the sidelines
is it enough you need to get out there
be part of it nurture it grow it lead it
and that brings us to this moment now
right now right this second you've
already begun the process I'm willing
bet that the person sitting next to you
knows something that you don't
actually that that's a really great
point Oh points4 glad all these people
all these days conf attendees they've
taken the first step they have yeah sure
how long have we known each other a few
years I guess and how did we meet ooh
have you bet my friend Todd no I mean
where did we meet well we met down on
the beach over there at Jazz cough 2013
Emily right and here we are two and a
half years later on a stage so to speak
collaborating together at all because of
this conference and the people that run
it Chris and Laura and the entire Jays
comp staff they've created an amazing
community they realize exactly what we
just spent 30 minutes trying to figure
out together that share your community
is everything everyone here has taken
the first steps towards better sharing
sharing but more than that sharing of
ideas sharing of code like we've been
talking about and sharing of ideas and
sharing of experiences it all makes us
better programmers better people and in
the end isn't that what it's all about
no no it's been about stealing code and
being proud of it he's Glenn good one he
works for SAS Institute you can find him
at all right net and he's Todd Gabby you
he worked for big nerd ranch and you
could find him at Teague Andy thanks