all right everyone I think I'm gonna get
started with my talk now I'm glad to be
here today at JS con fan to be a
follow-up back to the beer I want to
first a just spell some misinformation
or some ignorance that was put out a
moment ago by the previous speaker he
had a moment ago up a picture of a
policeman writing a Tyrannosaurus
shooting some aliens on the moon and he
said he didn't know where the picture
came from I'd like to inform you that
picture comes from not from google
closure from the stellar axe cop comic
and I know this because I recently won a
costume contest that is the subtly
nuanced character Abraham Lincoln
explosion god so with that all the way
maybe i can get to my talk a little more
comfortably so to introduce myself my
name is John Davidson I work with cloud
kick which was recently acquired by
Rackspace and we do a lot of work with
servers as you might imagine racks based
as hosting cloud kick does server
monitoring and this meant that for our
user interfaces for our web app we found
need to be displaying information that
couldn't be readily conveyed with
traditional widgets that would come kind
of baked in with the user interface
libraries that are popular and this
includes the Google closure library
Google closure library comes with your
stock set of widgets but those were also
not what we needed you know buttons
sliders things like that that's not what
we needed to show things like CPU usage
complex information in a tree regarding
the check on a system so it pushed us to
develop a lot of our own widgets and we
found the Google closure library was
valuable not for the widgets it
contained but because it exposes the
framework that Google uses to create its
widgets and we followed suit and use
that framework to make some of our own
so to step back a moment
what are the globule closure tools the
library is just the first piece of them
you also have the Google closure
compiler the Google closure templates
and the closure linter I'm going to be
talking primarily about the library and
writing a little bit of code in the
library to show you what it looks like
but I find that a lot of developers
haven't taken on any programming
projects with the closure library
because there's definitely a lot to it
and can be kind of daunting let's see
and so to reference some of the things
that we're doing at cloud kick we do
make use of the library the compiler the
templates but we buck the trend and we
don't need the Google closure linter
because we've got jslint and you can
deal with it okay so what do I mean when
I'm talking about some custom widgets
I'm going to bring up one of them here
and show why it's not something that's
conventional enough to be found in a
regular library if I can remember the
hotkeys oops there we go this is one
that I wrote and its function isn't
readily apparent when you look at it
right here but if you see it on a page
it makes a little more sense what you
have around here are the place is ready
to have some check on your system you
this instead of being d would be SSH see
would be paying you could have memory
you could have any custom checks that
you've set up on your own system they
could run on your side and the report
back to F this widget is ignorant of all
that in meaning and it's just about
displaying what you have so maybe you've
got some kind of aggregates of those
data you wanted to select one of the
subgroups of it I won't dwell on it but
you can see that something
unconventional is the kind of thing
where you'd like to be able to define
behavior exactly on your own terms and
not have to settle for something else
okay so before I start on that I'm going
to introduce you to the parent for the
classes i'm going to create which is the
google uicomponent the Goo Goo I
component it inherits from its
grandparent the disposable which imbues
it with some properties that give it a
life cycle where you enter into the
memory subsequently you can enter into
the Dom itself exiting the Dom maybe to
return maybe not and then be disposed
there's an event framework that gets put
in with google event target and then
finally there's the glue I component
that works in a lot of the helper
functions that you'll find in the
widgets in the widgets themselves all
right so widget lifecycle there's a
pretty important concept and what made
this frame were pretty valuable to us
the image on the right demonstrates the
paths that a widget can take in its life
cycle we're only going to be focusing on
one of them but i'm going to introduce
them here just because it's an important
concept to understand if you start from
the instantiated widget over there you
have the render path the decorate path
and disposed path the render path is one
where you would say I have a target
where I want to place this widget and it
will let me see if I can gesture this
it'll execute create Dom and Inter
document on its own and that means is
going to create its own dumb it's going
to do the functions that you've defined
an enter document to enter the document
and that point is displayed the user is
looking at it the user can interact with
it the user can see it the similar path
that's not as useful to us is decorate
if that Dom element already existed you
could take your widget and just attach
all of its events and handlers to the
existing Dom element but because our
apps are usually HTML generated by
JavaScript we don't find ourselves as
frequently needing some other part of
our JavaScript to prakrit creating the
widgets it makes more sense for us to
just encapsulate that inside the Goo Goo
I component itself and use the render
path
disposed over here is just if you were
to create a widget and say it was
supposed to be ready for some view that
popped in but the user never used it so
you just dispose of it when you're done
and over here we have some of the
functions and I'm going to be explaining
to you momentarily when I walk through
the creation of a widget itself so this
is a simplified widget lifecycle to get
rid of the other pads is the one that
we're going to be taking for the demo in
a moment we're going to be instantiating
rendering and disposing are the
functions that we're going to be calling
and in the background that's going to
hit create Dom inter document and then
way to dispose it's going to hit exit
document and dispose internal okay so i
thought the widget that i work on today
is something that you see on sites like
eBay or a lot of sales sighs I think
woot has something similar it's this
little countdown I would call this a
pretty simple widget where it's
displaying some number of seconds and
it's updating itself and it's telling
you that you better buy something fast
because time is running out so before I
do that I have to show a little bit
about how the class system works in
google closure the two important ones to
know strap the bat or goog provide and
goog require good provide is how when
you make a file you say this is what I'm
providing in this file if other files
are wanting to require it this is the
namespace it should be addressed by &
goo require is how you request that file
so for example the opening part of the
event target object that I talked about
earlier opens with guude provide and
then it gives out in string what its
name is gugak wire and it takes the two
things that then get incorporated in
during the file what we're going to be
doing here is kind of a bad example but
because we're doing a bad example I'm
going to put the warning in when you use
goog require the way it includes the
code is by taking what you've asked for
and generating a script tag that's
appropriate so if you wanted to use
goood UI button as we do here you would
have to use you'd have to have the
require statement in
separate set of tags to make sure that
it's inserted script tag gets executed
before you get to the next block if we
were to combine those two we would get
an error that says that goo goo I button
doesn't exist yet ok that is there we go
so let me bring up the stub of what
we're going to be working with I've
cheated a little bit in that I have
already created the file that we're
going to be using and I can't spell
evidently courtesy of the beer okay so
I've stubbed this out on the functions
that we're interested in and I put the
two dudes in each place where we're
going to have to be implementing it
ourselves the first thing we don't know
I'm going to go through all of these all
the way and the interest of time but I
can go through a few of the obvious ones
let's see here I'm going to angle this a
bit so I can see better
so right there we have that we need to
add our group provide a new require
statements simple enough we're going to
require the component actually this is
moving significantly slower than I
thought it would we've got timers
another one that we would want and goons
because we're going to be doing a little
bit of event handling and I will stretch
for the it in the goog provide we're
just going to call this one countdown
which is later we refer to this class as
which is to come down and actually in
the interest of time feel like this is a
cooking show all of a sudden but I have
something that I baked earlier is that
visible no excellent okay
visible ish now how we doing we're going
to work that for a second so let me show
you how I filled this out on my own
earlier I decided that we wanted to pass
in in the constructor here the first
part we need to know the time remaining
we need to have a timer and we need to
start that timer we're listening for
ticks on the timer and every time we
have a tick we're going to handle the
tick which is just going to decrement
the time that we have remaining the
appropriate amount for what the interval
is set to I think presently the interval
is set to one second and at that point
we refresh the content which just sets
the number of seconds into the element
itself and those are the kind of inner
working parts but let me show you how I
filled out the behind the scene step
that create down etc so enter document
all we had to do here we took advantage
of the event the event handler that
comes built in and the advantage of
using the event handler that comes built
in with this widget as opposed to using
our own listen calls is that the event
handler that comes with the widget is
coterminous with the widget so anytime
we set a bunch of listeners on this when
we finally go to dispose or we go to
exit document actually it's going to
remove those listeners automatically so
I think I had it just like console
logging because I wanted to set
something here I couldn't really think
of anything to put in disposed internal
because everything else was already
handled for us and the super classes
disposed internal the only thing I
really need to get rid of was that timer
that I created initially and let me see
if I have it in here
I think I oh that's right I was going to
put an exit document statement as well
but it turns out that because things
were handled for me I didn't even need
to author one so as you can see it's a
pretty simple function but it's pretty
simple to get it to fit into the
framework of Google closure itself and
evidently I changed something so let me
open that demo we have a moment first I
have to correct some JavaScript a moment
oh and you'll see that i included cheat
up there what she does is it goog
requires the component beforehand
because like I said you need to have
that required earlier for the way that
this is working at the moment because
this isn't bundled together if you have
this actually in production you would be
bundling this together and I'm actually
going to reference at the end of this
some of the better ways to package this
someone i've done i've literally shown
you the worst possible way to use google
closure today thank you let's see here
okay and if this works as expected I had
set a listener on this button which is a
regular button it's not a witch or
anything and this should take the
already created widget and render it
into the page Oh lovely thank you I'm
here all week something has no method
inherits
oh I guess I didn't
oh that's right I didn't fix this
okay one more try
if this doesn't work I'm going to have
to take it on a good faith because okay
so you notice it started at 27 there I
haven't counting off from the moment it
was created which was three seconds
before that and it had already been
counting because it existed in the
background and when we hit rendered as
when is actually entered into the Dom I
had a listener so that when your mousing
over it it tells you how many seconds it
has in milliseconds and it's spitting
that out at the bottom I'm going to wait
a second because i also have it waiting
for a change event that it dispatches on
itself and yep dang we missed it is the
listener that we had on that putting
that in and out was one line on an
existing Google library which made it
pretty easy as well and then we can
dispose of it at the end and we don't
have to worry about any of those events
or objects that we've created in the
meantime because it takes care of it
this is a really simple example but it
was also really simple to create which
was the beauty of it okay
I'm going to skip this a moment suffice
to say that this was simple but there's
actually a better way to do really great
widgets than what we've done here if you
want to have a widget that multiple
different representations this only has
one create Dom you could theoretically
hook it up to a series of different
create Dom's for looking one way in one
page one way in another so how good was
our deployment for this it was actually
pretty terrible it was the least optimal
way to do this of all of them oh there
we go every time we have the goog
require in live code it's just putting
in script tags which means more requests
and requests and requests and requests
on top of requests so that's slow it
means that the code that you're pulling
down is undefined it's uncompelled which
is slow not just for the time to pull it
down the time to parse it but also the
time to execute it so the ways to make
it better then this example would have
been instead of taking raw code which is
tons of requests it's not minified not
optimized we could have done bundle it
there's a script that comes with Google
closure that would have done this for us
in one line we could have served it up
it'd still be a fairly large file even
for pretty simple things so if you were
to minimize it and use the simple
compilation from the google closure
compiler this would have put you in a
better situation but if you're feeling
particularly adventurous you could use
the Google closure advanced compilation
and that'll give you code that looks
something like this which can be fun to
debug I'll tell you but otherwise it's
really a pleasure to work with in terms
of speed of execution and the
downloading um so I think I'm just with
in time for my demonstration today and I
thank you all for your attention did we
have any questions about google closure
library in general or about widgets in
particular I've spent most of my time
working with the widgets library but
I've also done a bit else so I've got
some experience over there the question
was if I'd done anything with mobile
applications no I've not actually for
the particular app that we do a cloud
kick I'm on the front end for our web
app team and we'd consider doing a
mobile version
of the site for a bit but presently
we've just hired on someone that's
actually doing native android and iphone
apps for cloud kick I think we actually
have both already but he's really
improving them so that's not the highest
priority as far as the mobile platforms
concerned for the mobile platform we're
pursuing the native apps at the moment
have you worked with it for mobile or
was it interesting
style
right if you're talking are you talking
to nate aviron seeeeee ok so for
appearance i think the task you would
have there is just to take the existing
widgets and write new renderers for them
which isn't entirely trivial so yes if
you're looking for something that looks
entirely like an iPhone app you're
probably looking at something like
sencha and if there aren't any more
questions I thank you very your time and