Jeff it's one of those cool languages
that sort of no one really noticed for a
long time it was it was launched in 1995
his Netscape to beta 3 that's almost 14
years ago which is pretty astonishing
really i sort of i don't think of
javascript as being over a decade old
but it is interestingly enough two
months three months after javascript
launched ruby launched as well the first
public release in February of 1996 and I
sort of remember at the time being a lot
more interested in Ruby than JavaScript
but that changed that's why I'm here um
and we all know the history or I hope we
all know the history the sort of naming
kuffel inside netscape livewire all
sorts of or live can something like that
all sorts of naming problems um and the
reason why the name JavaScript came
about of courses because of the big Sun
launch of java at the same time Java's
appearance in the browser for my
purposes that actually sort of suits me
if you look at the history of javascript
and how it's come to where it is i sort
of equate it to point cast and RSS for
those of you that don't know or don't
remember point cast was this like crazy
screensaver that took news syndication
feeds and displayed them as it turned
out it wasn't a very good business
displaying advertising while someone's
away from their computer doesn't attract
that many advertisers but um but here's
the thing it introduced the idea of news
syndication it sort of got us thinking
about that and RSS came along and won it
was an open standard the web decided
that that was the way it should be and I
sort of see the same thing with
JavaScript and Java the the web has
decided that javascript is the answer um
so
if we think about you know what
JavaScript's role was for a long time
you know had a single domain it was a
web page that was it and and that was it
you know Java had the dancing Duke and
JavaScript gave us mouse overs and
pop-ups that's that's what we wanted at
the time and that didn't really change
until nineteen ninety nine when
xmlhttprequest came along Thank You
Microsoft every now and again um but no
one really noticed until gmail and
google maps of course but around that
time I've been working with JavaScript
on the server or not necessarily the
server but not in a browser for quite a
while I'd been working for a company
called photon go in London we've been
building up where I'd been building sort
of workflow tools to join together rest
services and think about workflow tools
is workflows lovely until something goes
wrong and then all of a sudden you need
to make a decision and you can't really
do that without some sort of
decision-making tool a programming
language and so I was embedding
javascript in all sorts of stuff and
then a little bit later on for tango is
looking for a new product and we launch
this thing called Zemke it was probably
the first platform as a service out
there way before anyone was ready for it
and I spent a lot of the next couple of
years talking about how JavaScript on
the server side made a lot of sense and
everyone looked at me as if I was crazy
and and that's changed so that I called
this slight rise and fall it's actually
rise and fall and rise again just don't
have that much room so in them in 2007
Zemke had sort of vanished I moved back
to Canada from London as tired of London
really it gets tiresome big city and
anyway I'd moved to my mountain retreat
and I found myself with some time on my
hands and I had a whole bunch of ideas
and I wanted to implement them sighs you
know I did what everyone else was doing
at the time is doing now for the large
part and I picked up a copy of Ruby and
you know browse through the rail you
know the rails documentation
started to hack the ideas together what
I found was it was actually really
painful you know for for everything that
everyone says about Ruby illa it's
wonderful blah blah blah but you know I
actually found it really painful and one
of the reasons i found it painful was
because I've come from this world where
I could write almost everything I wanted
in JavaScript um so while I was while I
was trying to hack these ideas together
i was using get not yet had sort of come
up at the same time and I've sort of you
know out of that those experiments I
realized that actually get was what i
wanted to deploy things into the cloud
it was such a wonderful tool i could
just push things um and that gave rise
to a company I started with a colleague
who's here Brian called reasonably smart
in June of last year which was
JavaScript on the server side a managed
platform-as-a-service you deploy with
get but to understand why this is timely
you really have to understand why a
platform as a service is a timely idea
and it's about economics and
commoditization that line was supposed
to be earlier so um this my former
colleague of mine Simon wardley he
actually does a really great talk about
these ideas about commoditization about
economics if you haven't had the
opportunity to see him speak do so it's
well worth it and if you don't ever get
the chance his talks are all over the
web it's easy to find Simon wortley so
one of Simon's big themes in his talk is
pointing out that electricity was once
really hot technology like it was it was
a competitive advantage to have
electricity in your factory but these
days we don't really think about it we
have wall sockets we plug stuff in
electricity comes out and we don't care
where it comes from or why it comes from
there or how they generate it for the
most part i mean there's a slight
movement now to want green electricity
but let's face it when we plug something
into the wall all we care about is that
electricity comes out in the same format
it wasn't always the case as i mentioned
the place where electricity is a public
utility first started
was this little town called Godalming in
Surrey in the UK it's tiny little talent
to drive through it these days you
really wouldn't think that it was sort
of the center of the world in 1881 but
it was a company started providing
electricity to the entire town and it
was it was fantastic they had
streetlights no more gas is awesome and
then they had a big flood and in 1884
they basically bailed and no electricity
came back to the dorm until 1904 but in
the meantime what was happening was the
sort of rise of all these public
utilities public utility power
generators they were popping up left
right and center and by 1926 there was
600 of them in the UK thing was they all
operated on different standards
different frequencies ac/dc you name it
and in 1926 that what changed was the
Central Electricity Board was set up in
the UK it fixed all of that it's
standardized what the output should be
it it standardized how you would get
electricity out of a wall it's
standardized AC / DC etc etc um but the
thing is this you know factories up
until this point hadn't really changed
for years they'd been generating all the
sort of motion they needed with steam
engines and these great big steam
engines had engineers on site they had
their fuel on site you shovel coal into
a burner which heated up the water which
spun a flywheel which drove a belt which
drove all the machines in the factory
and the steam engine had really
revolutionized industry have changed it
completely in much the same way that
sort of having a server changed the way
we do computing rather than going to a
mainframe um and the sort of non
mechanized factory had vanished they had
all been sort of you know competed out
of existence the thing was when the
steam engine broke down the engineers
who were on site all of a sudden had to
get their stuff together you know they
took the blame they pulled an allnighter
sorted it out factory was running the
next morning it sounds familiar doesn't
it yeah um
we've all sort of done those as
programmers as engineers we've all had
the situation where something's gone
horrendously wrong and we need to sort
of out and and that's something that's
starting to change now and that's
something that starts to change with a
platform as a service just as when
electricity from a public utility
started changing factories from the
steam engine to machines that could be
bought off the shelf and plugged into a
wall or the proverbial shelf the the
platforms of service is changing how we
deploy and manage our software no more
engineers on site no more steam engines
on site and cloud really means the same
thing about computing we just don't have
to shovel coal anymore now often people
think cloud they think things like ec2
and that's it you know that's probably
one of the first things that pops into
people's head but that still means
managing machines and we can do better
and what we can do is platform as a
service we don't want to and shouldn't
have to want to to met worried about
scale or managing individual machines or
patching security or you know figuring
out how many database servers or app
servers we need and then load balancing
all of those things those are those are
things that give us no competitive
advantage whatsoever we you know
everyone has to do it there's no point
of us doing it and with things like easy
to you're still having to do that you're
still having to consider that you're
still having to make those decisions
spin up machines tear them back down to
you so with the platforms of service and
specifically with a smart platform you
write your code you push it to the cloud
with get and it just runs you pay for
only only for what you use and I don't
mean like a small subscription such as
ec2 I mean genuinely when something's
used you pay for it and when it's not
you don't metered billing much like
electricity so I'm not suggesting that
there is no place for having a server or
data center of your own what I'm saying
is that they're going to slowly
disappear and maybe they'll never vanish
I'm sure they'll never vanish but for
the majority of us we don't need to be
doing that stuff it gives us no benefit
so really it's a matter of economics
it's an inevitability whether you like
it or not if you're managing your
servers for the most part it's costing
you money that you just don't need to
spend but why javascript coming back to
the theme of the day well to me it just
sort of makes sense let's look at Java
scripts sort of common place in the
world it's in the browser has the Dom
it's got great libraries for the browser
like jQuery and prototype and all dojo
all those sort of things um hope I got
everyone there um but here's the thing
the Dom sucks we all know it that's why
we have these libraries but it doesn't
have to be on the server and in fact
it's not on the server the DOM is just
something that the Mozilla engineers and
the IE engineers and the Safari guys
exposed into the JavaScript space um in
and of itself javascript is simple and
it's beautiful and and I don't need to
tell you how I hope we all know
JavaScript that's why we're here and the
strange thing is everyone else knows
that to everyone not in this room almost
every internal IT shop these days has
given up the sort of desktop app as a
paradigm what they're doing is they're
writing web applications if they're
writing web applications then chances
are in fact I'd almost say it's
guaranteed that they've got people in
that shop that no JavaScript and if you
think about JavaScript on the server it
means you're not context switching all
the time you're not switching between
pearl or Python or Ruby and JavaScript
you're just going back and forth between
the server and the client and it doesn't
really matter and that gives you code
reuse as well so there are two others
sneaky reasons why Java scripts going to
win the first is that it's where the
money is trace monkey and v8 and space
needle or squirrelfish or whatever the
call in it there's there's loads of
money being spent on making these things
really really fast and I'd say if you
look at ruby in the end python perl and
all the other dynamic languages over the
sort of
10-15 years of their development they've
had less time and focus spent on
actually pushing the boundaries of what
you can do with a dynamic language
compared to JavaScript which has only
really had that time and energy and
focus in the last two or three years
let's say it's really incredible how far
JavaScript has come in a really short
time um there's another sneaky reason
from a platform provider perspective and
that is that JavaScript does nothing out
of the box there's no I of there's no I
pc there's no threads there's no process
management it does nothing it's
turing-complete but can't do much with
it unless you tell it it can do
something so as an embed of the language
in environment where I'm not vetting all
the code I can pretty much guarantee
that you can't do anything bad so
there's a lot of good reasons for
javascript in a platform as a service so
you know I am here from joint they're
paying for me to be here so let's talk
about the smart platform specifically
its utility build like I said you pay
only for what you use you build your app
you deploy it to the cloud with get and
that's it the key point and the
differentiating point I think is that
you can move away if you want the entire
stack is open-source the platform's open
source there's no lock in if you don't
like what we're doing or how we're doing
it you can take it and run it on your
own machines we think we'll do a better
job than you that's all we're saying so
in London there's a term that we use to
describe all the sort of stuff that you
have to do to run a web app it's called
the action and the idea is that for all
you know you wake up in the morning you
want a cup of coffee you are you find
you don't have any milk so you go to the
store doesn't get some milk and you find
you don't have any money so you go to
the ATM you put your car in you get the
money out your back to the store and you
go get and get the milk you take it back
home you make you a cup of coffee and
really all that other stuff other than
making the cup of coffee for the good it
was doing you you might as well have
been shaving it yak that's where the
phrase comes from but that's how I think
of what we're doing with a platform
we're taking away the need for you to
worry about all those all the Yak
shaving I was gonna say something really
rude there yeah we're just we're just
meaning we're just making it so you
don't need to worry about it so you know
like said adding removing machines load
balancing data storage multi data center
having to worry about backups caching
data storage all that sort of stuff it
just does the right thing without
developer interaction and it's because
we can abstract away behind what's going
on inside the jig the JavaScript virtual
machine nearly set JVM there um this
slide isn't all that interesting but it
does let me bring up a point that I
actually saw someone Twitter or tweet or
whatever the verb is this week yesterday
after the axiom stack talk which was
about performance and someone saying you
know really is JavaScript faster than
PHP you know blah blah blah um my answer
is yes and if you really if you really
find a way that it isn't wait a couple
of weeks and it will be faster it's just
going to happen all that all that money
being spent means yes so as a absolute
statistic with JavaScript contexts in
spider monkey I can create 797 797 of
them a second and that's in serial a
single thread spinning them up and
tearing them down so yes it's fast
anyway so here's the simplest piece of
software that runs on the smart cloud
it's really simple it's going to spit
out hello world to the requesting
browser not much to it really I think we
can all understand what it's doing there
it's a function called main it takes a
request object it returns the response
that's it um here's another version this
is just demonstrating efore xe4 x is
super cool it makes XML first class
objects if you don't know inside
JavaScript and then given that object
you can actually walk through the tree
it's awesome it has its problems as well
some weird things but for the most part
it's great and here's a slightly more
complex
main function it's returning more a more
specific HTTP response you can see how
you could build up almost any response
you at one the really interesting thing
about all of those three functions is
that they scale you can make one request
or you can make 100 million requests
through the smart platform and it will
scale and you've done nothing to make it
scale all that effort is taken place
beyond the scenes now yes I know that
you could write a PHP app or a ruby app
or Python or whatever app that scaled
because it just doesn't do that much but
you'd have to worry about a number of
machines you'd have to worry about all
the load balancing and stuff that goes
on with that with a smart platform you
don't it doesn't matter one hip or a
billion hits a second it'll scale so
this is the contents of the request
object it's got all the stuff that you'd
find an HTTP request you can dig out and
I've emitted the headers because they
kind of took up all the slide and tiny
font bad so the the body and the content
or in there the query string pretty much
everything the URI of course the the
type is an interesting one we're going
to make it so that you can request make
requests into the platform through XMPP
or through smtp or almost anything
basically if we can figure out a way to
hook it up we'll send a request in and
you'll be able to serve stuff from it
but the question probably all asking
yourself is how do you make stuff like
data storage and all that work well we
like to said we extend JavaScript so a
couple of examples here readwrite search
remove you don't have a huge API into
the data storage system but if you're
working with things like active record
you don't have that big of an API into
that either it's abstracted away from
you so this really lets you take
advantage of the fact that we can
introspect objects we can we control the
line between JavaScript space and the
and the actual data storage layer pretty
completely we can
make decisions as to how to store it and
why to store it in a certain way and you
know how you're going to query it later
on all that sort of stuff we can
introspect on the wire and take care of
it for you so the API while it looks
quite small does everything you need it
to and it scales similarly HTTP HTTP
requests out that gives you a response
which looks much like the response you
would return from your main function
blah blah blah la la la la there's not
much to say about that it's just sort of
interesting because it's in there that's
synchronous you're on the server eight
we're going to so as part of i'll
mention it later on again but as part of
what we're doing we're going to have
asynchronous workers on this on the
server so if you wanted to make it a
synchronous you could it's just that
it's out of band from the rest of the
requests as well you can always cash it
and pull it out in a synchronous request
so there's a bunch of other extensions
stuff that you probably wouldn't want to
implement in JavaScript yeah H max sha-1
that sort of stuff javascript not so
good at binary there's also a media
store so dumping large content items
similar to how you would treat s3
remotely you just put stuff in you get
stuff out it's easy huh but the thing is
um importantly you don't want to do
everything yourself so we're including a
bunch of libraries we're trying where
possible to find these libraries the
third parties have written we've written
some ourselves so templating there's an
application framework whatever that
means Jason parsing beyond just eval and
json string of occasion that sort of
string encoding there's a great library
called date j/s which does all sorts of
crazy formatting on dates and wiki
markup which serve brings me to the next
slide because i'm going to write or
demonstrate the writing of a wiki so i'm
going to use a couple of libraries and
this there's the
Sammy library which named Sammy sort of
half sarcastically after Sammy Davis jr.
because it looks a lot like the Sinatra
framework for Ruby and there's the the
resource library which sort of takes the
data store which is there and just wraps
it in some nicer nicer stuff as you can
see in the next line down which is
creating a sort of page page namespace
for objects so here's my first function
it's not as complicated as it looks i'm
giving a regular expression as the first
argument and the second argument is a
function that will execute when the
machine takes a request a get request
that matches that regex so that regex
will match / and anything after /
basically so typical wiki style page
names if there's not if it just matches
the / and there's nothing else after it
it goes through loading the homepage it
tries to get the page out of the data
store if that fails it'll throw an
exception it just create a fake one and
it returns a template that sort of mobs
that all up and dumps it out to the
browser in the pretty form and so
there's another library usage there the
wiki library that just does some wiki
markup conversion and it wiki markup
converts the the content of that object
and spits it out to the template so wiki
need to be able to edit it sort of the
point if it finds a slash edit at the
end of one of those URLs then it pulls
up an editor page again if it doesn't
have a page name it looks for actually
that's a kind of miss line so I take
care of that later on doesn't matter so
again try and get the page out of the
data store you return the template that
is the editor and if you don't have the
page name or if you don't have the page
then just redirect to slash go back to
the homepage someone was trying to do
something bad um
saving again similar to Sinatra we're
dealing with a post opposed to the page
name take the page as the first argument
as a function that's that so I should
probably explain that a little better
that a page variable that is the first
argument to the function is actually the
capture from the regex pulled out and it
goes in order of the name of the
captures so if you had more than one
capture put more than one argument you
can get the data out like that it
ignores the first sort of this is
everything I was matching against
response of an regular expression match
so anyway get the page out if you don't
have it create a new one set up the ID
if you do have it or either way dump the
content in save it and then redirect
back to it it's really quite simple and
that's a wiki that's that's everything
it works there's some HTML template
e-type code but that's pretty much it
again the point here with this is that
in none of that code have I gone out of
my way to make it you know quote unquote
scalable I'm not really worrying about
that at all I'm not writing to a
memcache first I'm not doing anything
clever i'm not writing to a message
queue to save the page at a date so i'm
not blocking etc etc i'm doing nothing
particularly sensible for a large scale
app not about not that I'm suggesting
this wiki will ever be a large scale app
but but if it was I wouldn't have to
worry about it because the platform's
taking care of it all it's going to make
it scale just like the initial main
function all that stuff in there the
performance should remain constant no
matter what so I think that's pretty
cool I've spent most of my career sort
of trying to make things scale and what
you find is that as time goes by most
your application is taken up with code
to make things scale rather than for the
business logic the functionality that
makes you different
and so yeah I like the fact I don't be
too worried about that we've got a lot
of things that we're going to add to the
core offering work use were one that i
mentioned to make it if you want to do
asynchronous stuff scheduled execution
is another one you know I want to run I
want to run this at one o'clock every
morning or every 10 minutes six cetera
et cetera more libraries that was a big
point xmpp and smtp i mentioned as well
I'd love to get video encoding in there
one extension I didn't mention that we
have is you know image manipulation flip
rotate crop blower all you have to be
able to do that these days apparently
video if we could do the same with video
we're not far off it's actually big
problem with video is making it possible
to have a downloadable version that just
works because of all the libraries that
are involved so just to sort of
summarize where we are we're just a
short way away from release originally
when well originally this had been live
i'm running and then when joint bought
reasonably smart we renamed to the smart
platform instead it's difference we
Canadians and Americans I guess yeah we
so it was renamed smart platform we
actually took it offline because we want
to focus on getting it right before we
released it to the world so very very
shortly you'll be able to download a
desktop version you'll be able to check
the source out of gip you'll know it'll
all be available and then shortly after
that when people have had chance to sort
of play around it with it and build
their apps you'll be able to just push
those applications right up to the cloud
so the workflow is kind of cool you know
you sit on your own laptop you do your
development you push the code up to the
cloud and it should just work exactly
the same if it doesn't it's my fault
sorry but you know don't envisage that
that's why we haven't done things like
the video extension I want to make sure
that works but the key point from all of
this is we're at a fascinating point
with JavaScript as a language we're
really coming to a point where we're
we're looking at it differently and not
only us who are involved
javascript but everyone is looking at it
differently just the number of people
who said they didn't know about this
conference I wanted to be here shows how
prevalent this thinking is the world is
really changing and people have been
volt involved in JavaScript for a long
time or best place to take advantage of
it that's all i have for you if there's
any questions I'm happy to answer and
meantime thank you very much one last
thing I have to do to obey the Creative
Commons these people deserve attribution
images from Flickr thank you very much
any questions before I hand over to yes
yeah i don't know if i missed it but is
there a way to include your own library
absolutely um yeah I it's it's an
extension but it didn't seem like a very
interesting one there is a way to pull
source code from other places in the git
repository that is your your application
so yeah you just use it it pulls it into
the into the system eventually we'll
have a way of submitting libraries into
the sort of platform library store not
going to have that from day one just
because it requires more bodies and more
time than i'm prepared to dedicate it to
it right now um but yeah in your wiki
example is this ready single frame so
the question was in the wiki event
example is the threading just single
threading yes from the purpose of any
given request with the asynchronous work
use if you wanted to do other stuff you
could spin it out but what you got to
remember is for that application there
could be one or a thousand machines
running it and it so you have you have
multithreading by transaction if you
like it's not the only one visitor can
be serviced at a time yeah threadings
kind of a key topic in JavaScript have
Brendan Eich I think that's how you
pronounce his name pretty sure it is had
a pretty good rant about
how threading over my dead body and I
tend to agree with them asynchronous
work use just tend to work a lot better
than than threading in a server
application nope oh go ahead let's let
I'll get you and then one of the back of
a time frame was arrested me about your
analogy for electricity and then
monetization of the actual machine book
is the time because the rate of change
my chance you know it differently how
long did it take for the commoditization
of electricity versus modernization of
machines it seemed like me much so so
the question was how long did it take to
with the commoditization of electricity
what how is that analogous to the time
frame that we've seen for the
commoditization of servers and actually
if you think about I think 1881 was
badal mming the first public provider
like I said 1926 was when it was
effectively commoditized later on it was
nationalized or monopolized but but
early on you know 1926 was when the
standard emerged that made it a
commodity so that's really not all
that's 40 years if you think about
computing we're not that far off 40
years since you know the the room in the
corner with all the lab techs wearing
white coats to the desktop and now to
just some random provider in the cloud
when we're not really that far away from
the same time frame although in saying
that I wouldn't be surprised if it was a
much smaller time frame in computing
what you're seeing in industry in
general with commoditization is the time
for something to be a have a you know a
WOW factor to being a commodity is
collapsing a great deal look at the
iphone you know when when the iphone
came out is only the people waiting in
line now i think probably about eighty
percent of the people in this room have
an iphone it's a similar commoditization
you know when i when i first got the
iphone i played with it for hours it's
awesome now I sort of like shove it in
my pocket I drop it it's become a
commodity too so yeah in general within
three we're seeing monetization really
speed up we treat things like commodity
much much faster last question the back
yeah you mentioned how much brain power
is being expended on advantage
JavaScript engines did you mention which
one you're using can we choose I mean
I'm gonna be very interested so yeah the
question is did I did I mention which
JavaScript engine I'm choosing not
explicitly I didn't mention it we're
using spider monkey and as a consequence
we're using trace monkey simply because
well you know that we've had discussions
about this you know should we be using
rhino it means we can use all the stuff
in all the jars blah blah blah blah blah
just embed java stuff the big problem
with rhino is it's not in a browser it's
not going to get the same amount of
eyeball time that spider monkey gets and
so to get those sort of benefits we're
better off we're better off using spider
monkey than rhino choosing spider monkey
over v8 or squirrelfish the the real
reason for that I suppose is that if you
look at the history of the Mozilla
project the spider monkey API really
hasn't changed very much it's an old
comparatively old projects you know that
has its roots in the first
implementation and the API has been
pretty stable throughout and so that
gives me a confidence that it's not
going to change that much in fact the
one of the biggest changes has been
recently with the 1.8 and all the trace
monkey work that's going on we've had to
deal with more changes than the almost
ever before in its history but I think
that's a pretty compelling reason why
shouldn't switch to something else for
this sort of stuff I'm not you know I'm
not a language guy when it comes to the
smart platform so I don't want to spend
my time you know rewriting code that
just embeds the language couple more go
there so you ready you're right nice
library
absolutely as I mentioned everything we
do the smart platform will be open
source so they will be absolutely opened
up no doubt so I think my question is
related I was curious some of the
scaling tactics that you guys use is the
release going to UM there will be some
things which we keep as not necessarily
secret sauce but you know because we're
a big provider if we go off and buy a
big object database for example for any
particular reason of course that's going
to be closed and the code that's going
to make the decision is going to be
consequently closed but you know right
out of the box they'll be less local
sequel light store there'll be a local
my sequel store there'll be a MongoDB
store that you can you know chop and
change of we're you know we're not
trying to protect our position in any
way with the source code now because we
don't see there being really a position
to protect we're competing on quality of
service not anything else yes very soon
we actually really hoped we'd be able to
announce here's the download here we
just had to be just going through an
internal QA basically and then it'll be
absolutely available lexa really wanted
it here couldn't quite pull it off maybe
next year I'll have more actual you know
visible you can download this here you
go I think I'm just about out of time
again thank you very much