[Music]
hi hello so hi I'm Ramon and I'm gonna
talk to you a little bit about something
that happens to me very often and I just
want to first a quick show of hands
anybody either got stuck while coding on
a problem now can all the liars put up
their hands so I'm just gonna tell you I
get stuck this is me trying to install a
ruby gem on my computer and I have no
idea why it's not installing I guess
suck a lot this is me trying to build a
Mac OS app this is how I originally
started my career and it's not just
encoding I also get stuck while blogging
I you know sometimes it just takes a
while for inspiration to strike so I'm
just gonna tell you a short story about
getting stuck and how we can all relate
with that and do better for ourselves
it's the stories
sorry it's a drawing a hand-drawn story
but please note my drawing skills stop
developing by the time I hit seven so
please bear with me so these are our two
main characters let's call them Joanne -
and it is a lovely day the Sun is out
the birds those are birds the birds are
singing and Joe's inside they're working
on their computer and they're kind of
annoyed because they encountered a bug
and they're just like I'm like I'm least
close to fixing it and Joanne - comes in
and said hey here's an idea let's go on
a walk
those are footsteps yeah
let's go on a walk I'm sure you can
clear head or whatever and she was like
hold on hold on I'm this close to fixing
it now what happened is that many many
hours later one thing I forgot to
mention ash wanted to take Joe on a walk
with their two lovely dogs right and
what happened is that many hours later
Joe was still at the computer ash was
not feeling that wild about it and came
over and said Joe I'm very very sad I
wish we'd gone on that walk and
unfortunately the poor dogs did not get
walked so I'm gonna tell you right off
the bat small spoiler that was me and
this happens to me all the time and it's
it's terrible because you know I get
stressed I get annoyed and the dogs
they're so sweet peace of my parents two
dogs they didn't get walked and but what
happens is one search wise I'll just be
like you know what I'll do it let's
let's go on that walk and being a person
who has a hard time getting bugs out of
their head I'm just like thinking of a
million ways you know I with Mac OS Ives
there's lots of memory leaks going on
and you know I struggle with it and then
all of a sudden the bang that's a
lightbulb but bang it gets the idea
comes into my head I hurry home and I
try and what do you know I fixed it now
I really short hair so now that for me
was a walk and of course to everybody it
doesn't have to be a walk it can be you
know going for a cup of coffee lately
I've been calling the public pool close
to my house my best debugging tool
because it you know you just go there
for half an hour and then you just
figure stuff out it doesn't have to be
pool it can be a cup of tea it can be
chatting to a friend it can be going for
a run maybe painting a picture playing
some video games taking a nap playing
with puppies or traveling what is
important is I find that you step away
from your environment for a little bit
and just let let the background in your
mind just just mull things over so what
I've learned over the years is that you
know it does happen you are going to get
stuck
and I have to remember I eventually will
fix the problem and if I don't fix the
problems I will get the help I need to
fix the problem and you know my most
important point is one below if I'm
gonna be stuck and unproductive I might
as well enjoy that time so that's it