hello everybody my name is Michael
Boland I'm here to talk to you about the
the width keyword the most evil thing
that we've ever seen in JavaScript
according to some people I'm also the
author of closure the definitive guide
so I'm going to commission a you some
actually some actually some of the good
parts about with some of the interesting
problems that you can solve with it and
also show you a little bit of closure as
part of that so first let's just look at
remember what people are saying about
with so you know some of our most
popular JavaScript books they're
basically saying don't even look at this
thing just this is the keyword it's
going to sell your program down and
you're going to have errors if you use
it like let's move on to the next
section usually when you see someone
give an example of what with is used for
its it trivializes it considerably it
basically says oh you're probably a lazy
programmer and if you want to add a lot
of properties to an object you're using
with you put the object properties to
inside there you do all these things
inside the block whereas you could also
just do what I show on the bottom of
this slide or just create a temporary
variable and then do the assignments
that way so basically the argument is
that you really never need with with is
actually doing a lot more it adds
another object to the scope change for
when you're resolving variables this
actually lets you do a lot more
interesting things then this little
example that is what you usually see
about with gives it credit for so let me
show you a problem that we had my last
job that we can actually only seem to be
able to solve using with so this is
actually snippet of code from from big
Matt Bing Maps version 63 so you know so
Bing Maps just like Google Maps or other
other other libraries something that you
would include in your application you
put a script tag or load it and then
you're actually giving that third party
the ability sorry oh thank you you're
giving that that library you know
ability to act access code in your
webpage and you're basically trusting
them to behave appropriately does anyone
actually see what's going on in this
code that could be a problem I like the
idea but in the sentiment in the energy
but no so so what's actually happening
is that if you look carefully this this
snippet of code is declaring two new
variables and Global's global scope the
eye and the Len for short for length
variables because the presumably heard
wrote this made the mistake of thinking
that javascript has blocked scope and
that they were defining a variable in a
block and it wasn't going to bother
anybody but obviously you shall know
better and knowing that javascript uses
function scope and this actually leaks
these variables into the global scope so
but why so here's an example so why
would this be a problem who cares like
what with the global definition of I is
and length like whatever you're going to
use it you're probably going to reassign
it and that sort of thing and you'd
override whatever this Bing Maps code
did well as it turns out we were using
the closure compiler to minify our code
and what happened was the closure
compiler decided to save some bites
instead of using four bytes for the word
true it was going to assign it to the
variable I and assigned so assigned true
to I and everywhere in our code where we
were going to reference the literal true
we now reference this variable I so that
means that once our application was
running along and then after we loaded
Bing Maps suddenly places where we were
looking for true we were getting the
number three this was extremely hard to
figure out where this was coming from we
certainly didn't know it was being maps
at first but then eventually we tracked
it down and so this is this leads to
kind of the basic problem of how do you
load code from another website and
protect your own code to make sure that
variables don't leak out of scope and
that sort of thing so most people would
say oh that's simple like all I need to
do
is load my code inside what a lot of
people refer to is immediate function so
a function that execute immediately
basically giving all of your code a
fresh scope protecting it from all the
code on load from another page so
normally that that is definitely
sufficient absolutely the right way to
go the problem is is now what happens if
you have a lot of code and you so much
code that you need to break it up into
modules so by modules I mean you have
you take all of your code you go a bit
into one file and then you actually
carve it up into bits that can be loaded
dynamically so for example an
application like Gmail where you might
have some core use some core libraries
like say string and array utilities
that's a that's one cluster of
JavaScript that you want to load
initially and then depending on what the
user does you might want to dynamically
load other other JavaScript tags so if
they go to the inbox you might want to
load logic that's specific to that
they'll go to settings load logic that's
specific to that in that way you
basically can improve the startup time
of your application you're not
penalizing the user for pulling down a
bunch of code for things that they don't
use so so this is this is a popular
technique fairly popular technique to
improve speed but the problem is is that
if you think back to to this if you
loaded every file every module inside of
its own immediate function then you have
this problem where code loaded in this
module can't talk to code loaded in this
module they don't share a scope anymore
so the problem is that you want your
modules to share scope but you don't
want to share scope with Microsoft so so
what are you to do what are your options
so there's there's a few ways right now
that people load modules so one is you
load each module via its own script tag
you just do in a pen child every time
you want to load another another clump
of JavaScript you just you just add it
one of the nice things about this
approach is that you can load your code
from a CDN the content delivery network
so this is popular because for your your
static resources if you send them off to
aqua or someone like that you know they
have they have data centers around the
world people your app should be able to
load a lot faster
so this is a pretty common way that
people though JavaScript but the problem
is that any code that you load in this
way it's going to all operate in the
global scope so now we're going to have
to come back to our problem where
JavaScript that we load from bing maps
could theoretically interfere with our
code a second technique is also if the
code is on the same domain you could
make an xhr fetch the code as a string
and then just eval this actually this
you can't even do in an immediate
function because when you call eval it's
either going to work in the the function
scope and which are calling it or in the
global scope either case it's not going
to work at this module scope that that
that we don't actually have yet but is
the type of thing that we want also just
as a as a minor in a problem with this
also the the JavaScript has to be on the
same domain so probably not usable with
the content delivery network and also it
can't be parsed as as it's downloaded so
it's not as fast to say when you loaded
something via via script tag and the
third option which is a little bit
better is to load the JavaScript in an
iframe and so if you load all the
JavaScript that you care about that you
want to be specific to your modules you
can create an iframe you could basically
create a new environment where all only
your javascript is loaded and it can
talk to each other and it's effectively
sandbox from from the other libraries
that you load in the top-level frame the
drawback to this is that it's just kind
of complicated and that when you do
things like load javascript in an iframe
when you refer to the document you're
referring it to that iframe and you're
not referring it into the page where
your application it most likely lives so
you have you so you can do something
like jiggering to keep the to make sure
that you use the right variable in the
right spot but it's pain and it could
also be error prone so of these three
solutions none of them are really
satisfying they all have drawbacks so
there fortunately there is a workaround
and we have and it involves using the
hated with keyword so this is a way this
technique works is that it's similar to
the immediate function but you wrap so
you wrap your code
in a function and what you do is
initially you create a scope so this
variable this is an object literal and
this is going to function basically as
the scope that we want to share between
all modules as as they are loaded and we
wrap our code in an immediate function
and inside that immediate function the
first thing the top-level thing is a
with block and it takes the the module
scope as an argument basically just so
that we can alias it to a short of local
variable so that in the page it's
something you know unusual or unlikely
to Clyde but inside our function we can
use a short name like a so we pass it in
and then we just do with that scope and
then we when we do assignments top-level
assignments like VAR i equals true
instead of doing VAR y equals true we do
at least the top-level assignments in
the cellular module code we assign them
directly on the on the object that we
are passing to with so you notice that
here the assignment is on is on a so
it's directly on the object the scope
object that we've passed in however once
you do that all your uses of that
variable don't need to be prefixed with
a anymore if you had to prefix it with a
everywhere this would be extremely
tedious but you actually don't have to
because what's happening is that when
this alert statement executes eyes goes
up the scope chain to get resolved and
it actually gets resolved on the object
that was passed passed to width which is
a or this module scope variable that we
created and so basically every other
every module that you load which you now
you can do via a script tag you have
basically this you have the exact same
thing as this except this declaration at
the top because this is going to be a
global that actually is shared and then
every every module we'll just call its
function and take and take module scope
and and pass it in so the one problem
that you might notice is that or your
complaint might be I don't really want
to write my code like this and I agree
that you shouldn't want shouldn't write
your code like that it'd be very tedious
it wouldn't be portable across different
different use cases and so fortunately
you don't have to so there's two
transformations that you need to do to
your code and i'll show you how to do
them with the closure compiler so
basically the two things that happen are
is that your function statements so
function f this style has to get
redefined into the function expression
style so this is the style that's you
know espoused in JavaScript of good
parts and other places but so some of
you may know that there actually is a
behavioral difference when you do this
type of trance transformation that has
to do only if you use function hoisting
and my experience that's usually not an
issue it's a feature of the language
that very few people use so this
transformation is basically fairly safe
and straightforward so this is the first
transformation that you have to do
basically different the function from
getting coy stood outside the with block
and the second transformation this one's
a little a little stranger so this this
part you need to make sure that all the
assignments are done on what it what
this shared scope variable is going to
be across your modules so so if you have
assignments so normally your code if
we're just VAR x and then y equals Z
equals 5 or and or another VAR
declaration where you're defining it in
terms of itself basically on the right
side normally if you just said VAR x you
wouldn't have to do an explicit
assignment on the right but in to use
this technique you need to assign it to
undefined because if this global scope
object a doesn't have a slot or a
property so to speak for X then when you
read it it's actually going to go
outside the with block so so basically
that's why all the initial all the
initializations are all the variables
top level variables in your module that
you're going to use have to be defined
or have some definition on the global
scope object so you can see here these
are the basic types of transformations
that you need to do is our chain our pre
fix things with whatever your you know
local variable that you're going to pass
to with is going to be so we can see we
assign X don't defined and we also find
eight like W to find that on a
find in terms of itself and now these
things will behave the same if if a is
passed in so again this would be very
tedious if you were expected to do all
this by hand fortunately this is where
the closure compiler comes in so if
you're not familiar with the closure
compiler is a whole whole whole program
optimizing compiler from google that
means it reads in the all of the code of
your program of your JavaScript and
compiles it all together at once so it
can do you know a whole program analysis
so it could find for a function it could
find all the call sites and that sort of
thing which is what part of what makes
this this technique possible so there's
there's two compiler passes that that
you need to run so basically these to
compile our passes take care of these
two transformations that need to be done
so you write your JavaScript as you
always normally would but this is just
an extra setting that you can enable
when you compile your JavaScript so this
this these passes have not been up
straight up streamed into the closure
compiler yet but that's that's in the
process I've built a build tool for
closure called plover and that's open
source its prevail on google code and it
has all the logic for these compiler
passes it's actually not that difficult
if someone wanted to port it to to
another another compiler perhaps most
interestingly most people are afraid is
that does this really work or is this
just some sort of toy exercise and
JavaScript transformations I can show
you assure you that it is not so I was
formerly at yext and it's a well and
there we built using a web applications
over a hundred thousand lines of code
had to run on ie6 and up we actually
carved our code up into 25 modules to
reduce the initial load size and let
people pick from the pieces that they
needed to and when using the application
to dynamically load modules and and
there were we did not witness any
problems using this technique so it is
definitely much more than a toy and has
been used at scale the one other
outstanding question is just that of
speed since most attractors from with
often claim that
it's going to adversely affect your your
runtime performance so I have not done
any sort of benchmarking yet however we
did not observe any any problems when
when running it yeah
I
Oh
hi
yeah I mean so so that's it so you said
100 times slower in a tight loop
okay yeah so I mean so that's and and
part of that problem though I would say
is that you know there's there's what
javascript interpreters do today and
then there's what we want them to be
able to do obviously recently things
like the eight we've seen interpreters
get a lot faster so I'm not really
certain if there's actually a
fundamental limit in with or really just
that people have not looked at
optimizing it very much yet obviously it
somewhat outcast in yes or is out are
outlawed by es5 script strict so
obviously that that makes it less
popular to work on yeah
yeah well I yeah so this technique is a
little different because it's using with
at the very top as opposed to very deep
in the AST so i'm not sure that many
people have been using it or looking at
it this way before but i could be wrong
about that
yeah well it's definitely worth
measuring to be to be certain but you
know telling other people it's still in
JavaScript and compared to say Dom
accesses or that sort of thing still
actually may be very cheap it's hard to
say without without actually testing it
out one is certain we differentiate
automated system
four bears over like the property
share pothole
these are way different
kind of like module context variables
and then strip these local like a bear
like hey I don't needs to be in the box
oh yeah yeah so I guess I don't really
demonstrate it here but the question was
you know our is this transformation done
for all very ductile erations or only
ones at the top level and so the answer
is that it's only done for ones at the
top level so inside a function scope you
don't need to do it in your life so you
got like 25 across your entire entire
occasion each one is it some closure you
don't need like opportunity you want a
very local
looked like all their options like can
you have my closure level variable right
in addition to module level barriers
yeah I think you can do that I don't
believe the way that the passes are
written right now do that because I
don't think they take what's called
cross code motion into account basically
code make it move co gets move to the
least common ancestor of where it's used
but i think that is definitely possible
that's true that would reduce the number
of aliases that you'd have to create
yeah it was good question though see
anyway there are any other questions
well I'm feeling questions okay so so
this is just to sum up this was actually
done by my colleague EXT American he he
basically we got stung by this this Bing
Maps problem and he tracked it down how
I mysteriously became three and it
turned out that this was so this
protected us from arbitrary third-party
modules but also we discovered that
there are certain web proxies that also
seemed to inject JavaScript into our
page we weren't really sure why that was
happening but this also protect adds
level of protection around that sort of
thing so I realized that because of all
the things that have been written about
within the past like it's it may be hard
to accept that this is actually a really
good solution to this type of problem
but I certainly encourage you to take a
look and I think that you know if we if
this becomes a more popular technique
than things can be optimized things that
are slow today or not not necessarily
going to be the things that are slow
tomorrow so I encourage you to take a
look at the code and contact me if you