good morning everyone let's start
talking about es6 the next version of
JavaScript and this is will be our
agenda today we will talk about some
basics and some of the main features how
to use in it today and talk about the
es6 rock project and they're not talking
about history because doesn't make any
sense today so actually the es6 spec is
about 700 pates so we don't have this
time so we have a lot of features and
try to cover some of the main features
before i start i am from Brazil and
Brazil is well now for the carnival
everyone knows we talk about Brazil we
think in carnival or you think about
football yeah it's a great joke thanks
for the both
I think Brazil is still being recognized
as the count of football I think so we
have this football in carnival but what
I want you to talk it we have a good
stuff in Brazil so I think you know
Sepultura Sepultura is one of the
greatest metal bands in the world and
I'm really proud that they are from
Brazil so we have this way we have great
stuff in Brazil if I have just Samba and
bossa nova we have great music so but we
also the country of our JavaScript here
is the conference we have per year in
Brazil we have almost 30 conference
JavaScript conference and front-end
technology conference and our company
community is pretty huge so let's talk
with let's start with the basics and
here's a funny thing in engineer 6 we
have this string that contains but this
week the spec change it so it doesn't
have any more distinct that contains now
the name is includes but why it's
because a string that contains will
break the web we think that contains not
web compatible because the community
figure out that mootools the popular
framework earlier popper framework have
this this method string that contains so
if we put a string that contains
natively in JavaScript will break a lot
of websites and so the specs change in
this a good thing because the tc39
the guys that are running the
specification are looking to the
community and looking to the problems
and now I have this now the method is
this string dot includes and we have
also string that starts with and swing
dots and we've there's new methods and
these three methods takes two arguments
it's a piece of string and we can
specify where you want to to start to a
JavaScript search so it's pretty basic
and we have string that repeat that is
pretty common in other language we just
specify how many times you want to
repeat the string keeping in context of
strings we have these templates drinks
now in JavaScript template strings are
string literals that allows embed
expressions and temperate strings
introduce these by this backtick grave
accent so we have now the single quote
double quote quote and this backtick and
here the the first example we have the
this just log in a temporary string
nothing different here and now we have
this mood line string until is e es5 we
are not allowed to do this so now with
templates week we can break the line and
we can have multi swings adults
concatenating and escaping and we can
actually do something more useful we can
construct a done query so we can use
this place holders inside of templates
drinks with the curly brackets and in
this example we are just defined some
variables the name and time and inside
of our 10 pallets drinks we can just use
it with the placeholders we don't need
to concatenate and we don't need an
extra library
to do such a thing we had another thing
integrating that is tagged at template
shrinks we can tag a template string
with a function and when we define this
function we takes to two arguments the
strings inside of templates drinks and
the valleys and then this not useful
example is I'm just looping through the
strings and then returning uppercase and
here's how to use it I'm just define
some variables and then I tag the
template string and now we have a
argentina and spanish argentinian
message no actually here is in in
english the next one is in Argentina
because with templates wings we can do
something like I etienne implementation
just define a current language and then
I i define the strings of my application
here I'm define the English message and
the Spanish Argentinian message and then
the implementation is pretty simple I'm
offline ok the difference here and look
to the strings and then we just pointing
to the object literal with the specific
language and this is how to use it I
have some variables and then I tag the
templates drink and bond we have now the
message in Spanish so you can you can
imagine a lot of things you can do with
templates ring this is a pretty pretty
simple example with I eating in moving
through four strings to numbers we have
a lot of things in numbers now in at six
one of the thing fun thing is we have
octo in binary literals so now you can
explicitly specify if you this number is
octo or if is binary this is pretty
useful
and we have this true matters is
finished and is not a number i think is
as well know the is not a number is well
no method in JavaScript actually we
already have these these methods but it
is in global scope and now they are
moving to the number object that make a
lot of sense and then they try to fix
some some issues if your your
application using a lot of math easier
if you are a hardcore programmer using a
lot of math you definitely check it out
all of the new methods in in math object
we have a bunch of new methods we have
also a lot of things in array object we
have a lot of methods like our hideout
from that i will show you a head off all
right fine phil and we can also super
class in an array but here in this
example I will show you I hate out from
that takes an array for another thing
like an iterator here is the Jays conf
website and then I'm just squaring the
dump looking through the today's
speakers and then I can specify a second
argument there is a map function and i'm
using an arrow function that we will see
later and then I'm just logging the HTML
we have a shorthand in objects if you
are a JavaScript programmer we probably
you you have this common situation where
we have a name the same name for the
properties so if you want to return or
created another object you need to
define the property and the valley even
if they are the same so with this object
literal shorthand if you have the same
name you can just put one you don't need
to specify the property and and the
value
also we have the structuring assignment
here is a way to define it's another way
to define variables here is using the
array pattern you can just define like
this and we have also the object pattern
that looks word but it works so about
the main features who have blog scope
you see I'm using lat in the other
examples block scope the difference for
lat and for VAR i don't know if that is
a replacement for VAR i think it is but
i see a lot of people saying that to
know that is not the replacement for VAR
but i think it is so let define a
variable in just the disco so in this
example I'm using great enough for loop
and this block I'm creating this J
variable so this J variable just exists
here in this block if I try to log
outside of this blocks will fail and we
have arrow functions that is well known
as lambda in other language like Python
I think C sharp and other language and
it looked like a dimebag flying v the
symbol so the error function is not
movable we we cannot make a new error
function that makes a lot of sense and
we doesn't have we don't have the
argument subject anymore in this error
function and this function is always
anonymous but and we have the DS binding
fix it and we know how here is how error
function works
a simple way so I'm creating this this
variable it's a function and then i
define the parent name and after the
arrow we have the return we don't need
to specify the return so it's a pretty
simple example in this constant dialogue
we will output 6 because i'm passing 5
and then here x 25 and then I after the
arrow X plus 1 will be 6 it's pretty
simple we can have more parameters so if
you have more parameters in an error
function we need to open and close the
parentheses and if you don't have
parameters you need to open and close
the parentheses like this and if your
arrow function will need some a lot of
codes you need to speak to you need a
body you need to open the curly brackets
like like this the main difference here
is that you need to return something
okay and here is the the classical issue
with the DS every every JavaScript
programmer know this this issue left if
we have a function inside a function and
it's right to to take the DS we lost the
reference for this so in this example we
will have this type error this the log
is not a function because here these
doesn't have the log-log methods so we
already have a way to fix the this issue
with es es five and here we just need to
wrap the function with parenthesis and
turn these into another function and
then we can call the bite methods when
you can pass to this but this is not a
yeah so in es6 we just use an arrow
function and then we never lost
this reference this is pretty good
grades classes class classes are
controversial because a lot of people
doesn't like classes in JavaScript don't
want classes in JavaScript but we have
classes in JavaScript now with es6 but
classes are just sugar syntax okay we
don't have any change in the core of the
language is just another way to do
something and how to use in class this
is a valid das six example a classical
example example we have the class
keyword we define a class animal and we
have the constructor and you have the
method here we it doesn't need to define
the function key words we just define
the method and we can extend a class and
we can use super so if you want to use
classes you can use if you don't want
you can keep with your peers on style
about modules modules is for me is one
of one of the most exciting features in
es6 but it's still changing we have the
module loader in another spec but it's
still one of the greatest features in
JavaScript so here's how to do it
creating a file bass is and i'm defining
a variable ok and then I'm just exports
what I want for this this module and we
have the keyword default that is if you
just have a single primary function we
can use the default in our module and
here is how to use in in our app we just
import this module and it works here i
am just defining a function and
return the function and here we can have
both named it exports and default
experts in a module and and we also can
import a module inside another module so
here you can see in this foo j s module
i'm importing another module and then i
can export the default foo that is a
single function but i can also export
and name it this this variable bar and
for for use in my application or in
another module I can just import the
name it with open and close the curly
brackets here's an example that I will
show you later how to use in modules
importing name it and default experts
and just using it and how to use in
today I'm using now the 65 projects 65
is a project that turns es6 code into a
Velde es5 code so why I'm using 625 and
not another transpiler like tracer from
google it's because 625 it's a pretty
active project on github I think the guy
that wrote the this library works a full
day in this 65 project and we don't need
any runtime we don't need extra library
for use in 625 so it's great and the
generated code is human readable you can
actually open the generated code and you
can understand what what has happened
and if you want to use modules with
kamoj is you can plug browser file and
you can known as grant or another go
pour broccoli or whatever you want for
so here is an example that is in my
github and I will try to
demonstrate
so here uncreated this grunt file that
just use 625 and use browserify and I
can run I can I don't know if you know
okay believe in me I'm running grant and
I specifying that I want you to convert
my modules to come on Jas i think is
commodious so i can use como eso I can
run with notes so here now run I'm in
the sample and come on fjs and then i
have my modules working with browserify
but if I want to use this in the browser
I can just serve the my folder
I can see the bar
so okay the thing is I can run the
modules and I can turn into comedy as
modules or AMD modules so I can run a
node which commonjs I can run in the
browser with comedy is using browserify
and I can run I can turn into AMG
asynchronous motors definition and I can
run if I want a synchronous motor
loading in the browser so here's the es6
super today and there's no bug in this
discharge yeah this is true internet
explorer is seventy percent of es6
implementation so we have firefox with
60 so we are almost there okay yes six
will be officially releasing amides 2015
and if you're using frameworks like
these popular frameworks they are also
moving to year 6 modules and another
year 6 features and here's a project
that i mentioned es6 rocks calm is a
weds website for spread the information
about es6 and today we are launching a
new version of es6 rocks so if you will
try yes 6 rocks com we have a beautiful
new website and last thing to build this
website i created armani key there is a
static site generator using es6 features
you need to check it out on github and
contribute and as it the here is my my