you
my name is Reed Burke I'm on the Yui
team at Yahoo I'm going to talk to you a
little bit about a project I'm working
on which involves using node.js for
something where it isn't accessory to
something and it's also not just nodejs
and just server-side JavaScript what I'm
working on is actually with the goal of
making client-side JavaScript both
easier to use for developers as well as
just way more performant and there could
be there could be a coexistence of these
two things using Yui loader so basically
we all agree that performance of web
apps is really important right but it's
way too hard it shouldn't be though so
what something with Yui that we've had
since the third version and made a part
of its core is that everything you
should only get what you need right you
shouldn't have to load the entire
library you shouldn't have to have all
this complexity of having everything on
your page and worrying about the
additional cost of parsing all this
stuff and downloading all this stuff and
everything so you use only what you need
with Yui and apps built with it can also
leverage the same kind of thing and
that's that's kind of the whole this
whole thing that we've had with Yui but
the problem with this and that it's it's
really good for the developer but it's
not so great for and we could probably
work on making developer tools better
for this and that I'll cover this in my
talk but whenever you find this you also
find dependency management so how do you
do that well one way is with the
configurator so what we had we've had
this configurator for a really long time
since Yui to back and why to how to
loader and the idea is that you know if
you want just certain parts you can put
this in here and it tells you all the
modules that you need and it gives you a
combo URL which most people in the room
would be familiar with it's basically
just concatenated that are used by by
what you what you need and then puts it
in one URL and so one way or another
you're doing this by either a build
script that's doing this or you're using
this service or you're hosting your own
combo like service or something right I
don't think this is the answer and so
the reason for this is that manually
updating a combo URL every time you
change something isn't scalable why
isn't it scalable well you think about
it your application isn't usually just
one page
you have a lot of different parts of
your website you know you may not have a
need an autocomplete widget on every
page you may not need to have a
scrollview on every page you may not
need your own component on every page
and so you want to be able to have your
templates or parts of your application
to just include what they need right and
that I don't think it's really easy and
if it's easy if you can do it it's it's
not that great for performance so this
is the easy API that Yui 3 gives you and
there's other I'm going to talk about
there's more than just Yui is not the
only library that does this there are
other ways to do it and you should be
using them and finding finding a way to
make it work but it's baked in and it's
it's scripts only have to tell the page
when it needs and so if you're using
something like this or making modules
with Yui or with something like required
at jas basically your your modules your
little JavaScript files that that do
implement specific bits of functionality
that's what defines what what's needed
on the page right so you could just
throw in the modules you want and they
can declare their own dependencies and
so that's something that's a really
great way to make an application and
it's what you guys should aspire to do
but it's not always perform it and
that's why we have people who are going
in and copy and pasting something out of
here or going in and actually you know
maybe you don't even have a nice tool
like this and you're just figuring out
how to combine this with shell scripts
or whatever and that isn't something I
think we should accept right we should
have an API that's this simple whether
it's Yui or not and it should be
something that that's also performing
and so again i want to i want to stress
that they're the reason why we use
modules and there's going to be two
great talks after mine that are going to
talk about javascript frameworks and
modules and you notice this is really
common the reason why we're doing this
is because it's you're delivering less
code it's only what your users need
right you're it's going to increase
performance because you're having less
code that's you're delivering even with
a fast connection you still need to
parse it that's especially significant
on mobile right even with fast
JavaScript fitting you know there's a
lot of competition with JavaScript
engines in browsers and that's great and
that is only going to continue but that
is an excuse
use the you know forgetting about
performance right it also manages
complexity so it makes things easier on
you so the problem is that yeah there
needs to be a way for things to be more
performant that's because with Yui 3 you
have the simple API but one running Yui
loader on a client side isn't free right
it actually takes it takes time it
doesn't take that long but it takes time
for these dependencies to be worked out
you also have to transfer all the
metadata about all the modules that
you're using on the page to the client
so that it knows about say when I asked
for YQL it knows that it needs some
module like Jason P it needs a module
like my order needs its sub modules or
what have you write as things that
requires and doing all that is expensive
even though you can cash we could we
could send things with far future
expires right like the for the module
metadata download and the Yui seed file
and all this parsing metadata and
calculating from it isn't cash and it
happens over and over one thing that
incidentally wasn't think that we were
trying to do to improve the performance
of Yui loader is actually take all that
metadata for say what the Yui library
and put it into some kind of local
storage mechanism and that didn't work
as well as we hoped because it turns out
that still taking it out of local
storage and then parsing this huge JSON
blob with everything that you would
possibly use takes about just as much
time as just doing the calculation with
with stuff that the way that we used to
and so basically we think we could do a
little bit better with this we think we
have an okay API and we could probably
even make tools for for you know making
modules that work with why I better as
well but you know in order to get there
we need to have a really good we don't
want to just say this is this makes it
easier on developers we want you guys to
have a reason to use it you know a
reason where it's not only just helps
you guys but it makes your website
faster and that's what I want to do with
my project I've we put Yui loader as a
web service and we call it why do I
loader server or why LS and so the first
thing this lets you do is you can you
could just pass it modules to load like
say if I want the drag drop module what
this is done is
I have this running locally and for Yui
3 30 it's just loading the drag drop
module and you can see at the it's
loading all of its dependencies that it
needs and drag drops at the very bottom
you can pass other things to this as
well so say I want to have the debug
version of this and you get that it's
just doing this on the fly this is
running a course in nodejs using why I
loader you could pass you know whatever
you want in the end of this so if I want
you could just passed a list right but
this isn't really what I came to talk
about this is kind of neat and that you
no longer have to go through i'm trying
to show the end of it but doesn't really
matter like this is this is all neat and
all let's see go back cool but there's a
better way and that's just using Yui use
okay so with with yls we kept the same
API right but we added extreme
performance to it but basically this
this extreme performance is on par with
something that where you'd have to go
through the painful way of using or
using your own build script or bye-bye
configurator or whatever and said you
could just have you know small
JavaScript files that that implement
pieces of functionality and actually
have them to clear the dependencies and
have it work just as well that's the
goal just as well as if you were doing
stuff the hard way and sort of sort of
downloading parsing and calculating
modded dependencies like we used to with
Yui we now ask why LS for them and so a
request would look something like this
right we give information about what
module you want yql what we have on the
page that's env right here and what we
have on the page is yui what version of
Yui and tests and I'll get into test in
a little bit but we think that feature
testing is very important and so what
we're doing is actually we're telling
the we're transferring state about what
tests have passed and failed on the
browser and actually transferring that
over to the server so it's very fast
because we don't have we're running this
calculation on the server and it's it's
it always winds up being faster than
what someone has especially if they're
on a phone
and you don't need to download and parse
module metadata like you did before but
the real win is the first one but this
is that this is the huge win this is
what's really exciting is that it's it's
whenever you go to the next page the
entire response has been cached so what
this means is that the first time anyone
visits some page on your website the
this URL right this this you are at the
bottom that's already been accessed if
it's if it's someone of the same browser
with the same test configuration it's
been it's been access it's cached it's
it's it's on a it's cached at least on
on yahoo side right or on the person
serving yls aside and so that means that
your other users will take advantage of
that and if it's if it's if it's the
person has visited the page and they're
getting that fast thing off of off of
the server cache that we have but then
it's in their browser cache no more
dependency calculation has to happen on
the client anymore and it never and
never did but now it doesn't have that
it's all local and you don't have to do
to go through any hoops to determine all
the modules here because that already
happened by that by that request being
available so right and the browser with
fire feature expires and then in the
server with its own caching layer that's
baked into the server not just yahoo
zone but the one that that's going to
ship with the open-source bit of it this
is personal so it's it's not just for
Yui the goal of the architecture the
system is that it can work with modules
that are outside of Yui while I gallery
two and three your own modules these all
should work really well and you should
be able to import them into this and use
them just like we can for Yui itself so
I want to give you a reason why I'm so
excited about this and so I want to show
you the speed difference right this is
this is you know something we try to do
by putting things in the local storage
and then getting them out and wasn't it
nearly as impressive so what I'm going
to show you is basically again I want to
reiterate that an initial page load is
is going to always be a little bit
faster since no metadata is download in
the server side JavaScript accolades
faster and everything but what I'm going
to show you is when you when someone
else's ran this once right when you
visited a page already the cost of Yui
loader right now continues to you
continue to have to do it calculate
dependencies even though
the combo URL is already cashed in the
browser so basically what I'm saying is
that no matter even though we can cash
responses coming back from the server
the thing is we still have to run this
JavaScript calculation as you navigate
around the page or navigate this to the
same page or if another visitor visits
they can't take advantage of this
calculation that already happened and so
what we've done is we've taken all these
instead of having you know 100 users
calculate this themselves we can now
have once you know one person do it and
so it's no slower than than it was
before right since it's the same thing
but just happening in one place and then
everyone takes advantage of it right and
so that's what I'm going to show you is
the difference between keeping it
keeping it everyone doing it versus
having it already done once and that's
that's the whole purpose of this thing
and so this is running on Chrome and
we're showing loading different various
combinations of stuff client side loader
versus why LS and it can vary as well so
this is just an example but it's always
faster sometimes dramatically so so if I
move this in a new actually a new
renderer actually winds up being even
faster this is actually even more
profound on mobile devices even with the
latest iOS we're seeing differences of
of things cut in half like nine hundred
milliseconds 150 milliseconds all the
way down to 450 the Wi-Fi here is
unfortunately I'm can't keep my phone on
it right now so but let me let me run
this in this again just to see how it
can fluctuate so yeah that's a little
bit faster and that's a lot faster this
is what the i just opened a new tab
that's only thing I did I've had the
presentation open for about a day so so
you can see it's this is what's really
exciting which we're comparing is 106
for this combination to 30 right 58 to
1444 243 and even in a less than ideal
situation that was still it was so odd
of being faster and so that's that's
pretty exciting and again with white
with the next version of Yui they'll
have this client side support in it
you'll be able to host this yourself and
hopefully even with your own modules
right but that's you won't need to
because we will provide this on our CDN
and that we do this already we have a
CDN combo
endler when you looked at Yui
configurator that's weird something we
host we're going to provide this on our
own CDN and it's just enabled with the
simple configuration flag so you just
tell say that you want to use this
feature and you get it when we're
building this this is some of the things
that we've we wanted to keep and
designing this kind of system I'm
running out of time so I'm going to go
through this really quick
capability-based loadings really
important so we have a excuse me a s we
have we wanted to transfer state over to
the to the server of all the things that
are on there so we transfer all these
tests and stuff that's already on the
page is sent as well like you saw
earlier and so this is kash friendly so
we don't this isn't a unique URL it's if
someone came with the same browser they
would get the same response we're using
this already in Yui library com we're
working to bring this to everyone some
other things to take away from this is
server side yui is what what I'm using
to do this it's already open source and
out there it allows why you out easily
run on node and really the loader part
of this is actually already open source
so what what's not is that is kind of
the tools and everything around it that
we're still working on scaling this
though as something I really want to
what want to show you guys is if you're
if you're working with anything that
involves an expensive javascript
computation javascript single-threaded
so when you're working with something
that's that that's blocking in
javascript that sort of requests will
pile up it's important to make sure that
you're doing the right thing so we did a
simple test of this on a machine with
two cores just to show you the
difference between running Yui loader in
the same instance of nodejs as a server
versus just putting it out in a separate
process than communicating with it over
a socket and the difference is huge so
what we're seeing is this is this is
running with two workers and this is
running with just everything in line but
with separated out the traditional
nodejs scaling way right which is just
to use spark to or cluster or something
like that for spawning different things
and this is the big part right so this
is performance we used to see taking up
to 33 or almost 4 seconds and now
everything is this nice low thing right
down here that's really nice so you want
to avoid blocking anything if you're
doing image processing working with
binary data stuff like this that can
block even if it's just for 50
milliseconds
you want to be very careful because
things will start queuing up outside of
outside of the stuff and that actually
causes memory to use it to explode like
really really bad explode on nodejs so
so we're using web workers by Peter
Grice and that's awesome library to use
again blowing through this stuff really
quick this isn't as interesting but what
I want to show you is this we this is
interesting just because we test the
different combinations and wasn't what
we expected instead of running one
master with 16 slaves we ran 16 Yui
workers we actually ran one master with
with a 16 masters with one Yui worker
and that wind up being most performant
because that's what you see down here in
green where we have this nice even when
we put it up to 400 requests per second
we still get a nice nice flat line with
this configuration right here that's
great and this is the improvement we
made from this is the in line when you
in line things it takes 1.2 seconds on
our production hardware to run to run a
two-run just all of the different tests
that we have with going all over
different configurations of modules
versus this green line which is running
things with with one web worker so that
makes a big difference so you want to
make sure you're doing that what you
don't see in this graph is memory to
which explodes which is not good if
you're using long if you're doing this
for the long run which I encourage you
to when you're writing node.js stuff
that you go through and stress tests
this stuff right you want to make sure
that you're using something like HTTP
proof and that's something that was
written by HP it's very old there's
papers written about it so you know that
that's the kind of thing you should be
using node the node load works really
well for first stuff that's you know
like I've used it for stuff that's 10 30
minutes but what I've actually noticed
is when I ran a 72-hour test with no
load I saw that my server performance
was just going through the floor and
turns out it wasn't my server it was
node load right so you want to make sure
that you're not you're not you know
giving yourself grief by by using tools
like that are for something they're not
meant for right note load works really
really well for and gives you a lot of
great data for small short test runs and
so another thing I want to go over
really quick is how what we're doing to
test why do I use to make sure that this
is really robust for the release that
we're going to do later this year of 340
is use
box I frames for unit testing which is
really useful for if you need to test
things that require a clean browser
environment feature on and this is on
the Yui gallery so I encourage you to
look more into that as well some things
would connect you if you're curious
about I'm almost out of time so if
you're curious about this kind of stuff
come and see me I would love to talk
more about it and Jalen's really nice
there's a node tool that I wrote for
jslint that's really nice pact is
something that I've used for testing
HTTP servers and it you could do it in a
really expressive way and I want to show
that really quick here so actually this
one no this one so let's see so this is
really nice so I could just write tons
of these things where I have with packed
i can just have the URL in it and just
have a topic thing as request this is
using the vows h oj s test framework and
it's really easy and this this kind of
extends off the last talked just because
you know i don't if i want to add a new
test it's really easy for me to do it
with packed and that's really helpful
and then annotated code i had that but i
didn't show it so right this is really
hard on the client side which is why
this isn't available yet but we're
hoping the next how few months to have
this out for you guys so something that
i think would be really interesting and
if any of you guys know people that work
on like required ijs or if you're doing
something like this yourself i would
love to talk to them because i think
this is a generic problem that we could
we could really have you know this
there's no reason why you'd have to use
Yui on the client side use a technology
like this right and so i would love to
have this be the way that you know to to
manage your applications javascript
dependencies a lot of possibilities here
so recap client-side module loading is
hard this this system hopefully makes
that easier and one size doesn't always
fit all like the traditional nodejs
scale and stuff didn't work for us so we
wanted to test it and if you guys are
more interested in that we've we are
hoping to have this replace eventually
place the ad the default way of using
Yui be using the system so it needs to
need to scale and so that's what that's
something that we're working on at Yahoo
so if you're interested in that please
come talk to me