hello so it's been quite a few days
already and it's the first time next
year I'm Jose conf which is amazing
because everybody thought I'm part of
the crowd already so my talk today after
I'd found all your computers here around
me with the Bonjour thing originally I
wanted to call it how to teach
JavaScript without sounding like a dick
but I didn't think it was a good idea so
I just called a community chairs
reloaded if you remember last year we
had Chris here on stage who talked about
he loved the pirate and damn the
privateers so he started to remind us
that as a community we're not quite
there yet we're not quite public people
don't see JavaScript developers as a
community much like we see you
excommunicate a community or the flash
community and we did some good things
about this and we changed it a bit and
that was good so first thing we did is
we did an operation cleanup where we
actually put badges on our own blocks
that linked to a documentation of
JavaScript on mdn to make sure that
certain websites that have bad
JavaScript information are not showing
up in google as the first results
anymore and well done we've worked
around that and we have a better thing
we actually went further with that and
we call these websites out on the
problems that they have with their
website so that was this w3c fools com
which actually showed all the errors
that are on w3 schools and allegedly
they are looking at that and actually
fixing the w3 schools as it is right now
so this is even better rather than
replacing something we didn't believe in
we're trying to fix something that is
out there and people use and find is the
first information piece and it's pretty
good that we managed to get there so
thank you thank you for doing that great
job everybody we really really go out
there and javascript is becoming more
understood by people as a technology
that runs the web and is therefore the
web and not something that should be
compiled into something else or you have
to ride a real
language to turn into JavaScript which
is always a fascinating approach a few
years ago so well done us so we now can
say great we've done it we have can pat
on back and say we've done something
great this is a real patent you could
look that up on the website it's a pat
on the back machine this is what we got
Peyton's for that's why it's good to get
Peyton so you can sue each other over
stuff like that challenges however are
they are there still we have new
challenges to face right now because we
have the old one of asthma being seen as
a community but we still are in a world
right now where Travis crypt is being
seen as something that is running
everything but the web is not quite
there the web is now in danger of being
something that has to change people say
it's not fast enough we don't have
access to things on Hardware the web is
dying some people said already and
you're like okay fair enough i heard
that several times but looking at
technology and looking at some of the
languages that other people use i'm
starting to think we have to ramp up a
bit and go out there and our challenges
the stuff that stops us from being
listened to and stops us from just
calling out that some of the things in
the press are wrong are actually all
homemade more or less and these are the
challenges we've got a lot of fanboyism
going on the meshing with other
communities is not working the way it
should be we quickly social skills is
something we normally have to work on
and sadly now if we don't because it's a
very well why should I change a passion
forget thing is going on and official
educational materials are painful then
there's a siren song of natives native
development like everybody like okay I
could do the web and learn about
everything around me or I can run an
iphone app and make millions of dollars
when I listen to TechCrunch that's how
you do it but sadly enough its lucky
enough it's not that way and tools are a
big problem to me as well so let's cover
the basics before we start doing
anything as a community what are the
things that we as the JavaScript web
community actually want to come from and
what did how did we learn it when it
became from
one of the things like view source wins
nobody here can tell me that they sat
down and they're in their kitchen with a
nice pipe and read a book about
JavaScript and started learning in from
scratch that way we looked at other
people's view source we copied and
pasted stuff hours until it broke and
then we read out why it broke then we
understood why there are the problems so
the view source is the main thing how
people get into what we're doing and the
view source doesn't only happen in the
browser it happens now on github it
happens on google code it happens on
whatever you wherever you put your code
in your in your in your blocks people
learn from what you do so it pains me
when I see new demos of cool new
technology to have really bad code and
really badly written code because people
learn bad mistakes from copying and
pasting collaboration wings of course
it's like you put things on github and
the day later somebody put something
cool out there and added something new
did you didn't think about and all the
stuff that I do my slides are all
creative commons my books are all all
the articles that I write a creative
comments so you can translate them into
other languages and people do that for
me so work together not be that one
guided does something and doesn't allow
people to add through the work they've
been writing and trial and error wins a
lot of times we throw things out and we
say it's awesome and then after three
comments on the blog we realize it's
actually not that awesome so stop
writing blog posts with one simple
example saying that's the best way of
doing it ever they're great
collaboration tools jsfiddle for example
is a wonderful thing that shows somebody
when they have a problem on an IRC
channel oh I it doesn't work in HTML you
can show them HTML Javascript and CSS in
one screen and an executable version of
that problem that it has and anybody can
fork that then in jsfiddle itself and
update it and fix it with you the other
day I asked for rotating headlines like
90 degrees rotated headlines in CSS that
also work in aid in older browsers and I
just pulled up on jsfiddle put it up on
twitter and like 20 people sent me
different versions of it and 50 minutes
later we had one that's now going into
the mdn documentation I could have done
that with on my blog and be awesome
would be the great blogger but in that
tool we just did it in 10 minutes
together in an afternoon on twitter and
you can all do that which brings me to
fanboyism and fanboys do something that
is actually a real problem to me because
we all have our why don't I go full
screen we all have our little things
that we like and everything else is not
as good and we shouldn't especially with
browsers working for Firefox I have so
many people coming up to me and the
first sentence is like oh I'm sorry I
use Chrome I'm like I'm not sorry for
you if you're happy with chrome fair
enough there's nothing sorry about it
you don't have to use the browser that I
work for you have to use a browser that
is modern and you have to update your
browser and when you find something
wrong with that browser you have to file
a bug about that problem then you then I
have no problem with it if you write
code that only works in one browser send
it out on the web and say like that's
the future that I'm sorry this is the
past this is what we did in 1997 that's
why we have these websites that only run
on 1990s an Internet Explorer and we do
the same thing right now with a lot of
WebKit demos and demos with experimental
stuff and said well of course it's
broken in other browsers because it's
experimental in this browser yeah then
write your code that it detects the
features and shows and if it doesn't
show it then show a video show the
people what the other browser that you
love actually can do with a video best
example canvas you do anything cool in
canvas make a screenshot of what you're
doing canvas and put it inside the
canvas element as the fall back not only
for people who don't have canvas but
also if somebody links that on facebook
that's the thumbnail so somebody sees
already what's happening in your canvas
thing before they go to it so love the
web this is the connectivity of the web
ended on this planet this is how many
people are connected and how fast they
are connected the how light it is is the
speed of it isn't that awesome is it
amazing why should I write things that
only work in one car
tree and a lot of native code das said
right now sorry you can't watch that
video because in America that is not the
web to me so we should fight these kind
of things we're a community that is
worldwide and talk to each other
worldwide in several languages we should
tell companies the same thing so www is
the World Wide Web never forget this
it's worldwide people with random
computers bad connectivity really old
browsers that cannot upgrade that don't
even know how to upgrade and they should
get something they should not get
everything you should not get the best
experience but it should get a
experienced you shouldn't block out
people so it's not we love WebKit and
it's not windows windows windows like
some companies tell us like oh look at
internet explorer 9 and 10 they're great
to use html5 or on windows XP sorry
about this you can buy a new operating
system then you get html5 as a community
we should say no this is not working I'm
sorry so you can't we have to fight ie6
and XP users every single day and we
should get some support in that as well
and it's not welcome Western world so if
something doesn't work in other
languages it will have to work in other
language slew sooner or later and I
don't see many talks about
internationalization in JavaScript
because there's a lot of stuff happening
there so stop following rock stars
that's another fanboyism that annoys me
like Oh Chris Hyneman said this Paul
Irish said that that pie said dad that
guy said that we make gimmick rock stars
out of developers and when you meet
these guys they're all down on the
ground they're all nice people they make
mistakes they make public mistakes so
don't just take verbatim of what
everything about everybody says what I
say what anybody else says become one of
those guys talk to us talk to other
people communicate over mdn over other
communities to become part of the band
and not just the one rock star that will
basically be in rehab in two years
because you just work too much meshing
with other communities there's a danger
to inbreeding
and this is an example this is a
JavaScript only community conference
great we talk to each other and get very
excited we release five different
libraries on every chase conf that never
get used in any product but it's awesome
this is innovation is great designers do
the same thing UX people do the same
thing symantec people do the same thing
we don't talk to each other if you look
at products that we build later on
though it's a mixture of skills you work
with designers to work with your ex
people you work with the semantic HTML
guys you work with the back end
developers and why why are we had
conferences on our own things and and
build things that only we are impressed
with rather than having talks with a
designer and a developer together look
what we built together and this is how
we worked with each other that's
something you can take back home so I
want all of you after this what you
learned here to infiltrate as much as
you can go to your ex meetups go to a
enterprise-level java architecture
meetups and just tap talk to them about
the cool stuff we've seen here because
if we don't do that we're going to be
this little geek group in the corner
that nobody cares about we now have to
spread the word out out of our community
into the world and that's very important
and its technology is always a pick and
mix it's never one technology I saw this
in the park in Poland I really liked it
I'm just kind of keep winning like
physics stuff like ooh it's wonderful so
this is the result it's basically took
canvas had some circles and rotated them
so I realized I do everything in
JavaScript cuz I'm a JavaScript guy and
then somebody you can rotate that in CSS
as well and I'm not okay so rotate in
CSS wrote ten thousand lines of years as
for every browser out that might or
might not support animation and I
thought why not actually mix the two so
if you look at the JavaScript of this
one I actually do the painting in canvas
but I do a rotation in in CSS when it's
available so i write out the CSS
animation only when it is available
because then i don't have to worry about
it the animation runs in the background
so i see a lot of talks about CSS
animation alone talks about javascript
animation not much mixing going on again
and this is what we should be doing use
browsers to their
they can do not what you like them to do
mostly so a little bit of respect for
other people is another very important
thing so whenever we release things as a
community and you have this great thing
with like a great imation in 3d and then
you look at the thing and all the
buttons are actually just like diffs
with a click handler on them and
somebody like me so I said okay how
about a keyboard user how about somebody
who can't see a blind user why don't you
use a button when there's a button
element and people say like well yeah it
doesn't matter that's only the HTML so
these people will not use our demos when
they don't apply to their rules so
partner with the designer partner with
with somebody who understands markup to
build really cool stuff together and you
see people like like Leia does that and
she's you see how good her stuff is I
can only do like nine cats in my slides
so there's part of a designer's and
others and stop selling our solution as
the only legit ones every community does
that PHP versus python vs Ruby Wells's
Java versus pearl yeah so did I mean
when you're small in there in it when
you work in a small agency you have to
jump from technology to technology all
the time so be at least aware of the
boundaries of what other people do
instead of saying like you should write
this in pies and I'm not going to take
it if you use it in PHP only or you
should do it in JavaScript I don't
understand what you're doing with your
stuff there which brings me to social
skills there's a big problem in the geek
community which is called well actually
and there's a really good blog post
about this linked from these slides who
already online that explains to us that
we always accumulate information we love
information that nobody else cares about
and they tell something interesting or a
tell a joke and we're like well actually
what you're saying is like we should be
doing this and that the interjection of
trying to force our knowledge on to
other people as eeks stops us from being
in meetings work where decisions are
being done that actually mean we have
eight more works 28 more works weeks to
do on something that could be one week
so think about before you intercept in
communications and also on our mailing
spreads and stuff like that I parties
douchebag isms and a lot of them are
actually being called all the time
when you start a sentence with in the
real world you lost because you're real
world is your own planet it's not like
anybody else's real world it's very
dangerous to start with that sentence
because it's very arrogant show me the
code don't talk about it another thing
like oh yeah well why would I commute to
communicate with you I just look at your
code thank you for before doing it by
the way but I don't understand care
about you at all good code explains
itself best example ever when you talk
about documentation yeah well everybody
understands my coat well if it has to
same knowledge as you have the same
experience in the same style of coding
yes it's probably you then that
understands your own code not the other
person that is very simple no need to
explain everybody knows this who's him
last talked earlier I went through her
slides with her and halfway through
she's like everybody knows this stuff
did you know everything in there no it's
the simplest things need explanations
over and over again because we forget
them we hunt after the new cool stuff we
don't explain the basics anymore go file
a bug another good thing like why should
I talk to you designers my favorite like
designers come to me and say like
Firefox looks like numnah okay well
go to a go to box Scylla and file a bug
like sending a designer to box Allah is
like not gonna get into anything nice so
stop that as well it's all on the wiki
like somewhere in the documentation we
have it just try to find it not a single
wiki engine I know has a search that
works they're all awful we fix that
later have you ever fix anything later
after you shipped it no you went to the
next project nobody needs that and you
know everybody right it's like there's
no use case when you haven't used it
because everybody else should be you and
if not it doesn't count and that never
worked before is another big thing that
we do all the time if we did this we
wouldn't have no choice we wouldn't have
CSS animations we wouldn't have anything
so nobody uses XY set nobody use
Internet Explorer what are you talking
about all my friends use chrome and
firefox yeah good friends I
all my friends were chrome and firefox
users but sadly enough there's people
out there still that haven't seen the
light or are not allowed to go to the
light that's what you get for using X Y
said you should have you should buy a
mac well you're homeless but you should
buy a Mac then you can show and you see
what I've been doing and my favorite I
will give you a script to you don't need
to worry about it have you ever
considered that and we done that so many
times people come to the office and
annoy us with something and a simple
task that doesn't work that doesn't work
we'll raju a bit of code you have a
button then depress it so you shut up
and you don't come back to me and that
way that person never learns and we're
the person that actually has to fix that
which is called patch and forget
libraries poly filter API so my we write
all these cool things to fix things and
the poly fields that layers talked about
are not the ones that I'm talking about
I'm talking about the ones that give web
sockets to Internet Explorer 6 and talk
to the ones that give 3d animations to
intermix for a 5 and the ones that
actually we touch input in somewhere and
say ok that's fixed now we don't worry
about it anymore we never test in these
old browsers we never see if these
things work and we just put the polyfill
or the API or the library somewhere and
then we never care about them and don't
fix them and don't upgrade them whereas
a new browser out because we're already
chasing the next library to build and we
do that all the time look at the
statistics of what shake very is in use
in the reel web jquery 10 has lots and
lots and lots of websites and nobody
upgrades even jquery although it's
Institute was linked to the slash recent
so if you offer a quick solution for
everything people love you they're like
out great i don't have to worry about it
but that geek friend of mine that gave
me that polyfill i put it in the page
and now everything rotates in 3d awesome
they also expected to maintain that for
eternity because if something breaks
they don't know what's going on they
just come back to you five years later
and sent you an email oh my company
website that sells are no sweaters for
budgies actually doesn't work right now
because of your script that you've
written eight years ago can you please
fix that for me cause it's holding me
back and if your patch becomes an issue
than other people wrote a patch on top
of it so I've seen libraries that extend
other libraries to fix around issues
rather than fixing the original library
go into the core
that one and it's not really useful on
all because we patch and shift and
release release release without looking
at it actually so educational material
the joy of tech editing I'm just writing
a book right now I'm tech editing a book
right out as in use in every University
in every high school in America they
make truckloads of money with that book
and it's basically by the thousands it
gets ordered because in order for seven
years and it's been seen as good cause
material the event handler chapter had
as an example a table that got generated
with 10,000 table cells and a mouse a
mouse move handler on each of them in
line that allows you to either color
them with blue or red depending on shift
or ctrl key that you pressed the video
chapter or as HTML 5 1 now the video
chapter shows a video of a game of craps
what the rules are and rides a game of
craps that was written in that in
javascript in 1997 this is the stuff
that people learn in universities this
is the stuff that they get graded on
they don't want to learn it they just
have to get the grade so they have to
read that stuff so I hope that the book
is a bit better now but this is the
things where we are so ask the people in
a no that's called universities let's
offer guest lectures let's go to
university conferences and tell people
this is not what you teach the folk out
there this is what we should be teaching
them is what the market wants and this
is what we have to learn every engineer
that I hire I have to re-educate for the
first half year how is that useful how
is that sensible it does it shouldn't
have to be that way and let's bring the
enterprise and universities up to speed
I just spoke at a Java conference Java
Enterprise conference everybody in a
suit don't know what I did there but I
talked about new technologies people
came up to me I now have video
conferences with s AP and a few other
big companies about these new
technologies and they have to learn
about a date they have to hear what we
have to say we can talk to each other
but we're not going to have an impact
because we have to use their room
booking systems and their ticketing
systems and all that crap that they put
on the web desk gold there you can make
money with this look at think vitamin
code school and code cat
me which is a very hard to pronounce
name it's a very cool website so these
are all video tutorial websites that do
five minute of video tutorials on things
that we considered extremely easy and
everybody knows and they are really
really successful with that they're
making money with that some of them are
incredibly bad as well and they could
feed back then from me mostly but think
rittiman for example had a PHP primer
that told you in like five lines how to
get your server hacked because it was
like passwords not even in a text file
not encrypted no filtering was wonderful
now native things show you it's wrote a
blog post that web technologies need an
owner that only technology is good when
it has one owner Apple is only
successful because they control the
hardware and software and control
everything that's why they're awesome is
the web doomed is it doomed let's
discuss that with him I don't think so
so taking action on these points web
intents you saw yesterday something we
really need I really really want to have
web applications then can just say I
want to have a photo I don't care what
photo sharing service you use you can
use the stuff that you have in my web
application rather than going to Flickr
where you have no photos or going to
picasa where you have no photos puto
gecko is mozillas thing right now well
we want to build an operating system
that runs on mobile devices that is
completely open because we all have
mobile devices none of them are open
android is open ish but the hardware is
still not ours we don't know what's
going on in there we don't have access
to it so we're trying to work work
around that open web apps and I'm
talking at future web apps tomorrow
actually about this is web apps that can
actually use the web and can be
installed from any website and then
dragged onto your desktop and send to
your mobile phone that's something else
we're working on web api switches api's
that are in boot to gecko de allows you
to access the camera or the
accelerometer all these code stuff that
the native kids use and we're not
allowed to use somehow and browser ID is
a way to actually log in into a web
sites and into web applications without
having to use a password because the
password is stored much like open ID in
a secret with you and you can take your
identity with you throughout the web we
have full screen API we have
notifications API we've got context
menus in the browser that's what I'm
working on right now in a few demos to
right-click and have a context menu to
do things that real applications do we
don't have sudden browsers yet but it's
coming which brings me to tools we have
a few talks about that already and I
think the thing about tools is that a
lot of the things that came in the last
few years taught people how to build for
websites because the tools in the
browser's were better let's talk about
this one quickly adobe muse anybody seen
that adobe released a
what-you-see-is-what-you-get editor that
is new and cool and creates html5 ish
things and everybody was in a tizzy and
and basically had a good laugh about it
and said like oh my God look at that
code that's awful and why do you do and
the question is why do they do why does
a company like Adobe who is not stupid
who made software tools for years and
years and years really good ones why do
they think 2011 is a good year to
release and what you see is what you get
editor when we've been telling the world
for years that web technologies are easy
and HTML is easy and see us as it's easy
and javascript is easy you don't need a
tool to paint and what you see is what
you get editor on the web is the most
stupid thing you can ever think of
because the power of the web is that
your web application your websites your
web your app can actually change
according to what the end user uses we
can give people the best experience in
all in their environments rather than
one experience for all so the whole
concept of what you see is what you get
is broken but adobe still had the idea
there's a market out there people need
this so we failed at reaching a lot of
people with these things that are so
simple and everybody knows debugging
tools are a big thing Firebug I think
was the main thing that made us as a
community starts to build things much
much better before they're with alerts
in the page and like we did not know
what's going on why does that thing not
green why is it blue what is that layout
doing you're right click did you looked
at it and it worked out Firebug is
getting old it's also slow it's actually
a it's maintained still we have a full
person on it a full-time person on it
but it's it's one of the main things
that people complain about
so to me developer tools that we have
right now are much more than debugging
so it's great that we have wonderful
IDEs but wouldn't it be awesome if we
just in the browser can start editing
and understanding things and
understanding what's going on there and
start fiddling with the page and having
fun with it so here's a preview of the
stuff that's coming in the next
Firefox's there's actually a demo game
GT you can download so this is now the
the picker the the element picker that
we had before so instead of
right-clicking in the HTML having the
blue and green bars that fall over all
the time when you move your mouse you
don't pick it anymore you have a real
animation thing going on here you've got
you've got some breadcrumbs to navigate
through the Dom to make people
understand it block the Dom in the page
is more less like a file system on your
computer as well we have a style
inspector which I'm not going to go into
much it's basically give you the same
things here and you can do the styles
what's really cool is that with with the
style editor you can start styling a
document life in the browser and saving
it back to your hard drive I always use
the web toolbar for that I always wrote
my sister styles and they are copied and
pasted in safe to them to my hard drive
put it up on ftp so that's now coming in
the browser and you can actually edit
that you see it transitions from one to
another so showing people some cool gear
CSS stuff just use that don't write any
slides to do it or that you have to do
there okay we went overboard with a 3d
display of your document that actually
is using the accelerometer of your
computer as well so you can actually it
shows the dome as a three-deep you and
you can actually fly through your
website right now but in a music
it actually Souls you when your
navigation is 40 levels deep that is a
idea so that is pretty good about
this so this would use his WebGL as well
and the web console is the same as we
have a fire before so you can
actually do all the alert stuff the
warning stuff and all the things that
you expected but actually getting much
better now because you can filter things
down that is already in the life Firefox
right now in browser scratchpad fair
enough you can write JavaScript you can
put it in the page why can't you trust a
bit of JavaScript in the console you can
do that but it comes really unreadable
so we put a scratch pad in that it
allows you to actually build things in
the browser itself and what you can do
with it and there's colors here as well
you can also highlight lines and I say
only execute those lines in the document
right now so you can debug bit by bit
without having to comment it out like we
did in the past or go through a hard to
understand debugger with like with like
stock points and these kind of things so
you can highlight parts of it and run
them in there as well source mapping now
this is really cool this is not coming
that soon fun let's write some coffee
script and have some JavaScript
generated from it and we have an error
in both of them and once we have the
error and it actually runs and we see
there was an error going on in the tools
it tells me that there's something went
wrong I haven't seen the video much yet
so i'm waiting a bit here so I tias
knowledge the era India and if I click
on the error message right now on this
thing it shows me two lines it shows
with JavaScript and shows me a coffee
script so I can click on that and
directly edit the coffee script without
having to realize that the javascript
error is somewhere in the generated code
and this is exactly what I want
and of course as is a geek tool all of
these things have a command line in
itself so you can turn on and turn off
all the things with different commands
if you don't want to use your mouse at
all so you can highlight nodes by giving
it a have using a highlight f function
and all these kind of things so I always
remember one thing that mediocre teacher
tells i can tell you cool a good
teacher explains why it is a superior
teacher demonstrate all of what i can do
a can live code for an hour you can't
follow it you won't have anything from
it but I'm and I awesome the great
teacher inspires so with tools in the
browser showing people what's going on
with us talking to developers and
designers and people we don't want to
talk about we have a chance that we
could listen to it but not this geek
community that does their own events and
actually only talks to it to themselves
that's all I have the slides are online