so I wanted to talk today a little bit
about a proposal that I've been working
on sort of to hopefully give us a better
Dom API to work with in the browser
I've been working with different browser
vendors I've been working with Mozilla
the Internet Explorer team I've been and
I've been talking with the w3c about
coming up with a good API that we can
all work with so with the core of my
proposal centers around is the build
list no list is a highly underused
object in java javascript in the dom
right now you can get a no list in a
couple of ways you can get a no list but
if you want to do child nodes for
example child nodes will give you a no
list if you do get elements by tag name
that will give you a no list query
selector all I'll give you a no list and
all these no lists have sort of
different states some node lists or
static in that they're just they just
don't change like if you if you do query
selector all you'll just get back
spectively a glorified array that isn't
an array it's much less useful than an
array and that's not changing but if you
do get elements by tag name that's also
no list but it's updated live every
single time a new for example div comes
into the page that node list gets
updated dynamically there's also the
concept of HTML collection it's in it's
in a it was in the current specification
but it's also on html5 and it's not
really clear why htmlcollection exists
since it is just an old list but so we
have this kind of you know bastard child
existing here that really should be
killed off or something but anyway so
what I wanted to do is take this concept
of a know list which is kind
neutered right now it doesn't really
like I said it's a sort of an array that
doesn't really have any meat to it and
make it actually useful part of dom the
reason why i wanted to do this is that
this concept of that you see in a lot of
frameworks now it's a thing sort of
originated by what we did in jquery
originally which is effectively instead
of operation instead of operating on a
single element at a time
you operate simultaneously against sets
of elements and as it stands right now
the browser doesn't really provide a
mechanism for doing that so i wanted to
provide some abilities to make that
possible to start i i'm introducing a
new method called a create node list and
create no list of works are like create
element and other functions of that
nature and you can pass in an array of
nodes an object essentially any object
that kind of looks like an array of
nodes so you can pass in for example you
could pass them down and it would it
would understand it and turn that into a
node list as the output now effectively
what I define a know list as because
since up until this point there has been
no no definition of what a no list
should be it's just sort of this kind of
mysterious sort of list so what I say is
that a no list is you know has has these
properties for each individual node
that's contained in the in this
container has a length additionally all
the nodes are guaranteed to be in
document order so if you have a whole
bunch of elements in it they're all they
will always come out sorted in the
correct order in which they're in the
document additionally there will be no
duplicates so if you if you had multiple
if you if you passed in multiple
document bodies for example you would
only get one body back so this is sort
of set the ground rules I mean this is
this is pretty standard in that all the
all the node lists that you get right
now and
have these properties you know that they
work like this they all come back in
document order and they have no
duplicates so I just wanted to maintain
that state but the where the really
interesting stuff comes in is if if we
have this know list
that's coming from get on with my tag
name Korea selector etc and we have the
ability to create custom no lists we it
becomes really useful to be able to
extend then don't list prototype so
effectively when my proposal centers
around is extending the no list
prototype with a whole bunch of really
useful functionality that we can use in
web applications additionally if we
don't end up killing off HTML collection
we should make HTML collection and hear
it from note list because right now
they're kind of two separate things that
don't really inherit from each other
it's all really weird but but again I
think a channel collection should just
die so will you see HTML collection come
up is if you do like uh dot children
it's all from there like the old Dom
zero days like if you do document dot
forms document dot links you know stuff
like that that no one ever uses anymore
when some like crazy legacy apps but
that's all HTML collection so one of the
things that's really easy to implement
is is a training like functionality and
one of the concepts the way you get a
chaining like thing is that on the no
less prototype you introduce a create
note list method so that means from any
note from any note list you can do
another you can create another know list
and when you do that the parent node
will always point back to where it came
from so just as an example here so this
isn't it doesn't work right now but just
to show you as how it would work so for
example if you did if you've got the
child nodes and uh from the body element
and you asked for its parent node you
would get back to where it came from
so you so any know list that you get you
can always go back to where from from
whence it came so additionally for
example if you did
query selector all and then you did a
query selector all on the results set on
the no list you could always get back to
that original uh no list again so this
way you can very easily traverse through
these result sets and again so this is
something that doesn't work it yet but
I've something I'm proposing
additionally on the so some of the
things I want to see on the node list
prototype or a whole bunch of array
methods there are bunch of things that
would be very very useful to be able to
use against no list so for example
different ways different ways of looping
so like if you only have like a for each
map filter all of those and and some of
the default built-in array methods like
sliced concat things of that nature
now all some of these like sliced concat
map and yeah there's a yeah slice can
catnap and filter will all return new
node lists as a result since they all
modified the node list in some way so
for example we said a query selector
home you know find all the divs and then
you know we map it so a map for each and
that and you have to come from that's
been a Firefox now for quite some time
and it's in a part of a construct five
so here we get me to say um give us all
the parent nodes of all the divs for
example so that's this is a an operation
that can't be achieved through normal
CSS traversal but it's something that we
could do using the power of JavaScript
okay so there's a whole bunch of
different methods that I want to
introduce and all these methods
typically end up what I say is then a
bleeding through to the elements
themselves so just as an example you
have traversal
so I showed an example of it so for
example if you do similar to what I
showed before so you could say get
elements by tag name and then say get
elements class name so I mean you get
you could effectively chain these
operations together because it doesn't
really make sense now because what
happens now is that were restricted to
using these methods only on either the
document or on an element and or in the
case of the query selector a document
fragment when it makes a lot of sense to
be able to use them against sets of
elements simultaneously so in this way
what we be doing is finding all the divs
that are on the page and then finding
all the elements the test class name in
that are in all these divs and so what
would be happening internally is that it
would be concatenated all these result
sets together and then returning one
unified know list back as a result so
again like each of these are going to be
returning no lists again and again like
the note list will have for example the
parent node which is pointing back to
the array of divs
sorry the no list of those so I propose
that we bring over a crea selector all I
also have some proposals for fixing the
selectors API because right now the
selectors API has a lot of mixed missing
functionality in it included including
there's one there's one that I proposed
to scoped query selector all
additionally a matress selector so being
able to say you know do these elements
match this particular selector and
additionally a filter selector so being
able to take a set and reduce it down to
a small or no list that matches a
particular selector so the parent
of analyst points to denote list that
responded yes Kevin this is just me I
mean it's I mean if if you uh I mean the
thing is that I okay yeah
something else to set a parent node yes
like parent is like I think of like like
I think of like a nose actually
paramedic Dom tree Trenton if you're
trying to like if in all these other
places we're trying to offend with your
mister seems like like that's that's
like when you're calling a parent over I
mean the reason why I late a parent node
in particular I mean there's nothing
semantically wrong with it and at least
in the fact that it is a parent node it
is still a node but the thing is that
it's you know it's it's giving you the
ability to you know to traverse through
much of the same way that you would
traverse through in the normal Dom tree
so I mean cuz theoretically if you
Traverse back far enough
if you said parent node parent node that
would give you document so you would be
able to you would be able to get back
from where you came originally either
way you did it
yeah it sounds singular okay all right
it's not a huge issue in either way but
um okay yeah all right so additionally I
want to make it so that if you call any
of the base methods provided in in the
Dom so if you call you know appendchild
remove child any of those you know
insert before anything that can take a
dom node can also take a node list so
for example you can say append child
know list and it'll insert every single
one of those elements you no longer have
to loop through each individual element
append each one it much in the same way
that document fragments work with the
document fragment you can insert the
fragment wholesale but it works in the
same way you can insert a know list a
wholesale so again so anything that can
take a Dom node append child remove
child everything also this it should
also implement the event interface so if
you do add event list or remove masoor
dispatch of them all of those will bleed
through to the actual Romans themselves
so if you say add event listener click
it'll added each individual element in
the node list now the peers where things
start to get really interesting so since
we have this nice API for encapsulating
all this functionality we can actually
solve a whole bunch of really hard
problems namely there's two problems
that I think are particularly
interesting one is the problem of having
mutation events and also the problem of
good Dom security so if we so in the
case of mutation events for example
right now we browsers say some browsers
implement mutation events which allow
you to listen to a particular point in
the Dom tree
wait and see like when an attribute has
been modified in an element or when an
element has been inserted or removed
from the page it's all really slow and
because the problem is is that it's all
synchronous so like for example if you
if you in if you have to go through an
insert in 500 divs that's gonna trigger
500 events and each one there's gonna be
on each individual element it's a
fantastically slow and because the
browser's can't delay it there's no way
for them to optimize it so there was a
proposal there was a number of holes uh
that came out to try and fix mutation
events there's a page in the w3c site
where all the browser vendors proposed
made different proposals the only one I
felt that had some merit was one
proposed by the IE team and I didn't
like the the particulars but the one
thing I did like is that these the the
main change that they made was that they
made it asynchronous there is no longer
guarantee that the mutation events will
occur synchronously so I take that
concept and apply it here so what
happens is there's so at least in my
proposal like if you do create no list
for example the result that's coming
back from that will always be static the
live load live no list to begin with are
really kind of crazy I think every
browser vendor would appreciate if live
no list this didn't exist since it would
make things a whole lot faster it
wouldn't have to maintain trying to
maintain this day all over the place so
the way I counteract the existence of
these live no lists is there's a new
query method so for example here make it
a little bit bigger
all right so so for example here we do
this is example I used earlier so we do
Priya sector all day if we find all the
divs in the page and that we do a map
and we get all that all the parents of
those divs so again this is this is a
selector that this is a traversal that
you can't normally do with it's just
plain CSS this is something that you can
only do through script so then later on
in your code the pages obviously been
updated some new dibs that come into the
page or some some devs have been moved
around and they now have new parents you
want to get the current result set so
all you have to do is say a parent stock
query and this returns and the new
result set the new known list based upon
the previous results so the way it works
is it actually it goes back up through
the tree so each individual method that
modifies the state you know that
modifies to no less that returns a new
node list so for example here creator
selector all is modified such that any
at any point it's possible to go back
and we query again yeah so we could just
say if we do a very crew something like
this we say odd divs and then we can do
like we do an interval and then every 13
milliseconds you know we query and do
something on those divs and and this
will give us the new result set and all
we query those results so in the same
way what's that modify those it returns
a new one it does not modify so that
that's a bit that's a big thing is that
none of the methods that I proposed and
modify the list itself it's it's not
immutable but at least that's just good
practice there's not not - I think
that's what like one of the things that
was that's was done very wrong like we
have like dot reverse for example in the
array API and that modifies and like
just stuff like that that this was just
wrong okay so we can do the query so not
only does the query we run the previous
sector all but also we runs
map again and anything else you've
you've changed along the way so in this
way you can get you can always get the
new result set and when you run the
query you don't have to know what those
original steps were to get the result
result
yes yeah that's exactly what it's doing
internally is that you know internally
all what it's doing is saying it goes
back to this step it goes back to the
map step and it says do you have a
parent that can be query okay go to the
parent first then it says do you have a
parent that you need query is this no it
runs this query then it goes back down
again so it's recursive in that way so
but the nice thing so now we have a way
to we query a result set we can add in
events so we can add in an added and
removed event to the know list itself so
we can say okay when something has been
added to the know list or removed from
the node list but it's not it's not
limited to just just the elements or our
CSS selectors you can have complex
things like functions that can be
running and manipulating the state in
that way you know maps or filters or
things of that nature so what you can do
is you can you can effectively reproduce
live events yeah you know um so you can
say alright we're psyched or I'll find
all the divs set a class on them and
then when new ones are added set a class
in them so this is going to set a class
on all the divs under page now and all
the divs that ever will be in the page
and so and then here's the
implementation of live events it's like
three lines so if you say dot live you
pass in a function and it runs against
all current elements and all future
elements so I don't I don't think this
would be a good thing to land and the
and the first iteration API but it'd be
some deputies so easy to write like any
framework that wants to extend this API
can totally write it okay so building a
then so this is something that can
provide a great deal of flexibility
something that isn't capable right now
with like delegation for example the
delegation you're you you're restricted
to only working with events whereas with
this case you can work with anything you
know modifying classes or or what have
you so the next thing is the next thing
the huge advantage here is security so
I've been talking with Alec Rockford
about this and what's really nice about
this particular API style is that it's
really easy to secure
and what I mean by secure is that right
now within the Dom anytime you have
access to a Dom element you can walk
straight back up the tree get to the
window and wreak havoc you can you can
do whatever you want and call well I
mean that the typical example is you
call an alert and you're you know you're
home home free but I'm introducing a new
method called secure and what that does
is if you run it on a know list it
returns a new know list that is
completely locked down and it's locked
out in some very critical ways and that
nodes are no longer accessible on the
nose noblesse itself so if you say no
list item at item zero it's just gonna
be nothing there's none defined
additionally but but but that's okay
because all the nodes are gonna be
encapsulated within the no list itself
so all the nodes will be there and so
like you could call like dot remove or
or any of the other methods that exist
but without having to access but without
exposing the actual Dom nodes so just as
a example here so if we call a previous
lecture on some widget and we you return
a secured version of that element of
that node list for example so if you try
to call parent node or a parent node
list that will return null if you try to
walk back up the tree take a break out
that will return the empty no lists try
to access first element that will return
undefined you try to loop through to get
to the elements each the elements will
be null but what's nice is that even
even though it looked it looks like it's
crippled like this you can still say you
can still say all right nodes query
selector all did that foo then you could
call Leon like append you know some
stuff you know or you know like you can
still perform Dom operations against it
but without exposing to the user that
that dangerous path of being able to
walk back up the tree to get to the
window so again like this is this is a
Dom API that that continues that
specifically obscures that particular
way out yes what happens
so you've got that like appendchild here
right seven kinda funny though this
we've got at the appendchild method oh
yeah so one thing that has so we're I
talked about some of those yeah um yeah
okay so what happens when say you give
it an argument I mean obviously this
this will be incorrect but if you say
something like we've got another ski
call appendchild
document dot create element yeah you
created one div whereas you might think
you could anyone do for every item in
the list you're really just creating one
div and depending it over and over to a
collection so the one thing that
obviously that'll have to be worked out
but the the way at least we we solve it
at the moment at least in jQuery for
example is that we clone the the first
one's the real insertion of then the
second through and ones are clones of
the original
you can append to okay so to clarify it
so there's did presumably so there's
there's a separate sort of API here that
I didn't mention which is the ability to
create dom nodes but not through the
traditional create element means because
like right now we don't have like there
isn't an api specified for doing you
know HTML to dock to dom fragment and
like that needs to exist and like any of
these methods should be able to take a
string HTML string and be able to still
work so in the case so this is to
clarify what you're saying you wouldn't
be able to call document.createelement
in this secured environment in this
theoretical secured environment some
because you want to have access the
document to begin with some of you guys
if you did then what's the point of
having it be secured your are you
already free so one thing i want to
mention real quick so these so these are
the things that i haven't I haven't
completely specified yet but it doesn't
really matter since their implementation
isn't critical like all like the
implementation for these are like two or
three lines per item it's not massive
when I considered to be the critical
part is getting this good initial API
out that we can build off of and in at
least getting this specified and in
browsers so that we can extend it and
build better API and then so one last
thing that I wanted to mention because I
think I'm out of time here is that in
order what when I'm so I'm working on
this and again I'm working with you know
Mozilla ie
and the w3c is I'm working on
implementation
that's pure JavaScript implementation
that implements the full API and a full
test suite to go along with it so for
example here's history I'm over five
hundred tests at the moment and I'm just
trucking along and adding more and more
tests to prove that this not not only
were
but it's actually feasible and works in
current browsers so hopefully while
we're waiting for browser vendors to
implemented which hopefully shouldn't be
that long we can actually use it in the
interim so any questions really quick
before I have to secede to the next
person it's now published I'm publishing
this month it will be up at I'll be
publishing it a couple places yeah so at
least my goal is to is this month to
finish to finish the test suite and
implementation and publish those and
then work with Doug's duck shoppers over
at the w3c and work on a draft of the
recommendation so the endlichs Amaury
i'm already communicating with the IE
team and the Missoula team on
implementations but I'm hoping at the
very least that having a test suite and
a sample invitation should be enough to
get them off the ground and towards
implementing a pending
to document um
I mean I'd imagine that internally it
would probably work similarly to a
document fragment but it's a little bit
different in that like like for example
if you call clone node on a document
fragment that clones the document
fragment and incidentally the contents
of that fragment
whereas what I'm proposing is more it's
everything just passes through so if you
were to theoretically clone the no list
you wouldn't be cloning the nola you'd
be cloning the contents of the node list
so another question
so it's impacting in some way so I'm I'm
deprecating some things in jQuery that
just should hope to help but get us
towards a because I guess there should
be a much more pure implementation I'm
also very interested in being able to do
that the thing that I mentioned the dot
query like being able to wreak weary
state like we don't have that right now
in core but that seems like something
that'd be really cool I'm really useful
so that's something I'm also interested
in I know I have a deprecation page
somewhere that's up an ether pad so yeah
I don't know if that's still there yeah
so I've been collecting things that I
want to deprecated but anyway so yeah I
think some of these are related to this
the API that I'm working on other
questions oh yeah if you have any
questions proof proofread uh hump me
down and I'll be able to answer them as