how many builders in the room right
builders holy Sh as love okay so how
many how many breakers okay now how many
people do its security of for a living
here is there any other security people
in the room yeah this is what it feels
like to be a tacit a developer
conference as a security person this is
really exciting so I'm going to talk
about it's broken I didn't do that
all right that was great unexpected so
I'm going to talk on builders versus
breakers if anyone is a scared of scared
of talking about feelings please leave
now it's a non-technical talk if you're
looking for live coding it's elsewhere
if you're looking for 0 days that's
elsewhere we're going to talk about
builders versus breakers hi everybody
I'm Adam you can find me on Twitter Adam
underscore Baldwin lift security node
security and github as evil packet I am
the CSO a chief security officer as well
as the chief of software operations for
and yet and I am the team lead at lift
security and yet sort of project so that
puts me a builder on one hand and braker
on the other and wedges me firmly in
between these these two communities and
it's the topic of builders versus
breakers has has tormented me for a
number of years in my career and I
didn't realize that first it sort of
snuck up on me and I I approached
approached things as a typical breaker
would I only looked at my perspective
early on in security i looked at in my
perspective of of how I thought of
security problems and how I approach
them and so what I'm going to talk about
today is basically all the things that I
screwed up as a breaker and try to give
the builders a perspective of that and
hopefully we'll come away from it
understanding a little bit more of both
the Builder perspective and the breaker
perspective and how we can both actually
work better together by understanding
each other a little bit more and again
through my failures and then through
some just ideas that I have so how many
of you have you've met a lot of a lot of
people at the conference right a lot of
new people is
anyone walked up to you and said hey uh
that shirt yeah that that not sure that
hat doesn't really work on you you
should you should you should wear it a
different hat it is better shape for
your head and for your face right nope
nobody walks up to you and introduces
themselves that way right thats thats
tends to be how security people do it
how breakers do it we this is how i met
adam brault the the founder of an yet
five years ago and this is when this is
when the start of my thinking about this
topic sort of started i sent him an
email and i said fix your capture so the
values and actually in the form it was
insecure put the site put it in the
session and check the post here's a
mutual friend of ours that's how i
introduce myself I you know in hindsight
that's that's pretty crass that's that's
not really a good way to start a
relationship with somebody it's like hey
your stuffs broken yeah do something
about it whatever I don't like here so
that was sort of the beginning of my
thinking on the subject introduced
myself and so that's one thing just kind
of keep this in mind as we as we go
along this is the start of that another
project that I worked on was evil packet
net and I thought I was reporting these
web vulnerabilities to to builders to
developers to projects and you know I
was getting like nobody cared nobody's
responded respond might fix it and I
thought maybe maybe that understanding
was founded in not or that
misunderstanding was was founded in they
didn't understand the impact developers
didn't understand the impact of what
those vulnerabilities what could cause
right and turns out that's that's that's
wrong and it's sort of like end up being
so when I look back on it it was
effective in getting things fixed and
sir sure some people did learn some
things about vulnerabilities and
exploits and whatever
but it was a very negative way to do it
and I'm going to talk specifically about
some of those in a minute just kind of
keep keep these in mind as we as we go
Ryan are you here running your all right
so this one's this one's for you back in
in as a as a breaker I thought it was a
great idea to start going to developer
conferences you guys see I said it right
there Builders are my audience right
from a security perspective I want to
talk to you it's really hard for me not
say to you guys and separate myself so
at JS conf in Portland Ryan gave me the
feedback during my talk I kept saying
you guys this you guys that point point
point you know rant rant rant typical
breaker mindset and yeah I was giving
very direct feedback like you know I
don't remember the exact sweet i
couldn't find it but it was something
you know something of the you know this
guy's saying you guys like a lot like
stop and its really really really
impacted my thing like those two words
and that feedback I don't think you
realize how just how much it's had an
impact on my on my thinking about the
interaction between the two communities
and when you're speaking if you as a
builder the developer if you're going to
go speak at a security event remember be
a part of that community because because
you are we really are we really have a
limit like relationship that that is
very dependent on each other don't
alienate yourself like I did like don't
it was just I missed a huge opportunity
to connect with people and get my
message across because I just put up
that wall I'm an outsider looking in I'm
not you know I'm just saying blah blah
rant so again keep that in mind and
thank you so it's still a little bit of
a story about a specific organization
that will kind of demonstrate some of
the things that I'm talking about
basecamp classic 37signals was the I
found a vulnerability in base camp in
which you could take over any account
this is a few years back and I let
37signals know it's actually the second
video i published an evil packet and
during that process i contacted support
and I wrote him a nice email I don't I
try to look at if I didn't have it and I
basically said here's the problem I got
a response back from the support and
said basically you know our clients like
to be able to do this like to be put
javascript in the pages and whatever and
basically what they said is that it's a
feature and this is was my answer
cross-site scripting is not a feature
and i made a video about it and put it
on the internet and they got raked over
the coals in hindsight feeling wise i
felt a terrible for what what was being
what what was going on there but we'll
get to it now feelings so let's let's
talk about what's happening during both
on both sides when when these things are
reported so you know imagine yourself as
as the developer as the builder in this
scenario I want you to really think hard
about how you would feel as the breaker
this is how I feel i get an enormous
adrenaline high from finding soft you
know security bugs in your software i
love it i get so i do this thing at work
like i skipped down the hall and i like
like do a jig and and as the co-workers
going to test i skip and holler and jump
and get excited and I'm happy I'm happy
to find a flaw and what you did and
that's most security people they get
really excited they're like they just
get just pumped up what happens on the
other side when I tell
the developer about that flaw what
happens is they feel right you get the
you get the exact opposite reaction and
this this realization that I've had that
that it is actually it's causing anxiety
if you don't know how to handle the
problem you have immediate anxiety about
how do I address this problem you might
be pissed off that I pointed out your
flaw who wants once their stuff paraded
around the internet that they had this
flaw right you're pointing out mistakes
or the breakers pointing out mistakes
the Builder has made its it's not a nice
thing to have somebody to say hey your
stuffs broken and as a security person
we don't have a lot of vested interest
we we we basically don't empathize with
your position we into traditionally we
think of hey this is the most important
thing in the world we found this
vulnerability this is the thing the
security you should take and fix it
right now because I'm excited about it
but you're not you it's the complete
opposite plus you have things like I
don't know conferences to do it
conferences to go to and I don't know
bugs to fix and other things to do
besides fix my thing which to me is the
most important thing in the world to you
it might just be a very small thing so
instead we can kind of look at it this
way and my son said there needed to be
flags on the castle so on the on the
plane he drew flags on it so imagine
this one instead that that extreme
extreme highs like instead looks like a
wave and and really what a breakers
bringing to you sort of depending on how
they bring it to you there they're going
to say here's this problem really
they're saying there's a wave coming
there's something coming and it's gonna
hey you got your sand castle you might
want to you might want to do something
to your castle to protect it
move in and if you're prepared for that
communication and you understand you
understand that their intention is not
to knock your sandcastle over but to
actually warned you about something
coming towards your stank ass what's the
beach I to make sand castle analogy it
is if you understand that that's their
intention it's going to reduce that
negative aspect that negative feeling
that you have when that when you get
when you have that thing that problem
reported to you when you when you have
that when you have that experience it
actually becomes a more becomes a more
positive experience so how can we work
better together and I love this because
you know we're builders and breakers can
work together and should we rely very
heavily on each other breakers if if you
get I said it again if it's really hard
I if if builders don't build anything I
don't have anything to do as a breaker
and so so we need you we need we need
builders and builders need the feedback
of breakers because they think
differently they they have that
different opinion that different
different perspective so what's what's
the biggest thing here communication
right it's it's it's really all about
communication between the builders of
the breakers my coworker stephanie meyer
i wrote this this morning got published
about listening this this applies to
both sides when we listen really listen
we reveal respect support understanding
and empathy we also possess the power to
impart a renewed confidence clarity and
a sense that everything is going to be
okay when we listen well
so let's give some thoughts on how we
can listen better and how we can
communicate better let's go back to the
base camp a classic story because that's
not the end they didn't just get raked
over the coals and everything okay
that's where it stopped what happened
was is they they responded by
understanding that this was going to
happen again that they were going to
have somebody else report something them
they were going to have to deal with
breakers and so they built a Security
Response process they've made a page
that said we appreciate your concern we
appreciate the breakers they're trying
to understand the breaker perspective
and understand that that what we're
offering to them is of some value to me
that that makes me actually that makes
me actually that feels good makes it
feel valuable for for what I'm providing
and makes me want to go a little bit
more of an effort put it more effort in
they they said here's how here's here's
expectations for tracking disclosure and
security issues right here's here's what
you can expect for communication such
and thanks for working with us and we're
going to put your name on this list so
you get some you get some credit out of
it because that's the motivation of a
lot of breakers right the people getting
paid to do a lot of consulting work
don't have time to work on random stuff
and just throw stuff out there the ones
that are have the time to do that are
the ones trying to make a name for
themselves they're working on they're
working on it for the ego for the credit
so they can build their resume and they
can build their skills in the security
community and whether it's right or
wrong they're going to play with your
apps that's what they're going to do so
they give them some credit because it
gives them it gives them something to
hold onto and feel good about so it's a
developer what you know what can I do is
the developer for projects you can we've
got contributor at MD we got to read me
right wine out of security at MD want to
add to your projects how you want issues
reported to you
because unfortunately based on the
relationship of the builder in the
breaker and the responsibility for the
project you have a lot of the
communication onus on yourself as a
builder you have we have way more
responsibility and you're gonna get
these things logged over and you don't
know how they're going to come in so try
to try to put it out there and how you
want these reported to you what are some
of the expectations that this personal
receiving your respond 24 hours just
doesn't have to be detailed or complex
and put a list of humans or put you know
people that have contributed thoughts
bugs security bugs whatever give them
some credit we know a lot of open source
projects can't you can't give them cash
gets not a big bounty program right
maybe some swag or you know I mentioned
is that's great for they're there for
what they're looking for if you want a
good example this look at the amber
security policy and how they do things
it's bit so it's a great baseline for
for what you could include it's pretty
detailed and it goes it's based on a lot
of security community research and
things like that go check it out one
other thing you can do is self disclose
your vulnerabilities who wants to do
that that's that's a hard thing to do
it's a hard thing for us to as
developers to just put our flaws out
there instead of just patching it a
little commute message throwing in the
repo and I'm going to talk about a
project here a little bit that I'd like
if you're writing no taps I love you to
disclose too because we got a really
interesting project going on and
actually handling a security failure so
you know a problem properly and publicly
can build trust there's a great example
from a client of mine github and they do
a great job of handling these things
whenever they have a problem right they
disclose a ton of detail they write a
blog post about here's what happened
here's what we're going to do about it
here's the technical bits and we all
learn from it and they do this because
they realize they're in the they're in a
position of technical leadership in the
community and
chances are so are many of you in your
different areas as a builder so you can
lead in the same example in the same way
so now I'm going to talk about a project
that I started based on what I've been
learning over sort of the past five
years of these and as one thing that I
hadn't mentioned yet is that all of
those all those things those failures of
mine and the closest that I've been to
and yet and a lot of other development
teams have got me to really empathize
with builders and the feelings that you
go through when when you have something
reported to you it's really really hard
for me now to note to have to have these
feelings in empathy to drop a note a
about a product I feel like a complete
asshole if I did that right I would just
feel I'd feel horrible and it doesn't
help anything it's a very negative thing
to do there's a there's an interesting
example out there right now a PayPal
PayPal has got a bug bounty program
there's a 17 year old that tried to
disclose a bug to them and he's not old
enough to get a bounty so he just
dropped and he just dropped it on full
disclosure and so don't hear you
actually made it worse by not really
trying to work through the problem with
their just like whatever it's just
simple now we got the information just
go away they actually actually turned
into a lot much larger wave and then
using it as a sort of early warning so
now that I've covered all the stuff that
I forgot to talk about earlier let's
talk about the node security project
who's here has heard about the note
security project Wow awesome so the note
security project is something that uh as
I as as as a CSO and and yet my job is
to care about building secure software
and I started by trying to figure out
how how are people going to try to break
our product and bang how how are we
going to find who's going to report
flaws in it and how
how can we attack it what I came down to
was well there's NPM thing we're
trusting a lot of modules we're trusting
a lot of third-party code and so we
started sort of looking into problems
well we you know we we had one thing
where you know the password hashes were
disclosed from NPM right people might
have heard of that and had to change
your password on NPM so all those were
disclosed we had a cross-site request
forgery protection to the the NPM site
I've had a lot of discussion with Isaac
you know about the security of NPM and
so there's been a lot of conversations
between builder and braker community
there that that led up to this
particular project in some of the things
that the security of NPM so I thought
what's the next layer well what's the
next node security projects is we need
to check out the security of the modules
the things that we trust right the
things that all of the builders doing
node projects trust so it's an
experiment to bridge the security
community with the Builder community
we're taking both of these communities
and mashing them together and trying to
get them to play nice and I really
really really was nervous about how we
were going to have these researches and
how are you going to handle the
organization it turns out it's not very
hard the ones that have come on board
are really really excited to work with
builders and they understand that we
don't have to be you know gasps holes to
get to make change and have have good
progress here's some major contributors
to date Adam Brault from our team Nathan
lafreniere bear Michael Rogers mr.
Daniel Shaw Neil pool is a security
researcher Luka Cara Tony Stephen dravis
was a node developer he's building he's
helping us build tools he doesn't really
know anything about security but we rely
so heavily on on builders that can help
us build tools that are mindsets we're
not that's not that's not what we do so
we have to like static analysis and
things like that to do it really
efficiently and well we're relying on
our workflow we're relying on builders
to help us our low brow and Jacopo
Tarantino again another
another builder it's helping us build
our portal to disclose advisories and
things like that our workflow so what
are our goals we're going to audit every
module which is pretty much absolutely a
crazy thing Isaac said it's a massive
ambitious potentially ocean boiling
undertaking and it is we've figured out
a way to do it efficiently and if you
want to know some of the technical bits
and go into that sort of after but we're
going to audit you know say 31,000 if
that numbers gone up since I fixed this
last night and then we're going to fix
the broken modules but traditional
security projects just go your things
broken your things broken go fix it
we're going to report the issues we find
is as best we can we're going to try to
do it privately can't do that try to get
ahold of with a maintainer we can't do
that we'll end up putting an issue in in
the repository stop texting me and we're
going to try to do it in a very polite
and positive way we're trying not to be
like all the history of that we're
trying to break out of that mold and
we're going to send pull requests we're
not going to publish an advisory without
something fixed if a module is two years
old we find a vulnerability in the
maintainer doesn't want to do it and or
got it you know doesn't exist anymore or
whatever we're going to supply a patch
pull requests
all right actually that's that's the
difference we're trying to cross that
line and fix stuff instead of just cause
problems so here's an example that of
communication on Hugh bot github so
their client we tried to report it
internally they said go ahead and go
ahead and put it in the repo and the
maintainer will take care of it we
published it and at midnight-ish the
issues is closed silently so we put this
vulnerability in there if she was closed
silently no comment one of our
researchers said I think you may have
closed the wrong issue it's small sorry
the code for email that coffee is still
vulnerable not taking an attacking tone
thinking maybe there was a mistake
making sure that we communicate not just
say well alright we're just good publish
an advisory whatever and be done with it
no so tom says I closed the correct
issue he bought have run a trusted
environment if you don't trust people
you allow access to you but I think you
should stop at you know allowing them
access to Hugh but we didn't particular
agree with that but again we didn't we
didn't take an attacking tone Neil Neil
did a great job of communicating this
since it's a great example what we're
trying to do I appreciate that he
acknowledges because it's true if you
have trusted people sure he says I
appreciate that but Hugh bought as open
source there's no guarantee at Hugh bot
will be running a trusted environment
and also even if you even if that
guarantee did exist just because you
give somebody access to Hugh buy it
doesn't mean you want them running
arbitrary code in this case on your
server right at the end instead of
arguing because we could just continue
to banter back and forth this fixed
should be really fairly straightforward
would you be willing to consider merging
a pull request I think the next day he
just we whipped up a patch Senate merged
done didn't have to argue didn't have to
fight over at de neve just done so it
was fantastic and then we're going to
publish the results we're not publishing
anything that does not have a fix for it
so we're going to try really really hard
to have
pull requests have those patches here's
an example of just a few that we found
already that have gone through the
pipeline how you can contribute is is
basically all detail that note security
I oh I need people to do patches there's
there's issues we have mark there it
says need patch and I don't necessarily
I'm not the best person to write those
so I need help in that area and it's
something that somewhere you could
contribute usually they're just quick
little one offs that probably takes
somebody that's a good good builder
15-20 minutes maybe you know less it
take me you know okay I got to figure
out how to write JavaScript again today
yeah quick recap so each we have we have
a relationship builders and breakers
that rely upon each other we all have
and need to respect and understand the
feelings of the other of the other party
and realize that that we both do have
good intention we have to communicate
and listen effectively try to be nice
and positive about it this this we can
break out of that mold we can do things
differently some we have an amazing
community and it's ok it's ok it's ok to
screw up like there's going to be
researchers that you're going to be
jerks to you and there's going to be
builders that don't listen to two
researchers and breakers and we just
have to fight through that and remind
those parties that that hey here's how
we could work through this and don't
don't immediately take the attacking
tone don't immediately dismiss something
that a breaker says we have good
intentions both sides and if you want
more information want to chat about it
I'll be available later i also have note
security stickers because when you put a
lock on something it's more secure right