(Phillip Roberts) Hi everyone, come in and sit down. The last meeting in the afternoon.
Be quiet The speaker was Phillip Roberts, who worked in Scotland and drove over from London.
What Phillip is going to talk about is the event loop.
Please applaud Philip
Hello everyone, thank you very much for being able to speak on the platform, this is great
Can you allow me to stretch myself, I need to stretch it so that I don't look so weird
I want to talk about the event loop, what exactly is the event loop
As a JavaScript event loop. First, like he said, I work at Andyet
Andyet is a great little software company in the United States. If you need help developing some real-time applications, you can consider us
That's what we are good at. About 18 months ago, I was a professional JavaScript developer
I started thinking about how JavaScript actually works
I don't fully understand. I've heard that V8 is the JavaScript runtime environment in Chrome, but I don't know what it is and what it does
I've heard of single threading and it's clear that I'm using callback functions.
How does the callback function work? I started to do some reading,
I also did some experiments in the browser, which was probably the beginning.
My feeling at that time was, what exactly is JavaScript? The answer looks like this: "JavaScript is a single-threaded, non-blocking, asynchronous, interpreted scripting language"
Right, very cool. "I have a call stack, an event loop,
Callback queues and some other APIs. "OK, I don't have a computer science degree
What I want to say is that these terms are professional terms. I've heard of V8 and other operating environments and different browsers
So I want to ask V8: "Do you have call stacks, event loops, callback queues, and other APIs?"
"I have a call stack and heap and I don't know what else is"
Okay, it's fun. Well, 18 months have passed and I think I understand now
(Laughter) These are the things I want to share with you today. hope
This can help people who have a relatively short exposure to JavaScript understand why JavaScript is so weird
When you compare other languages, you may not understand why callbacks are a disaster but still introduced
If you are a experienced JavaScript developer, I hope to be able to
Let you gain some new insights into the runtime environment of JavaScript, so that you can think more carefully about it
So if we look at the environment in which JavaScript runs. For example V8, V8 is the JavaScript runtime environment in Chrome
This is a schematic diagram of the JavaScript runtime environment. Heap records memory allocation
Then there is the call stack, this is where things like frames are located
But if you clone the V8 code, then
When searching for setTimeout or DOM, HTTP requests are not in them
They don't exist in the V8 engine, I'm surprised by this. When you want to program asynchronously, these are the things you first consider using
But they don't exist in the source code of V8?唔 .. very interesting. Well, these 18 months of exploration
I started to realize that this is an extremely important part
I hope you all understand what these parts are today
The first is the V8 operating environment, then the other things provided by the browser
Called web APIs, DOM, AJAX, setTimeout, and so on, and then mysterious
Event loop and callback queue. I'm sure you have heard these terms beforehand
But you don't necessarily understand how these parts fit together. Well,
I will start by explaining these terms. Maybe some people do n’t know, some people may know.
We go through it quickly, and it's clear that some people need to endure for a while
But I guess most people won't. Well, JavaScript is a single-threaded programming language
Single-threaded running environment, it has one and only one call stack, it can only do one thing at a time
This means single-threaded, the program can only run one piece of code at a time
So let's try to visualize what we just said
If I have some code like this on your left, we have some functions
A function that multiplies two numbers by multiply, and one that calls the square function of the former, square
A print function printSquare that calls square and prints the results using console.log
Then at the end we called printSquare. These codes look all right
OK, so let's run it. Call stack basically
A data structure that records the location of the current program.
Some function is put on the stack. If a function is currently left
This function will be popped off the stack, which is what the stack does. If you run this file
There will be a function similar to main, which refers to the file itself, we first put it on the stack
Then we look at the declared functions from top to bottom
Finally, printSquare, OK, we know that printSquare is called, so we
Pushed it on the stack, and then it called square, so it pushed it on the stack too
square also calls multiply and also pushes it onto the stack. Finally we got the return value of multiply
We popped multiply from the stack, then square got the return value, and popped square from the stack.
Finally to printSquare, it called console.log. There is no return value here.
We reached the last part of the function, and then we were done. This is a visual call stack
Can this be understood? (Yes, Phil) Good, then if you haven't heard about the call stack before
Now you know, when you are doing website development on the browser side,
If you run this code in Chorme, the baz function calls the bar function, and the bar function calls the foo function.
The foo function throws an error, we see that it will be like this
It prints the entire stack tree, the errors start from foo, to bar, to baz, to anonymous functions
That is to say the main function. Similarly, if you've heard terms like memory leaks
This is one example, what happens if we have a function foo that calls itself
We have a function that calls foo, and foo calls foo, and so on.
In the end Chrome will say, "You probably don't want to call it yourself 16,000 times"
"I terminated it for you so you can find where the bug is." OK
I may show you a call stack, and you may have noticed it while developing
Well, now there are some bigger problems.
What makes programs run slower? So let's talk about blocking
There is no strict definition of what is blocking and what is not blocking. It simply means that the code runs very slowly
For example, console.log is not slow, traversing from 1 to 1 billion is very slow, and network requests are very slow
Downloading pictures is also slow. Anything that performs very slowly on the stack is called blocking.
Here is a small example, let's say we have some pseudocode like this
Just like jQuery's AJAX request
If you don't add callback functions to AJAX requests, they will be synchronous
If we run it, first call getSync, then we are waiting .. because
We are making network requests. Network requests are slow compared to the computer local, then
We will not proceed until the request is completed. Then continue to wait and continue. What i want to say is
These requests may never end, so ... well I can't wait to go home. it is finally over
When all this is done, the stack is cleared. Then if a programming language is single-threaded
For example ruby, the situation just happened. Ok we
To request a resource, we have to wait for the request to finish because there is no way
So what's wrong with this? The problem is that our code is running on the browser
So let's get started ... OK, this is Chrome
This is the code just run
I faked this with a while loop because it is synchronous and wants
Loop for five seconds before I can continue if I open the console here. We can see that
What happens, is requesting foo.com, why is this happening, I can't do anything, right,
Even the run button hasn't finished re-rendering when I click on it. Browser is
Blocked, it's stuck, it can't do anything until these requests are completed. And then all
Something popped up because I did some operations before and it understands that I've done it but it can't
Actually render. It cannot do anything. That's because if there is something in the call stack
Then here it is. Yes, it is still running. We have figured out the synchronization request,
Browsers can't do anything else right now. It cannot render, it cannot run any other code, it
its stuck. Not surprisingly, right. If we want people to have beautiful and smooth user interfaces, we can't block
Call stack. So, what should we do? Our easiest way is to provide asynchronous callbacks
There are almost no blocking functions in the browser, and the same is true in node, they are all
Is an asynchronous function, which basically means we run some code and give it a callback function
And run it later, if you've seen JavaScript code you've seen these asynchronous callbacks, this
What does it actually look like? Here are some simple examples to show where we have run. Code like this, console.log output
Hi, right. We run setTimeout, but we put console.log in the queue and run it later, so we skip
And run JSConf here, and then 5 seconds later, we output "there", right. Got it? Happy. basically
This is what setTimeout does. So, asynchronous callback with greeting to
We used to see chimneys ... how does it work? Let's run the code. CONSOLE.LOG Hi. setTimeout.
We know it wo n’t run immediately, we know it will run in five seconds, we
Ca n’t be pushed onto the stack, somehow, just after disappearing, we have no way like
Describe this, but we will come to it. We log in to JSConfEU, clear, after 5 seconds
Somehow magically "exists" appearing on the stack. How did it happen? This is-this
Basically, where the event loop comes in for concurrency. Yes, so I always have
The part is lying to you and telling you that JavaScript can only do one thing at a time.
It is true that the JavaScript runtime can only do one thing at a time. It cannot make a
AJAX requests while you are doing other code. And you are doing setTimeout which it cannot do
Another code. The reason we can do it is because there are so many browsers
Just when running. So, remember this diagram, one thing the JavaScript runtime can do
For a while, the browser gave us these other things, gave us these APIs we wanted, these
Is a valid thread, you can just make the call and the browser that piece
Everyone knows in this concurrent kick. If you look at this person
Basically the same node, not the network. Our API has a C ++ API and threads are
By C ++ is hidden from you. Now we have this picture let's see how to run this code
The fuller look of the browser looks like. So, as before, run the code, console
Login hi, hi login to console, concise. Now we can see what happens when we call it setTimeout.
We-we pass this callback function and delay, setTimeout is called. SetTimeout now
Is an API browser provided to us, it does not live on V8 sources, which is redundant
We stuff get our javascript running
time. Browser kicks off your timer. Now it has to deal with numbers
Down yours, right, so that means our call to setTimeout, itself is now complete, so we can pop it up
Stack. "JSConfEU", clear, so now we have this timer in Web API, it
It will finish in 5 seconds. Now the web API can't just start modifying your
Code, it ca n’t chuck something onto the stack when it is ready, if it does n’t it will appear
Randomly in the middle of your code so this is the task queue or callback queue
Kick, any network API pushes a callback to the task queue when it's done. At last
The event loop we get, the topic of the speech, what exactly is the event loop like
The simplest kind of piece is in this whole equation, and it has a very simple job.
The job of this event loop is to look at the stack and look in the task queue. If the stack
Empty it takes the first thing in the queue and pushes it onto the stack to effectively
run. So here we can see that the stack now obviously has a callback in the task queue,
When the event loop runs, it says, oh, I'll do something and push to the callback
Stacked. Remember its stack like JavaScript land, back to the house V8, callback will appear
Run on the stack, execute console.log "there" and we're done. Does that make sense? everyone
Where am I? Awesome! Ok. So now we can see how this works it could be the first
Confrontation you have had with asynchronous things which for some strange reason someone said
You want to call setTimeout to zero,-well, you want me to run the zero function
time? Why would I wrap it in a setTimeout? The first time you run across this piece, if
You are like me, I see what it is doing, but I don't know why. The reason is that, generally,
If you want to postpone things to the stack is clear. So we know that we are watching
This, if you write JavaScript, then we will see the same result, we want to
Look at "hi", "JSConf" and "there" will appear at the end. We can see that
How does this happen. The setTimeout is zero and now it will push to completion immediately
It goes to the queue, remember I said the event loop, it has to wait until the stack
Very clear before you can push the callback stack so your stack will continue
Run, execute console.log "hi", "jsconfeu" and clear, now the event loop can kick
And call the callback function. This is like an example of setTimeout being zero, and execution was delayed
The code, for whatever reason, ends at the stack. Or until the stack is clear. Ok.
So all these web APIs work the same way, if we have an AJAX request, we make an AJAX request
Using a callback URL, works the same way like this, oops sorry, console log, "hi" so that
An AJAX request, running this code AJAX request does not live in JavaScript
But the Web API in the browser, so we rotate it with the callback in the URL, your code
Can continue to run. Before that, after the XHR request is completed, or it may never be complete, this is
Fortunately, the stack can continue to run. Assuming it is finished, it is pushed to the queue and picked.
YoY event loop, it runs. This is where everything happens when an asynchronous call occurs.
Let's make a crazy complicated example, I hope this goes to work if you haven't realized
It's all in the theme there are 500 animation steps like this I did not know throughout this entire deck.
(Code blows up, flame animation) (Applause) Hmm ... no ... so ... funny, we
Give a link. Hmm ... it's big enough that others will see? Ok, so basically i wrote
This time talking to Scottish JS, I will say later that I broke half of the slide and ca n’t
Disdain to redo all the slides because it suffers ass in the keynote
Do it, so I took the much easier route (laughs) and write a tool that can visualize JavaScript
When the runtime environment is running, it is called a loop. So let's just run this example and where
Is the kind that we have to have a slide in this example, I have n’t evened XHR yet,
It works, I just haven't done it yet. As you can see in the code, we want to record something,
This is the gasket around addEventListener, setTimeout and we are going to make a console.log. -
I'm going to run it and see what happens and so on ... Add DOM API, add a timeout, code
To continue running, push the callback to run in it, and we're done in the queue.
If I click here, then it will trigger ... Network API, queue click callback
And run it. If I cluck a hundred times we can see what happens. I click, click
Not get processed immediately, itself is pushed to the queue, such as queue get
After processing, my click is finally processed, right. So, I have a few
For example, I want to run through here. Here we go, ok, so i just have to run through
A few examples are just a way to talk that you may already be running, there are several things
Haven't thought about the asynchronous API, in this example we call it four times the setTimeout
With said a second delay, and console.log "hi". Get queued by the callback at the time ...
This fourth callback, we are asking for a one second delay and it is still waiting for the callback
It's not running yet, right?
This illustrates-like what time out exactly what it is doing, this is not a guarantee
Time execution, this is a shortest time execution, just like zero of setTimeout
Run the code immediately, it runs the code around ten years old, sometimes, right? So ... here
For example, I want to talk about callbacks, so it depends on who speaks and how the phrase
Things, callbacks can be one of two things, callbacks can be any function, the other
Function calls or callbacks can be made more explicitly asynchronous callbacks as a
Get pushed back to the callback queue in the future. This code illustrates the difference,
Correct. On the array in the foreach method, it won't run, it needs a function, which you
The callback can be called, but it doesn't run it asynchronously, it runs inside it
The current stack. We can define an asynchronous forEach so it can take an array of a callback
And for each item in the array it will do a zero setTimeout with a callback,
I think this should pass the value, but any way, so, I want to run it, we can
See what's the difference, so for the first running code block, it has to sit
And blocking the stack, right? Until it's done, and in the asynchronous version, well, this slows down
Down but we basically have to queue a bunch of callbacks and they will clear
Then we can actually run through and make a console.log. Console.log in this example
It's fast, so the benefits of doing asynchronous aren't obvious, but let's say you do
Some processing on each element is a slow array. I think i have something to show
No, no, I don't know. Ok. So we said-oops. So I have a delay function
It's just slow, it's just a slow thing. So ... let's say handle asynchronous and handle synchronous here.
Okay now i am going to open i have one thing this morning and literally hacked it all together
Is to simulate redrawing or rendering the browser, which is what I haven't touched
What's going on, this interacts with rendering-I'm touched, but not really
Explain it. Therefore, basically the browser is restricted by what javascript you are doing,
Browser wants to redraw the screen every 16.6 milliseconds, 60 frame seconds
It is ideal, this is where it will do the redraw as fast as possible. But it is constrained by what you are doing
This is done in JavaScript for various reasons, so it is not actually rendered, if there is
Code on the stack, right. Like rendering a kind of call almost like in a callback
itself. It waits until the stack is clear. The difference is that in presenting a given
Higher priority than your callback, it queues a split every 16 milliseconds,
It can be clear before the stack that it actually does the rendering. So this is-
This rendering queue is just a simulation rendering, every second is this what I can do a rendering? Yes,
Can I do a presentation? Yes. Among them, because our code is not doing anything now. If I run
Code you can see while we are doing this kind of synchronization loop slowly through the array our rendering
Blocked, right, if our rendering is blocked you cannot select text on the screen, you cannot
Click something and see the response, right, like for example I showed before. At this
For example, okay, this is faster even though our queue is blocking the asynchronous timeout
But we are given-we kind of give every element a render because of the chance between
We have queued it to jump there asynchronously and do the rendering, is this
sense?
>> Yes >> Yes, it's cool. So this is just a kind of-
It's like what a simulated rendering works, but it just really reflects
You when people say don't block the event loop, that's exactly what they're talking about
on. They say don't put inferior slow stacks because when you do code
The browser cannot do what it needs to do to create a beautiful fluid UI. This is why when you
Do image processing or animation effects like this if you don't have too much stuff to become sluggish
Be careful how you line up the code. So an example of this, we can use to see
Scrolling handlers-scroll handles like this-are like triggering a lot of scroll events in the DOM,
Yes, they like to trigger-I believe they like to trigger every 16 frames
Milliseconds if I have this code pair. In document.scroll, animated stuff,
Or do some work. If I have this code, for example I scroll it to be queued like
Tons of callback rights. Then it has to go through and process all these and each
If these are very slow, well, you do n’t block the stack, you
Floods queued events. So, it's like just helping visualization, I guess,
What happens when you actually trigger all these callbacks, there are ways to shake
This is fundamentally okay, we have to queue all these events, but let's do
I work slowly until the user every few seconds or stop scrolling for a certain amount of time
Think this is basically it. There is a whole other conversation in Hell about how this works. because
Basically the code is running, such code runs correctly at runtime, and it slows down
I run the parser through an Esprima and a JavaScript. When I insert a large loop,
For half a second, it's just slowly moving code. Shipped to web workers and did a whole bunch
Something visualizes what happened, and it makes sense to do it at runtime. entire
Other conversations are here. I'm super excited it will talk to anyone afterwards