hi everyone and I'm sorry about the
slight delay in my starting I can't hear
you at all I've got no idea what's going
on wave your arms at me if you can hear
me oh wow look at what i can see as
brilliant thank you very much you are
like hi hi everyone and so I guess you
know why I'm not there so instead I sent
my hologram over I hope this will do
it's kind of like I'm there in person
right except obviously I don't get to
hang around with you the whole time and
annoy you I suppose that's a good thing
really but you've got me to the next
half an hour I've got half an hour right
is that right everyone anyone if I got
half an hour yes i'm just going to
interpret a wave as yes there how about
that okay good right well we're going to
have quite a fun time in this half hour
I can tell you I mean obviously I'm
delighted that I can can come and join
you here at the end of jazz conf it
seems like it's been a pretty amazing
conference so far is that right again
wave your arms because sue I'm so sorry
I just can't hear a thing it's all we're
really good at technology aren't we ask
programmers it's brilliant anyway really
pleased but I could come and join you
guys because I kind of feel like you are
my programmer brothers and sisters or do
you mean to go forward and my slides yet
and you know and I love sharing
programming stuff with people who love
programming that's you guys right yeah
i'm just going to imaginary ones go yeah
because i can't hear a thing it's
brilliant and but before i talk a bit
about for what i'm going to show you
today some creative programming i'm
doing going to do some live programming
it's obviously going to work flawlessly
and before I do that I'm just going to
introduce myself briefly so this is
their creative JavaScript workshops that
I've been running probably two or three
years now and it's some something I love
teaching because JavaScript obviously
you all know you're the top p
in JavaScript but you've all been
watching JavaScript's rise too I don't
know to stardom in the last few years
and obviously in lots of the areas but
the area I'm particularly interested in
is creative programming so of course
you've got the obvious things like html5
canvas like moving dong elements around
with steer since we've got all of those
things and but there's also just the
fact that javascript is so damn fast
nowadays right is ridiculously fast is
brilliant so opens up all of these
potential avenues for creative
programming and that's what I teach my
workshops is what I've been doing for
years in loads of different platforms
and programming languages now of course
taking all this JavaScript it's really
fun time to be learning this type of
programming it built into the browser so
the workshops spun off a website called
creative jazz calm hopefully we will see
now I'm sure you subscribe and follow us
on Twitter don't you know all right yes
okay good so I really wish I could hear
you guys it's just it's fine we live
with these restrictions you'll be boring
wouldn't it there was too easy anyway
careers of Jess calm there's a team of
us that posts all the fun things that we
find on the internet all the fun
javascript stuff you know creative demos
and the tests and games and there's also
loads of tutorials on there as well and
there's like I said it's a small team of
us here at CSS comp earlier and Link you
would have met well head and she's one
of the main people behind creative
guess.com so strongly suggest you check
that out if you're interested and what
else ok so these days I things be a
digital artist and you know obviously
you guys are programmers but normally
when I tell people this they think I
just do Photoshop living you know
obviously I don't do photoshop and well
I'll show you some of the things that I
do here's a project called lunar trails
now I love this 70s game
an arcade game called lunar lander so I
programmed it in JavaScript and I put it
in an arcade cabinet you can see it
there that arcade cabinet is just
running a full full screen chrome put in
some physical controls so you can play
the game now cool part about this is
that behind you as you play this huge
plotter this hanging V plotter plots the
trails of the past that you take in the
game nardone as you've seen the game the
idea is that you land your lunar lander
on the surface of the Moon so as you
treat as you move your ship and gently
try and land it on the surface of the
Moon this plotter will mark the path
that you took and over time you can see
all the trails of people that played the
game build up over time it wasn't just
JavaScript there was a processing
element and obviously the plotter itself
is quite a big electronics project
that's programmed with arduino i'm sure
you guys your guard Reno's doing is that
right I hear that right yeah our jury
knows are pretty awesome so the plotter
that I made there along with an engineer
called Paul straaten but the brains of
that clutter is an Arduino mega so now
you've all got our drina's i fully
expect you guys to be able to make one
of those names right maybe maybe your
second or third project maybe not your
first one take it easy to go it but it's
great fun I love playing with
electronics next project i want to show
you is this one called pixel Pyro's it's
a digital interactive fireworks display
the idea behind this wall we've got this
massive screen 50 foot wide we've got
infrared cameras that pick up version
and I'm projecting these orbs of light
onto the screen you can see as people
touch those without hands I'm using
motion detection to see where they've
moved their hands and if they find
notice and emotion then it fires
triggers of firework this is a bit
complicated this project is programmed
in C++ using openframeworks yeah we just
have the most massive projectors it's
absolutely ridiculous and we're taking
on tour in the UK for the next
what between September in September this
um really super excitingly i'm adding
lasers so I've got to learn how to
program Labor's in the next few weeks be
easy right how cool is lasers next time
I present remotely i'm going to send
myself a laser version of myself yeah
yeah that's pretty pretty cool ok anyway
what's next ok yes so the thing that
this project our weight in your arms hi
it's so you guys you guys are awesome
right and think about these projects
that I've shown you and in fact all the
projects I do they're all designed with
code so I mean obviously the web design
communities come up with this brilliant
new idea which is designing websites in
the browser well that's kind of what I
do I design all of these crazy projects
in code sometimes I'll have an idea of
what I'm trying to attempt other times i
won't i'll just make it up as I go along
but it's this process this creative
process that as programmers as jobbing
programmers you might have forgotten you
know we all used to do this when we were
a kid we lose the little sketches and
stuff we used to being created but as
programmers I think a lot of our work is
like it instead of check boxes that we
have to take off one by one I love
getting back to that creativity that
iterative process trial and error those
joyful the it's a really good fun way to
program so you probably this message
like we're probably like us programmers
were probably saying to all the desires
yeah learn to code and we're being all
snooty about it but obviously and it's
well you know I I do a lot of web design
conferences as well but the designers
and I've been telling them to learn to
code honestly clave loved they've loved
me telling a month as the brilliant it's
not just all about us telling them to
lend cage you know we've got to be
willing to meet them halfway so I say
let's learn to get creative because in
some of the most enjoyable what you do
is when it's this
most creative process that I've
explained so let's do some codes yeah
live coding on a computer that's 5,000
miles away what can possibly go wrong
it's going to be brilliant all right can
tell you're into this right so I'm going
to be using at remi's jayus bin Remy add
you there it's remy in can't see him is
he there no I've seized property gone to
the other tool class that's fine
whatever Remy we're using Jasmine if it
goes wrong we'll just blame him shall we
all right let's make it full screen so
I'm running the stairs been it's a bit
of HTML you can see there it's just
putting in a canvas 400 by 400 i've also
got gang reference that comes you hands
up hands up if you've done canvas
programming before you yeah it's pretty
good fun isn't it what we're going to do
today at quite a few who hasn't ever
done any canvas before yeah a few of you
all right well why wants to do today is
just do a little bit of graphical
programming we've become so let's start
easy let's draw a line yeah exciting and
until you're excited it's really hard to
type with a slight delay so if I if I
make a mistake then just wave your arms
in the air and until I fix it oh it's
going to be really it's going to be
perfect okay so i want to draw a line
that starts at the origin and like that
and then i'm going to do a line to let's
draw it along and down side vision see
no we don't see any of that that line
yet until we tell the canvas to stroke
path that we've just defined there you
go it's pretty exciting we got a line
yeah I can tell you're excited about
that are you guys are awesome right
let's make a line that instead of goes
down and to the right goes straight
saves minus 70 we have a problem with
that now we can't see it off I of our
screen so one thing you
do with canvas which is pretty fun is
move the origin yeah have you done this
before yeah G of you the entire
coordinate system so that subsequent
drawing actually is in a different place
so I'm going to move it two hundred long
380 down so now we draw our line it's in
the bottom pointing upwards we've moved
00 point to the bottom middle this so
what am I going to do with this well it
doesn't look like it but this little
line is going to become a beautiful tree
I know it's pretty amazing that's of
course the draw a tree we're going to do
we're going to impressive function which
I love blows my mind okay so fun right
so let's let's let's define our function
well i'm going to take take it step by
step let's make this a function that
draws a branch and i want to draw a
branch of a particular length I'm just
going to indent my coach eggs I can tell
you're all getting a bit disturbed about
that yeah program must indent um and so
now instead of just drawing a line minus
70 and a droid minus length right the
length of the barge that I want and now
when I cool then I can draw a branch as
long as I want 100 maybe or there's a
hundred or a stick with like 70 I'm just
getting a little delay every time I type
it comes back a bit later is brilliant
right and so here's the scary bit oh my
god what if at the bottom of our branch
function we make another branch well
obviously nothing happens even at loop
right it's going to keep calling itself
the thing with recursive functions is
that there has to come a time when it
stops cool
well so I'm going to find some condition
in this case I'm going to make or a new
branch I'm going to make it a little bit
shorter than the one I just drew so
after a while the length of that branch
will be so short I don't want to carry
on drawing more branch and so I'm going
to test if the length the branch greater
than 10 then draw a child branch
indentation woes don't worry I've got it
covered don't worry everyone it's fine
and instead of just drawing it the next
branch 70 I'm going to draw it at length
time say point eight right so that means
that our second branch will be eighty
percent of the length you can see that
all of our branches just stop at the
bottom and so what I want to do before I
draw the next branch is translate the
origin onto the end of this current
branch I can do that with translate now
translate is always relative to wherever
the origin is right now so if i move the
origin up i minus the length then it
means that when we draw the next branch
it's at the end of the first branch
castle hook we have a beautiful tree now
which way is the screen is it this way
so that way i don't know which way never
is it that way yeah yeah yeah I don't
know I can tell I'm a mirrored it's very
confusing right so now and in fact just
to show you what that's doing I've set
the line which to be the length / 10
there you go so you can see that the
longer the branch lengths the the
thicker it is ok now we see I'm
beautiful tree what do you think yeah ok
fur yet live it's gonna get even better
I know can you believe it it's going to
get even better so now these branches
are all kind of a bit straight let's
make them a bit then d I know ok so
let's bend these up a bit right and not
as well as translating the origin you
can actually also rotate it and so I'm
going to rotate the origin well when
use the canvas context command rotate it
requires an angle in radians so if i
wanted to do it's a 10 degrees in order
to convert that to radians i need to
multiply it by PI over 118 I'm sure poo
what's that ah so hard to type from here
and so now every time I draw a new
branch it's rotated ten degrees to the
right i'm going to rewrite this function
so that we now pass in the angle as a
parameter so i'm going to change that
tenth to this new parameter and then
when we call Child branches I can pass
in rotation of the next class there you
go maybe I'll make it 15 a bendy branch
okay this is not quite what we wanted
how about at the end of every branch we
draw two branches and we can do this
just by copying that and pasting it and
drawing one will look at that whoa
that's not quite what I want to minus-15
now one branch go much goes right now
this is probably not what you expected
to see right the problem is is that
we're going to go all the way down every
right-hand branch until we get the end
and then we're going to go back one
little bit and then back one again to
the other left hand brush but every time
we're moving the origin to the end of
the branch that we're currently messing
with so in order to fix that or what we
can do is before we start messing with
the coordinate system we can save it and
then after we've done all this messing
around we can actually restore it and we
have our tree yay i'm imagining applause
at this point I'll just I see you're
waving as I guess that's a good sign how
my day of time think I've got ten
minutes left so how about we make this
tree grow and animates what you think
yeah all right you guys are up for it
let's do it well the first thing we need
to do if we want to make our tree growth
is cool if you want to animate it also
you have to draw it over and over again
I'm going to do it the old school where
the moment is in settings well obviously
you should probably use and
requestanimationframe i'm just going to
use this settings will call it thousand
/ 40 milliseconds every frame that means
it's going to get cold once 40 times a
second so Nell and I find this function
loop you can see here I'm translating
and drawing the branch every time but
before I translate I have to do a save
and a was the end so that's our court
system doesn't get too messed up it's
really hard to code from so far away
right and so now the trees getting drawn
over there but archery you can see it's
not very interesting licking and I'll
tell you what I might do just while I'm
showing you this um I'm just going to
call this loop function once to draw our
tree once and I want to add a bit
randomness to this well I've got this
random function that returns a ruined a
number between two numbers to going to
pass in instead of an angle of 15 i'm
going to pass it a random angle between
0 and 15 and on the other side i can
pass in a random angle between 0-15 so I
trees looking a bit wise a bit rubbish
looking to be honest Blitzer I'd be a
bit more wideness in our angles getting
bit better but the other thing we can
randomize shashi the length of the next
branch so I can make that between point
seven point nine maybe
I can't see where my cursor is so now
every branch is a random amount of the
previous part between 70 and 90 say you
can see it's looking a bit more
interesting looking now our tree is a
lot more kind of beautiful looking and
might just make it a bit shorter but the
problem is so now if you want to animate
this well we have a slight problem in
that well first of all we're not
clearing the screen every time so I was
just building up into a mesh let's clear
the screen every time it helps at all so
clearing in it the size of our cameras
so you can see that every time the tree
runs it makes a complete round tree
which you know it's kind of fun if it
doesn't really if we want to make this
tree grow we're going to have to be able
to draw the same tree every time right
which is kind of really hard and crazy
and I just saw that someone told me
there's 15 minutes left I've no idea
where he said that I think I've got ten
minutes is that right anyway type it in
10 minutes yes good okay right and so we
need to figure out how to draw the same
tree every time so we need to stop this
branch function being a function that's
just cause a random tree to being a
branch object that stores they march
what what data does our branch have well
it has um has a length of an angle so
that's part of our properties on this
list Oh wonderful maybe slightly nasty
things that you can do with javascript
is turn a function into your class
definition no I'm going to make a new
object which is my tree and I'm going to
make a branch and it's going to be like
six it's be nice i should probably turn
a an angle as well and we're going to
probably well this is where at now you
did what is actually an object
it has local variables that scoped
within here called length and angle
that's good that's what I need the other
of the product I need for this branch is
children there's no not before no store
data for the branches I'm actually going
to repay them here that draws the
branches having some problems with
latency oh damn it to that yeah it
seemed very hard to control the mouse
from so far away I could cut and paste
that up there and and here instead of
just calling branch I what first of all
i'm going to make variable children i'm
just going to say it as a property that
is externally accessible Hockeyville
area and now instead of just call it
branch i'm going to ask a branch object
to the children so it reads my type
there's like a half seconds delay or it
comes back so that's why it's a quite
slick as usual quite see one side and
got live coatings hard times her and so
there we are right so I'm adding a new
branch on to the children array it's all
this stuff here and need to put instead
of just having there is this block of
code i'm going to put it into a function
called render and obviously i need to
then all of that stuff or i could tell
you get nervous den for God's sake man
in dense right in the only thing i miss
boring the cut the branch object that
were in but we actually need to check to
see if it's got any children that it has
then we therefore each one of those as
well so here we cool and i thought this
game last is lazy oh look I made a
mistake I made any mistakes this place
probably add a semi boom probably see
what else is complaining about missing
saw another missing semicolon well I
like putting my semicolons in so I'm
going to put that in makes me feel
better alright so now what we got well
we should hopefully have a tree and I'm
here instead of calling branch where we
should probably draw our tree no idea if
this is going to work probably made some
mistakes she notice anything wave us run
it we run it and see what happens it's
the same as we had before except this
time that tree is getting drawn over and
over again but in exactly the same place
this means we can now make this tree
grow and I am running out of time let's
do it see how quickly i can do it well
i'm going to make a variable called
growth or didn't spell that right Oh
fuzzy you know rvn seeing into this
computer by the way in case you're
wondering when i set the growth 20 in
the render function every winter come on
scroll up and i'm going to add a little
bit to the growth ok grave plus equals
0.01 and and here in i'm going to
instead of well let's make us a local
variable called Belin sorry about the
meaningless names i'm typing a bit too
fast to give it sensible long variable
names growth times live so down here now
whenever I retire if Claire to add to
length then i need to change it to be
then ok that's probably all now
hopefully ah I've done I run now
hopefully it should grow there you go
it's growing it's great eyes not stop
I've we have a problem everyone the
trees and stopping grown everyone that's
pretty serious oh my gods it stop it
I'll just going to need and i can see
you appreciate thank you only I could
hear you would be brilliant so instead
of just adding point 01 to it I wanted
to ease towards under there's this and
thick function you can do to make it
easier position I'm really running out
I don't even really have time to explain
this but I'm going to want it to ease
towards one so now hopefully it stop is
it gonna do anything yeah it's I
eventually stopped when i get that it
doesn't look very realistic the growth
so i'm going to iron you know I need to
do i need to stall which generation
wearing it's going crazy and then every
time I make a branch oh my god it's so
hard to do this I'm going to score
generation in a local variable there and
at the beginning I need to add one it's
a generation and at the end of this
branch functional needs perforation
really running out of time and the
screen is it updating fast enough it's
all going to so now hopefully I
should have a property called jen as a
property inside of this inside of this
object i can use to know how far down
the generations I am I could use that
for anything but at the moment i'm going
to use up here to set a delay and i'm
going to set that to be gen x 10 and so
now down here instead of just adding
anything to the growth i can say if oh
if delay is greater than zero delay
minus minus up that's where i can make
the growth eating my screen isn't oh
there it is again sorry i would normally
put on brackets so now hopefully that
the new is the branches at the end
should grow last now i have absolutely
run out of time I'm afraid and but there
is one here I was going to make its way
as well but I've just got no time but
instead i'm going to show you this one
but i made earlier which is using
exactly a system but this has got it
grows it also springs and it's
sways a bit look at this every time it
does it slightly differently and it's
called cool render style now this
awesome looking robo tree was a bit of
an accident really didn't mean for it to
look like this I just wanted it to
figure out how I could draw a branch
that was fat at one end and dinner at
the other end I got that system of
circles in there and actually I decide
let's load about why frame is nearing
yeah and then all over anyway huh this
is an interesting i'm going to post up
all this code and tree I look guys you
guys are awesome if only I could hear
you I'd be amazing right so that's
enough of the live coding they'll fact
so the final a few slides in my
presentation but hopefully that's been
an interesting example of the sort of
discovery of these journeys of discovery
that we can do so we're next if you want
to do more of this type of thing we
obviously as creative juice com also
there's a book called nature of code
which is by Dan ship really really
brilliant creative coding is such good
guy and what's mostly in processing
actually so is worth looking up posting
to the loads of resources about
processing but thans written a nature of
code book which is pay what you want but
also is got a vimeo channel which is him
doing all these videos of all these cool
particle effects and graphics generation
of generative art and all kinds of
brilliant creative coding techniques if
you wanted to come to the UK or europe
you could maybe come along to one of my
training workshops said dolly / training
i am really trying to figure out how I
can make these available to Americans
with the problem that i currently have
of my visa situation oh well i brought
you it it's fine when there's a
Holograms no problem so yes maybe follow
me on twitter said underscore ly and and
you can keep town forget with my visa
application or also if i manage to get
any more training stuff online hopefully
you'll be else you know
I mean the incredibly fortunate shouldnt
where been doing this creative Co stuff
and obviously when you start doing this
stuff you can get all personal projects
but the internet is a great place
professor put your some cooking cool on
the internet one tweets about it and
shares it before you know it you become
known for doing the things that you love
doing things that you do before in your
spare time eventually end up doing that
for a living that's the position that
I'm in now very fortunate it's not
really any clients any Marge's work on
way which is our art projects and do
these conferences and workshops and
stuff but if that's something you're
interested in them you know you should
be exploring this stuff i'm sure you all
are you doing plane mode copters and
marjorie nose and all sorts right last
couple of days yeah must have been
pretty awesome so while you're all
excitable from the conference don't give
up go home do some personal projects
don't just start the personal projects
finish them the reason people don't
generally finish personal projects
because halfway through it just becomes
work right can I always take 10 times
longer than you thought so keep my
advice would be to keep your personal
projects on a small unbuildable and
maybe finish Apple because if you don't
finish project there's no point in
starting and so these are personal
projects finish them stick them on the
internet that's kind of all the time
that I've got right now I'm so sorry I
can be end that there in person I hope
this was the next best thing I've really
enjoyed showing you some creative coding
techniques I hope that you're going to
carry on well you know take catch me on
Twitter tell me what you can do and
share the work you've been doing really
love to see it and maybe next year I'll
be there in person but until then I just
like to say thank you so much it's been
great to virtually meet