my name is Tobias nada I'm from Munich
and I'm the guy talking about flash at a
JavaScript conference what is this talk
is about is about yeah some flash some
html5 and of course JavaScript because I
created Gordon which is a flash runtime
written in pure JavaScript yeah what
what why did I do this this bro check
them because I'm don't really like okay
so yeah because I don't really like
flash but I love JavaScript and I love
html5 is it ok and yeah but I yeah for
me that this does not just that hearts
on flesh so it is also yeah bunch of
good part and these are I like the file
format they they used to deliver their
content this is the swf or quotes with
and i think is this really well
structured and it's a extendable file
format so it's really cool and yeah and
I think they did a really great job in
creating cool authoring tools to create
this flash content and to give ya people
they are not well if you're familiar
with underlying techniques or with we
are a programming staff or something the
ability to create rich media internet
and they don't have to care about
underlying techniques or how it will be
run in the browser so they felt really
yeah but that doesn't of course a lot of
more things I don't really like about
flash and that's because yeah the
runtime really sucks especially on
non-windows systems but there's no day
that my browser will not crash because
of the browser plugin yeah I'm a Mac
user and yeah i think the Durant I'm
would also suck on iPhone and on the
iPad and third one is there's a big
problem with X ability and semantics in
flash files so according to Douglas
Crockford I have to set another
statement and this is the flash runtime
must die so give me an our way up with
me so I like a backlash I have to of it
but the second is like a fancy one
because it has yeah lasers in the
background yeah and what and what is
going so corn is basically it's a like
it just just in time converting of yeah
flash files or Swift files into SVG or
javascript in your browser with no
blogging so it's pure JavaScript so you
can load in your browser javascript file
and convert it into a sweetie and
JavaScript so yeah and there's another
state one why I did this why i created
this project is to skip the
sorry yeah and flash intro and open the
web so some facts about about go on what
is going on Gordon's flash and France
sitting in the Dom that means you have
fully access of the behavior of your
embedded flash fires no no more black
box embedded files sitting in your dorm
it don't have any clue how it's working
and what is what is going on in there
and of course it's a hundred percent of
JavaScript there's no flash fallbacks in
there so no but so no no web as we do
something to render ddd the output SVG
and flash it's about 3.1 it's about
3,100 lines of code in total and it's 15
kilo byte gzipped in size oh how can I
go back n is n is fully customizable so
it used m/s vici by default at 22 doing
the rendering stuff but you could also
write an in canvas renderer or in WebGL
renderer and use it with gordon i will
show you an example later yeah go on
supports you following browsers supports
a chrome firefox safari also the
Mobile's of files will also run on the
iPhone and on the iPad and it supports
the latest opera yeah what about the
flash compatibility and gorham supports
the full flash one features and supports
all flesh two features except love
embedded sound and I'm currently working
on flash 3 features so there are over 7
there seventy percent done so how do you
how do you use gorn's as really since
it's really easy so after you include
sir after you download to do the main
file and included it in your website you
just have to create an instance of
Gordon movie and pass the path to your
as we have
file and giving some options like yeah
like the width and the high and the
autoplay which calls going to plate if
the file immediately or after wait up to
another statement so then you can use
the the movie file in this training
methods way that you may be no because
of jQuery
and how do how'd it go and do this today
first have to load and as we fi land
yeah this wave file is it's a binary
file so you how do you load it but how
do you load and parson binary file in
java script so that's really easy you
just create a regular xml httprequest
object but you have to write at the team
I'm tab with the override mime type
metal so to white at the browser
interprets it as a UT vesa a utf-8 file
and by setting this method by all
writing the mime type you tell the
browser to to pass the binary data as an
ASCII file you're gonna have to deal a
lot with different file formats wet so
it is not just the problem to two bars
in SF and sorry in Swift file format so
there are also a lot of other embedded
five moments like sound like video or
images so I do that with this data URL
which lets you and encode and binary
data stream and attach it to an image
tag and so you can embed it all your
files in line in your markup
so what techniques are going use to add
to render a flash fire in a browser so
it used them these html5 techniques they
use web workers to lodi as wav files in
the background and to parse the
different information of an SPF and so
you can yes so you so you can so you can
pass the as wav file in the background
without you block the user interface
ended use SVG to do all these rendering
stuff and of course canvas so
so how can Gordon we see how Gordon can
load a binary data and yes where if I
could also be compressed so I'm flashy
user set with a decompressing algorithm
into a compress the flash file so how
could you use that in JavaScript so the
one way is to use this in Fletcher's
library by ms and now is zoom oh yeah
it's a it's a part of the set lip
compression algorithms in JavaScript and
it works very well but it takes too long
time so it tooks for a 32 kilobyte
compressed data about 150 milliseconds
that's tested in the v8 and step that
that is tell me too long and yeah the
aromatic and go on implements its own
set loop implementation and it tooks
just 50 milliseconds that's just it's
about 10 times faster than the other one
how how how yeah how Gordon did it is
could be really interesting because it's
yeah some kind of odd because I'm
imagine you have a set lip compressed
data string and you want to decompress
it in the browser so so what I did is I
remember that the PNG file format also
compress this image data and what I do
is I take the decompressed data string
wrap a PNG head around it and hold it
encoded with base64 attach it to an
image tag draw that image take into a
canvas and then read the color
information of each pixel out of this
canvas
that's how I get the performance of
movement for about 10 times that's
really quick yeah what is already
implemented in Java Script fds we have
file specification and it supports all
kind of shapes yeah so its shape is
defined in Swift file it just just just
a bunch of path points and information
about the field style in the line style
I will give you some cool demos after
that presentation so I know my my
English will be Starks name but excuse
me use all kinds of images so there are
different types of images inside of in
Swift file they could be embedded jpeg
files and Barry PNG files and budget gif
files so that's ready to read them out
to encoding base64 one attachment to me
image tag that's no that's really easy
but it could yeah but em but of them in
the most jpeg pictures inside of these
days we have five you che back tables
and the header information are separated
from the data so if you have more if you
have a more than one images in your sbf
file yet it just saves a lot of memory
to do that they can and they cook yeah
they also support all kinds of of
embedded phones and text in Sullivan's
will file so it it just converts the
fonts cliff path informations into past
informations of SVG so by current is a
chest the WebKit supports embedded as we
have SVG files and you have over should
it should support it but for some reason
it doesn't work for me yeah there's
another way to to to get embedded force
work in firefox or two ways is is to
just set this ddd pass information of
each shape in line or you can or you can
create an ODT file or in an embedded web
form file and based encoded with base64
any tattoo to data grill so it supports
em buttons for interactivity I've not
implemented yet morphing so this is yet
in an intense WAV file the Yeti I'm
sorry it just defined it to start shape
and the end shape and do all this
transition and transformation stuff
between these two shapes I have two down
by the runtime yeah I have not
implemented yet but there's a really
really great solution and Raphael chairs
if you I think Dmitry we will show up
empty
it is bright bright digest yes with
files inside of another Swift file so
they have their own timeline they have
the old set of our frames and yeah I
will show you in a demo later yeah sound
is not implemented yet because there are
two types of sound in a non Swift file
its embedded sound which means added to
the raw data over of a sound file is
embedded into the Swift file and there's
there's another metal and there's
another type of chest define and sound
tech like similar to the html5 sound
tech that gives you an x-axis over an
API so that makes the sound scriptable
so it's not embedded in in Swift file so
so you can ensnare them yeah load an
external sound file into it yeah also
video embedded video is not implemented
yet in Gordon but Thurston our solution
is the video frame just to define just a
video frame which which is scriptable
via JavaScript or actions with ya gon
supports scripting by ActionScript so
there are two action models defined in
the as we have indeed Swift
specification on this D the first action
model was just a bunch of simple simple
instructions like play stop next frame
previous frame go to frame wait for
famous / etc and they introduced
ActionScript one in the swift for
implementation
and and the actionscript is just
compiled into tears in the into this
wave file yeah and it's compiling to
bytecode that is there's a bunch of
instruction which is interpreted by a
stack-based virtual machine so if you
have a statement like this one plus x x
3 and it will be compiled into this by
code or in this by code instructions
that i am pushed it pushes string on top
of a stack and then get the value of the
variable with with the name is on this
on the stack as a string then push
another value on the stack then call the
action multiplier which push the two
values from top of the stack multiplied
it and a pop state to vary from the
stack and multiply it and push the
result back tuesday
yeah and there's a damn then there's the
Swift 9 action model which which is
actually actionscript-3 and using
example how you can erode your own yeah
golden renderer like it watch it I
Randall if you want or a canvas renderer
you just have to define a custom class
which at which have to have to be a half
three merits it's define its place and
remove and yeah you can take the ED as
we have SVG r an aura of born as an
example so ya think it's better show you
some demos because I really up
so
so it start with a simple animation demo
so this is the flash ide and we just
open one of the demo files which is
shipped with the flash ID
but it must be yes
it's a similar animation you can show
you running in flash
so you can see it's not very spectacular
so we'll show you how to run this in
barn so just support it as an Swift file
this
so
just save it as task tops with
ok
go ahead let's create some demo file
create a new instance of Thor movie has
the name of this without you
it
and let it run in the browser
so this service area
yeah and this is yeah this is a flat
file interpreted by JavaScript converted
into SVG so i will show you that I'm not
lying so here is this that's the output
it works really really smooth so let's
create another example yeah I want to
show some scripting stuff so let's
create yeah movie so a swift file that
blast movie over that stream so we can
just go in there create a new file new
flash document so
so we just have to create a video frame
and we choose video which can be
scripted by agents ActionScript so try
drag it into the stage
I get to full screen yes
yep
adding some javascript actionscript
sorry echemus group sorry yeah it's
better you just need a new net
connection object
and good in you met stream object
we have to give this video frame an
instance name so we can exit every week
so we can access access it via script
call it my video
I should even something before start
drinking
ok
then attach 22 touch to that stream to
this video instance touch with you
let's play big buck bunny
start playing it
yeah we're finished chips save it as on
that foot file this and I'll write this
that's okay
all that work
so
Oh
to change this here from task to real
run it
I'm sorry
okay just credit card on it just copy
and paste it
so
yeah this should look
yeah there's there's Oh video
yeah we have necessary for scripting
Nash dreams of working Gordon and
you can see the script Gordon is
decompiling from the bytecode inside of
this web file and runs it as JavaScript
and see here the output
Curtis
it works
so I have another demo which is really
think it's really cool
try it here
it is a crash yeah this is the / f you
are running in borden and it's really
fast and each slide is loaded as a as a
swift file and it's interpreted by
gorham they can use zucchini you can use
any any presentation on SlideShare to