yes normal day for me so hi I'm
Cassandra I am currently funemployed but
that may change soon for reasons I can't
get into um anyway I'm gonna go to my
slides cool this is all mirrored awesome
should me see if I can change the
resolution to that without it like
yelling at me awesome cool alright so
I'm like the slides indicate i'm here to
talk about my nodebots outfit from
version 0.1 point zero two zero to two
point five point zero which is what I'm
wearing right now and I'll go into each
part of the outfit in just a bit but
first a little bit about my personal
story of robots art in Redemption so
when I was a kid I was an inventor um I
had access to a ridiculous amount of
Robo lab equipment my mom's an educator
and so every summer she would bring home
the Robo lab equipment from her school
and I get to play with it and I built
things like vending machines and coins
orders and and tennis ball four homers
for the dog and I also the best fashion
sense my art can't quite communicate to
you how awesome I looked in a yellow t
shirt and plaid pants but I swear I
rocked that anyway the best fashion
sense and I was an inventor but then I
had to grow up um so I actually started
my college education pursuing a degree
in chemistry because I had spent the
last four years of high school being
treated terribly by the computer science
community and so I decided no I'm done
with this and I was told I couldn't make
a living in art so I was told not to go
to art school so I can go to art school
I didn't go for a computer science
degree I end up finishing with one but I
didn't start it I started with a
chemistry degree because i was told that
being a woman in tech was was terrible
and i was told all these things in high
school like oh how many how many guys
were on your team that helped you code
every time I did a team project they
always assume the guys did the code
things like that and the funny thing
about being a victim of the pipeline
problem is it actually really prepared
me for being intact because I get the
same now that I did then but
it's really just wrapped in a faux
incredulous attitude now like what used
to be
oh but women aren't computer for
computer programmers now it's wait
you're really a computer programmer wait
you really do robots so being a victim
of the pipeline problem was actually
kind of funny because now that I'm in
the tech scene it's pretty much the same
stuff it's just like I said full
incredulous but j/s comp 2013 everything
I had gotten my computer science degree
but I I was a front-end web developer I
wasn't I wasn't an inventor anymore and
I certainly didn't do a lot of art but
what happened at jas comp 2013 is Rick
Alvarez and Rick Waldron gave a talk at
a workshop on how to do node BOTS and we
all got a little arduino uno in our bag
and without them and then additionally
people like CJ Silverio and Francis
colada and Sarah Gorecki and like the
node bought community in general I was
seriously about to quit check just
before the 2013 jazz comp I actually
went as an SOI was planning on quitting
tack and my so at the time was a web
developer he says like you should come
see this you can see this node boxing
and I'm so he dragged me to it and I was
like oh yeah fine whatever but without
them I don't think I would still be
intact i think i still would have quit
but because of the node box community
and i'll go into why a little bit later
it gets a wonderful community if you're
all interested in hard-wearing you
should check it out and thanks to that
I'm back I am totally an inventor again
I am an artist again I am everything
that little 56 year old me wanted me
like as an adult to be I remember I was
just doing my hair last week while
wearing all of this and I thought wow if
you told ten-year-old me that this would
be meat like now she would lose her mind
like she would be supremely happy and
probably wouldn't have tried to quick
tech in the first place um but yeah no
I'm back I'm an inventor and artist
again and it's awesome
it's been a really interesting journey
for the past year and a half though um
I've done all these things learned how
to do all these things I'm naturally an
introvert and I'm mildly autistic so
keep in mind that like just being up on
stage is still like a thing where i'm
like whoa wait what so yeah I'll go into
a little bit about as well why talk
about the outfit so um this video is my
first node bot oh it's fine if you can't
hear it because all of this is me
talking to my dad so my father is an
electrical engineer and this is from
Jay's comp 2013 I had just built my
first robot what it was was that web
page you could set the color of that RGB
LED from the web page I built that in 18
hours thanks to Rick and Raquel's
tireless dedication teaching me
everything I needed to know about are
like don't ya it's a big joke but like
that's what i did in 18 hours and that's
really what sparked this is that because
when i learned that i could go from not
knowing anything about arduino to
building that in 18 hours i thought well
what else can I do what else you know
where else can I go so like I said I
remembered I'm an inventor and I
remembered I'm an artist and I spent the
three months after j/s cops 2013 I was
working part-time so I spent every time
every moment I wasn't working on client
work I was working on robots and I built
just about everything under the Sun with
RGB LEDs in color and I really like
playing with light and color so I kind
of stuck to that because I wasn't like
doing much else so then I learned how
not to be afraid because most of the
stuff that I've built of course the
skirts freaking out because it's demo
day just because it hasn't been done
doesn't mean it can't I've not found a
skirt like this yet and when I wanted to
build it the first thing I did was
google to find someone else who did it
so I could copy them and when no one did
it I go wow too bad i'll just go build
something else and then I can't remember
who i think it mighta been Raquel she
was like why don't you just build it
anyway that's like oh right I can do
that I don't have to like wait for
someone else to do this I can do it
myself and and I can code I can stay up
all night I can do this and the
thing is I can't be afraid of the trolls
actually when I built my skirt I was
worried that some stupid person would
say some stupid thing at some conference
and I would never want to wear the skirt
again and a lot of people backed me up
and said hey look you can't be afraid
you know I know it's I know and if
someone will actually that was the best
comfort I got which was someone will but
you got to learn how to live fast and
you gotta learn how to move through it
so yeah so I'm going to go into the the
construction of the first node BOTS
dress and this was premiered at jas comp
2014 in june of this year i started
building it in March I was so excited
that I just kind of got started really
early I don't have a ton of photos uh
and i have to mention no cats were
harmed in the making of this dress but
one felt he wasn't getting enough
attention um he would actually jump up
in my lap and get between me and the
dress and just like stare at me until i
would pat him for a livin and he won her
off so that I and you can kind of even
see like the cat hair on the dress
because ace wouldn't leave it alone so
about the dress it was powered by an S
Purina that I just got enough
Kickstarter if you've never seen in s
Purina before they're about half the
size of a credit card and they run a
modified version of JavaScript like on
the board so you don't have to there's
no see there's no Johnny Five wrappers
there's no tethering it's just running a
modified version of java script on the
board and the reason i picked the board
at the time was it was the easiest
smallest wireless way to handle
individually addressable RGB LEDs which
is what the the skirt is it's got one
data pin of course again demo day it
just doesn't want to work up today
anyway so I also used a photocell which
you can see on the left side of the
lapel that was to match the lights to
ambient light these get really bright
and so what I did was when the outside
was dim they would dim and when the
outside was bright they would get
brighter so you could see them it sounds
like the inverse of what you want when
you think about it you want to be able
to see them and then them I forgot to
get pictures of jazz cause of my dress
so that's really like the only full
picture of the entire dress so one day
the one that I'm gonna go over what I
learned and I guess I forgot the bullet
point take lots of pictures of it anyway
uh always bring a backup power supply
the original node box dress was powered
by lithium
polymer battery the lithium polymer
batteries headers fell off the day
before the conference and I'm not
confident enough my soldering to put a
500-degree satire near life lithium
polymer battery I don't know many people
that are so what I ended up doing was
taking you know those those big old
batteries you can plug a USB cable into
like recharge your phone I didn't put
any one of those my purse running the
cable through to the back of the dress
to power the micro microcontroller and
using that as a power supply so always
bring a backup spot power supply
hardware debugging 50 RGB LEDs is tricky
and I think I'm really proving that
right now with the fact that my skirts
decided to freak out today and that I
love making wearable robots all of the
strife all of the blood and there was
blood I can't so very well all of the
everything that went into that dress the
second i had a six-year-old girl walk up
to me and ask can I do this and are can
I do this when I grow up and I looked
down at her and went you can do this now
that made everything worth it so I
learned from that project that I love
doing this I love making wearable
robotics that do light in color and
possibly sound and all sorts of stuff so
I really don't and so when I got home
from Jas conf I knew immediately I was
going to build an outfit I was going to
take apart the dress figure out what
went wrong because there were a few
things that went wrong and rebuild and
so it started with the skirt the skirt
I'm wearing right now which is the first
part of version 2 it is premiered at
Thunder planes Jess about two months ago
and other than the flight here it's
never really sustain any damage I think
someone cut a wire in it because like a
really thick wire was cut when I got
here so I don't know if the TSA just
decided to go work and are happy or
whatever but there was actually some
damage to it when I got here but other
than that it's been pretty darn
resilience it's still powered by an S
Perino mostly because I just really like
the S ferrino code and I already had all
my algorithms written for it so I
rewrote it for the Esprit know so it's
actually the same LEDs I took apart the
old dress it does not exist anymore in a
current state mostly does the wiring was
so awful that I would have had to redo
all of it to keep the rest and because
it was sewn in I accidentally made a
couple holes trying to rewire it knows
just like you know I'm thought I'm just
going to
the LEDs in recycle them plus these
discs LEDs that come from Adafruit are
not the cheapest 30 sheet of 25 is like
$35 so you can I definitely want to
reuse it has a new wiring system part of
the reason the right side of the skirt
is freaking out and not the left is I
split the power into several different
rails because this is one chain of LEDs
and before when I would put just one
power in one ground rail the last led in
the the skirt would not be nearly as
bright as the first so I learned to fork
the power into four different rails so
that all for you know I could split it
up to four different chains and they all
pretty much have the same brightness so
that's the more stable power system
where I learned from the skirt I still
need conductive thread tech to get
better I really really do you show me a
a Kickstarter for a conductive thread
that isn't really really awful and I
will show you I will find a million
dollars oh I will send wires which I
used 26 gauge silicone coated fin wires
they're great for flexibility but they
break for no reason you look at one of
these wires funny and they break so I
actually never rewiring the front of the
skirt before I came before i went to
robots comp with thicker wire so i have
to like adjust i got to move the skirt
because though if a wire bends it'll
bend the cloth with it but it also
doesn't break for no reason and then
when i finish this card i thought well
okay that's cool but now what where do I
go next so then um while I was debuting
the dress I got a little bit inebriated
um and I ended up talking to a gentleman
named Ryan day maybe madam he works for
Pinocchio and apparently I talked myself
into a dev kit for Pinocchio because he
handed me this little cardboard box and
then I woke up the next morning and like
Oh what I don't remember this and sure
enough there was Pinocchio in it and so
the first thing I thought it was a pair
of shoes because Bluffs right you know
it so if you've never seen a Pinocchio
before they're a mesh networking robotic
system they speak to each other with a
low-power radio and then the lead scout
for any troop has a Wi-Fi shield or
can't have a Wi-Fi shield that will
communicate with the internet so in the
case of my shoes the left shoe has a
Wi-Fi shield which is connected to my
phone's hotspot and the right shoe is
just a reg
troop and it communicates it gets
information from the internet by
communicating with the left shoe so it's
like I said powered by Pinocchio I have
a nitrous server that pulls down my
twitter user stream and watches for
favorites and when someone favorites
something I've tweeted online on the
shoes turn gold right now they pulse
purple the other thing I can do online
which is kind of fun is I can use their
HQ so right now you can kind of see
their pulsing purple I can actually tell
i've done this demo enough if i can type
with one hand and hold my foot up and
stand on one foot so i'm going to change
these red I think that's righti so I
think imma change the other shoe so I'm
gonna wait for success it takes it takes
a second sometimes it worked Oh did
didn't it alright so now you can kind of
see Oh maneuver there it's now pulsing
red so this is kind of what the last
speaker is getting into with a dedicated
cloud they set this up for you when you
when you set up a troop so you have this
at your disposal and all I do with my
little nitrous server is I is I tell it
when there's a favorite call this
function that makes it flash cold so
yeah neat stuff so yeah really cool
platform really easy to debug as well
especially cuz them so for waterproofing
what I did was each Pinocchio is in a
waterproof radioshack enclosure and then
I just drilled holes for the wires and
then hot glued around the wires sorry
waterproof it so they're waterproof
thank goodness Oh Florida I would have
been interesting without that and yeah
so my electric is swelling up pardon me
got robots flowing out of everywhere
that's still flashing yes anyway
robotics demos are hard robotics is not
hard robotics demos are hard so what I
learned from the shoes is people will
almost always laugh when you say
something like hold on I gotta charge or
debug or paying my shoes um people who
almost always laugh when you something
like that comes out of your mouth and
now I have it with my hat to and sew
sewing in the converse is easier than
you think if you just get the right
sewing Neil
and like I said sometimes getting drunk
sometimes being drunk yields free
hardware research is ongoing um I got a
lot of free hardware robots calm fine i
drank a lot of booze on a correlation
causation so I'm not working on version
3 i'm halfway through version 3 i'm at
2.5 point 0 with this if you can see
it's actually the robots conf logo
that's because I this was part of the
robot conf goodie bag and I actually the
wearable speaker put regular LEDs and
like a battery and so which is like a
regular circuit and I'm like okay cool
i'm going to put RGB leds in it so i SAT
there in like soldered RGB LEDs into a
beanie and this is what I got out of it
it's powered by an electric imp which is
actually really cool and I can show you
because I didn't sew it into the Hat I
totally wasn't being lazy I did it on
purpose um so the electric imp is it's
an it's it looks like an SD card so this
little SD card looking thing is the
microcontroller and so like you plug it
into a shield like you would plug Sun SD
card into something and like it's got
the pins on the shield and then in my
case it doesn't have a battery like
connector so I kind of put the battery
connector on the pins because you know
that what's that legal disclaimer about
not you know mimicking me that might be
good right now better just fill it in it
see I told you robots demos are hard
robots are really clumsy me today but
anyway yeah it's it still needs some
code for interactivity it actually just
cycles through rainbows when it's hooked
up to power which I can still do this
come on there we go then you get back
there so yeah and what I learned from
this project is it be an easier way
hackable I'm getting conductive thread
through the cloth of a beanie is just
leaving the only trick is leaving enough
conductive thread so that when the
beanie fabric stretches you have enough
conductive thread in there not snap
because it does not stretch also see
number one of what I learned from the
shoes yeah people will really find it
funny when you say hold on I got a ping
my hat squirrel is weird it's their
their language cool weird and they have
this agent device setup which i think is
really cool because it's kind of what
I've set up for myself with my other
projects this is their ide and so you
get a device and you you program and
squirrel the device
code and then you can it you can
implicitly tell it to ping the agent
which is the code on the left I actually
haven't done anything with the agent yet
but they set all this up for you and
they give you a nice little URL I should
make this a little bigger they give you
a nice little oh not that not that a
nice little URL at the top they'll let
you access your agent from like say a
node server or whatever so you can you
can do a minimal amount of squirrel and
then just like push it off to a node
server for all the processing of
whatever that's really cool and then um
yeah so I have one last kind of
wearables project that I'm still working
on so somebody at spark drop this off at
robots comp it's called their internet
button and it's got 11 RGB LEDs I've got
their little battery shield on it so
that it can run without wires and then
on the back it's got four buttons and
it's got an accelerometer on it I want
to make a wireless presentation advancer
with it so that it changes colors as I
move and then I hit the button to
advance my slides but I'm not quite
there yet just wanted to show that off
because that's a really neat thing and
the photons going to be awesome really
really cool stuff coming up there so
back to my slides I also built a bunch
of other stuff this year that wasn't
wearables I have an NPM module called
open pixel control for controlling large
amounts of RGB LEDs with beaglebone okay
oh so that the project on the left
that's 1024 individually addressable RGB
LEDs that I have arranged into a panel
at cascadia what it did is it would take
your picture with a tehsil and then
pixel eyes your picture and then put it
on the grid and I have a really cool
picture of Carter in sunglasses on the
on the grand it looks so cool but yeah I
know but but you chose to wear those
cool lime green sunglasses with the red
shirt like it really kind of showed off
what I really like the picture of the
think like the toddler who's just like
staring at the light grid so his eyes
are all making he's like if you could
see his forehead in his eyes adored
layman flickers a thing um so and then I
built a name tag that kind of broke but
I'm still working on getting that back
to normal and I guess I put the picture
the internet button up there too I also
helped run to node BOTS days in Austin
so node BOTS days july 27th of every
year I say I helped run I really didn't
do all that much
ray Pearce actually did like 90 for the
loric and I just kind of like stood
there so he's the best and I had I had
to give him a shout out because I'm the
22 no BOTS days we've had 2013 we had 10
attendees and everybody walked home with
a spark fundamentals kit thanks to local
sponsors this year we had 30 spark
course delivered to my house one for
each attendee we did have 30 we ended up
with 35 we let five other people and
after registration ended and then we did
the the puffle BOTS the little suma bots
and yeah 30 tenis we also had Donovan
buck who's doing some really cool stuff
with hexapods come keynote from Houston
so the node box meeting in Austin is
thriving and growing and it's really fun
the scene so the things I've learned
from node BOTS day or more about
community than about node BOTS and I I
feel like those are inexorably linked
because no bots is such an amazing
community we have a code of conduct for
everything for our contributions for our
forums for everything there is a code of
conduct to be involved in the node bot
community and I really appreciate that
on a level that I can't really
articulate very well the things I
learned about community code is by no
means the only way to contribute you
don't need a pull request to be a
contributor to a community if you have
docs if you've helped people if you've
taught people if you've done knowed
school you've commuted you you've
contributed to the node community like
just because you don't have a pull
request on node core because who does
there's 20 of them for reals and you've
still contributed to the community
you're right no means not a member of
the community just because you haven't
contributed directly code there are many
many ways to contribute to your
community even it was just helping out a
newbie codes of conduct are important
and feel free to argue this is me off
stage all you want because I'm not going
to budge codes of conduct are
extraordinarily important and the last
thing I learned is do not ever make
assumptions about people ever because I
learned that's the easiest way to say
something remarkably silly is to assume
something about a person by how they
look or by an arbitration you might know
about them like for instance I have
friends with various visual and hearing
impairments and if I assume they can't
do something without asking them first
well I easily look like ayaats most of
the time
so the number one thing I've learned
about community that I think kind of
makes everything else work is don't make
assumptions about people regardless of
what you know about them already we just
ask it's a lot easier and seriously we
do have some issues with community I was
at robot conf last weekend and it got
out that my dad is an electrical
engineer and I had a guy come up to my
glue scene he goes oh so your dad built
these yeah right that gasp right there
really write like oh my gosh League I i
actually was silent for about three
seconds and people who know me know
that's amazing um i just kind of stared
at him for three seconds I go excuse me
and he goes well your dad built these
right and then you kind of coded them
what you want a shovel um did and III
apparently I I told him to just get the
hell away from my booth like I just like
told me go away um yeah that happened in
2014 I had a name tag and I wanna I'm
gonna be honest and I haven't really
told the story I don't want to rebuild
my name tag because some guy at a party
was like now I have an excuse to stare
at your chest because i had a color
changing name tag that was an LCD for
real in 2014 that happen so the last
bullet is do i seriously need to be
talking about this in 2014 yeah I I
really do because this stuff still
happens and we all need to be aware of
it I think nodebots is is easily the
best community I've been involved in the
this this is not a thing that happens to
me at all regularly with node box I've
had a couple of isolated incidents but
when i get out into like the real world
it happens a lot more often so keeping
it you know think about what you say
because it can really really affect
people in ways that you you may not
understand well luckily for me my love
for robots a node and javascript and and
the amazing people in the node and node
bots community many of whom are sitting
in this room right now outpaces my anger
and fear and frustration at the system i
live in i will break down and cry
sometimes i will break down and get
upset i will break down in few
expletives for minutes on end but
luckily my my love of robots in the
community is going hopefully forever
outpaced my anger and fear and
frustration and
I'm not going anywhere so what you can
do to join me if you're interested in
node BOTS specifically forums node BOTS
thought I oh we're kind of picking up
steam is it doesn't have a ton of post
yet but we're working on it and your
local node BOTS meetup day whatever
brian hughes runs the node BOTS SF and
in fact they're doing an event on
saturday i'll be there with this giant
suitcase of robotics I've been carrying
all month and i'll be working on
different projects i want to see what
you build the community is too but like
I specifically me and like this person
wants to see what you built I love it
when people email me or tweet at me with
things that they bail even if it's just
like look I got an LED blinking I still
want to see that it's awesome and
amazing and it makes me happy to see it
and when you document and write about
what you did also write about what went
wrong because people learn so much more
about what went wrong with your project
I won't what right so always always own
up well it's not good owning obviously
saying like oh I made this decision it
didn't work out and here's why so thanks
for listening that's just a really funny
gift like that cat and not banana like I
can't I sleep like he's just so
possessive of that freakin banana and
it's late and at the end the best part
is right now that right there we're just
sitting in the hallway like anyway I
love like if I'm no botanist on twitter
and github and that's my email address
if you want to email me your awesome
projects I'm just part of that battery
still alive um but yeah thanks for
listening and