okay and I'm here to as a last minute
kind of request to back on the excellent
presentation by Sarah Sweden on SVG to
make a long story short
Sarah was originally going to talk about
shapes and I was really going to talk
about his Fiji and she got in and I
didn't quite get him but then she
changed your mind so I'm gonna try and
do a accessory top to that featuring a
little bit of my own work and talking
about some of the things that Sarah
didn't have time to address but I would
recommend that if you're watching this
now you go see Sarah's verse so you can
get the basics from her but I'm going to
start off from just a little bit of
perspective so I am lovely story at
Dublin on Twitter I have a blog called
demosthenes dot info where I write about
web development and I'm a by trade I'm
web development teacher that's what I do
I teach full-time part-time night
classes all the time that's what I do
I'm also a writer I published through a
press last year Pro css3 animation and
I'm also a contributing editor to
Smashing Magazine I do their coding
section so most of the requests for and
offers of writers come for coding at
least come through me for special
magazine so it's VG s VG's been thought
of and debated and worked through as a
kind of very often as this foreign thing
thus foreign not terribly understandable
kind of battle against
and it's really not right we really
shouldn't think of SVG and CSS as being
enemies or even being frenemies they
really are two parts the same side so
don't think of them as battling each
other just think of them as one tool
that's like a kick-ass light saber
that's essentially the joined together
and I'll show you ways in which both CSS
and SVG and ultimately HTML can really
start to complement each other they're
not oh it's only just as SVG or it's
only just CS yes the two really do start
to work to give him very interesting
kinds of ways so I'm going to give a
very quick little breakdown of a couple
of things that people need to do again
Sarah covered a little bit of this but
I'm going to do a in addition some of
this is again from my blog but I'll give
you your ELLs so Adobe Illustrator work
for SVG production so very quickly if
you know and most people will be using
Adobe Illustrator to get some sort of
work out if you know that you're going
to be using Adobe Illustrator for export
to SVG then there's a couple of things
that you do want to do you'll want to
set up your canvas in pixels and that
seems kind of weird at the first because
SVG is meant to be the scale free
doesn't matter what kind of Units you
use and that's true but it's easiest if
you set up a canvas first in pixels
because it's the easiest thing to relate
to it doesn't mean that your SVG is
limited to a certain pixel dimension
don't get that me here at all but it
does help move things across work out
where components are that sort of stuff
the artboard that you make so whatever
size of artboard you want to make is
perfectly fine but the artboard is going
to become the view box of the SVG
essentially although view box does a lot
of things in SVG it's
the visible area of your SVG so if you
want to do things off canvas that's
perfectly fine
just make sure that your your art your
borders a certain size but if you want
to make it larger later that's perfectly
fine as well just be aware that the two
will by default match up in Illustrator
again you can change them
SVG again in illustrator will set itself
up to CMYK don't make the mistake that
generations of people have made when
using these tools and setup for CMYK
when you really want RGB in most cases
so make sure it's RGB the thing to
remember about making components in
Illustrator is that as you make them the
way that I like to think about SVG is
you're making drawings as data you're
not just making pretty lines you're not
just making curves you're making
drawings as data so as you build things
give them some sort of naming convention
get any kind of naming convention it's
fine as long as you're consistent and
you stick to it so stick to building
something and name everything as you
build it while it's not absolutely
necessary to do so it becomes a whole
lot easier later when you're trying to
then manipulate that as a purist VG
simplify it's a couple of things as a
rule I use the fewest number of points
to create a shape again a lot of people
will start to use point point point
point point to try and get something on
the screen don't do that try and use the
fewest number of numbers of points I try
to avoid filters in adobe illustrator as
they're not yet translated into SVG with
the adobe illustrator xpg export so
don't tend to do that don't stroke
things if you don't have to stroking is
going to add another level or layer to
your SVG that you really don't need if
you need it fine but if you don't make
sure it's not there
and try to keep polygons and circles as
geometrical objects don't try to break
them apart create a background if
necessary understand that SVG elements
are transparent by default they're
automatically off mask that's awesome
but it means that there's no body to add
SVG element there's nothing there that
you can say oh okay I'm just going to
color the background of this black or
whatever it happens to be you can do
that in the body element of your HTML
page where the CSS is sorry where the
SVG is ultimately going to be used but
you can't do an SVG itself short of
drawing a giant rectangle or something
behind the whole ad board you can kind
of sort of do a background on the SVG
itself using as well we'll take a look
at this a little bit you can use CSS to
create backgrounds so it's it's possible
to do you're just going to be a little
bit careful about how to do it
finally if if possible before exporting
from illustrator to SVG try and merge
shapes so use a finer tools try and
merge them together if possible again
fewer elements simple elements better
doesn't mean the SVG can't be complex
doesn't mean it can't involve a lot of
Elam's but obviously the fewer things
you have and better finally I decide how
you're going to treat your text it's
important to understand that you can in
SVG have takes the text so it's readable
it's styler belitz everything else but
with the downsides that we've
experienced with the text readable style
text on the web forever that is you
might try and load a font and the font
doesn't load right if you're trying to
use a special kind of fun so it has all
the same problems in that regard or you
can break apart you can absolutely break
it into outlines downside of that is you
it's not readable anymore it's purely
path information you just can't use it
that way anymore
so do you try to make a decision about
is this going to be readable because it
is by Google by everything else they
leave it us takes style it and
understand that ok
styles might not always be applied in
every circumstance we've got to be
careful with that or you want it exactly
that way but you don't want it
ultimately readable by anything but you
want it manipulable so you can move
points around then absolutely break it
and convert into outlets
finally crop the outcrop the Apple no
point in having areas that you don't
need and export to SVG one thing to keep
in mind about that the export for SVG
adobe illustrator kind of even adobe
illustrator CC kind of sort of lies to
you it does allow an export it
absolutely does but adobe illustrator CC
has this semi vaunted new feature of
make responsive and it's not totally
true
it goes part of the way it removes the
height and width elements which I'll get
into a little bit but it doesn't really
do everything that you need it to do in
most circumstances so take the make
responsive in option in SVG with a from
illustrator with a grain of salt there's
a one important point in illustrator do
try to you've got an option to reduce
the number of decimal points used in as
the export and honestly decimal points
are the position of each little element
the position of each and a point in the
SVG drawing you don't need three decimal
places for drawings in the vast majority
of circumstances so if you can avoid
that because all it does is add file
space it just makes the SVG larger or
longer if you possibly can reduce the
number of decimal points to ideally one
all those stuff can ultimately be done
post-processing with some of the tools
that
Sara talked about but why post-process
something when you can make sure it's
right the first time so and finally
obviously export the file as an SVG
treated as SVG it's all good to go from
that point okay basic SVG cleanup
so again Sara was talking a little bit
about how to make a SVG clean through
the nature of some tools and that's good
to know
and that's important it's also really
useful to know what those tools are
actually doing it's not terribly
complicated for the most part and if you
understand a little bit about what
they're doing then you can do this by
hand if the tool doesn't work you can
understand what might go wrong things of
that nature
so there's a couple of things generally
speaking the export of an SVG document
will be from illustrator from Inkscape
from a number of other tools will be
extremely verbose you'll have a lot of
information in there and while it's not
wrong to have the information in there
you can usually save yourself quite a
bit of space by doing a couple of things
so first of all note again that this in
this case has five decimal places for
the SVG points on the path and again
wouldn't be necessary I'd I could
post-process this take them out but I'm
not going to concentrate on that for
right now okay things you don't need you
honestly don't need in the vast majority
of cases unless you're doing some sort
of of deep deep dive with XML um you
don't need the external POG you don't
need the doctor
you don't just don't need them you do
need the XML NS namespacing stuff mostly
for the fact that without it's not going
to be valid so it may as well leave it
in version you don't take the clean need
with the height width and height other
things that for the most part
get people a little bit screwed up
because they they think that what's
constraining this thing is the width and
height or the view box I think the view
box out they get confused between the
two so I'll explain what's going on
there for right now take it out notice
that I actually changed
you don't need ID on the SVG element
itself unless you're doing a whole bunch
of work a whole bunch of SVG's on the
same page so again we can take that out
everything's fine
don't need it ID at the same time of
course make sure that it's still valid
make sure that everything is still
working don't need devs
very often unless it's defining a filter
or some other stuff do be careful about
group transforms you'll very often find
empty groups or groups that don't
actually do anything Google Group does
geez
if they don't do anything they can
usually be removed if there are groups
with IDs if they're groups with
transforms on them beat them the heck
alone you don't want to play around with
them because otherwise removing them or
changing blue eyes spoil your work then
there's a whole bunch of stuff in there
here's where it gets interesting okay so
I started off talking about the fact
that SVG and and CSS are really
copacetic they're really buddies they're
not fighting against each other so let
me demonstrate a couple of ways and what
tests true you can see that by default
most tools will put a lot of the styles
for this stuff inline doesn't need to be
in line at all doesn't it ever a path
I'm sorry an ID but doesn't need to be
in line at all you can do the self same
stuff that you've always been used to
and work with by doing an embedded style
tag inside the CSS and that style tag
can absolutely contain the vast majority
of the CSS that used to it it can
contain media queries it can contain
hovers it can contain most of the stuff
they used to again sarod that are very
nice little screen of here's what
the page will take is what it won't take
so there are some exceptions but for the
most part every every piece of CSS you
used to can actually be applied his word
gets interesting
so our path has an ID of path one let's
just change that this is called a Jedi
okay so it has an ID if it has an ID it
can be addressed like an ID or a class
or most anything else that you used to
it can be addressed as an ID just like
anything else right it's a fragment so
it's a piece on a page it's part of the
dom the really interesting part is this
stuff can get used as part of that style
we don't need even on we don't need
stroke in this case all right okay
so what's happening essentially we can
take many not all but many of the style
attributes from SVG and apply them as
styles in CSS that starts to make things
really neat and really interesting what
it means is that you can use any CSS
color in this case associated with that
style right so it means that you can
have immediate manipulation of this now
people get a little confused often
students I think you get a little
confused the first time I show them this
because they say but there's no fill
property does that mean I can now go on
to my normal agent email so a page and
say they've fill read no you can't it's
only applicable to SVG but within the
context of SVG it's perfectly understood
and perfectly reasonable so the the
really interesting part is that all the
CSS the apps are all CSS that you know
can absolutely be applied so if we say
let's say HSL hsla
goodness sake and we say okay 150% 50%
come 0.3 so yeah any HSL any colors any
kinds of things that you want to apply
you can absolutely do it doesn't mean
that you have to stick with hex if you
want to stick with the X that's
perfectly fine there's a Pasadena
okay so SVG has a thing called opacity
for obvious reason so fill opacity but
you can do capacity in however you want
to set it up in just the way that you
wouldn't see us yes all right it's a
it's a CSS thing so now we can use CSS
directly on our SVG okay you can do
hover fix inside your SVG just using CSS
so if you say let's say hover over their
element okay it's got an ID power over
let's say we want to do a partial fade
okay now there's a couple of interesting
things to note about that and of course
yeah you can transition as well right
let me push that down all the way down
to zero
so yeah it fans then it fades out so you
can absolutely do all the interface
stuff that you're used to and css3
applied to SVG there's a couple of
interesting things to note about this
SVG is defined by shapes
if the SVG is defined by shapes it's not
the box model you used to in the sense
that you'll notice that if this was a
picture like a pink and normal
circumstances as soon as you move over
the area of the thing right the
rectangular box that contains it then
this thing's going to activate right but
in SVG that doesn't count it really only
looks at the shape so I have to be over
that shape before anything happens and
that starts mean very very precise pixel
responses we've all seen icons big
rectangular icons with circular shapes
inside and the problem is you move over
the rectangular outside area and the
circle turns on or clicks or does
whatever it's going to do and it's a
Miss registration in SVG one of its real
advantages is there is no registration
if you make a shape and you say their
shape is a link or the shape has a hover
vehicle the shape has whatever that's
the shape and that's what registers
which makes it really really powerful
and very very good okay so that's your
basic SVG cleaner that's and some of the
ways in which you can start to use CSS
practically I'm just saying okay I've
got this SVG I want to make it hover the
one thing I should mention the one thing
you have to be aware of is that CSS
written inside the SVG it will affect
the appearance of the SVG but not as
interactivity in other words you can't
write a hover rule inside the SVG and
then take that SVG as an image and put
it on the page as image here's my SVG as
inside rage demo the the appearance will
work but the interactivity won't if you
want the interactivity
you've got to move it either as an
object or as a typically increasingly
just as a flat SVG straight inside the
HTML you just bonkers inside the HTML
and then you get all the interactivity
you get everything else so you've got to
be a little bit careful about okay I can
write rules absolutely but those rules
won't necessarily translate interactive
ways into the SVG as and as an actual
image but SVG straight on the page
absolutely well okay so a surprising
number of people in the conference that
we've just been attending don't know
about SVG filters or using filters in
general there was a quickl hand up and
very few people were using them and
that's surprising to me because one of
the things that we're talking about
increasingly is okay we want to get
pages loaded as quickly as possible we
want to have interactivity as snappy as
possible we want to not have a lot of
work to make things happen we don't want
to have to do multiple things in our
workflow so traditionally with filters
people think of filters with WebKit and
and understandably so because filters
and WebKit they've been in there for a
couple of years now and people say hey
they're really neat and it's it's
totally true you can absolutely while
they went through a couple of changes in
terms of the spec yeah you can
absolutely do filters in that way but
not too many people know that the same
filters were also built into IE up into
IE 8 right I'll talk a little bit about
IE 10 and 11 and so on so forth in a
second and very often they were really
simple stuff like that sorry this stuff
like this so all right so you have
Safari and at least modern Safari and
modern chrome covered with the modern
web kilt css3 thing that unfortunately
other browsers haven't great yet you
have
ie up nine covered by grace the
grayscale filter what do you do about
Firefox well in Firefox you can add a
tiny tiny little SVG farm and that SVG
file is so subtle but during various
Fuji file is like the world's simplest
SVG it's tiny in this case to be fair
it's a color matrix the the nice thing
about this is you really don't need to
understand totally it's it's a matrix
math it's no big deal but you pop it
into a page or you can pop it in as a
separate file if you want to but it's
such so tiny I usually pop it straight
into the page okay what is it doing
very simply it's a bit of SVG that
essentially does the same filter job so
that fills the grayscale for the URL
grayscale because it looks at the ID
right in this case it hit the filter has
an ID of grayscale so I use it here and
it does the exact same job in Firefox
and the nice part about this is that you
now have the same thing and it's one of
the really good examples of progressive
enhancement unless you or your client
are real stickler for everything it has
to look exactly the same way generally
speaking people aren't going to be
hugely upset if they're in IE 10 for
instance and if they don't know that the
the thing is meant to be black and white
and then transitioning into color later
and they just see a color version
because ia 10 is a between a rock and a
hard place it doesn't use support the
web should be the WebKit css3 style
filters it doesn't do the SVG filters at
least in this way so unfortunately it's
in a rocky place at the moment
but if they don't they're not aware of
that then that's fine the advantage is
you load one image once you want to turn
to SVG so you want to turn it into
grayscale that's that's perfectly fine
you had it you had a filter and it's
done you don't have to load multiple
versions of the image you don't have to
have multiple HTTP requests you don't
have to do weird things with image
sprites they just done so it's it's nice
it makes a whole lot of sense to it you
could do the same things same idea with
things like blur again traditional
Microsoft blur filters
okay so ie 8 etc etc modern blur filters
in terms of WebKit and blur in terms of
SVG and you can transition the things as
well tell ya you can absolutely have
blur on and off sepia toning totally
possible as well let me think from out
here but very quickly because I'm almost
out of time a couple of other areas in
which people don't necessarily
understand that is Fiji can start to be
used image maps for anybody who's been
around on the web for 10 years plus
we'll remember image maps and they went
in kind of the way of the dodo they're
not responsive they will grind these big
cloud images but they still do have
their place they were actually really
good for touchscreens because especially
for kids because they could see them and
they could touch them touch the pictures
and navigate away from their problem was
they're not responsive at all
traditional image Maps copying SVG you
can absolutely make responsive image
maps because you can make SVG responsive
or you can put an image bitmap image to
the background and that hotspot will
exactly scale with the image as it moves
up and down which is really neat
animated measurements using
clip areas you can clip out bitmap
photographs using parse and SVG you can
then again because it's perfect pixel
pixel perfect registration you can start
to both link those areas and animate
them inside had an article a knit
magazine a couple of months ago about
that same technique if you'll read up on
it perhaps my most fun adaptive
illustration so adaptive illustrations
are the idea that you can do media
queries inside of SVG so a lot of
traditional kinds of use of SVG is in
responsive design is making things small
again nothing wrong with making things
smaller rearranging them placing them in
different orders that's perfectly fine
what's somewhat unexplored I think is
the concept of well we we don't just
need to make things smaller we could
also do things like as an example
starting to remove components and you
can remove components you can see the
top there you can see other components
moving outside of this because each
fragment is identifiable inside that SVG
so you can absolutely remove them using
media queries and simplify designs not
just say okay this thing has to get
smaller and not just saying oh we have
to switch to something else but
literally simplifying diagrams on
smaller screens simplifying tree
diagrams for instance on smaller screens
because you don't have the space no one
sort of zoom in/out it's all kinds of
really wonderful possibilities there
very finally the CSS spec for gradients
is meant to have animation it's meant to
do it
and fortunately it doesn't know no one
to my knowledge no one supports it yet
which is really really unfortunate
however SVG has supported animation
gradients for a
forever so you can start do really
really interesting work but this comes
up by animating the actual gradients you
have to use animate tags inside of SVG
and they're not too dissimilar to the
concept of transitions so it takes a
little bit again you see but it's not
too too terribly too simple
so you can finally this is a basic sky
24 hour Skype intermission you can
finally start to animate gradients which
is wonderful and there's a lot in there
but eventually of course this won't be
supported in CSS but if you need it
right now
and you you wanted to animate it great
in don't in SPG absolutely so that's all
the time I have I hope this was helpful
again if you have follow-up questions by
all means ask me on twitter follow up on
the blog and I hope to do a fuller and
more complete a track presentation in
future CSS cons thanks very much