you guys hear me yeah that's good okay
I'm gonna give a talk on how to rapidly
prototype with JavaScript but for
multiple devices multiple platforms
pretty pretty serious stuff so i'll
expect you to pay attention and you will
ask questions at the end you guys ready
are you guys ready all right I think you
guys are ready all right my name is Joe
McCann i work at frog design in the
united states in austin texas home of
this dickhead i work at a company we do
a lot of innovation work so we do it's
probably a lot of stuff that you never
see or if you do see we can't claim it
it's kind of sucks for me but it's fun
fun stuff we work on we work
predominantly with Fortune 500 companies
like hewlett-packard and disney and
other companies i can't really mention
unfortunately but we get to do really
cool stuff and since i've been working
that i've been trying to integrate using
javascript instead of things like WPF
cutie like that
so so what would you say rapid
prototyping is anybody have a clue
thanks captain obvious all right yeah
it's fast right for sure so a more sort
of formalized discretion oh by the way
let me back up for a second before i
define rapid prototyping I will be
talking about rapid prototyping tools to
use it and then i'll be showing some
demos at the end so they're prototypes
so if they break no big deal rapid
prototyping it's an extension of the
design process it's highly iterative
highly collaborative it allows you to
test earlier for cheap so one of the
biggest advantages to rapid prototyping
is say you have six weeks to do a
project and you have to work with a
project manager a biz dev guy a couple
of designers and then you've got to
implement it of course what happens is
five weeks goes by and then you get a
week to implement it typically that's
what happens at a lot of places
unfortunately so JavaScript lousy what
i'll be showing is how JavaScript will
enable you do that fast and actually be
able to work with the designer side by
side so there's a reduction or an
elimination of design artifacts and what
our design artifacts what I mean by that
is a designer makes a design emails you
of ping or a PSD you get to go implement
it and then the designer sends you a
revision and you get to go make the
changes in back and forth rapid
prototype allows you to sit right next
to the designer and just be building
while they're doing so it's pretty sweet
so in a nutshell rapid prototyping is
taking a concept or an idea with a very
short amount of time with design and
development associated with that other
words for rapid prototyping research and
development and labs groups so there are
small companies that have labs groups
R&D group
these types of things and a lot of the
times you may never even see what these
prototypes are in production but that's
kind of a concept there's an exploration
and discovery phase you just kind of
want to see what's available what's out
there but labs groups specifically there
are some companies that have been able
to take the concept of building out
prototypes and utilizing them for
production ready applications what have
you one company that's really good at
this is google which this was perfect
i'm in the google room so this is
awesome they they've actually had they
have the i think the twenty percent time
so i think one day a week get to kind of
build on whatever smart folks then
google owns all the IP and so for
examples of things that google's created
our google news gmail google adsense and
orkut now all these are public face
saying people mainly know about these
these four things and there are other
ones but i'm sure there are ones that
never hit production or things that
they've shut down all together like wave
how the good thing there to deploy here
is rapid prototyping is not just hey i
got this crazy idea and i want to use
node and CouchDB and whatever else and
just slap it together and see what i can
do there's actual real business value
behind this and that's big when you're
talking with clients about the purpose
and the concept behind rapid prototyping
for example finally I can actually
mention this HP is releasing I don't
know if anybody's seen it HP has a
touchscreen computer called touchsmart
it's about about the size of a small TV
it's touch screen and it's a normal
computer we did some rapid prototyping
for them and they just launched it I
think this past week so it's good timing
for me but the rapid prototyping work
may or may not actually ship you just
don't know the point is that there's an
exploration that enables you to be able
to put this stuff in a production
environment and then hopefully be able
to ship it however like I've mentioned a
lot of the business use cases will
actually go unseen and that's why it's
called a prototype a prototype again for
those you may have never built
prototypes they don't have to be
production-ready they can be they can be
quite I don't know rigid and robust but
at the same time they can they can break
very easily it's okay one of the things
that we also like to do is create a
fairly consistent user flow and we're
not talking about catching every edge
case we may be called the happy path
where you just go through these steps
and you show the different screens and
the interactions and the design and it
works and that's what we shoot for with
a prototype so like I said Google is
doing these types of things there are
other companies doing these types of
things there's a company in Austin Texas
where I live call bazaarvoice they have
a labs group and they're actually doing
very well with with this model one of
the other big advantages to rapid
prototyping is that you can do it fairly
cheap so if you have six four six eight
weeks to build something out you don't
have to go and hire a full enterprise
level engineering team and a stack of
interaction designers and a stack of
visual designers you can actually do it
with a fairly small team excuse me
fairly quickly so the key is that rapid
prototyping is basically innovating very
very cheaply so at this point I think I
think an example would help so while I
was preparing this talk last week I
wanted to think like you no min I was in
Amsterdam last week knew I was coming to
Berlin I'm going to Stockholm next week
for Android only I don't speak any of
those languages so what could I do what
could I what could I build quickly that
would enable me to you know be able to
speak so I wrote this language
translation app
and it's I like it's pretty cool I've
actually used it and basically way it
does it's called lingua and basically
what it does it allows you to input a
string or phrase and translate it into
the language of your choice and it uses
a number of free tools and techniques
that are out there and I'll show a
little bit of that in the demos so then
I was thinking myself okay how would I
actually get this from a client so
typically a client may come in and they
will say hey we need this really awesome
you know device this this really killer
translation app to work on the you know
the ipad or the you know and a mobile
browser so you figure yourself how do i
do this sort of thing and that's what i
applied to the lingua I was thinking
look what device is what I actually want
to put this on and I thought where am I
going to be using this thing than most
so so I have a nexus one and this has a
mobile browser on it but then I may be
on my computer so why not make it a web
app right so I'm putting it on multiple
devices and that's that's the key is how
do we wrap a prototype for multiple
devices specifically a desktop browser
mobile browser native desktop app and a
native Android app so think about that
you need a desktop browser version a
mobile browser version a native desktop
app so it works on windows 7 mac linux
and a native android app just these are
your parameters can seem pretty daunting
if you weren't able to use javascript if
you could not use JavaScript you
probably thinking to yourself am I
going to do but we can use JavaScript
pretty sweet so because we can use
javascript we can we we don't get so
overwhelmed drink a lot of coffee and we
get going right but in order to really
start to make this this work and really
start to happen you're going to need
tools to do it and so I was thinking
myself what tools do i actually need to
make this work and I said all right well
have a web app version and me a desktop
app version only and native Android app
I don't know all that stuff so I just
need to actually use javascript and HTML
and CSS and some other things that I'm
familiar with right the first thing no
Jess all right um I'm not going to go
into how how awesome this is
because if you don't know you should
probably be at home coloring right now I
use Express and connect it's not so much
because you know these are what these
are the best or anything like that I use
them mainly because number one you've
got really smart people working
behind them and two I believe the guys
that are working on these projects I
work at a company that's pretty well
funded to fund this project to make this
happen so you maybe have you may have
your own little framework and you've got
a full-time job well if your full-time
job is to work on that framework you're
probably going to get a lot more out of
it so i select express and connect it's
pretty pretty simple stuff so that
helped me set up all the server side
component for the desktop client Reeves
appcelerator titanium is anybody
familiar with titanium wow really all
right so this is going to be sweet then
okay so appcelerator titanium enables
you to write desktop and mobile but I
use it for desktop desktop and mobile
apps using HTML CSS and JavaScript so
they've extracted all the low level
stuff and just expose it in JavaScript
API it's really nice
you get file i/o access notifications
like system beeps and that sort of stuff
and I'll show this in the demo here
shortly next of course phonegap anybody
have a phone yet really even after
brian's talk half the room are you guys
that tired you can't raise your hand
alright so phone gasps pretty sweet it's
it's similar to similar but different to
the titanium model where they abstract
away a lot of the underlying mess with
Objective C and Java and the other
underlying languages for the mobile
platforms and expose JavaScript API s so
it allows you to do the same sort of
thing you use the camera use native
notifications vibrate all that sort of
thing it's pretty nice and then I
thought myself what about what I'm what
about when I'm actually I don't have an
internet connection what am I going to
do on a mobile device and I'm in you
know a club in Berlin and I really gotta
go use the bathroom and I'm underground
and my phone doesn't work well Cal chibi
is really sweet because you can dump a
lot of stuff in the cloud somewhere
that's the simplest way of putting it
and then that stuff can actually get
dumped to whatever is hooked up to that
it's about as simple as explanation as I
can give and it essentially allows for
offline data sync which is really really
cool and really big I can't emphasize
that enough I think the the couchdb you
guys really really know what they're
doing with the offline data sync stuff
it's gonna be big next year for sure but
I needed to have a database big enough
to have a ton of already translated
phrases and words potentially and I use
YQL to do that so YQL anybody familiar
with yql ok not bad about a third of the
room yql try to keep this simple it
basically makes the entire web a
gigantic API so for example it does you
can use things like screen scraping and
any website and you can request it the
response to be in Jason and it makes
being able to say parse an entire
website and grab little bits of
information out of it very very easily
and I'll show I'll show a demo of how to
use YQL it's dead simple and it's Tom in
the room if he's not yeah Tom's like the
white white call guru so ask him all
your questions not me so what about the
UI we've got multiple devices we've got
multiple devices multiple screen
resolutions multiple platforms we figure
out how to handle that with JavaScript
right how do you design a layout or a UI
for all these devices with with just one
index HTML file well the first thing and
if you don't take away anything from
this talk please take away this from the
talk is that you should not be designing
for a specific device I repeat you
should not be designing for a specific
device you should be designing for
flexible you I something that can
actually change based on media queries
and media queries do you guys know that
is anybody CSS media queries so CSS
media queries loud that you I to change
and flex based on certain properties of
the UI and I think this make more sense
if I just end up showing your demo so Oh
first you can go here and play along
this is running on node so and i'm not a
server-side guy so if it crashes it's my
fault not nodes fault so go here you can
actually pull this up on by the way i
only tested this in google chrome
because it's a prototype so if you pull
it up in IE or firefox i have no idea
what looks like to be frank the other
thing is you can also pull it up on a
mobile brown
that doesn't suck so specifically iphone
the too big let's see can you guys see
that probably not huh alright so you may
not be able to read very well because
the text or can you guys now you can't
see that at all so if you excuse me
thank you so all right he did the demo
for me I'm moving on no um so so let's
so one of the things that I needed to be
able to translate when I was in
Amsterdam was where the coffee shop was
that's pretty sure I was going to need
to know how to do that so it's pretty
straightforward you put put something in
and you get translations so there's
there's all kinds of languages to choose
from all right what else we could pay
aquare we're in Germany looking to you
German same thing pretty sweet it's
probably is that wrong that's totally
wrong right well you can blame google
for that i'm using google's translation
api so i didn't write some amazing
translation thing i'm actually just
using their api so cool right but let's
let's let's show you what the media
queries actually will do you guys see
the UI change there it's the same
codebase same CSS file and it's
immediately being formatted for mogul so
if you pull it up on a mobile device
you'll get that the cool thing is you
can actually do stuff like this and then
when we flex it back out it goes back it
retains the state but you have to know
how to do that in JavaScript that
doesn't get handled with media queries
ok so moving on native desktop app this
is going to be the apps elevator up
so you can see here lingua app this is
now I'm not making this up different to
you I chromeless it's kind of cool let's
do it nice for now let's build it oh yes
yeah alright it works so that was a
system notification that was not me
embedding some wave file and it
triggering that's the the native beat
that I had set on on this mac so
absolutely allow you to build it for mac
linux and windows from the same codebase
pretty sweet so now you've got it
running out as a widget appcelerator
also uses webkit so you're going to get
the same sort of bonuses from it right
oh oh by the way so for the next demo
I'll show yql but if you have an Android
device you can download excuse me you
can download the apk and install
directly and you'll have it running on
your phone we'll get to that in a second
so yql action yeesh that was not a
translation alright
just checking okay so here we started
off that should look pretty familiar to
anybody at ease node and what we're
going to do is we're going to make sure
that the server works and then we're
going to connect to couch 1 whereas all
the translations are stored and then
we're going to run the YQL script to
translate all the headlines in the New
York Times right now into Dutch and
store them in couch and you'll notice
here it's just updating a timestamp
because I ran this an hour ago and the
headlines haven't changed but it's
headlines were different or if there are
different words that were going to
translate it it would be storing it
directly in couch so I can build a
massive database really quickly with yql
the other thing is cool the way I wrote
it is i can actually add say ten minutes
and it'll in early every 10 minutes and
just start grabbing new ones and
populating that database so if you need
a big data set yq o will enable you to
do that really really easily and then of
course you can dump it in couch over
HTTP which is also pretty sweet okay
next demo native android app so this is
going to be hard because I don't have a
document camera so you won't be able to
see it but you'll have to either install
it on an Android device huh photo good
that's new
alright we're not going to do that so a
totally impressive results thanks guys
so I've got the native app here you
can't see it unless you're sitting
really close but is the native app and
to show you that it's native and I'm not
pulling up the browser if it works that
if the prototype works it will vibrate
and beep there you go so we're actually
yay the demo gods don't hate me today
but we're online right there so big deal
right let's do the a flight access so
now I'm going to go into airplane mode
and by the way this does require couchdb
to be installed on your Android device
reload lingua can you verify that we're
in airplane mode music can you say that
again yes I can't ok good so we're in
offline mode so if the demo gods don't
hate me they'll allow this to work as
well we're going to translate the same
thing we're offline mode and we should
hear a beep and that's the guy works on
couch so he must be really stoked ok so
we've got an app that works on all these
different platforms and devices i will
show you really quick i'm not one for
really showing code during talks i don't
people want to see it but i think one of
the things that's important to check out
let's see i want you to see how i have
this setup it's in the directory
structure so if you'll look
here I've got my android client my
desktop client and all my time I bill
kind of an you probably already know
about this but it's something we're
sharing because it makes deploying and
testing on multiple versions really easy
to do it this way so it's pretty sweet
right so what we learned today you can
wrap a prototype on multiple platforms
for multiple devices really easily using
javascript and of course you can design
flexible use UI is using HTML CSS CSS
media queries pretty cool stuff couple
that with open source projects like
CouchDB and nodejs Google Translation
API I believe I used Mike's request
jayus which is HT client my rocks
translate digest and I think Andrew
Lonnie worked on that it's all open
source stuff that I'm dumping here and
it works it's pretty cool yeah and you
can you can check out my stuff will be
dumping a lot of this code if not all of
it on github so you can have it and do
whatever you want with it and then i'm
on twitter as well so questions you will
ask questions
or it gets the hose I don't remember yes
say excellent question so the question
is why did I choose titanium for
something and phonegap for another very
simple titanium mobile which you can
build iphone android apps etc I think
blackberries and the pipe as well for
them they require to do it all in
JavaScript so your UI and everything
which is not bad but I still like to be
able to work out of an index.html
titanium desktop allows you to still use
HTML CSS and JavaScript so you can still
lay out your UI with an HTML CSS and
it's good to go phonegap allows you to
do and index HTML as well so again I'm
just working out of one directory and
being able to target two different
platforms and that was the sort of
tipping factor there of why I went that
route that's to keep them coming let's
go really
you
now look how cool that was man
that's no way it's actually pretty
pretty pretty sweet when you can deliver
a really cool prototype that they can
see on multiple platforms and devices
and say that they want to target one
device and you show them like pay by the
way if we go this route we can put it on
all of these that's way cheaper than
doing it with four sets of developers
four sets of designers etc so yeah it's
actually I don't do the biz dev stuff
but that's one of the upselling factors
right now with using the HTM the web
tech stack as a software platform to
make sense
and the simple answer to that question
is it's a prototype seriously I mean
it's fundamental as that sounds that's
the biggest thing is that hey we've
rigged this to work potentially right so
that it shows you the user flow that
we've outlined that you've agreed to
client and then when they say yeah but
if we want this you you already have it
built let's just go to production no no
that's cost a lot more money and then
you you know bill them more anybody else