hello hello can you what you can all
hear me you can alright that's good
right
fantastic thank you for that wonderful
introduction from Kevin um I'm a
front-end designer developers you might
have heard and as you might also be able
to guess my accent I am also British but
please don't worry I'm actually one of
those British people who likes Europe
unlike everybody else in my country and
that's why I live in Berlin which is
such a beautiful amazing place but I was
attracted by certain things they
attacked it's got some the best food on
the planet
really quite gourmet quality food which
I love it's a very conservative and
quiet place where people keep to
themselves and it's just generally be
German it's gotta be nice quiet
respectable attitude so I love living
there and then the Berlin I word for
spring to nature as a senior front-end
dev and if you haven't heard of spring a
nature it's actually one of the largest
academic and scientific publishers on
the planet so should have heard of them
justified by med central Scientific
American and the eponymous journal
Nature that kind of place where you get
published in there it's Nobel Prize
territory for you and he helps
scientists to get their work seen by
other scientists and the community in
general and I really love it there but I
didn't come to talk to you about that I
I came to have just a quick chat about
the single biggest invention in human
history so hopefully I can go through
this in 30 minutes and it should be fine
it's no biggie and I just want to riff a
little bit on Jeremy Keith he he does
something based somewhere and I just
want to talk about the web about how
utterly incredible it is and it's
incredible because of its Dominus it
really is done it's stupid and that's
what makes amazing
it's a bunch of dumb stupid technologies
put together and they come to make
something amazing so I'm just going to
talk very quickly about some of those
things and I think we can safely say it
started with Telegraph's yeah
everybody's familiar with what
Telegraph's I love the B beebeep beebeep
kind of things yeah yeah and these
things completely changed the face of
global communication I mean we went from
weeks it would take to send a message
anywhere in the planet to seconds there
was such an incredible change and the
Telegraph allowed the invention of the
telephone you know people want to get in
on the act they wanted to get their
voices heard and that use the same wires
and then those telephones allowed the
invention of computer networks not
obviously we had to invent the computer
first but we those computers could then
communicate with each other and I don't
know if anyone else is blessed with
being gold enough to remember this
particular movie wargames Ike you
remember stuff with the acoustic
couplers you put the mode that telephone
on the modem then the modem screamed
another computer somewhere in the
distance and then that computer screen
back and they were all screaming
together and that allowed this whole
distributed network thing to happen and
then we standardized things we
standardized with tcp/ip and computers
could talk to each other and eventually
they all merge together they form the
interconnected networks the internet big
story by itself and then we built
application protocols on top of this no
common things to enable us to do this
stuff that we do every day email and DNS
and HTTP and we had to figure out ways
for those to communicate so we had you
our alleys which allowed you no
standardized ways of finding things so
you might have you know whitehouse.gov
or
ultimate idiots at whitehouse.gov but it
could be anything
on that and then finally HTML vague but
exciting as Tim berners-lee boss said
seriously understating the whole
foundation of our careers here in the
world and that but a world change in
this of it and I think we should stop
for a second and think about the web
about how amazingly strong it is and
it's strong because of that dullness we
mentioned because of all these dumb
technologies that have come together
especially HTML which is this simple
very simple declarative language and by
declarative well what do we mean by that
I guess you could say that's suggestive
HTML suggests to the browser what it
wants to happen it's all like hey could
you maybe do this for me and the browser
comes back with oh yeah now yes nicely
yeah maybe I could do that it's got a
little bit of flirting again it's a
little bit of suggestiveness
but this suggestiveness is what makes
the web and HTML incredibly robust
because you can pull a page apart as
it's running you can go in that it's
like the Terminator man you just can't
stop it you can go in there and rip its
guts out you can remove 90% of the code
from page but the end of it you can
still click a button and proceed with it
and that robustness is why the web
dominates a stricter language would have
broken 100% it would have fallen over
it's so fragile what is shattered as
soon as it encountered a huge error like
it's code but it's been removed and in
addition to that the web is well it's
unrestricted and in the early days
anyone can build a browser and anyone
could get a browser for any machine or
any operating system and that meant that
anyone could publish things and the
early web was weird
it was fantastic for that weirdness
people used to just get the brain dumps
onto HTML page and put it out there in
public they said declare their love for
things and people and even some famous
Souls you know got their early starts up
and they're on the early weird web but
unfortunately some darker times came
possibly more dark than I thought that
given the contrast issues
what used to be free and weird suddenly
became balkanized and commercialized and
completely locked in I don't know if
anybody here is again blessed with the
age have been able to remember this
particular stuff the web at one point
got split between these two browsers and
devs effectively had to build two
versions of their sites in order to cope
with this and users how to like declare
loyalty to one particular browser and
stick with it it was a weird time of
just like frozen innovation and in fact
everything froze development froze
innovation stopped and resumed really
weird crappy time for a number of years
but history restarted from an unexpected
direction when the first iPhone appeared
and while it wasn't the first smartphone
certainly it was certainly the first
popular one and he gave us this huge
enormous diversity lesson because we've
been assuming up until that point that
our site had to work in you know one of
two browsers effectively and they
couldn't cope with this new diversity of
things and so we had to learn things
like responsive web design ether my
codes grades like synthesis of a few
simple dumb techniques again because we
didn't want to exclude people we didn't
want to stop people from using our
websites
and while I'm not an Apple over by any
means
despite laptop it was a gift to us
these were really good times because we
were suddenly designing with all kinds
of devices in mind it was the ultimate
of the web but are we starting this
cycle again maybe with different aspects
different technology reasons but with
the same result
which is that suddenly we're starting to
exclude people from the web
again we suddenly got websites that
require megabytes to download just like
how we talked about earlier this is this
is incredible
basic information science with text
content not YouTube not videos
accessibility who is that it's still a
complete unknown to most people it's
somehow not a core requirement of being
a front-end developer somehow it doesn't
appear on on our job applications and it
should be one of the core skills and
this is not going to be popular
JavaScript as a default delivery
mechanism just to deliver HTML
now I'm going to take a moment to just
ran to you a little bit because here to
me this feels like building a Boeing 747
to commute to work you know build their
plane up take it up into the sky land
it's two kilometers away which is
technically amazing and I've got such
awe and love with you for you for doing
that but what didn't you have been
better getting a bicycle you know we
should have this layered approach to
things it's HTML CSS JavaScript and it's
led to this weird situation now West
sites are no longer robust like we saw
earlier it used to be the case where all
sites could just run no matter if
they're in it to a website but now sites
die easily they're fragile and they
shatter things like Network conditions
user choices blocked JavaScript can all
destroy a site
and maybe as a response to this we've
got this whole new focus
we know talk about tooling and packaging
and ecosystem stuff which don't get me
wrong I mean I use this every day I use
webpack I use NPM I write modular
JavaScript I get why we need this stuff
but the focus has become on developer
happiness on us having fun and the word
uses despite these talks that we've had
today would have been superb the word
uses from the general consensus in the
industry has disappeared and we're back
to building sites that are not for
everybody we're starting to explicitly
say my site is not for some users
because we won't have our fun
so maybe it's time to stop this kind of
cycle which is a common one in tech
let's face it I mean remember when we
reinvented IRC just so we could have gif
ease in there or we reinvented RSS and
called it's accelerated mobile pages
we're afraid to build on top of things
now we just want to disrupt it's about
the prestige and the money and the bling
and it's not about the people anymore
but you know maybe that's just life
under late-stage capitalism and we
should just accept that well maybe not
maybe that's a bit negative there are
things that we can actually do before
it's too late so what can we do to break
break this cycle how can we make the web
better again well firstly we can learn
the basics and I don't mean of
technology here I mean about people
I mean about human things such as
empathy
and we've got this assumption that
empathy is some kind of innate traits
that you're either born with it or
you're not born with it and that is such
a lie
empathy is a muscle it's a learner will
that you can reinforce every day just by
practicing it and practicing this
empathy allows us to be more aware of
other people's needs become aware that
not everyone is like us here like us
here in this room right now because
we're genuinely quite rich people in
this industry I know we don't always
feel like it right now I literally
stopped paying off my student loans last
year I feel you on this but in the
assumptions that we make about things
for example how many people here of
Gotland
the latest technology I've got the
latest MacBook how many people here have
got the latest iPhone X on order for
next month not everyone else is like
this the rest of the world doesn't think
in these ways and yet we do and in fact
we kind of make these idiots into the
norm for things when they're not and
we've got to be better than that so what
else can we consider we can consider the
fact that not everyone is well connected
in the world
and I think sometimes we consider a poor
connection to be something like this
they must be autumns poor person in a
hut somewhere you know you know there's
poor poor people which is a bit of a
weird racist thing because the actual
reality is this I saw statistic the
other day there was something like 30%
of rural America is still on dial-up
internet 56 kilobits per second is a
standard for huge numbers of people in
the richest country on the planet and
again we had Harry talking about this
earlier what the realities of the
internet connection are for people
around the planet another step in
empathy
you know maybe we've got to consider
that not everybody is able but it in
fact 12% of all people have a disability
of some form or another and that's not
just things like wheelchairs and
blindness you know the stereotypes that
we think of now she covers huge areas
stuff like color blindness arthritis the
use of crutches we've just got to keep
these things in mind constantly because
our job at the end of the day is about
building things for other people it's
fundamentally about empathy that is the
core of our job
okay so maybe you've listened to these
things and maybe you take them on board
so how can you start using them in the
real world
what does building with empathy mean
well it's this doorknobs
I know doorknob calm Budapest now both
of these doorknobs are absolutely lovely
I'm sure we can all agree in that we
don't discriminate against doorknobs
here but one of these works for
everybody on the planet while the other
one excludes people excludes people who
might have arthritis who might be
amputees or who might be using crutches
and if we start thinking in this kind of
mindset just with that simple example we
start helping more people again as we
heard earlier we start helping things
other than just the obvious case so
designing a door handle in a proper way
you know actually helps people who were
carrying large loads were carrying bags
who've got a baby in their arms
and you can take this empathy into the
workplace and try to get it in there
from the beginning by progressively
designing and that means starting right
at the very start sketching things with
UX people testing ideas with people
before you ever touch code Before we
jump in with the latest exciting
technology that we've heard about just
stop and think about how a person will
use it and then then you can get those
ideas into HTML and I do mean just HTML
you know the traditional thing with
forms and hate wands and no styling test
if this kind of stuff works with real
people again because this hTML is going
to be the foundation of your website
and why should you do it like this well
if you build it this way from the start
you're checking the basics from the
start and because HTML is super generous
it gives you so much accessibility stuff
for free without you even having to
think about it
if you do things this way think about
basic HTML first you're going to have
something that works from the start and
as bonus you can be seen how a screen
reader might see it or how someone using
a text mode browser might see it and
then once you've got a working hate
smile foundation then you can mold it up
okay get some ghost music soundtrack on
stop molding it into a beautiful design
forming the HTML into components and
then only then at that point do you add
the fancy things do you put the
JavaScript on top upgrade those boring
forms that we talked about so that they
I don't know connect to rest api's so
the pagination now works without a page
reloading I know that's a bit abstract
so let's give you a practical example of
this now this is gonna be something that
I've been working on for the last few
weeks you know as part of a small side
project then we've got our workplace and
we start out in exactly that way we
talked about starting with HTML and then
we add the most simple style sheet to it
something there's barely more than
styled hate smell and we make sure that
that works everywhere and it does work
everywhere just buying by nature of what
it is this is fundamentally workable on
every device iPhone desktop whatever it
is
and then we do a test against a fancy
media query wonder is being crafted to
catch the latest browsers and then those
browsers we send an upgraded experience
we send him and a full working
stylesheet and in fact this is a reduce
form of the BBC's cutting the mustard
technique and yes we've deliberately
chosen to exclude some browsers from
having a full enhanced experience here
because we know even if those older
browsers get that reduced functionality
that reduced styling more it will still
work for them and then like I said
before only then do we load in fancy
JavaScript and we touched up by a match
media event because we check to see if
the CSS is loaded and if the CSS is
loaded that we know we can it's advanced
browser we can attach javascript to it
and then we can do tabbing we can do
animations we can do your drop down and
we've got all this documented in an open
playbook that we maintain I'll post a
link to this afterwards on Twitter so
you can all take a look at this in more
detail and that ties the fundamentals of
progressive enhancement a really simple
example but it's about making a site
Universal from the start and only
upgrading it when it becomes necessary
and doing something like that makes a
site robust as hell again you can make
it so that it doesn't fall over when one
aspect of it breaks
and in addition it's the ultimate in
agile development because by doing
things this way you don't you don't
sketch something in sketch and then try
to code towards that as a final goal you
know you don't have this waterfall
approach to things that is quite frankly
common in our industry right now no you
do things a jille you build you test you
iterate you build you test again over
and over making something gradually
better as you go along and for people
like me who were fundamentally lazy this
is amazing it means you only build what
you need to you don't start on trying
the latest techniques you only add
advanced things as they are necessary
this incredibly lean approach to things
I think also fights FOMO
if if people don't know what FOMO is
fear of missing out and again this is
something that I think we all have we
all suffer from I know I certainly do I
hear about the latest techniques as I oh
my god I haven't learnt about that one
we tend to get excited by the latest
technologies and rather than asking
again does he benefit the users does
this make things better for them it
stops us and puts a break on that
excitement because we do frankly tend to
build too complex at the moment we're
trying to keep up collectively with
giant engineering companies that have
tens of thousands of engineering staff
doing the latest things and we're all
running behind trying to keep up with
them and thinking this is must be the
best way of doing things when it isn't
necessarily maybe we could just start
keeping things simple
a bit more
and there are some limitations I will be
the first to admit that it's absolutely
amazing
but one thing progressive enhancement is
still beats by easily by the client-side
JavaScript framework so right there
right now is state management absolutely
state management is a big thing but I
will still argue that it is only a
minority of sites that actually work
that way the high profile sites all rely
on it but the average site that we are
producing does not need to jump into
full state management immediately I
thought maybe we can work on that I
actually think this is something that
will come in the future we'll have that
merging of easy state management's and
progressive enhancement and that will be
incredible for the web at that point we
should remember what it excels and again
doing things this way makes it robust
and makes it Universal makes it work for
everybody it will always work in the
worst conditions when this broken
JavaScript when there's bad Network
conditions when people deliberately
disable things and believe me they do
deliberately disable things now Josh
Cribbs being turned off by people I know
but simply because they want to avoid
the adverts and the huge number of
third-party downloads that come from
those it's lightweight and it loves
people first anyway even if you don't do
progressive enhancement there's still
are those things that people have talked
about earlier in the day you can do
stuff like turning on your in your dev
tools turn on 3d performance turn on the
CPU throttling start using the site like
average people do out there in the real
world simulate those real-world
conditions
and if you can use real hardware because
again as we've heard today your 3000
euro Mac is not anywhere near the
performance of what a real-world person
has it's vastly overpowered the new
iPhone that people are going to have
next week is infinitely more powerful
than the average phone that people hold
in their hands but because we use these
every day we assume that everybody else
uses them and they don't and again as we
said earlier if you can make this run on
a low powered device if your site runs
on the lowest end of things it's going
to be screamingly fast on the real high
powered devices and then in addition
just another one those little tasks you
can do you can turn on your screen
reader and again if you're a stereotype
for the developer which we all are you
can just have to do on your Mac you just
have to go command f5 and you've
immediately got voiceover turned on and
you can start testing these things you
can start navigating your site by sign
and believe me this is so much fun when
you actually do it for the first time
when you actually find out what a whole
new interface to use him websites and
there's a steep learning curve with it
don't get me wrong you have to learn a
100 new key combinations but if we're a
group of people who can learn a pianist
by hearts and all the different CSS
properties I'm confident we can learn
that kind of thing for sure and
similarly start trying to navigate with
your keyboard every day and this one is
incredibly easy you just it's wonky just
time tab through everything start seeing
where your website looks like with that
try and discover those little things
that we saw earlier those little
ordering areas that can creep in so
easily by going visual first you'll be
amazed at how much better you can make
your site's straightaway
be my he was said by the CEO somewhere
but these aren't my users I don't have
users like these poor users or disabled
users and I will come back to you and
say you do have users like that you do
because you don't know a user situation
at any point you can't always assume
they are in the best situation they
might be even your millionaire user your
high petrol user might have borrowed a
phone of somebody else they might be
sitting a scaled down work computer they
could just be in a bad situation on
holiday somewhere you cannot know this
and at the end of the day even those
millionaires are going to have crappy
days so let's try and be kind to the
poor old millionaires anyway the web
success is built on it being robust
being built on a robustness that works
for anybody I know that people depend on
that robustness we have to keep
defending it we have to keep that beauty
and that weirdness in the web because
the web is beautiful because of its
diversity its diversity of people and
its diversity of technology we are the
enablers for that diversity so let's not
make it about us and let's start making
it about the wonderful weirdness of the
web thank you