um I want to talk about the jQuery
divide its kind of you know I got the
email for multi things so what are you
talking about and I made this up this
title but I want to talk about it and I
hesitated to do a talk about jQuery in
front of this audience because I think
that by and large this audience is is
pretty aware of some of the limitations
i didn't want to get up here and tell
you stuff that you already know but i
think that i do have some important
things that this audience does need to
hear about jQuery and the role that I
think it's playing in the JavaScript
community at large so I know we're all
tired and it's near the end of the day
um so I'm going to keep this nice and
short and you should all use dojo the
end I wish that it was it was it's it's
been a wonderful tool kit for me to
learn and its really opened my eyes to a
lot of things i'll be going to jquery
Boston in a couple of weeks trying not
to say you should all use dojo we'll see
how I do this to me came out just I
don't know a couple days ago and I think
it speaks really well to what I want to
talk about today that it used to be that
JavaScript was a toy and we just used it
to get stuff done and somebody was
saying that they would actually get
resumes from people who knew JavaScript
but they wouldn't put it on the resume
because they were afraid that it was
going to make them look like a less
legitimate developer a less serious
developer and I think that's really
changed and now it's becoming the case
that if you don't know JavaScript and if
you don't take it seriously you are
setting yourself up for some real hurt
so there's three things that I want to
kind of hit on today number one I want
to talk about how I think jquery and its
popularity among newcomers is making
those newcomers learn some really
terrible things and you know the ease of
the ubiquity of it the popularity of it
means it's the go to library for a lot
of people who don't have any programming
experience
on some levels that's wonderful on other
levels it's terrifying as a I work for
myself I consult with companies who call
me up and say you help us fix this
gigantic mess that we've made so i'll
talk about that in a minute i also want
to talk about why i think that this
audience needs to care about this this
audience who'd you know very few of you
would admit that you didn't understand
call and apply so that's probably true
here but but i know that i'm not
speaking to an audience that needs a
lecture on the jquery api or what's
wrong with it or what's good about it
but i do think that this topic is
important to this audience and number
three I want to talk about what I think
that we as the people who assemble
together at this fairly exclusive
conference that you know turns away more
people and probably get in why what we
who are here actually need to do about
this that we shouldn't just let the
status quo be what it is I think that we
actually have a responsibility to take
some ownership of this problem it was
about a year a year ago year a half ago
that I started talking about code
organization in the jQuery community it
was a problem that i was running into as
i was using jquery it was a problem that
other people were definitely sensitive
to so it's about a year ago that i
started talking about it writing blog
posts about it i spoke at the jquery
conference in Boston about it last year
and through doing all of that talking I
find that a lot of people are calling me
and saying help we've done terrible
things and I'm proud of them for calling
me I'm proud of them for asking these
questions I'm impressed that people are
realizing sort of like Nicole was
talking about the CSS people are
realizing that this is actually a
problem it's a maintenance problem it's
a skill it's a extensibility problem
they they find themselves copying and
pasting like Nicole was talking about
instead of actually solving problems or
looking at their application in a big
picture sort of way so I applaud them
for saying you know I have a problem
that's the first step right so I say
sure I can help you and you know jquery
it
events a Jackson effects library it's
decent most of that it has some others
parts of it that I don't like when it
comes to some pieces of that but that's
what it does dumb Ajax events and
effects and what I'm hearing you tell me
dear client is that your needs are
actually a little bit bigger than this
and in my experience when you start
doing anything remotely serious with
JavaScript then your needs are actually
bigger than Dom Ajax events and effects
so we're off to a good start needing
this client and then but we must keep
using jQuery because it's easy and it's
popular and we don't want to hear about
any other options you know yeah you can
talk about the other options but really
we we want to stick with jquery we are
not willing to it's too easy it's too
easy we can't give that up and so at
this point now it's just sort of
entertaining because I'd been I've had
these conversations over and over and
over again and so this might say well
let me see your code let's take a look
at your code and see what it is you're
doing um this is obfuscated adha you
just enough that the client who sent it
to me to review it won't know it was
them but a terrible terrible this
is I mean Pete and I were upstairs
looking at it it's just it's amazing it
is so completely Dom centric it's
selections happening over and over and
over again on the exact same thing I
mean some of this stuff i don't know if
i put it up on the screen but some of
this stuff is like line for line
repeated except it's in a different it's
like a different if statement this is
what people well intentioned people who
are using jquery this is these these are
the answers that they're coming up with
to mildly complicated problems this I
think was on a search something from a
search results page or something like
that so mildly complicated problems not
you know we're not talking rocket
science here my only complex problems
that are more than just get some
elements and do something with them but
they're still approaching it's a get
some elements and do something with them
kind of problem instead of considering
how to actually architect their
application and then this is my favorite
part
is when they say that the real reason
they need to stick with jQuery is
because their database guys like they
get it and so and you know maybe they're
java developers they get it to and so we
can't do anything that actually means
that those people can't continue
contributing to the team and it's uh
yeah I don't know what to say about that
a really big believer that front end
developers should be doing front end and
let's groom the front end developers to
get the front end developers doing
better front end stuff when we pull in
people who don't have expertise in the
browser environment well we get that
code that we saw so I tell the story to
illustrate four points number one the
perceived popularity of jQuery is
pervasive the Percy's perceived ease of
use if factor is pervasive and it really
factors into the library choices that
people are making number two people who
don't know how to write JavaScript are
doing non trivial things with it and we
can't stop them the best that we can do
is help them do them better I've talked
to some people this weekend whoo hoo I
think would prefer to see the market
just just dispose of these people
because they're not good but the fact is
people are doing our writing complicated
things whether they should or not and I
think that's problem we need to address
number three there's actually demand for
the answers to these questions people
are realizing they've created problems
they don't know what to do about it
number for the people seeking these
answers they're not necessarily dumb
they just don't know what they don't
know and so they they come to me with
this sort of code and they don't even
know how to begin to solve the problem
because jQuery again has taught them
this get some elements and do something
with them and that's the only way that
they've really learned to think about
JavaScript this is a really freaky
moment because there's crockford and
there's crockford and weird but in in
one of your UI UI theater talks I went
and they have a transcript which is
fabulous i didn't have to listen to the
whole thing again to find this quote
um mrs. it turns out if you have
absolutely no idea what you're doing the
language you can still generally make
things work and that's very true weed
and I know I personally that's kind of
how I got started with this and I'm
embarrassed about it a little bit but
the frightening thing especially is that
you were actually talking about the good
parts when you said this was actually a
good thing and I is a good thing it is a
good thing because it has exposed I mean
I like to see people learn new things
and jQuery has provided a gateway to the
to that that didn't exist before and
it's almost in some ways like this this
is jquery's mission statement and that's
slightly frightened part for me is that
it it seems to almost encourage he's
going to tweet this I'm gonna get in
trouble it seems to almost encourage
people not to learn the underlying
language not to learn the bigger
questions and Pete talked about this
this morning saying big inspect by this
is smarting saying that we need to
encourage people to actually learn the
language before they learn libraries
because we lose a lot if we don't so
it's this being jquery's mission
statement in some ways is good because
it means that instead of writing this
which was terrible and scared me when I
was looking at javascript before their
libraries like I had no interest in
trying to figure out what all this meant
instead of writing that we can write
this and that's cool this jquery wasn't
the first library to make shorter syntax
as possible it was just the first
library to make it so stupid simple that
that people really started to embrace it
i think and people who didn't have any
hope of understanding this started to
embrace this and start to say we can
start doing neat things with javascript
so would i see often and what i showed
in that example code is that when we
have an application like this jquery
offers a really pleasant way to make it
work it's like 15 lines you know we go
out we
when somebody enters some text into the
search box we fire off an AJAX request
get some results and throw it into the
search results area it makes it really
easy to write code like that and that's
why this ubiquitous graph is what it is
this shows the pop the search trends of
jQuery versus everything else in the
last several years jQuery is the blue
line and it wins so it's that simplicity
that's led to this and it's that
simplicity that has led to this this is
a graph from indeed com which tracks job
advertisements and the number of people
looking for jQuery in their job
advertisements is just going off the
charts so it's that simplicity that has
driven this crazy adoption jquery even
teaches us how to do you know tabs we
can do that with jquery UI we can do a
little accordion over on the side we can
do some radio buttons and style them all
fancy and i have no doubt that there is
a plugin because there's a plugin for
everything that will let you make a
little tag cloud over on the side so
jQuery teaches us how to do teaches
these newcomers how to do all these
things but they only want to build this
which is all those pieces turn together
they have no earthly clue what to do and
they end up using the same strategies
that they use to build this to build
this and the the people who are drawn to
jQuery i think i have a really hard time
looking at this and seeing how we could
get here from there but fundamentally
this is just a more advanced version of
this this is just dis with more features
and this is what i see happening is
people who started out building this
this was the original spec for their
application was was to just make this
simple little thing and they wrote it
that way that I showed you either at
their current company or at the new
company that hired them because they
said they knew how to write JavaScript
now they're being asked to build this
and now terrible terrible things are
happening
it people have no idea about JavaScript
or like that's the best picture they
love it so yeah it turns out that J
queries approach to mildly complicated
problems let alone like actually
complicated problems is terrible and
people these newcomers are learning bad
habits that they are really preventing
them from they're trying to you know
stick knives in power outlets basically
and I'm not telling you anything you
don't know here but this slide will be
in there for the people who see this on
SlideShare tonight when we're building
applications we have to actually think
about components we have to think about
loose coupling we have to think about
how do we dry it out so we're not
writing the same one that was I hadn't
looked at that code until earlier today
and I was like wow it's me fun email the
right on Monday we have to think about
components that work with each other
without depending on each other we have
to think about how can we drive stuff
out we have to think about how can we
communicate between components without
having them be completely tied into each
other and we have to think about how can
we actually grow that simple search
application into something more
complicated because that's the use case
that's happening over and over and over
again people come to JavaScript to show
and hide some stuff or out of menu or
add a little bit of Ajax they've arrived
at jQuery to do that and now the knees
just keep growing and growing and
growing and at no point do they step
back and say I might not know what I
need to know to do this so here's a
simple little rewrite how we might
rewrite the search results portion of
that application to actually be reusable
and actually be a component and not be
tied in to not be so dependent on
dependent directly on the input into the
search box it's obviously this in and of
itself is almost as long as the simple
little code for for making the first
version of the app but
this is where I want to see people going
this is how I want to start encouraging
people to think about these slightly
more complex problems I'm not saying
like that James Bergstrom is is the
answer to everything i'm not i don't
want to get too much into and this is
how you should do it I've seen lots of
different approaches to this but the
main point is that we have to be
thoughtful the other main point is this
scares the hell out of the client
because and and the database guy he's
like what is that I knew this told get
some elements and do something with them
but wow so this is the part that is
really for this audience I think that
instead of being judgmental towards
these people and instead of saying well
you know people who don't poach
shouldn't be coding we should just eject
them kick them off the island it's not
going to it's not going to happen we
can't just shake our fingers at them and
say rtfm there's there's no manual on
this we're still making this up in some
ways we're still figuring out how we do
build large applications or non-trivial
applications we're still figuring out as
a community how we manage dependencies
and how we structure our code and
there's different answers for different
questions so I don't think that we can
get that upset at the at the people
making these decisions they're just
they're just doing their job and they're
just trying to do the best they can do
what I do think that we can do is be
more proactive about exposing them to
these more complicated concepts be more
proactive about letting them know what
it is they don't know so that the the
jQuery get some elements and do
something with them doesn't dominate the
conversation so much and I think that
this is not just an altruistic thing
this is not just me saying we should be
better people and help our friends I
think that there are actual impact that
I hear about among other developers from
people taking these uninformed
approaches there's a friend of mine who
works at a very very large media company
who
is really struggling with decisions that
were made a couple of years ago and they
are having to the decision to use jQuery
a couple years ago and they're having to
really evaluate how they're going to
proceed because they have created such a
mess so there's there's we should help
our friends he's a smart guy but he's
working with a bunch of people who
didn't necessarily know what they were
doing and now what so we should be
helping our friends number two I think
that the perception of javascript is
diminished when we allow there to be bad
code and don't do anything about it when
we allow people to claim expertise and
don't do anything about and I don't
think the thing to do about it is to say
you know stop doing that the thing to do
about is to help educate them and this
is the number one thing that we need to
explain to them I think this is jQuery
and this is JavaScript and if jquery
would just put this on their homepage
probably self like thirty percent of the
problem probably not that's a lie
companies are looking for JavaScript
developers i do not know an unemployed
JavaScript developer I don't know I get
recruiter emails from like crazy
regularly I'm not interested in moving
to the bay no how many times do I have
to tell you this and we all do get these
emails from people people are desperate
for JavaScript developers this is
JavaScript Ruby PHP and Python I was
actually kind of shocked to see that
graph but God people are looking for
JavaScript developers and they're going
to hire them whether they're good or not
because they've got seats to fill they
have they have jobs that they need done
and they're going to get good people to
do it that what they're aren't good
there aren't enough good people that's
kind of the problem there aren't enough
good people and so they're going to get
bad people to do it and that's not good
for us as a community so Aaron Newton
wrote a blog post a few weeks ago about
how he's been searching for a JavaScript
developer at Cloudera and talking to a
recruiter evil people talking to a
recruiter and
and the recruiter saying these people
that you want don't exist they don't
exist and you know he had some pretty
high expectations from from his his
posting these people don't exist and
again I think the answer to that is not
to you know his post was like something
about how hard it is to find badass
JavaScript developers and the productive
reaction to this is not to say well
aren't I lucky that I'm a badass
JavaScript developer and all those other
people can just you know go to hell the
productive answer to this is is to say
how do we how do we help them how do we
fix this because these are the people
that you're going to be working with on
some job and then your future and you're
going to be sad so Jake we is is is
drawing in crazy amounts of people into
this JavaScript community and the
applications that are writing look a
whole lot like this there's lots of
disparate pieces no organizing principle
lots of pieces that are fun you know it
slide show lots of uses that are fun but
the pieces aren't made to work together
unless you have a fairly talented
developer what I want is for us to be
encouraging people to make applications
that look like this Nicole beat me to
the Legos so yeah lame no but javascript
will be better off when newcomers are
thinking about applications as a bunch
of pieces that work together and instead
of a bunch of pieces that they just
assemble and copy and paste and through
under their application so there are i
came up with kind of five things that i
think we as a community could be doing
better to help address this problem and
we're not going to solve it there are
always going to be just hopeless people
who are coming to javascript to solve
some problem and we can't help everybody
i know that i don't want to sound all
Pollyanna about it so yes there will
always be hopeless people but I think
there are people who just need a nudge
in the right direction and so here are
five things that I think that we can be
doing to as a community give that nudge
number
on that graph that I showed you earlier
of jquery's popularity it is a
decision-making tool for the deciders at
companies and this is not okay and I
think as a community we need to be much
more vocal about the fact that this
graph is about as meaningful as this
graph this graph compares you can read
it never mind so yeah these are both
dumb they tell you nothing hey gay porn
I tried to find a picture to illustrate
that and just decided not to um you
haven't searched for food porn on Google
you have no idea Wow bacon though please
figures very prominently into that so I
think that as a community we've got to
be this is this is the thing that gets
me all worked up we have got to be
intellectually honest when we're having
these conversations about you know what
is the best library there is no best
library there is the right library for
your use case there is no best library
and when somebody asks on stack overflow
and when somebody asks on Quora we need
to be very clear about the how we
actually come to those decisions that we
don't come to those decisions based on a
graph and I think that when people
reference the graph as part of an
argument about why their library might
be better than another we need to make
clear that then among us among those of
us who are actually thoughtful about
this that is not a legitimate argument
and it's not helping the conversation
it's not helping javascript progress
that's probably my most political thing
that I'm going to say but I feel I get
pretty bent when I when I see people
reference that as sort of the argument
ending graph that says well jquery is
clearly better there are times when
jQuery is a wonderful solution and in
the hands of good developers jquery can
be a wonderful
solution but there's a lot more to
picking a library than looking at up
looking at a graph oh dear when I was a
kid I used to make headphones out of a
coat hanger and wrap masking tape around
it and so this is like I have arrived
that was so fun when I was three and now
it's really it works it's amazing number
two I think that we need to encourage
people to be choosing tools not API is
in David Walsh who's a mood tools guy
who's now working at site pen and doing
a lot of work with dojo has written
about this and done some some
demonstrations of how the of the
different API is that the different tool
kits have and and just talked a little
bit about how api's are they're friendly
they're great you know Jake where's API
is awesome but that is not a really good
way to be picking a library we can
either learn another API because it's
not that hard or we can maybe wrap to
the API that we don't like in an API
that we do that's what dojo is done it's
done with plug d and dojo even has a
shim that will provide almost the entire
API of jQuery 132 and then they changed
their API in 142 so they got to go ahead
and do all that again but yeah so yeah
jQuery is short and sexy and awesome but
we're smart people we can figure out
that these things all mean the same
thing and I think that we can also
actually educate people that these
things mean the same thing but more
importantly we need to to let people
know that ap the API of a tool is but a
small piece of it this is the original
example I showed for that basic basic
search up and this is the same thing
written in dojo and those of you in the
back I mean the indentations all the
same and a lot of the words are the same
you probably can't even tell the
difference so we're smart enough to
figure these differences out we
shouldn't be intimidated by them and we
should be encouraging other people not
to be intimidated by them either sort of
as a corollary to the point number one
about the grab
I think that we need to be more doing a
better job of explaining how to evaluate
the question before we come up with the
answer and we all know that clients are
bosses or whoever they like to do this
like we should use html5 why I don't
know I just heard about it on NPR and it
sounds really cool so yeah html5 is on
NPR in americo's they talked about the
arcade fire thing was wild so we need to
be talking more about how we make these
decisions because this is dumb but
lemmings was an awesome game decision
makers need help making actual decisions
and I'm going to my my timer says I have
three minutes and 35 seconds and
counting so I'm going to go through
these really fast number one we have to
understand the project understand the
team understand the life cycle of the
project because those are are pretty
important decision points for what sort
of tool and how robust and approach is
going to make sense number two we need
to assess the actual applications needs
do are we going to need dependency
management is it going to have a lot of
similar but but not exactly the same
codes are we going to need some sort of
module system or some sort of inherited
system are we going to need templated
widgets are we going to be
internationalizing this is that a
question we're going to have to address
and only then once we answer those
questions on those two slides that I
just went through really fast only then
should we be choosing our tools and I
think that that formalizing this I hope
to write it I hoped to write a blog post
about this on the plane here and I
didn't because it was 80 degrees and
they only brought me one gin and tonic
the whole time but i think that
formalizing this decision making process
is is something that we as a community
can do a little bit better and be
educating people about a little bit more
number four there are lots of times when
rtfm is a great answer this isn't one of
them what I'm talking about again there
is no manual here we can't tell people
to go look it up in the docks there
there
aren't docs that give a
one-size-fits-all answer to these
questions of how do you structure a
large application and how do you deal
with the the problems that you confront
once get some elements and do something
with them stops being effective and a
commenter on Aaron Newton's post about
finding a unicorn said the this person
said it's really difficult to find good
resources and I think that they're right
and I heard another conversation just a
little while ago somebody's saying the
same thing that's it can be difficult to
find good resources we can't point
people to the MDC that's overwhelming
and crazy we can point people to books
but a lot of people are going to read
your book and just like I didn't know
such a thin book could be so hard so I
think that that we need to this is a
problem that's going to require a little
bit more one-on-one or a little bit more
interactive problem-solving than just
sending people to read the manual and
unfortunately that was that was the
answer to this guy was you know read my
blog posts I did it so can you and and I
think that the we need to be a little
bit more proactive a little bit more
sensitive to to the fact that these are
challenging questions and of the fact
that different people learn differently
you know I teach jquery classes and I'm
always a little bit mystified like you
need me to come and read the manual to
you okay you know I get paid for that
but different I have to remind myself
that different people learn differently
and so we can't just dismiss them and
say that this is their problem i really
do think it's a problem that we as a
community need to address 20 10 seconds
um fifth and finally I think that we as
a community have been struggling with
these questions and these problems for a
couple of years and some of us are
solving them really well now and we as
you knew much guilty pleasures we might
get out of making people suffer through
the same things that we suffered through
it's not nice
we shouldn't make people suffer through
the same discovery process that we did
of what these big questions are there
was a time when Dom Ajax adenosine
effects were the big questions and those
those new jquery was absolutely
revolutionary for the fact that it
helped solve those so cleanly and
pleasantly those aren't the big
questions anymore various libraries have
saw them in various ways we need to be
talking about now what are the what are
the bigger questions and so some things
that I'm trying to do to address this
number one someday we'll make a new yay
query I swear to God Paul says yes I
think that was a real a real success we
put out about 18 episodes of HOD cast
talking about jQuery and front-end
development and I think that it did a
really good job of with humor and
singing and stupidity talking about some
of the more advanced questions that we
might want to be that we wanted people
who were writing jquery to be dealing
with and I mean that was fun we drank
and swore and made up silly songs so
this doesn't have to suck this can
actually be fun number two of we the Y a
query team put together a conference in
texas texas united states last in june
and that was another effort that i think
was successful in making people like
Doug Crockford and Pete Higgins and
Brian LaRue and Tom crusher making them
available to an audience more more
diverse less skilled in this audience
and I think that's an important thing to
be doing making sure that people have
access to the smart people in the field
this is great java the JS comp is
amazing and i feel really lucky to be
here to be part of this small small
gathering but i think that as a
community we need to be doing a better
job of reaching out to the people who
aren't as tuned in and so they don't
know that they have eight minutes to buy
a ticket before they're all sold out
and there's other there's other good
resources Microsoft script junkie as
much as I mock it is actually kind of a
useful resource for for reaching a wider
audience and so I applaud them for doing
that I wish they had comments that would
be nice and and people often ask me like
so is this are you saying this is Jake
worries fault no this is not jquery so
jQuery is an open source project with
limited resources a small dedicated team
they're doing the best that they can
there are things that I'm English that
they were doing differently there are
there if time and money were no object
certainly there are things that jQuery
could do to address this but I think as
a larger community it's up to us to be
grateful to what job jquery has
contributed to the community be excited
about the fact that it's bringing
ridiculous numbers of potentially good
developers to the community and then
take them by the hand and actually make