I'm talking about preprocessor
preprocessor a STS harder to say than I
thought
STS stands for abstract syntax tree I'll
go into that more if you're you're not
familiar with it but I just thought I'd
get that other way up front I work at
strike now
so that's outdated I think I have one
more bulleted list but my style is a
little different and it's actually not
different at all
from the way I used to do presentations
so it's completely useless information
for you anyways abusing and hacking is
is a term I'm using in this presentation
to mean using something for a reason
outside of its intended purpose oh
that's their correct size how about this
HTML slides for the win so this is I
think some sass or s CSS specifically
and it's kind of like a fairly
declarative syntax so what is there to
hack what is there to abuse with just
some text that turns into CSS right so
it's not necessarily an obvious place
when you're talking code you can say
like oh I can inject this here or inject
that there but you're limited by syntax
here and it's not necessarily even like
I guess it is turing-complete
especially with like checked and stuff
any Ryan's got to talk about that so so
the place that we're gonna try and
inject ourselves is in the compilation
step so how does this sass so it's just
a smaller part of this same thing turn
into actual CSS right so how do we take
that variable pull it out and then put
it in the right place to output actually
decent CSS parsing and compiling so how
does parsing work so let's narrow it
down even further we just have a single
variable declaration in sass and
naturally sass is Ruby and I don't
really program Ruby so most of my will
be in JavaScript so sorry your Ruby fan
so parsing I can I can talk about it on
a high level here and that's just like
no
the syntax rules of the language and go
through and assign what everything is
this is a variable declaration or this
is a even more specifically a string or
a value or a semicolon right figure out
all those different parts so inside this
little little guy we have the the
variable prefix we can look for the
dollar sign and we know that hey this is
about to be a variable we know it's
gonna be a variable until we hit like
white space or a semicolon and in this
case we get the variable name it's blue
and then we get a semicolon then we can
have as much white space as we want and
then we get some random string and
that's gonna be the value most of the
time CSS will let you put anything in
there as long as it's not like the
semicolon or another colon or something
like that so any non invalid character
there it's going to be the value so it
might not actually be anything to the
browser but it would be valid and then
obviously the the rule delimiter so this
is how this would parse down whenever
sass was was pulling this in more
specifically it does that
programmatically so it's going to go
through and check every possibility of
each thing of each character that it
gets to and so this is the the most
simple parser that I could write on a
single slide you have a result array and
you just want to push each token on to
the array so you say I hit a semicolon
push the semicolon token which in this
case is the string semicolon probably
would not work out well but you go
through and then you you end up with a
list of each of the tokens so rather
than having just random text strings you
know like hey this is a variable this is
a rule delimiter this is a value and
this is a rule ending statement more
realistically most people are going to
write a parser expression generator a
peg a parser expression generator is is
what this is and you don't have to know
anything about this I just wanted to
make sure I was being realistic you kind
of define that like hey a class is a dot
followed by an identifier and then
whenever I get this just give me this
object back and then
a computer will generate a parser for
you so you don't have to write all those
like reverse while loops and do a look
ahead and all that stuff
so if you are looking into writing your
own parser I probably suggest starting
at a parser expression generator so you
just write the grammar and it generates
the parser much more simple so when
you're done you need to represent the
code as data instead of pure text so now
we have somewhere in between there we
have like here what all of our symbols
are we have tokens if you will so so
this first becomes this so we have the
the variable start which is that dollar
sign we have a string which is blue
that's technically like the variable
name and then we have like the equals
operator which in CSS is the colon the
string is is the value that we have
there and then we have a rule end a rule
ender Enders game coming up soon a
sponsor but we add structure so if you
go back here you can see that it's it's
a very small CSS file it actually would
output nothing on on the other end but
we have that and we turn it into this we
say this is a single node and inside of
it has two nodes inside of it and that
is of our name and a value and so now we
have this this idea of this is a single
node and inside of our two smaller nodes
and the way the entire CSS file is going
to parse out is into these leaf nodes or
write like this so you'll always have
like a variable name or a CSS value or a
CSS property and you can go deep into
your your tree which we'll talk about in
a second and everything reduces down
into these very simple things they're
just put all in a list together or in a
tree together depending on how deep you
go CSS is actually not very deep sass
and compass and all that stuff they
actually allow you to nest a lot further
and so when you're parsing
pre-processors you you actually do see
like larger nesting and so you have a
CSS syntax tree inside of a CSS syntax
tree instead of a CSS
in texture so this is more realistic for
another very small but it actually would
output something we say like our our
outer object is a stylesheet and inside
of it it has some declarations right so
style sheets have declarations first
thing we do is we do that we set blue
before so I've omitted that section so
this fits on mostly a slide pretty close
and so we've set that variable and then
we set the the left and right and so we
know what the the name is and we know
what the value is and then we have a
declaration and we say the selector is
here RP and dot stuff and so that would
whenever you compile that that would be
P comma dot stuff and then there would
be the brackets and inside that are the
rules and the rules you have a list of
rules and so this is just going to be a
list of rule nodes and so in this case
it's color and value so this would just
have a single value if we wanted more
rules we could have you know background
and then have have that whole set of
rules for background and things like
that visually this is what you might
write in SAS or stylus or less I think
the and syntax works in all of them
maybe someone probably knows but in this
case we're just saying we want to modify
the hover pseudo-class of the outer
class so this is not valid CSS at this
point but it is valid SAS and we're just
saying I want the original style of a
but I just want to change the hover case
for to be underlined in this case I'm
trying to simplify so that would
actually be kind of silly because you're
not sharing anything in the long run but
simple so this becomes this so this is
our object at the bottom is a stylesheet
we have a body node and we have an a
node and inside of that we have rules
the color is black one is text
decoration and the hover is a new level
more nested so if you go back here you
can see even in the code the brackets
kind of represent that nesting
and that is an abstract syntax tree so
it's not an ast is a kind of a scary
word and everyone kind of blank stare at
you unless they've worked with them
before but it's actually an easily break
down a bowl word that's totally also
hard to break down word but abstract
means that there's no rules you can make
them however you want it really should
just be like arbitrary syntax tree
because it's it's just like whatever you
want to do is cool as long as it's a
tree syntax implies that it's about
syntax so if you're parsing code then
it's a syntax tree and tree just means
that like there are objects with an
object so it's like a very very vague
term and it almost means nothing other
than it represents some sort of
structure for code but these are
generated by every preprocessor or at
least most so what can we do with this
section so we no longer are reading text
and we don't even have valid CSS yet so
we have this object that represents our
preprocessor data and data is really
important there we can change the data
we can read the data we can add to it we
can do anything we want at that point as
data it's it's much harder to regex in
extra rules and regex
out rules that you don't want than it is
to just say like hey change the rule of
the third node to this new thing or add
another rule it's a declarative way in
code to add things in rather than regex
and and string position and stuff so
there's a compilation phase after this
so what we'll do first is reduce your
preprocessor ast into a CSS ast so you
have this ast this is the data you have
two nodes here the first one is you're
setting a variable blue to this blue
color that we've been using and then we
have a rule somewhere later that
wouldn't
actually be that well I guess you can
set a variable inside of a declaration
you have a rule and it sets the color to
that variable named blue and so this is
not this is not a valid CSS node because
there are no variables and CSS yet and
so we couldn't compile this into CSS but
what the compiler does first is reduces
the ast from the preprocessor into one
that is valid in CSS so it would take
this store that blue was the variable
and then reduce it to just say hey this
node is the color of that color and so
you no longer have the invalid variable
node and now you have a totally valid
CSS node so you could compile that to :
or color : that blue color and that
would be totally valid so it does this
recursively until you get back to a
valid CSS ast and then you compile that
to text so reduction goes from this to
this and it goes leaves the trunk and I
call that up the tree but that's kind of
a weird leaves too trunk would be down
the tree I don't really know I think
there are people who disagree with me
especially really angrily on Twitter so
the recap of how that compilation step
works is first it takes this block and
it changes it into something like this
and I know that's ugly you don't have to
actually be able to read that this is a
declaration it's got color in it and
then there's declaration don't that's a
special type of CSS node you know it's
too advanced but so so you have
essentially a declaration inside of a
declaration here and that's invalid in
CSS it's valid in sass and so what you
do is you first reduce that to three
separate declarations and you'll notice
the a and a:hover are now mixed in the
second declaration and a hover has its
own third declaration with the extra two
characters of whitespace
that are bugging me
so and then you convert that to text and
since CSS knows how to take that ast and
turn it into text that's a very simple
compilation step and so this is what
this text from before this was our
original stuff we have the extra inside
declaration and we do those few things
and now we have two separate
declarations that make sense in CSS so
in words it takes one type of text
converts it into a known but arbitrary
data format then it converts that data
into a different but arbitrary unknown
data format and then it converts that
back into text and that's the entire
preprocessor world and nutshell and so
all of you should be able to just write
pre-processors now and that's the end of
my talk so this is these are the faces
you could probably break each one of
these down into to a lot of smaller
parts but really the only hard part is
that the rest is kind of like solved
computer science II stuff right it's
easy to write parts for expression
grammars and like compilers we've got a
lot of them we can we can do better I'm
sure but there are tools that you can
kind of just use off-the-shelf to do
text to data and data to text you have
to kind of write the the bindings but
that's about it so the only thing that
like in sass or in stylus that that
people are doing really is focusing on
data ones data to what data can I take
in to convert to this regular CSS data
that we know about so the hacking part
of this is is the fun part
so what can we do data one is very
interesting because you usually have the
most amount of data usually reducing
data into data to data to could be
interesting as well if you need to know
something about the CSS structure and
I'll use it a little bit in in a demo
but data one has the most amount the
most dense information that you that you
can have so just my my other bulleted
list here is some things you can do with
data one that I thought I'm off the top
of my head that I won't necessarily
actually show you how but you can go
through those leaf
and you say like oh I used that variable
let me just count up all the times that
that shows up you can say like it turns
out I never use these ten variables that
I declared at the top of my file and
that can be interesting
you can change variables in real time
you say well I know I set this as this
but I'm gonna go change half of them to
a new value just by replacing the dot
value of that node and then when it
compiles it doesn't know that you
changed something you can reduce
duplicate code you can go look for
duplicate selectors and and rules and
say like well let's get rid of these you
could write a linter I think Nicole
wrote one of those and you can output
statistics and do all sorts of fun stuff
so I'll show you some some fun stuff so
as long as data one is valid when you're
done it doesn't matter what you did to
it so you could completely replace it
with a new ast and then compile it and
would just compile to your new ast I'd
probably be ill-advised so here's my
first example the important eyes ast
modifier so you take in data which is an
ast and usually have a type on
everything because that's how you know
what to do with it so we check to see if
it's a rule if it's a rule we change its
value to have important at the end is
that this is the Bango there is it on
the other side oh it really is that man
I'm I'm sick so I'll play that now it
goes on that side right someone tell me
no it doesn't all right man
CSS not a fan
anyways so you'll go through this rule
and you'll say if this is a rule well
which it is because we're going through
this rule you'll add important to the
value and then whenever it gets printed
out that'll have important at the end so
if it already had important you're kind
of screwed we didn't check and then
we'll say everything is recursive in a
tree right so you'll say my children
might be rules too if I'm not a rule and
then so go through each node recursively
down the tree and if it's a rule change
the value to have important at the end
of it and really in recursive functions
you should like return it and stuff like
that but in JavaScript we're passing on
the same object and it'll just work
sorry yes that's the whole one here's
the opposite the undo in turn work AST
so we're going to go straight into the
children of the ASD and we're gonna see
if the child is a rule and it matches on
the string important at all then just
return null and essentially delete that
node so if if a rule has important in it
no longer put it in the set of rules
that we're gonna send to the compiler
otherwise return the child and then do
that recursively and then we'll take out
all those null rules at the end with the
compact which is a non-standard array
function that I'm allowing you to trust
me on and those rules if there were ten
rules before and six of them had
important in them now you have four
rules and when they get compiled just
the four rules come out so you have both
ways to turn on globally importance or
to remove any rule with an important you
could also just remove the important tag
which would probably may be reasonable
but just write them don't write them to
begin with so this is every preprocessor
every preprocessor has this face this is
not unique to stylist or SAS or anything
that we're doing up here it is varying
levels of difficult
to actually get into this phase though
in different preprocessors rework is a
pretty new one
by TJ Holloway J Chuck it's close enough
Vision Media and he'd he brought stylus
originally and rework was kind of like
based on what he learned from that he
wrote this and it is essentially just
like exposing the ast layer as soon as I
submitted this talk maybe like two days
later he put this out and I was kind of
bummed but it actually made the demo way
easier so I was no longer bummed as a
kerning nightmare or what so let's go a
little more real-world so compilation of
styles is pretty fast right like I can
compile like that tan line CSS or sass
file and like milliseconds right that's
pretty cool but it's not fast if you
want like a slider that changes a
variable right you can never hook this
on to an unchanged event and have things
update on the page you get a send a
request back to the server have it
compile send the file back up re-inject
recalculate styles that would never work
you'd have to have it unlike a second
you know max of minimum delay on the
change events so if you're building a
theme builder which say what you will
about the real world goodness of that
but I had to do it you want a color
picker and you want a size slider for
some of your variables you don't
necessarily want to say like make this
thing bigger you want to say like make
my base color different right you wanted
to change all the places you're using
base color in your code and that's
signified by variables in your CSS files
and you want to do it in real time and
the only way to do that is to avoid
recompiling because a compile step is
just going to take too long so we'll go
to my demo so we have this fun page
conventionally 75 it all right so we're
running this this is a page with a
little bit of CSS I can show you my
example CSS file this is the my CSS
if I literally adapt my CSS it is my own
rework CSS preprocessor which has one
feature which is variable so I've turned
on variables so I'm using BG color for
this background border-radius big border
radius that type of stuff and then in my
index.html file I have a header and a
sub header and then I style that with
with those things and then somewhere
that isn't open I pass the data for what
those variables should be and I won't
try and open that right now so we have
values for this and this comes out as
CSS on the other end so now you can see
the values so this is example that's the
SS it comes out the other end
precompiled actually pre-compile onload
so each time it'll do that and you can
see you have a background color here we
have more background colors and so those
are getting set what I also add it was
an endpoint to add dot JSON to the end
of every single CSS file what that'll do
is it'll take the ast go find every
variable and then reduce essentially
flipped the file on its head so what we
have here is data that says this is the
BG color variable this is the app width
variable this is the border color and in
here we have a list of selectors that
end up using this variable and then the
rules that they use it on so we know
that dot container contains a border
radius where the value is big border
radius and that seems cool like we now
have a list of all our variables so that
was pretty easy to get based on on just
going through the nodes and saying is
this a variable node and if it is add it
to this list and then you kind of have
to do some hacky stuff in order to get
the selectors back out
depending on your preprocessor but we
can pull in that data here and it got
way bigger we can pull in that data here
and we have this thing I've injected on
the top and I have all the code for this
for you that I'm not going to walk
through because that's a fun demo but
essentially what we're doing here is we
go through those variables we list them
out here and then based on with they say
width or color I'll give
the correct picker forum and also tell
you how many times they they were used
and so bgcolor is used twice and we know
the selector and we know the rule so
I'll use the selector real fast to show
you the three pages on the three places
on the page that bgcolor actually gets
used or at least which elements so this
is being used on the HTML element the
body element which I guess starts at the
top of this thing since I have a margin
on it and then also bgcolor is used as
the text color for leaf them alone which
is more hilarious than you guys gave it
credit for
and so we're using a single variable it
shows up in two selectors and it's on
three elements and this is data that you
can never see like where are my
variables being used in my page that's
pretty cool you see like app width is
used on this you see border color border
radius all that stuff so that's pretty
cool but also we can we can inject new
styles we know the selector we know the
rule and we know our new value that we
want to try out so we can pop up a color
picker and say this is BG color and just
inject a totally new style like so we're
not recompiling we're injecting a new
style like a style element and we'll put
the selector bracket rule :
and then whatever we're picking from
this color selector on a change event so
we can do this straight off of our
variables so this is completely
generated from the data inside of your
ast you don't have to program this
somewhere else we can add a new variable
to our file it will automatically show
up in this list so we can come in and
change the app with to something that's
more CSS friendly change the border to
invariably if you give someone complete
control it looks like this every time
right this is my favorite doesn't like
that trips me out man
I'm I like nyquil right now but that's
that's good anyways and then we can get
a bitter header color in there and so
that's that's my one example of some
crazy stuff that you can do I have this
available at this URL talk slash abusing
- preprocessor - STS and you can see
that you had to run an Express app in
order to do that compilation step but
you can kind of see it's all well
commented on on how that works but thank