my name is Felix caisson deferred and
I'm going to talk about how to do
testing and noches if you are looking
for me on github Twitter IRC that's my
handle yeah Tom already gave a little
introduction about me but I've guess
I've been an early contributor to the
project and I kind of worked on a bunch
of model modules and actually really
liked that mad heads a talk right in
front of me because a lot of the
problems he's describing that he has was
running node and production have
different solutions in debugging lindo
stovall recently I don't know how reason
but rode on a mailing list there really
are only two acceptable models of
development sink and analyze or years
and years of testing and thousands of
machines now for most software you're
going to need a certain combination of
the two you're going to need to do a lot
of thinking and analyzing and a lot of
testing a lot of machines but i think
the sink and analyzed part can be
creighton hants to certain techniques
when it comes to testing noches
applications and they can save you a lot
of time on the debugging part and the
running on thousands of machines so let
me tell you a little story how I was
using node before I learned my lessons
and how we're using it now it kind of
started in june 2009 we were building a
product called trance loaded which is a
service for file uploading and
processing is an infrastructure service
it's kind of similar to what mess you
talked about at the MRC actually using
the note formidable file upload parcel
for that that we wrote and we initially
did set in peach key and we try to do a
lot of things that were difficult in PHP
like running a lot of processes in the
background and getting events for their
standard out in standard error to show
encoding progress information to the
users and it always felt very tedious
where were using workers we're using
hues and we just got nowhere with that
we didn't get results out upset said we
wanted it we're certainly doable but it
felt painful so we found no chairs
no jst m and we kind of fell in love
with it and we had a lot of fun using it
it really solved our problems and we
were thinking yeah that's the answer to
all of our problems but actually our
first version we totally crashed it it
did not work at all for us to be more
precise note crashed for us we were on a
very early version sing it with co 118
or something and it had a buggy piece in
the networking layer and every so often
more sober which is died without slowing
an exception just this little message
you see here f come receive success
while awesome success and then a sec
fold but without the sexual part so we
were really close to launching at that
point there we were like oh no and well
as those things happen when stuff hits
the fan there's more coming and this was
exactly the time where Ryan was changing
the promised API and nuking it
completely from the core and putting in
callbacks instead we were like oh no now
we have to rewrite all of our code on
top of the fact that our initial code
base didn't even work to begin with but
an even bigger problem was we had no
tests we had written like 10,000 lines
of no she s code and now refactoring
every single piece of the coats it uses
a promise to a call back I mean it was
not going to happen so we device the
greatest plan of all software
development ever we decided to rewrite
the whole thing that's what software
engineer that's right no that's we
really kind of went back and forth of it
if it made sense or not but we decided
said not having a test suit was actually
a really big problem even the bigger
problems and the fact that promises were
changing underneath us and at that time
I was watching a real con 2009 keynote
by robert martin also known as uncle bob
and he gave the presentation called what
killed small talk could kill ruby too
and it was really energetic presentation
about test ribbon development and i got
all pumped up and excited i even all
that one of the little cream wristbands
he he has for people to look at and be
constantly reminded to write the tests
first and i was very excited it's kind
of me in the
backgrounds they're being very excited
and so that's kind of how I got into
that it's been a years that have been
doing test-driven development so take
pics of what I have to say with a grain
of salt I'll talk what works for us what
doesn't and yeah let's get started with
us how to test asynchronous code when we
will start this when we decided we want
to do this test for the development
thing we want to be really disciplined
and do it all right we kind of looked
around for asynchronous testing
frameworks and but it kind of felt hot
everything we try didn't really work the
flying closure monster didn't really
help you know you already have those
closures in your code everywhere and now
you also have some in your tests and you
kind of need to make sure that each test
kinda has a done call back where you
tell it it's over and if there's an
exception that you didn't catch it's
really difficult to trace it back to the
tests that it was happening in I wishes
a mess it didn't really work for us it
turns out this is not a new problem or
anything this problem has been around
for a very long time the asynchronous
stuff is only piece of it but there's
some old news here that's why I brought
this last week's newspaper it's a German
terrible tabloid magazine and there's
little demonstration we can do with us
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
fold to sing seven times guess that's
two right now three four five
six gets tricky here seven okay there's
a lot of geeks in the room how many
pieces of paper are stacked up here now
anybody under 28 who set 128 can you
come here for a second it could need
your help on something all right come up
yeah folding it again would probably be
hard but I want you to try to rip it and
set religious yeah can you rip it oh
hell no okay there's no way to rip it
right no one okay okay thanks they all
you have to do thank you so so what's
the problem here well the problem is
said you can think of this newspaper as
a metaphor for something else you can
think of it as a simple computer program
that managed seven boolean variables you
have seven bits thing that can adds up
to 128 states and each bullying bullying
in this program has an impact on the
behavior of the software in this case it
makes a newspaper sicker and as a result
of set it is really difficult to rip
through this once and it's kind of the
same as if you try to rip through a
complex program with a single test
that's the whole premise of this
asynchronous testing you're kind of
doing end-to-end testing once you're
doing I oh and it is not a good wave for
testing it has certain benefits but it's
certainly not a solution to everything
why is that the case it's the problem is
the more variables that you get in this
case let's say boo lengths the more
possible states your software can be in
with the boolean's you get an
exponential increase in in complexity of
your software and each of these possible
combination of states could affect the
flow of your program and increase the
size or amount of tests you would need
to write from an integration perspective
exponentially so that's obviously not
going to happen but what's even worse
you don't have Bowling's you have
strengths you have chasing objects which
are really complicated because they're
nested and they have different data
structures in the marais dates whatnot
so
you don't actually end up with an
exponential explosion the end up with a
combinatorial one and if your math geek
you know that's one of those curves that
you kind of run straight into there's no
way to write enough tests for even a
simple program you'll need millions of
tests so how to test a synchronous code
as the answer is not really difficult
it's really an old answer and the
answers make it synchronous I'll get to
what that means in a second but we did
it at Prince loaded and we released
version 2 which was a lot nicer kind of
like you see in the picture with a
unique room well almost we have still
problems but it's much much better than
worse before we now have processed many
terabytes of data we have really low
buck raid I think the amount of box we
had in productions that affected users
is less than 10 and of those ten maybe
eight have been boxed where we wrote the
tests that actually specified the wrong
behavior there's not much you can do and
it's pretty clean code base or since we
want to refactor but we have close to
ninety nine percent test coverage so how
does it happen or how do you micro test
code well what I meant when I was saying
you need to make the code testing
synchronous with what I really was
saying is you have to unit test unit
testing means no io takes place you have
to inject all the stuffs that would
perform I oh you have to inject test
apples for that and that way you never
have such callback hell because
everything you're going to call is going
to be synchronous and if not well you
need to do more stopping and mocking so
how can you do that well rule number one
as I said no I oh that's how you get
there you start out when you load your
modules you make sure that nothing ever
does I oh and your tests rule number two
is that's optional depending on what you
want to test how you want to do it but
test-driven development really really
helps writes a test first if you can if
you have a piece of software that you
need to get and later on you can always
add a test for that late for that later
but TDD is much preferable the last part
is discipline I will not kid anybody
writing tests forever you seeing a line
of your code it's a pain in the
ass
it is I mean anybody who tells you it
kind of gets easier with time and it
comes really fun there hasn't really
turned that way for me I mean it you see
the results if you like what you get
there so you keep doing it but it's
really hurdle to do a big project from
scratch and write tests for everything
but I think the benefits of it kind of
outweigh the disadvantages so there's
still one problem what libraries to use
what do you lie breeze do you guys use
for testing right now anybody using bout
anybody doing like real unit testing
without io with it okay few people other
test libraries to the public expresso
maybe few people on expressive maybe
more general who's testing at all who
who's happy was there testing a few
people I need to talk to you guys later
on to see what you guys I do so my plan
for today was to release sweet
completely new libraries and I pretty
much managed it the fact that my
computer was broken the week before I
came here and chat leg and partying
didn't help but I'm pretty closed it and
they already in a state where they can
be played with the first library is
called node fake and what it does is
it's basically a simple mock mocking and
stopping library but it doesn't force
you into the concepts where you really
have to think about defining all the
methods of your mock objects beforehand
you can simply say I have an object here
I expect a method call on that on that
object with this signature and then
please verify this is happening in my
tests and on the other hand you can also
do as a kind of stopping approach where
you just inject a value but you don't
care return value but you don't care if
the function is ever executed or you can
as well verify state after the fact so
you can going to go for the market
approach of testing behavior or you can
go for the state association approach
and to wrap this thing up I wrote
another library called node micro test
which i will try to life them out here
but
you guys know how that always goes
something goes wrong but you'll get a
good laugh and what's this library does
it kind of helps with the discipline
part of performing no I Oh in your tests
because what it does it loads your test
faults in a separate v8 context so the
global object is completely free of any
note libraries you don't have a require
call you don't have a process object you
have nothing in there I doin checked a
few things that are just little
convenient but you have no way to get IO
down in there unless you kind of hack
around the system which which you
shouldn't do maybe there's valid use
cases what it also has it has no fake as
a mixin so the message i was talking
about on the in the fake library you get
on the same class object and i also have
a very basic test described framework in
there that if you're testing a little
structure i might separate that out
because everybody's kind of crazy but
how they want their color coded output
to look and all that stuff that i didn't
care about when writing this library but
it seems in the note community like
colors are the coolest thing in the
terminal I won't talk you that they're
cool but there's other problems to solve
first year and their Zilla so the live
coding will will start in the second and
the third libraries this one's actually
working well nice thinks of
documentation is also complete it's
called note far and it's basically find
and run so you give it a directory of
files of tests fault it will find some
more and execute them in its own note
process and kind of give you really
useful real-time output show you how
long the suit is running it prints it
all on one line it will only show you
output of your individual tests if one
of them failing you can kind of sets of
a paucity on that and that's the third
library so let's try to yeah do them bad
life coding
so I was trying to find really simple
programs that we could test here without
running out of time and this is really
cool using that stabilizing a note now
called stream pipe who has blamed played
with the stream pipe stuff okay cool and
so what we're going to do we're going to
write a little cat program which
basically takes one argument which is
another file and then opens a file
create read stream on that and then to
dust we'd stream pipe and then process
that standard out so that's like a few
lines of code and we can easily test
drive that so since we're doing
test-driven development the first thing
we're going to add is a test file so
we're going to name that test dash cat
and we're going to use the micro test
library we're going to say test equals
require micro test module then we're
going to tell it where the module is
that we're loading one of the cool
things at this point is the way this
library works is it can load any chava
script file so I'm pretty confident that
I can explai turon to actually test
browser scripts as well because you get
a new v8 context you can pre-fill the
global object in that so it's pretty
easy to say do the same kind of testing
with the same library and another thing
that's good as since your unit testing
here you don't actually care about the
browser behavior so the fact that this
will probably be limited to running a
node is exactly what you want here would
you want to do browser test and use
selenium or something more higher level
so we should already have a failing test
here because I haven't created saket j/s
file so yeah right here it says file not
found so yeah that's readable so the
first thing we need to do for test room
development does make a test fail we did
said and now we have to make it pass by
creating a CAD file so
close this little window so when we
execute the test now it's passing so
it's verifying our test is there the
next thing we want to do is we probably
want to include CFS module because we're
going to need that for the read scream
so we're going to say our test requires
CFS module and to make this test fail we
have to do one more step we're going to
have to say our our cat module is
created by compiling this test and
what's this will do it will actually
load the source code run it in a new v8
context and if use a marshal exports
back and like creating this module that
exports object and injecting that that's
as far as I go in terms of mirroring the
node API few other things like
underscore file name and your name but
not much fluff beyond that so if we
execute that it's going to tell us this
calling off the screen I'll have to
switch to terminal for that
ok I guess that means bigger
okay module test kit has no method
require Oh requires this a functioning
here that's why it didn't work so what
it now says it gives us a expectation
that has failed it says I was expecting
a different call i was expecting require
FS to be called in your file but instead
module that verify was called which is
called when you call compile it verifies
that all expectations that have been set
up until that point are met and so it's
telling us what to do includes this
require FS module so that's what we're
going to do we're going to go back to
our catch ES File we're going to say bar
F s equals require FS and that should
makes a test happy ok so the next thing
we want to do is we want to assert that
on the FS object we call a create read
stream so what we're going to do is
we're going to say test expect and then
some reference to this module is
actually on the test object in a in a
property called required so it's test
that required FS and we're going to say
create we'd stream ok now if we execute
that ok my
let me do that over here ok so again we
get failing a sortation here it was
expecting FS that create read seemed to
be called its not being called so let's
fix that ok
now as the test is passing again so what
do we want to do next the next thing we
will probably want to assert is that
this create read stream call returns our
injected read stream which is not a real
one and then we want to make sure that
it's a pipe message is being called on
that so what we will do is we're going
to say we're probably going to name this
variable file and I use all upper case
for my test variables just to
differentiate stuff I'm you're serving
against from the other stuff it's a less
annoying form of duplications and adding
like a prefix or suffix to them and it
really helps because sometimes we
actually also get variables out of the
test and you use those with underscore
and they asked the same parameter
signatures so what we're going to do
here as a actually the underlying fake
library includes a little semantic sugar
that lets you create a test object what
this really is it's just an object and
if it failed since I'm a certain it's
going to give you this name again and so
you have a very clear idea of this is a
test variable and since you say object
you could probably care about reference
to it you don't care about the value so
what we need to do now is we need to
return that file object here so we can
do and return the file you wow that's
crazy let's not do that again so what's
this will do it would we return the file
this should not fail the test yet yep it
doesn't because we're not really doing
anything with a file object yet at this
point it might also be worse knowing
that there's shortcuts because you're
going to write this stuff a lot so what
you could have also done at this point
is to put put set and third parameter in
an array of all the arguments it's
expecting that's kind of semantic
shortcut for that but we'll go for
readability here so what we did not want
to do so we want to expect the pipe call
so we're going to say a test expect file
pipe
okay and let me do that in the other
window again so yeah it's saying I was
expecting a different call i was
expecting pipe but it didn't happen so
let's fix it
okay we're not really sure where to pipe
yet so let's not do that that makes the
test pass for once and now what we want
to do is we want to pipe to process
standard output so what we need to do is
we kind of need to create our own fake
process object this time I'm actually
going to just use a plain literal
because it's a little easier for what
we're doing here what we want to do is
we want to have the test object called
process standard out on this and we need
to tell our tests to use this object so
another way to inject it is we can
actually inject into the global object
of our sandbox so we're going to do test
context that process equals process and
now we can ask that our parameter to
pipe is actually process standard out
i'm using the long form here again with
arcs and process then it out
okay now it says unexpected argument
count it was expecting one occupant it
supplied function it gets 0 what's also
kind of nice it it tells us whereas the
expectation was set up that tells us in
our test cases worst line 18 so that
kind of makes it really fast to jump
back to where you need to fix things and
now we're going to due process standard
out oops
oh this didn't work i need to uppercase
that sorry okay if we run the two test
passes again that's pretty much almost
the whole cat program it's the only
thing we didn't implement was telling
what file to actually open on the weak
stream what we really want to do is we
want process och v2 because that's where
node has a first parameter we pass into
it so let's do that real quick we need
to create a fake v object here the first
two parameters don't matter so we're
going to make them know and yeah for the
third one where we're gets just going to
say file duchess or something so we go
back to the read stream test we add a
with ox expectation here crosses rb2
yeah we we get to expect a exception
again we go back into that we're going
to fix the test
okay looks like it ran anybody see
mistake so far or do you guys think we
can try running this all right let's try
running this let's try it out put our
CAD program ok that worked so we just
test drove that whole thing seeing I'm
running out of time shortly so I'll skip
ahead to the other slides there's a lot
of stuff in the API you can there's a
lot of ways you can verify this behavior
it has excellent support for also
setting expectations again classes being
called with a new operator and checking
you and stuffs there but there's lots of
stuff in there let me try to find my
remaining slides yeah so one thing
you're probably asking well those kind
of looks like a lot of code for very
little behavior well that's the case and
I'm gonna lie but let's look at what
that actually means I trans loaded so we
have to around six thousand lines of
code of library stuff there's a lot more
dependencies a lot of stuff rewrote but
we kind of have a lot of test code for
that we have twelve thousand lines of
code just testing the behavior we have a
lot of fixture data server configuration
to customer websites and dependencies
but those are not included in this
amount of test data what's really
interesting here is to first see that
measure one to two I think that's too
high we went a little crazy there but I
think one to one is what you're going to
get if you're going to do it seriously
probably a little higher what also worth
knowing is as a distribution between
micro tests and integration tests so
unit tests that we said I was showing
how to do we write a lot of cells and
those are actually we've written huge
amounts of our programs just that way
and then we write one integration test
and kind of works the first time it's
beautiful to see thousands of lines of
code coming together like that and so
the factor we have here is 124 and we
have a more integration test on trans
loads and I would like for other stuff
because we need to do crazy stuff with
ffmpeg we need to extract some nails
from the videos we encode and send your
visual verification against a set of
fixture data to see if it still works
ffmpeg is one of the most broken open
source projects ever I mean it's not
broken but
it has a very strange way to interact
with the community into people using it
I'm very grateful for their work but
notice such a nice community in to work
with and but what becomes even more
clear here's when you look at knotts the
amount of code butts amount of
hesitations see it already looks pretty
good we probably have too much
duplication our integration tests that's
what it means we have I don't know 190s
Ertz on the integration tests in 2300 on
the micro test and just a reference
point for something else for library
code note mysql has a factor of 12 1.35
for library versus test code I think
that's much more reasonable and I hope
to get that even first down to one to
one with that new micro testing I was
just showing it has a similar in the
creation versus micro testing here and
it's also doing pretty well when you
look at citations so to finish this up
yes this is a lot of code and it kind of
feels like it slows you down but one
really good quote on the subject us why
do you have breaks in a car they're not
there to go slower they actually there
to cook faster because you can speed up
two curves and hits a break and slim
around it and that's what we really see
with this it costs a lot of it costs a
little bit more time to develop new
features but if we hunt bucks in
production like someone neta sonic we
can actually test a lot of things on a
very low level like what happens if an
error event is being emitted here are we
handling that and we we are able to
usually pinpoint sources of error very
quickly write a test for it on the micro
level sometimes also on send equation
level depending on how easy it is to get
scissors past and then we sometimes
throws into creation test that shows the
back away because the micro test is
defining the behavior of our program so
the too long didn't read don't use
integration test to show the basic
correctness of your software and write
more micro test I don't know if I have
time for questions we can do one
question while we're setting up so
oh one or two questions so if you have
questions ask them quickly questions
anybody this whole I hear micro test
sent me down the dependency injection
sort of daiquiri and yes their approach
is there a frame or packaged drinking
use for di yes basically you don't need
to do dependency injection because you
can inject a reference to the class
that's being required you require
another class you can inject your own
constructor for that and then you can
actually say test expect it's a
reference to your test double
constructor and so you don't need to
change your code to test it that was one
of my design goals for this don't write
your code for tests right in for your
human readability and then figure out a
way to test it okay thank you sorry for