hey everyone it's great to be here I'm
Kevin dan goor this is Patrick Walton
and Joe Walker when we are three parts
of the Mozilla developer tools team I
just wanted to mention that since we
first introduced this presentation or
first proposed it we are we have a
broader mission now we used to be
working pretty much on this exclusively
now we're actually responsible for a
whole bunch of developed tools within
well within Mozilla and i'll just point
out that like this is Firefox 4 and
there's a console that that's all right
well then moving on basically I forget
what you knew about Bespin last year
because we basically made in the
inverter intervening time we've made a
bunch of changes to the project and the
code so it's a very different kind of
things than where we started so and it
even has a new name okay and it has a
new name that's y a much more recent
skywriter and actually you're going to
see during the presentation if we can
show you anything you're going to see
that there are still bits of the best
big name left over so ants let's go 1-1
yeah let's not yes yes see if we can get
the screen out
alright hey we got slides again this is
gonna help okay all right so on that
note let's have Joe talk about what
Bespin actually is or skywriter sorry
food yeah we're gonna make that mistake
to sky ready so a javascript-based coded
it's a very very simple the idea is that
the text area that we have in HTML is
kind of sucky there's a whole ton of
problems with it for code it doesn't
have tabs it doesn't have not line
wrapping you can't do selection properly
whole ton of issues with it it degrades
a lot with lots of code and everyone
that tries to use it comes up with all
these problems the other thing we wanted
to do was to experiment with html5 of it
we think that that generally speaking
developers are going to have up-to-date
browsers on their computers and kanda
upgrade so we kind of freed ourselves
from the shackles well to start off we
freed ourselves from the shackles of
Microsoft entirely and just concentrated
on Chrome and Firefox but I think we'll
be supporting ie9 now as well so we
wanted to play around with canvas web
workers and flex box etc if anyone from
IE 9 is in the audience we want web
workers thought I'd throw that out there
and the idea different to how it was
when we started is that we should be
able to code in any cloud the idea
originally was that we would have a best
bin server and Mozilla would host this
coding environment with you and there's
always a ton of problems with with
scaling that and there's also a ton of
problems we trust as well you know why
should you trust Mozilla with your code
and why should we trust you with some of
the custom stuff that you may want to do
with your code on our service so just as
you can deploy a client now you should
be able to deploy a server as well so
it's a bring your own cloud kind of
solution so in addition to being able to
develop code and run it on a server
we've seen a lot of use of Bespin in the
embedded case in which people who were
developing apps wanted to take the
infrastructure wanted to take the editor
that we had built and use it in their
own products and so we've seen a ton of
community uptake for it and here are a
few examples there is a wiki software
called X wiki which uses Bespin to edit
wiki extensions it's kind of hard to see
here because they're using a dark theme
but you can add it actually edit
extensions for the wiki using Bespin and
there is a there is a product that was
just released that integrated the
etherpad and Bespin together it just
appeared out of nowhere on the mailing
list somebody said hey we made an either
pad with vespa and it works so it's
called ether codes and that we are using
it internally for the add-on builder
which is part of the jetpack project for
creating extensions you'll be able to
create extensions using Bespin with an
IDE around it and make extension for
Firefox so palm has Ares and they've
been using vestment for a while and then
there are several other IDEs like shift
edit and J gate and Megara and all of
them are using Bespin so when we decided
to reboot the project we found that we
wanted to make embedding one of the top
use cases we really wanted to focus on
it because when vestment was originally
conceived we like Joe said we had this
all-in-one encompassing vision for it
and it turned out that what people
really wanted was to take parts of it
and use it in their own application so
we really wanted to make that a first
class citizen and I think we've done
really well so as of today we've got two
supported uses for skywriter the first
basically supported way to use guy right
oh right now it
the bookmarklet actually which is a very
simple way that I can demo that right
here oh well first I'll mention that you
can get it from vestment that mozilla
labs com / bookmarklet but here is
basically the page that you'll see there
so the number way you use it as you drag
this up to your bookmarks bar but I'll
just click it right here so I can demo
it in the page but basically what
happens is if you find a text area
somewhere like if you go to just or
whatever you find a text area here's a
plain text area and you hover over it
you'll see this little Bespin logo
appear next to it when you've clicked on
the bookmarklet so I can click that and
it will convert the text area into a
better text editor right there one that
you can choose a language for syntax
highlighting you can switch themes if
you want so that works pretty in almost
all cases you know if you're coming to
come across a random text area and you
say boy I wish I had a better editor you
can click the bookmarklet and get a
better editor right there so the next
case add yes so you made in case this is
when you want to upgrade your own
website rather than upgrading the
website of somebody else so how do you
embed best been on on your pages and
pretty much I think if you trying to
imagine what you would like how you
would like it so that you had best been
to your pages with one tiny exception
that's pretty much exactly what you do
you have to download some stuff and
we'll talk in a bit about how to do
custom builds if you need it but so
there's your page before any
modifications you probably going to be
slightly more complicated than this but
you're going to have some text area or
something that you want to upgrade it
doesn't have to be a text area so if you
if you wish to turn that text area into
a best bin text area then you have to
import best bin so the thing that you
perhaps might not have guessed is this
link thing so that we can get at other
resources but obviously you're going to
need a script and you're going to have a
class of best bin which you enter text
area now I would say we've not yet done
a release of skywriter in fact we
haven't even reason we change the name
is because lucasarts of
scary with their lawyers they have lots
of lawyers and they're very pointy and
they had a trademark on Bespin and they
let it lapse but they also go around
suing people for stuff than trademarks
so we thought where we're going to we
have to change the night so the next
release that we make will be called
skywriter we haven't done a skywriter
release yet which is why for the letter
the most recent release which still
class equals best bin and your page
suddenly looks like that that's all you
need to do very very easy so we have
custom builds that was a very simple
example and Bespin has a lot of features
Bespin has so many features that we
decided to split it out into plugins and
shoot so that you can not only choose
the ones that you that you want for
example syntax highlighting you might
not want all the syntax highlighters in
there but you can also write your own
and to integrate that with whatever
environments so it's really customizable
I'm just going to give a simple example
of how you do that so we have what's
called this manifest it's just a JSON
file that you give to a tool that we
call dry ice and here's an example of
another manifest so it just tells dry
ice which is our build tool where to put
the output and what plugins you wants
and whether to include some sample pages
that you can try it out right there so
so before we had just a few plugins and
now you can here's a lot of plugins so
you have JavaScript you have CSS syntax
highlighting you have JavaScript code
completion you have growl notifications
and jas lint integrated and so here's
the example I'll just mention also those
all of those plugins on that last page
or ones that ship in the best been
embedded package so you don't to
download anything
for those so this here is a spin from
that trick tank example earlier okay so
showing off the JavaScript code
completion so let's say jQuery is loaded
on your page this is actually all the
tags from jQuery not tags but I mean
well tags is like the internal name
basically these are all the names of the
functions and things that are in jQuery
that he can get out right there we kind
of suffer a bit here from the projector
turning any color darker than medium
brown into black so sometimes it doesn't
look as nice as it does from down here
that you get the idea okay and you can
also see down at the bottom of the
screen there there's the command line
that's something that is available and
people have been had been requesting for
quite a while to have it and Patrick
just around jslint which gives get the
giant plug in there against it you could
see it popped up a notification saying
hey you've got errors in your file so
it's a very easy way to quickly do a
check if you look at the command line
out but you can actually see these are
worth this where the fight went wrong
what the problems are so pretty quick
easy check so it's very easy to actually
take take and customize a skywriter
build so that it got so it's got just
the features you want okay so now we get
into the more complicated part of our
session where we're going to do some
live coding so you've probably heard of
pair programming we're going to be doing
like three-person programming we're
going to be explaining what's going on
Joe is gonna be typing and Patrick is
actually gonna be the one who's not the
driver's seat who's actually making sure
that we're not making errors in our code
so let's go again right do this here
okay so yes one of the things is that
before you create a plug-in of your own
you might want to check the best band
plug-in gallery Bespin plugins mozilla
labs com there are a bunch of plugins
there already like different syntax
highlighters and things like that
different commands people created so
somebody may have already written either
something that you can use or something
that that does what you want to begin
with so we frequent have this debate do
you use
keynote or do you do live coding the
good thing about html5 investment ism
can actually have both at the same time
so okay yep so to get started with this
particular project we're going to be
showing off making a markdown current
conversion command to mark down preview
command so we can actually take mark
down text convert HTML and view it in
the browser we're going to use this
library that somebody else has created
this is a markdown parser that we've
packaged up as a library we can use with
best bin which basically just means
adding some little bit of scaffolding
around their code but it's just a
library that converts marked down to
HTML so we've downloaded that already
and then we're going to go ahead and
create a manifests markdown sampled
Jason actually just manifest I Jason's
probably a good name for that so first
thing we need yeah we're going to be
doing Jason's we need the output
directory and we're going to put that in
dot dot slash build because there's
going to be relative to the build tool
dry-ice this is where it's going to go
the next thing that will need to do is
list our plugins now the screens are
pretty dark so we see that but about
time that one oh we didn't include the
white snow to build yes the best man has
multiple themes that you can you can
include and that probably would have a
nice if we included the white doesn't
however have to show nicely okay so
we're going to list out the plugins so
the plugins we're going to be using here
are basically embedded which is
basically a plug-in that gives you all
of the basic stuff of an embedded editor
the second one we're going to use is
called you I commands that does things
like giving you command command J
shortcut to switch to the command line
so basically just a handful of
convenience commands for building
working within a larger Bespin you I the
command line plug-in itself or something
we want so we actually can run our
markdown preview command conveniently
then we're going to include the markdown
j/s library which is the library that
we've downloaded that does the
conversion and we're going to create a
new plug-in called Bespin markdown so
basically what that plug-in is going to
do the actual command the integration
with the editor and the last thing that
we need to do is we're going to be doing
our code
in a separate directory from where the
build tool is so we need to give it a
search path to tell it where to find our
packages so the search path will point
to dot slash demo smoking works and then
I think we've got our manifest file
right and through the awesome power of
PB pace so we're using we're halfway
through read by rewriting the server the
server was in Python originally we're
rewriting it in JavaScript so we're
using the embedded version here nothing
with that so there's no server behind
this so yeah p be pasted to be our file
system
it works okay so the next thing we're
going to do is we're going to start up
now that we have our manifest file we're
going to start up dry ice which is our
build tool again and it's got a server
mode if you say dash S and a port number
it's going to start up a little web
server that every time you reload the
page it will be rebuild best bin which
is like an instant affair it'll reload
it and show it to you it may actually
not work now okay it worked with a bait
with the basics though but basically so
the next step is we have to actually
define our plug-in so we'll start
writing our plug-in so at the top the
first thing we need to do is basically
provide some metadata so every best been
plug-in is going to have some metadata
that tells best been about the system
that you're but the plug-in that you're
creating and what it depends on and what
its providing to the system and this
this basically is up there's a couple
ways to do it you can put in a separate
package.json file because these are
actually common J's packages or you can
we have a single file plug employment
where you can basically stick the
metadata right there inside the same
file you can see you put a defined
metadata marker around it we're going to
start off by listing the dependencies
this is basically these are the
dependencies that our new plugin has so
since we brought this library down
marked on Jas this is responsible for
doing the actual conversion to HTML for
us so we need to say that we're
dependent on that and we know which
version of it we get download it is zero
point one point two so we're going to
put that up there zero point one point
to those are the common J's package
system actually dictates that those
should be semantic versions if anybody's
seen the semaphore respek so that that
tells us something about you know what
we can expect so we can expect lexa 2012
that we can't really expect anything it
quite a semantic versioning so we end we
end up metadata section with a little
end tag there and that basically the
bill tool can just pull that out
use that metadata or provide it to the
client in the server case so we're going
to write it out to our best bin markdown
that JS file which is our our plugin
okay and now we could actually go over
to the web browser go to the page and
reload and we should see actually
nothing of interest if we if we try to
look for our mark down command it won't
be there because we haven't actually
written the command yet yeah the nice
thing about Lord Oakley about our
packaging format is that it's all common
J's packages so if you find a package on
the internet you can just download it
and put it right there and it becomes
the best been plug-in plugins and
packages are the same thing so we're
really trying to make it easy to pull
third-party lives off the shelf like
you're doing right here yep so the next
step is we'll start actually writing the
functionality for our plug-in so you
want to bring that up you lost your
metadata at the top there
just now I've reloaded it am I yeah well
just yeah he cut it so when you don't
have a server involved it makes it a lot
harder to reload a file but we have the
clipboard so Wow okay all right and you
need your end tag that under the
metadata okay so now we're going to get
into the writing the code of our plugin
and it's going to be actually a pretty
straightforward plug into right so the
first thing that we're going to need to
use is the environment we're going to be
using that to get at that's the
environment module basically investment
will give you access to the various
parts of the best environment so the
different things like the text editor
itself and other resources that are
available within it then we're going to
import our markdown library so the one
that we just said we depend on we know
it's going to be available so we will
import it now so now we're going to
create a function so we say export
previews the name previews the name of
our function we're going to export it so
this is all common jas format for people
who aren't familiar with it I guess
there's so many note users that people
are probably from where is it by now
exports that preview equals function all
of our command functions so we have the
concept of a command which actually
defines pretty much anything you do in
the editor including like cursor
movements and things like that are all
commands so the the basic functionality
of the editor all follows along with
with that same pattern so so you can
extend the editor in the same ways that
we built the editor in the first place
so right now we're taking a making a
command function that includes arguments
that's the the stuff coming into the
command and a request object which is
allows you to send stuff back out from
the command and basically we've got
we're going to get the text as either
the selected text so we ask the
environment for the editor and then we
ask the editor for its selected text if
it doesn't have any selected text will
go ahead and take the whole file which
is just envy dead eter you if you use
text area objects you've seen that
they've responded value just like
our editor does so once we have the text
in hand that from the editor we can then
basically create a pop-up window so
we're just going to open up a blank new
window and we're going to use that
window is our preview window and then
we're going to set the document body
enter HTML to be the converted markdown
so we're going to go ahead and run the
conversion function mark down at to HTML
text and then once you're done with your
request you can say request done the
reason we have to do this is because we
have a lot of requests commands that are
actually asynchronous so you'll have to
say request dot or if you're not done to
me basically you have to wait until you
are done to say request done that way
the editor knows that the command line
knows that you're not done yet and it
will provide a little spinner and stuff
like that so at this point we've gone
ahead and defined the command function
but we haven't really told the best bit
environment anything about it like
nothing actually knows it exists so what
we've got is this system of extension
points so we've got an extension point
called command and basically we've got
an extension that we've made for command
here and what we're doing right now is
in the metadata we're telling the editor
about that now the advantage of using
the system is that in a server
environment or actually really in any
environment where you want some dynamic
behavior we can take this command and we
can basically provide all the metadata
of the client so the client knows hey
I've got all these commands but it
doesn't have to load them all it'll load
this command actually only when the
command is executed so you can have a
million command you can have 50 syntax
highlighters things like that the system
will know they exist but it won't
actually load them until they requested
if you do know if when you do a custom
build you can actually choose you could
actually choose to build things in from
the get-go so right now we've said we've
got it we P stands for extension point
so we say we've got a command command
extension and the name is marked down
preview so that's what the user will
actually type and see
okay all right bigger font those easier
than that okay so description on the
command we actually have so one of the
other advantages you get out of the
metadata is that you can type help and
see all the commands even though it
hasn't loaded them yet so this code the
code doesn't get loaded but the command
does the command meditated us knows that
I can display this description if the
command takes two arguments then it can
even display information about those the
next bit is basically how the lazy
loading is made to work you provide a
pointer which is basically it's like a
URL for the piece of code and in this
case we're saying that in this plugin go
ahead and look for a function called
preview so that is where the command is
so the whole plug-in system now has the
ability to say okay well when I need
this command I just go ahead and load it
so it'll call the load function of the
extension and it will automatically grab
grab that preview function okay so I
think with that we have finished our did
you copy at all thanks that okay good
yep so we finish our plug-in we've
pasted in there we go get we've got our
file now we just reload in the browser
and let's see what we get
get try it's good yeah that's so that's
the when you that's the basic text that
comes up when you have like the default
dry ice server so you want to select all
that your what the command is there
that's good that doesn't look like
markdown so why don't we add so that's
not good is it so it's something more
interesting to preview let's do
something work down like
that looks like we're ghosts on stunts
alright see worked on preview well it's
the blank window on the screen but it
gets just off the screen a little bit
and in cburg town
the danger of live coding is that maybe
you'll end up with a blank screen at the
end
try and see what is what let's see the
windows that open need that third
perimeter we double check the card here
that was interesting okay well anyway I
guess while they try to troubleshoot our
plug-in do you carry
oh yeah
yeah it did look the plugin
that looks like carrion to go into the
next thing
you could just run the commands if
there's anything
no there you go fixed it well so it took
us an extra minute there but but it
didn't take a lot of code I guess that's
the general idea it didn't take a lot of
code and it does that it does offer a
lot of dynamic behavior because the way
the plugin system works so we definitely
put some effort into that part of the
system so go back to the next slide
ok
so I'll mention that this is a tutorial
and that's available online if you go to
MZ la MZ l la / sky tutorial you'll
you'll see the the full tutorial here
which adds a couple other things that
are pretty easy to add keyboard shortcut
we've got a very complicated and
powerful keyboard system but it's very
easy to add a keyboard shortcut to a
command and also a command that can
actually convert the selection from mark
down to HTML which is obviously another
very easy and desirable thing to be able
to do so just talking a little bit about
where we are with the project now so we
I mentioned that the two supported ways
Hughes skywriter right now are the
bookmarklet and embedded and we've shown
you some of the embedded uses right now
something that is kind of in the works
is we're basically moving or we've got
Python infrastructure our build tool and
our server or Python we're moving that
code to JavaScript and we're going to
create a desktop version of best been so
that you get actually with Governor
desktop you can say edit your local
files use it as your everyday editor be
able to write plugins for it with this
be able to actually build embedded
skywriters with the desktop editor so
we're going to build that probably on
top of zul runner and then the next step
after that which would be fairly
straightforward is to build a node based
server that will basically use the same
infrastructure so we'll have a big
difference is that between our original
server plan and the current server plan
is that the idea is that everybody will
have their own separate skyraider server
or either individuals or small groups
will have their own servers and the
reason is that if you can trust the
users then you could actually put have
server-side plugins and can do whatever
they want because I mean we have people
who are like you know I want to be able
to edit my PHP code I want to be able to
actually preview it and try out my PHP
code and and you know we missoula do not
want a rotten peas people's PHP code
that's not our thing so with the server
people can actually do whatever they
want and the server infrastructure is
going to be based on the same plug-in
architecture so you can basically make
plugins that do things like get or hg or
really deploy you know via
whatever the popular deployment tool is
these days so that's that's the general
idea is the server will follow same
plug-in model go ahead and to the next
one which means the the nice thing about
this is it basically we have one
codebase one will have one git
repository that basically has all of
this stuff in it and knows how to build
these separate collections of plugins to
put together one once in a code so runs
you know in the browser runs in
different three different browser of
JavaScript engines it runs in you know
spider monkey and zool runner it'll run
a node so it's it's actually pretty cool
to be able to do that with JavaScript
and I think this really goes back to our
focus on embedding we really want that
we really want Bespin to be a tool that
you can adapt for your needs and I think
this this fits into the book Marcos fits
into the embedded case with the
bookmarklet you can take it and use it
anywhere you see a text area with
embedded you can take it use it in your
apps with desktop you can use it on your
system and with the server you can
deploy it into the own built your own
build infrastructure that you already
have and just add it as a piece and that
way you don't have to switch you an
entirely new model you can just start
using it and use it with the build
infrastructure that you have and
integrate it into your workflow that way
and one more thing I'll mention also is
that even even today with the way
skywriter ties in with the with the
existing Python code server that is
actually done in a plug-in so there's
really it's possible just swap out that
plug in and talk to something else on
the other side even today there's
there's really nothing to prevent people
from doing that and people do so talk a
little bit more about the future we get
lots of requests in fact our number one
request right now is for ipad support
this so people people want to be able to
code on their tablet computer without
having anything else with them and I
think you know that's certainly possible
I think actually iOS 42 is likely going
to add better support for canvas than
what we got now so i think that that'll
be coming before too long part of the
trick there as i was figuring out what
you want the backend to be like because
obviously you need needed talking to
something and we've got the server when
we got the new server obviously there's
there's a real answer there but it might
be cool to be able to even just attach
it to dropbox or something like that
so social editing I think um well i know
i love github pull requests to i think
they're an awesome way of doing
development and and there's if anything
about github who would have said like
three four years ago that you could plug
a social network into your VCS and it
would fly and i would love to do is have
it so that your editor understands pull
requests and it understands when you go
edit a file it can tell you how these
are the guys have also been touching
this file and they want to change it in
this way and how much merge pain could
you save yourself if you knew more about
what what your friends were doing and so
there's a ton of stuff in that area that
would just I think change the way we
collaborate with each other in
developing source code and when it comes
to the syntax awareness features we we
have this project called JSC tags which
essentially breeds a Java reads a set of
JavaScript files and tries to extract
tags and it's a lot smarter than C tags
or any or most of the other traditional
packages it can handle things like
jQuery like like you saw and but it
interrupts interoperates with all these
other formats so if you already have
tags for whatever reason you can you can
use them investment and you can just
hook them up to an embedded best friend
it will provide syntax highlighting and
encode completion and we want to use
that for the flight deck the add-ons
builder for it'll be really helpful when
developing extensions to have the code
completion and that infrastructure is
there for you to use in your own
applications as well we plan to expand
JSC tags roll over time to become a sort
of hub for smart analysis of JavaScript
code you've already seen it with some of
the things that Brendan alluded to in
his talk with the static analysis we
have people working on this code base
and it's it's part of Narcisa it's an
extension to narcissus so we want so we
want this project to be a sort of one
place where all of the
upper tools at Mozilla can we basically
want this project to be a sort of core
component of all the developer tools of
Mozilla and so it's going to make its
way in the best bin as well cool and as
far as command line goes I put a real
beef with our command lines that they
they're all making assumptions which
were true 30 years ago but I just not
show any more so there is no good reason
to assume that the output can only be
characters that's just rubbish even if
it's remote we can have a richer
environment than simple characters
there's no good reason to assume that
commands execute one by one I mean
command lines blow up when you put an
ampersand over it and you're doing a you
know you're doing a find which takes
time then you switch to vibe x is going
to get completely confused and there's
no good reason to have that kind of
distinction to say you know this command
is in the background and stuff can only
write into its own little area that's
all things so come ons don't need to be
serialized and there's just a ton of
problems like that which are making
assumptions from 30 years ago which no
longer true and we can have really cool
command lines that help you to be far
more efficient by telling you you know
telling you what the parameters are as
you typing and telling you that
something's wrong and you know here's
how you can fix it command lines are
fast that they're opaque and if we can
put some smarts onto them we can make
them fast and easily discoverable as
well so I think we're done and that is
that is what we know so much we kind of
I don't know how we doing on time but we
would be happy to hear questions yeah
five minutes okay we were planned our
time yeah yes we had they had planning
for that mark down
so that's not the it appears more like
that because at the moment we've we're
rewriting the server from Python into
JavaScript when it's in javascript is
going to be the kind of thing that
anyone can deploy and then you're going
to have your your projects exactly as
before so we've not thrown that away
with the demo day if you know we're kind
of halfway through going to the going
through the JavaScript rewrite on the
server yeah and actually we have we have
plugins for a filesystem plugin that's
kind of abstracted away and it uses a
very simple REST API and we have all
these commands we implemented so even in
the rebooted Bespin you can we have a
full file system with all of the normal
things that you would expect we have cd
we have the ability to change
directories now which was one of the
most popularly requested features but we
we actually a full auto complete also so
as you as you start typing it'll start
matching on the file so we've actually
put quite a bit of effort into trying to
come up with a smarter way to do the
file systems and the idea is rather than
having like one file system you can kind
of mount stuff this is where we're
headed so you can have stuff stored in
s3 you could have stuff stored you know
wherever you liked and it will it will
do the fancy editing things for you
that's the idea yeah
yeah sorry I I think he's asking on what
framework we're going to use for desktop
like titanium or whatever it's actually
going to be zool runner is the plan so
we're going to use the Mozilla
infrastructure for that but it but it's
not going to be a zoo lap it's going to
be an HTML at the zoo it will simply be
enough to get an HTML browser up and rub
rails are up and running so like iTunes
is a wraparound WebKit this can be a
wrapper around best bit if you like yeah
you will not need to know zool to
contribute the best but don't worry yeah
yeah yeahs anyone else ok we're done