you
alright for those who have seen hackers
uh see if this goes it's not gonna go oh
now use your best buyers is to buy us
some time we have to get into plagues
file and copy the worm all right there's
a little tension breaker they had to be
done all right okay so tension breaker
right I think only a few you got that so
before we go any further I want to give
a very thank you to the organizers of
jas comfy you who believed that security
had a place at a developer event there
is there was three talks about security
at a developer event and that is
absolutely unheard of and I am very very
grateful for this opportunity please
everyone give a giant thank you too jaan
Holger Tiffany and ma thay yes thank you
so hey everyone I'm Adam as was said I
am NOT a Baldwin brother you can find me
on Twitter at Adam underscore Baldwin
and a whole bunch of other places I'm
evil packet on github and I'm the chief
security officer at and yet we're a lot
of these things that I'm going to talk
about have transpired I get to work on
some really cool things like an bang
talkie I oh and I'm also the team lead
at lift security where I get to
basically help developers secure
software and build security into the
culture of their dev teams and also the
founder and organizer of the note
security project a rather and exciting
and insane experiment to audit all of
the things on NPM which there's like
40,000 modules now and bridge the
security and devel try to make them play
nicely together and we'll talk about
that more later so as it turns out when
it comes to security we're
right that's basically it nothing is a
hundred percent secure this is this is a
realization that we have to come to in
building software there's going to be
bugs we're going to inject security
flaws we are going to be eventually at
some point so let's talk about risk
risks a board game about world
domination you spread out armies around
the board in pursuit of conquering the
entire Earth it's a it's very slow to
move around armies so typical strategy
is to focus on deploying new armies at
entry point or entry points for defense
and building up armies when you're going
to attack right in a risk battle you
match dice one-to-one highest to lowest
and the attacker gets three dice the
defender gets two dice right there you
notice that the attacker has the
advantage but the defender can only roll
with as many dices they have armies so
when you only have one died left you're
rolling one against three so the
attacker has broken through the outer
boundary and it's pretty easy to sweep
through and if Iceland attacks Greenland
in this scenario which is totally prone
to happen Greenland is going to get a
roll with two dice and it's going to be
a pretty big battle but if green land
only has is the only need offends with
one army in this scenario let's be
honest Iceland's going to pone all of
North America yes including Alberta
sorry Alberta and attackers have the
advantage attackers basically have the
advantage and that's it's it it's akin
to the way it works in software two
attackers have to find one flaw to get
it gain a foothold and as defenders as
developers we have to find and address
them all it's a rather daunting an
impossible task software is hard I don't
think that anybody's going to disagree
with me that billing software is hard
enough without adding additional
complexities software is also full of
opinions we've got things like mobile
first right lots of first content first
off line first
whoo but a lot of what you build doesn't
mean crap if it's not built on a
foundation of security and privacy which
can take all of the fun out of what
you're building in software is full of
constraints right we've we've we've got
constraints like time and money a boss
you know pointing her boss that's
breathing down our neck to get a
features ground out right I but security
is one of those constraints that that
has to be filtered into that sort of
equation so who is responsible for
security anyone want to take a guess you
are sorry but you need to be up to the
challenge right like it it whether you
like it or not you're the first line of
defense in addressing and fixing
security flaws in the software you build
your the ones building it it's time to
take some responsibility for this I was
talking to the martine before the talk
and as a developer if you if you don't
care about security but others care
about security in your organization or
that deal with that software your
negating their effort a bit security is
not something that you can just it's not
a department that that or a third party
that takes care of it for you and if
it's that if that's the way you're doing
it you're doing it wrong it's just not
bolt on so why is your responsibility
well people like my wonderful family
there use your software they use it for
banking transactions and social networks
and you know all those private messages
that we you know send back and forth you
have a responsibility to handle people's
data with respect and help me as the
consumer of your library or your final
product that it's being done on how that
security how you're treating that data
with respect many people that user
software would would likely be outraged
by how Cavalier we handle some of some
of their data we owe them the respect
to handle that appropriately last year
excuse me 2013 I think that's right at
the NSA spent 25 million dollars on
software vulnerabilities they purchased
Oh days and vulnerabilities to you know
do their bidding we have a
responsibility as developers to stay off
of that menu right we we should just not
be part of that procurement process also
litigation is coming we have the FTC
which is forcing a company called
trendnet who had a vulnerability in some
camera software to suffer 20 years of
auditing we would love if somebody from
the government forced us to have to
audit our software right as developers
you would love that right that'd be
that'd be great so if we don't police
and handle our in our own community in
our own software that external force is
going to come it's going to come
eventually it's happened in other
industries so it's just something to
remember okay so enough doom and gloom
already should we give up hell no we
fight back we don't make this easy we
don't give in not every geek with a
Commodore 64 can hack into NASA so
something has to change right we have to
build a security first culture we have
to we just have to we just have to do
better and the thing is is that that
sorry I mentioned earlier we're
right well it's just it's a constantly
evolving process we just need to take
one step do better iterate so I'm going
to tell you about the story of and yet
and how I came to be at and yet and how
we handle security at and yet basically
how I was a seed crystal in and yet and
most people know that a seed crystal
will produce beautiful results given the
right environment and the right
sort of the right right growing
environment but it can't do its job
without that right environment given you
know even best efforts so I met Adam
brault at and yet about five years ago
and I was running a consultancy called
ingenuity and basically a single person
consultancy to two of us and he was
running a web development shop and we
realized very early on that it was a
very symbiotic relationship I could help
him grow and build his business and it
meant a business from for me as well
it's old contracts for him to have a
partnership with with security showing
that the level of care that they took in
security for their software was the
difference between many other very
larger and named vendors and so it
started there and so I would tell him
about you know hey you wrote this and
you did this you did this wrong right
all intensive purposes and so I taught
him so early on when I was him but as we
started to add people I was still this
external entity right and so as he added
people they write code and I'd review it
and as we moved along their people
eventually started learning hey we don't
have cross-site scripting
vulnerabilities as much as we review
code we've those have just sort of gone
away because we've we've learned about
that and and as he grew from you know
one to two to ten to now say 23 people
at some point I sold ingenuity and
actually went to work for and yet we
actually emerged the security practice
in right into the company and that's
where I had a really interesting
revelation I i I'm part of the company
now I can do more impact because I'm
internal right so secure all the things
I thought and yeah it doesn't work like
that you can't just come in and say
we're going to do this this this this
this this it just doesn't it doesn't
work like that I really learned that
you have to take steps one at a time and
just iterate and do better and increment
or for a short period of time you're
going to see it you're going to see an
improvement but then it's going to it's
going to die your people are going to go
back to their old habits and there's
huge push back to all the things that I
wanted to do and we're still a couple
years later starting two imps continuing
to implement on that initial vision
we've had and so it's been it's been a
slow iterating process so the one
interesting about education which I'm
going to go to this a little bit later
so why do we avoid during during dirt
avoid security why do we avoid doing it
one why was I getting a you know push
back on securing all the things and
things like that one of the big things
is ignorance we don't know we don't know
we also don't like to have things
pointed out when we do them wrong it's
it's it's the sonic it's not a good
feeling in any way we also procrastinate
it's it's way easier to procrastinate
and put off this adding those features
because it's really cool building the
new hotness right rather than figuring
out how to actually secure the new
hotness it's not you know it's not
particularly exciting work and it's not
rewarded it's sort of the inverse we get
we get shamed when something goes bad
but if it's working right and fine
things just move along it's not a
problem until it's a problem it's
there's a there's a good analogy Adam
was telling me about you know the people
who produced the sound for events like
this if my audio was just to cut out and
not work right or feedback or whatever
there's quick blame to go to the sound
to the sound person but if it works
flawlessly it just works no one's going
to go give that guy a high-five that it
worked great it doesn't so when it when
it goes wrong it just it goes wrong it's
just not glamorous so one way to combat
ignorance is through education
right we need you know which need to
sort of understand vulnerabilities and
this is where I welcome you to the
security community please wipe your feet
so as we learn about the things that we
learn we pass them on and just like that
seed crystal our community grows and
when I talk to developers I often get
asked about you know what is the new
scary what's what's what does the
security community know that that I
don't know and that I should fix in my
app and and I'm going to tell you the
simple stuff still works it still works
from years and years and years and years
ago when we found these vulnerabilities
and the information has been out there
we continue to go along this mobius
strip of development moving ahead and we
were not learning from our past mistakes
we're just not doing it there's some
other things there too while I have you
captive we're going to sort of talk
about a few things that devs fine fine
scary well let's talk about a few sort
of tangible things i pulled my twitter
feed and asked developers what they
cared about security wise and what they
found scary and difficult to implement
things that they thought that they were
going to screw up implementing and those
two things fell on the top validation
sanitization and crypto right my quest
already talked to you about content
injections so I'm not going to do that
and you know about the ways to validate
and sanitize your data you know properly
in content security policy in those
things and Martine talked about crypto a
bit if you want to learn more I think
you mentioned this the motto sano has a
crypto challenge where you can learn
about building crypto systems and
breaking them I really recommend going
through those as a developer will level
up your game quite a bit when it comes
to crypto martine also suggested before
the talk that i mentioned the core
is on by Dan Bona Bona Bona on Krypto
there's a there's a crypt of course it
will blow your mind but it's a short
course and it's worth it so I'm not
going to talk about those things I'm
going to talk about something that I'm a
bit more familiar with it that is
JavaScript related it is not note conf I
realized but it is jas related all the
same and it is npm we're using NPM to
install a lot of things client-side code
server-side code all the modules right
there's 40,000 plus modules out there
and the node security project is working
on auditing those things and that came
we started the project because we're
trying to secure a product our product
and bang it's built on node and we were
finding ways to compromise the product
we felt we had the car codebase really
solid but we had one interesting thing
we had we had code injection a bunch of
people in this room were writing code
for our product right and they were
injecting it into our app and I was you
know basically trusting that that code
was was good so it's looking for ways on
how I could inject code into other
developers projects right how what what
exists for vulnerabilities are so come
along NPM install CoffeeScript is this
right no this is not right it's NPM
install coffee dash script and there's a
number of developers out there that hate
me for publishing the module so I
actually took it down please don't put
it up please do not put it back up I
mentioning this here and now because
this is a problem we are a smart
community everyone here is much smarter
than I am in terms of solving some of
these problems we need to address this
so what I did was I took the top 100
modules and I did a typo analysis of
those and then I did a passive analysis
on all the NPM blogs which the project
was gracious enough to give me so I
didn't have to publish all of these
modules and see what happened
and a lot of things bubble to the
surface package names with punctuation
dashes periods things like that get
misspelled way more often than other
things but it's an interest it's a
really interesting attack surface is a
really big problem so when I publish
CoffeeScript it got 200 installs roughly
in about a week and it took that long to
be discovered it did nothing it was
blank it had to read me if I hadn't
mimic the behavior of coffeescript
chances are it would have taken a lot
longer to to be identified so there
there's my random scary for the for
the talk so what else process right so
we go back to the the hey we can't make
one hundred percent secure software it's
going to be processed it's going to
exist and we're going to do it forever
what you can't do though is you can't
just shove process down in the face of
developers and expect them to abide by
your your law of security in your
organization it doesn't work I tried to
do that and yet and they basically said
right we don't we don't love strict
processes we work in in much different
ways and I'm sort of being vague 'insahn
this because you need to find out what
your processes for your team it's going
to differ a lot for each team so let's
see one other thing is that we can take
it we can taken a lesson from attackers
here and that we have a really
interesting position inside of our
organization inside of our communities
and that's that's a position that
attackers would love to be in insider
threat we can sort of turn that on its
head right we're in a position where we
can effect change we can actually
influence and we can just change the
process it's it's not immutable it's
like code your habits your education
there they're not mutable we can change
them so
we need to wean do that we need to take
and change what your which how you're
approaching things and integrate
security and every basically every
aspect of the organization and do so
from you know if management doesn't care
well there's there's ways to help
influence that just doing it and and
just sort of take over community bridge
all the world's so I want you to read a
blog post by Adam brawl has published a
few days ago from some discussions in
topics at that happen at node conf and
it talks about how to be a good
community member in terms of other
development communities pointing and
laughing and shaming we're we're really
good at that in the security community
we're really good at pointing and
laughing at all the code you write the
things that you do and we you know we
don't pull any punches right we
basically that that's what we're good at
and I used to think of myself not as a
not as a dev and earlier this year so I
used to think of myself just as a
security person trying to help
developers and I dropped out on the
floor earlier I dropped that trope
earlier and said ok I'm going to accept
that I'm a developer and I'm that I
belong in both communities I dropped
that rope and now I'm just a bad dev I'm
just not like the code I right of
but I'm embracing that role which as
soon as I embrace that role I can get
better I realize that this is my
responsibility to learn how to do these
things better and I'm wondering if it's
not time for developers to drop the
trope that they aren't a little bit of
security people or any other fringe
community that might be related to
development that maybe you should be
involved a little bit more in that and
say well well i'm a bad security person
i can get better one thin I realized why
devs don't join the security community
is because we can be very abrasive in
crass and it's an unappealing place
right we're not
necessary that kind but we can combat
that come in numbers you know it'll be
good the last thing that I want to plug
sort of out of the blue something random
and what I think that we all should do
is we should put security down md files
in our projects it helps explain how you
want vulnerabilities disclosed in your
projects it helps communicate the
security constraints around your
projects it tells how the constraints on
which your project was designed
communicate the things about security in
this file maybe it's just an email
address i want vulnerabilities disclosed
here i want you to tell me here and give
people a process if you want a good
example JSE's they've got a fantastic
disclosure process it is a model for how
we think how we should be doing things
with with other JavaScript related
projects so I've got homework if you've
got nothing I want out of this at all do
this go to 0 asp look at the top 10
learn about one type of vulnerability I
don't care what it is hopefully it's
something related to something that
you're working on audit some of your
code dig in if you don't understand it
jump into some security communities IRC
channels try to interact and learn about
that figure out how you can fix that
vulnerability and then teach somebody on
your team about what you did just show
them over lunch that's going to take
you're going to be that seed crystal
that's going to start forming and start
changing this community and I've got
some homework for you now so I'm going
to finish up about five minutes early
you've got some comfort to do I want you
to take lunch as an opportunity to talk
to each other about what you do in terms
of security some good questions are how
do you handle security on your projects
and if the answer is I don't come talk
to me or find somebody else bring
somebody else in and talk about it
what's a vulnerability that you've had
in your
what's a bug that's affected security
and how have you addressed it tell those
stories talk to each other and that will
have an immediate and it will have a
lasting impact on our community thank
you