alright and weston y'all yes thank you
for making it out today I'm just going
to do a quick overview of authentication
and happy and what it takes to
authenticate users and protect your
resources so first slides will be
available on my github page and i also
have examples of the happy jas supported
plugins that are available in that
repository with authentication and happy
it starts with an object that every
server has that objects going to have to
registration methods ones for schemes
ones for strategies there's a method for
testing your strategy against the
request and then there is a method for
setting a default strategy first couple
points about schemes it's just a plan to
determine how a user is authenticated um
are you looking for specific headers are
you looking for a cookie or some other
way when you write a scheme it's going
to make a call to server off scheme but
most of us aren't going to have to worry
about that because there are plenty of
plugins that do this happy Jas has for
specific types of schemes that it
supports there's a basic authentication
which is just HTTP basic authentication
there's a an RFC out there with some
specific headers that you're going to
pass back and forth that are going to
determine whether the user is
authenticated I'll be stepping through
at the end of this presentation of some
specific examples of how to actually
implement these plugins happy off cookie
is a the plug-in which will use a cookie
to determine whether a user is
authenticated just the presence of that
cookie and it being valid will determine
if that user is authenticated bail is a
plug-in for third-party authentication
so if you want to use OAuth and you want
to have password list authentication let
users log in with Facebook Twitter
github and such and then happy off hawk
is a plug-in which allows you to specify
an authorization header and it's
probably more designed for different
applications to authenticate with one
another not necessarily authenticating
specific users hopefully we'll have
enough time to get through all the
different examples but with schemes it's
already been done for you you're going
to spend most of your time configuring
an authentication strategy so when you
are configuring that authentication
strategy you're going to give it a name
you're going to reference the scheme
that you're using you're going to be
able to specify a mode it's not required
you have a couple options there the
default is true you can set it to false
which will be equivalent to optional and
try I'm not sure if that's the case
actually I'm sorry but true and required
are the same optional and try are the
same with optional and try you don't
have to be authenticated in order for
your handler to reply you could do that
on your landing page if you want to have
mixed content and then each
authentication scheme is going to have
some very specific options that you
would specify when you're creating the
strategy with the different plugins they
each have their own name which are all
pretty straightforward with hawk it
actually registers two different schemes
depending on which flavor of
authentication you want to roll out so
after you have chosen an authentication
scheme after you've specified the
strategy that you want to use you're
going to want to have to secure your
routes you'll be spending a considerable
amount of time doing this so we're just
going to step through some of the
different ways that you can add the
authentication to your route this is the
basic idea in your config option
specify the name of your strategy and
that's you know the long and the short
of it not much more to talk about but
you do have the option to specify a
default strategy instead of going
through each individual route and
securing it so if you specify the
default strategy now all of your routes
are going to be using that strategy
however you may want to override some of
those settings or actually excuse me the
default strategy can actually take on a
couple different options but you may
want to override that so if you specify
the default you can go into individual
routes and you can turn off
authentication if you set off the false
you could change the mode or any other
configurable setting so that's pretty
much it actually implementing it like I
said these examples are all available in
this repository but implementing it is
not too much work you're going to load
the plug-in that you're going to want to
use as long as well with happy Oh with
basic auth you need to have some place
where you're snoring username and
passwords and then you're going to
create a function which will compare the
username and passwords with database
you're going to receive from the request
a username and a password and then
you're going to compare them and
determine whether that user is valid if
the user is valid let me just step
through this real quick so the
validation function takes a username and
a password and a call back in the
signature and you compare the user and
the password determine if it's valid and
then you specify a object known as
credentials which will be available
later on in your request through request
off that credential you can store any
information you want in there in this
example we just store the name then you
call the callback with an error
you specify whether the user is or is
not valid and you pass along the
credentials object um when you're
setting up your server you're going to
specify your different handlers you'll
have a public handle or you'll have
private handlers or whatever it is that
you happen to have in your application
create a server you register the plug-in
and you specify your off Val your auth
options for basic auth it's just the
validation function and with that
particular object validation function
then you call server da thought strategy
give your strategy a name specify the
scheme and the auth options then within
your routes you have your public route
which doesn't specify any authentication
you have your private route which you do
specify basic off um and that's it if
you were to go to the private page your
browser's going to prompt you for
username and password all browsers
support basic authentication with cookie
off a couple things change in this as I
step through this this is just going to
be highlighting the differences to get
from basic off to cookie off um we're
going to load the off cookie plugin
we're going to load joy as well because
we're going to actually have to accept
the username and the password through a
request so the validation function that
we use previously now becomes a handler
and the username in the password will be
found in the payload will step through
and compare the username and password
the same way we did previously if the
user is not valid we're going to
redirect them to the login page and if
they are valid we're going to get past
that point we'll set the credentials and
then we're going to set a session the
cookie that gets stored on the user
system will contain
everything that's within that object
credentials by setting a request off
session dot set which is specific to
cookie off the the session property and
then we'll just return reply the users
logged in this is just a handler for
serving up our HTML and when a user logs
out we just need to clear the cookie and
you can accomplish that with request off
session clear so now once we've started
up our server or excuse me once we've
created our server we're going to
register the off plug in the auth cookie
plugin and then we're going to specify
the different options for cookie off
which would be a password to encrypt the
cookie um the name of the cookie that
will be visible to anybody who's trying
to hack your system up a redirect page
so that whenever somebody does hit a
resource that is supposed to be private
it'll redirect them to that page and
then the is secure flag which doesn't
change anything anymore and I'm not sure
exactly what it used to change so um and
then we register the strategy the same
way you would any other strategy passing
those new options with our new login
page we need to specify a route log out
page needs a route and then our post to
the login page we're going to validate
the payload that should look straight
forward at some point and that's pretty
much it for cookie off once you have
implemented cookie off you can
incorporate that with third-party
authentication using bail
Bell has support for pretty much every
popular social network that you might
want to use to authenticate users all
the last slide and this stack will
highlight that but to get started you
include the bell plugin you include
happy auth cookie now we're going to
include happy off cookie as well because
with bell you need to use OAuth you need
to have a series of requests and
responses which will happen every single
time you try to authenticate the user
that's not going to maintain any type of
state so what we're going to do is
specify on our login page bell
authentication and when we validate the
user we're going to set a cookie and
then every other page will use the auth
cookie in order to know that the user is
validated if the user isn't validated
then you bounce them back to the the
page that uses though so now our login
handler will check to see if the user is
authenticated um if they're not then or
excuse me if they are authenticated
we're going to set the cookie and we
register both plugins off cookie and
bell and when we create the strategy for
cookie auth it's the same as what we
kind of hit on before and then with bell
if you're not familiar with OAuth um
you're going to have to go to the
provider that you're looking to work
with they'll have a developer program or
some type of option to get the client ID
and get the client secret um you specify
the provider you specify a password to
encrypt your third party off cookie and
then you specify the client settings you
register your strategy and then
this is just how you would go through
with github under your settings there is
an applications link you click on that
you have the option to register a new
application and when you register it
provides you with a client ID and a
client secret which you'll use when you
configure your authentication strategy
so when we're setting up our routes are
private handler our private page we're
going to use the auth cookie but on our
login page we're going to use the third
party off that we set up and that's uh
you know pretty much it you can see the
support for all the different social
networks and and others um now with
Belle you're not forced to use these
providers this is just what there's
existing support for the api api allows
for you to roll out any provider you
would like as long as it's with a
one-point OA or two um the last type of
authentication that we have from happy
Jas has it's called hawk it's for
passing tokens back and forth um what
we're going to hit on in a couple slides
you actually are going to need to roll
your own client that's going to use hawk
um but for using with your happy server
it's the same straightforward process
where you load the plug-in you need to
store the credentials somewhere this is
what a hawk credential would look like
with you have an ID you have a key and
an algorithm that you need to specify
and the options for that scheme require
you to have a function which will get
the credentials you pass that back to
the callback which will take care of
actually validating the credentials um
and this is excuse me I'm sorry so you
would have some type of resource that
you're protecting and you'll reference
that strategy
um and then you would have a client that
needs to go out and make a request to
that strategy so this is an example
using wreck you see we specify hawk um
which is not a happy j/s module it's
actually just under errands uh github or
npm but what that library will do is
allow you to generate a header that
header will then be passed in through
your request you need to pass the same
type of credential that you'd have on
the server side where it takes the ID
the key in the algorithm and then you
create that header using the URL the
method that you're using and the
credential options and then when you
generate your request you specify that
specific authentication header and then
the supported model will take care of