yeah here to introduce you to unify
unifiers nice little framework we have
created and I first must say that I'm
really happy to be here because it's a
pretty complicated thing to release open
source software and such a big company
I'm I'm really really happy that we have
worked it out finally so it was quite a
process about half a year of work maybe
but finally it's it's done and I'm
really happy to share it with you today
so some words about me I'm software
developer at Deutsche Telekom in yeah
near Frankfurt a city called darmstadt
and I will lead developer and initiator
of the unified framework some of you may
know me from cooks too which was a
framework I worked previously on so one
thing we had at our company is the
issues that we need to create mobile
applications and mobile applications for
a lot of different platforms so we have
some kind of fragmentation issue and I
think as many of you might already know
about it because there's so many
different systems and nearly every
system has another programming language
and technology on it so you can't easily
port one application from one platform
to another platform and even if it's not
yet sure how the market with your
continued to evolve we finally see that
there will be more of them than one
platform this is really sure for the
moment so but there's one major contrast
which is really interesting that you
have a more operating system and more
system fragmentation in the future but
WebKit is an web engine which is seen on
more and more smartphone platforms which
is really quite cool because there seems
to be some some joint venture going to
WebKit where all the major windows are
too so our idea was to use web
technologies I like many people use them
as well together as html5 css3 and
JavaScript and build a unified
cross-platform environment to develop
applications so ideas to basically have
one code base which is deploy to
application stores like the itunes store
or to a typical web browser where you
can have a mobile web browser on a
smartphone or just a desktop web browser
or even have a widget on your desktop
using technologies like adobe air or
titanium or such things the benefits are
easy to list so basically we are talking
about reduced costs and we are a lot
faster so we basically improve our time
to market it's really marketing sling
here but okay yeah we have the right
platform support because web is
basically supported everywhere at the
moment and yes huge number of developers
at conferences like Jays convert seems
to even be increasing every year so it
seems to be really a new focus area at
the moment so and the technology is
quickly improving one goal which is
maybe different from other solutions we
have seen or might now already is that
our goal is to create real application
fear not just a better mobile website or
something like this so we really have a
zing which we try to solve is that we
have some kind of product manager at our
company which simply say yeah it's
pretty cool when you are more efficient
but it's not so cool if it looks not
like a native application so it will in
so really after this year to have the
same level of user experience on our
applications like on
native developed applications so this is
basically a quite challenging task one
thing for sure is that we might that we
make a massive use of JavaScript so we
created with interfaces and stuff
completely out of JavaScript directly on
the client to make this all possible we
basically have pretty strong
requirements thing is that this hardware
stuff is really improving year-over-year
so basically any moment it seems that
some of the stuff is only for as a top
notch of smartphones but in a year later
so on we really have a lot of devices
which are in the area to be supported by
this technology we are currently
regarding smartphones we are currently
only supporting touch screens yeah Wiz
do a three inch screen resolution and
here in something like this and we
really require a go to html5 and css3
support so oh it internet explorer's or
something like this it's really nothing
we can be care about this is ok because
the most applications we ask it for item
moment for iPhone and Android so this is
really the market most product managers
are looking at the moment so we are
increasing our platform support in next
month's but for the moment this is what
most product manager assets for so let's
give a small overview of the features
one thing is that we want to have a
professional workflow which basically
means that we want to bring JavaScript
some kind of professional development
style where you have fully
object-oriented to totally event-driven
all the stuff and you really can develop
your applications and your local browser
which is pretty efficient
compared to doing it on the smartphone
every time and have with the requirement
to push it to the simulators or
emulators every time we have built an
generic HTTP proxy witches used to
bridge the cross domain limitations for
some generic services like Twitter and
so on so we can basically talk to these
external services even if the
application runs on the local browser
which is quite limited sometimes and one
thing which it's really nice as well as
that we have worked on automating these
native rappers so basically you have
heard about phonegap already and they
created a built for gap com platform
where you can upload a zip file and just
build a phonegap na bit version of your
web application something like this was
our original ideas well we are not as
far as them at the moment I think I'm
not sure but we have at least some kind
of preparations for these native
applications so you basically write your
web app tested in safari on your own
machine and then just say generate me an
Xcode project out of it something like
this regarding the UI interface I said
that we have idea that we really need to
bring native feeling to the to the
smartphone so we don't try to be some
kind of better website so what we
basically have is that we in unify we've
created a lot of components or controls
which are optimized for smartphones and
touchscreen usage which perfectly try to
emulate the native stuff we found on
iphone and android and so on things like
animations and destroy view things
might have seen other where I on lips
like sprout car and Yui as well also
included and here full support for touch
events is just one thing as well one
thing we have also built in as a will
navigation stuff on most smartphones you
basically have a layered approach where
you a go deeper and navigate back then
so each time only one layer is visible
and you just drive down and up and
something like this this is completely
automated and you basically only right
links to other sub views the world
system makes use of the browser location
so basically all the stuff behind the
hash we have the will and irrigation
structure supported to behold in the
browser location so basically we can
store this will information in some kind
of local storage so at restarting the
application we basically just go to the
original location yeah one thing also
included is some kind of data handling
where you have some automated
client-side caching integrated
accelerator Jason converter oil stuff
which really improves a usability and
efficiency of the developer and we
unifies basically some kind of
integration project where we use a lot
of existing components so we thought
about that the application developer
basically should not need a lot about
the infrastructure needed to create the
native applications so basically there's
an Xcode project skeleton and an Android
project skeleton which you can basically
just use and create your own application
from there's also a lot of tooling
integrated so some kind of automatic
dependency detection and stuff and you
can really optimize for each platform so
and your final code for Android
basically has no information about
iphone stuff it's it's really compiled
out so there's the world code from other
platforms is completely removed in
removed in one of the distant of the
office of the target builds we have some
some pretty amazing CSS tooling built in
modular turns us later and here and you
really have application API viewers and
unit testing stuff also integrated so
basically you have the world stuff
offered by components we are using so
let's have a look at the foundation one
thing we headed SN requirement was that
all of my bosses said that we shouldn't
really start from scratch everywhere so
basically we looked out what we can use
and what makes sense for us so basically
at the moment we say cook stew is a
brilliant JavaScript framework for these
things like tooling and such stuff but
is a but at the moment it's quite
optimized for the desktop so there's not
a lot of mobile stuff but still it's a
good foundation then we thought adobe
air might be a good solution to bring
applications to the desktop phonegap is
good solution to bring applications to
mobile devices at the moment so you can
deploy your web application as a native
application to android and iphone ends
us i'm not sure how many people know
about it it's some kind of improved CSS
where you basically have a preprocessor
for CSS which allows you to have
includes mix and all this kind of stuff
which is really amazing which really
feared some kind of 20 years ahead of
something you write at a moment so just
have a small peek on the road map of
unify at the moment we are at
10 so basically we at the moment support
three platforms which is iphone OS or
iOS android and webos and these are the
three platforms currently supported for
smartphones we also support Windows
Linux Mac for the desktop part and we
really plan to support more platforms in
next year so a blackberry or 66 really
seems like a nice upgrade from the guys
at rim as it really brings web
applications to the same level as native
applications with the same API access
and stuff and regarding these nokia
platforms really hopes they get their
cutie based web runtime ready so we can
build up on this and have access to the
native stuff as well for windows phone i
really hope they bring ie9 as fast as
possible to the mobile stuff and Windows
Phone it really seems to be a decent
phone but yes bras I the moment is not
as good as it should be so I really hope
yeah with the success of i90 bring it to
the Windows Phone platform so one thing
we have is that we will sing is
published as MIT and do a license with
apache version 2 we thought about what
license to choose apache seems to be
quite preferred by google at the moment
and MIT is basically used by yeah a lot
of JavaScript projects at the moment so
basically every stuff I see it edge it
up at the moment seems to be MIT so the
best solution for us might be to just go
MIT as well so you can basically just
copy it to your stuff or
ya ever look at it and keep inspired by
it so one thing you have made seen is
that we have some some flyers around
here and yeah singers basically it's
nothing of this regarding coat is at a
moment public so it's just in internal
repository at the moment so basically I
thought it might be a good idea to bring
it live today so edgy top we had a
moment have a private repository Freddie
decent platform for source development i
know i think you know about it so i will
take the switch now to make it public i
hope this works so never done this
before so if all worked well then you
should now have access to jet hub com
unify / unify unifies our github name
and unifies also the project name you'll
find a little bit of other code as well
there so we have some Fox of a phonegap
for example where we have some minor
things added or fixed for our project
and we also have a fork of cooks too
which just contains a few things more or
less and so original one and here you
might have a look here as well and just
give you just give you a little peek on
how such applications look like you
might have a look at our video on the
homepage we basically I thought it might
be a good idea to start it here as well
so you might have a look this was one
application we created for the soccer
championship something like this in the
last year so it's not a really recent
version of unify but
you get an impression what it's done
yeah what's possible with this
frameworks I'm not sure how well it's
seen there so it's pretty pretty dark
style yeah this is a custom-made your
scissors elastic scroll views and other
stuff and basically the real component
system and yeah so you have segmentation
controls and such things so you have
basically the typical iphone like
navigation but you also have as with
animation stuff and you can click around
in these applications and straw it's for
them one thing which is really automated
here is the will sing like data loading
and stuff so basically if you start the
application again you basically started
same position as you were as you left it
even if there's some dynamic data
involved so basically every information
is kept in local storage and so on so
yeah you might get some further
information on our rent mini new
homepage it's at the moment it's still a
redirect to some github page which is
pretty easy to create and so we are not
sure how how long it will be hosted
there but for the moment just enter
unified project arc or just go directly
to the jetta page and get an impression
about what we have done so far yeah so
i'm basically done with my presentation
are there any questions yep
yep
not really i'm singers at deutsche
telekom is a pretty huge company we
basically have a lot of separate
divisions there says one part which is
t-mobile which is also known in the US
and so on and they basically decide what
handset say bye or create contracts with
our stuff is basically from the App
interest so we have also a few portraits
which are key in Germany available so
like emo Scout or such things and these
are asking us for applications and this
is a completely different story so this
is not really involved with the handset
stuff so it's really a separate seeing
where we just look how to make
applications for the most prominent or
successful other platforms we already
own so it's it's not that connected to
each other
and no no no and we have some internal
software development and it's completely
a separate thing but it's closed for the
company only it's not available for
contracting and such things so yeah any
other questions
so
and since that it's a huge movement at
the moment so basically every framework
which is already existing like sentra
maybe this yes origins in X J's and some
some frameworks like sprout car also
support touch strings and cooks itself
also improves as well so I'm not sure
how this will evolve in the future and
there are some different EDL's for sure
so basically jQuery Mobile has really
the idea of supporting a broad range of
devices while unify basically only tries
to bring native look and feel to the
devices which have power to support this
so basically we are not trying to
support Sumi NSA s60 at the moment so
basically it's just not powerful enough
and we have communicated this internally
already so basically our ideas to really
bring native like applications to the
smartphones because this is what our
product managers asked for and this
might be different and some other
solutions out there and we really try to
have pixel perfect iphone style
applications nothing where something is
offset or something like this it should
really look like a native applications
and feels like a native application as
well