my name is andreas scholl I live in
California and a mozilla chief
technology officer
I'm responsible for missoula's
technology roadmap and overall all the
technologies that we do at Mozilla
missoula is the place that really gave
birth to javascript through been denied
or former CTO who invented a JavaScript
language if you look at the history of
JavaScript over the last many years it's
still the case that essentially with
every year the new tools and the new
technology is available in JavaScript
and through JavaScript are accelerating
there's more more things we can do with
JavaScript and we are also seeing a very
healthy addition of new language
features sue sanitization and we're very
excited about that I've not been in more
size before so this is actually my first
time en w'en Osiris and also in
Argentina I've traveled to pretty much
every part of Latin America except
Argentina because missoula has been
launching since last year Firefox OS all
over Latin America and in Argentina is
the last place where we launch Firefox
OS so I was didn't have the opportunity
so far to come here but I'm very happy
that I finally had the chance to do so
yesterday I had for the first time the
opportunity to eat steak here in
Argentina so I had steak in Brazil and
here in Argentina but I only tried one
restaurant so I think I have to try a
couple more before I can decide where it
is better I talked here about j2me jas
which is a java virtual machine written
in JavaScript we're using this Java VM
to run feature phone applications on
firefox OS I think it's great I have
attended quite a few JS comps in the
past before even though it's the first
time for me in Argentina but it's really
great there's a lot of people and a lot
of very interesting talks and I'm
particularly excited that I get to give
a keynote together with Brendan so that
that's a very special occasion we have
never done that before that we are
basically back-to-back keynotes between