hi I'm Rachel I'm oh ho everywhere on
the Internet ask me what it means later
and the answer is nothing but I'll
explain it um so yeah I am going to tell
you so many things about me from when I
started developing and all the horrible
things that I've done on the internet to
people and that I've had done to me so
it should be fun and we're going to
start at the beginning and hopefully
some of you will recognize some of the
stuff that I'm talking about if not
sorry uh so yeah I've always been kind
of weird um I started getting into
computers and when I was like three or
four through video games um does anybody
know what this is oh yeah so this is a
video game system that got put out in
1988 by vtec it is an educational
learning system and it's called Socrates
and it would teach you how to do like
CAD like stuff so you could draw and you
could do interior design and you could
do like it was really cool especially
for like a four-year-old and yeah so
this was my first video game system /
computer and so it pretty much all went
downhill from this moment there's some
more weird stuff so AOL was pretty much
the start of when I made websites and
got involved in online communities I
used to take place in if you know what
muds are so like text based rpgs don't
clap yet they were for professional
wrestling
so I was on a hoe well I was really into
wrestling and I would like I was in like
email groups where we would have matches
and we would like right stuff and do
that and when i was on a while i got my
first taste of any kind of development
or i'll say development i'll say bad
things you'll know if you recognize the
next slide oh wait no that's me that's
me and my stepsister on the computer on
AOL which i would also like to mention
my parents put a password on so that
they wouldn't let me on the computer so
i put a keylogger on it to get the
password so i could go on when i went
there so this is familiar to you your
parents probably hate you and everybody
on a wall probably hates you so our AOL
account was controlled by my dad and so
he had the main like parental account if
you did anything to violate a ltos as
like a child account it would go to him
so these are all AOL where's or Prague's
whatever you want to call them and they
were the lamest hacking that you could
possibly do and it was just basically a
big annoyance to people my favorite one
was to spam chat rooms with like porn
links and then if people clicked on it
it would cut them off from AOL and like
mess with their dial-up and they would
have to get right back on um so I
recently I recently told my dad maybe a
couple months ago hey Dad remember how
you used to get all those emails and it
was like your Europe whatever my email
or whatever my AOL account was has been
posting spam links I was like we must
have gotten hacked I don't know how that
could possibly happen i'm a perfect
angel i would never do that and i told
him that it was me and he was like
Rachel that's not funny at all I still
think it's pretty hilarious and then I
found this great site uh this site's
been around for over 10 years maybe way
way more than 10 years uh it's where I
learned how to do HTML see
ss I say gifs and I will not apologize
right you can hate me and may just do
like fun stuff we had to get like stars
trailing behind your cursors and stuff
like that and this is pretty much what
got me into making fan sites I also made
fan sites for wrestlers but then I
started getting into pop punk and so I
found these girls that lived here in
California they had pressed contacts so
they have like PR people for bands and
they were like you know how to make
websites so let's make a website
together and I'm like 14-15 at this
point and so we made a fan site for
teens for people that like music and we
would contact the band's PR people and
be like we want to come interview you so
the first concert that I ever went to
was warped tour when I was like 14 years
old with a VIP press pass to interview
good charlotte and i was in Florida at
the time and I'm a very pale person and
I didn't think to put sunblock on so I
got like a third-degree sunburn and my
face was blistered and then I had to go
interview them looking like Freddy
Krueger pretty much mrs. uh one of the
site's December first two thousand one
that's New Found Glory um some other
interviews that they had was lit Slayer
injected sum 41 good charlotte bad
religion flickr stick who's that band
that one like the vh1 got tons of other
people um uh everybody that i was
friends with online thought i was like
the coolest person ever and everybody
high school really hated me um they they
thought I was a groupie apparently
because 14 year olds do that and this
was my own personal site so after those
girls tried to get a little bossy and
they wouldn't give me the good bands
they like wanted me to they wanted me to
interview really bad stuff so then I
made my own and this is from archive.org
which is why there's broken images it
wasn't cashed well enough but the whole
left side is little Elsa gifts gifts
that move a little bit and
started doing my own interviews and
getting sponsorships and I'm from Long
Island even though I grew up in Florida
so I interviewed like taking back sunday
and brand new when they were just
getting started so it's really weird to
me how big they are now so from here is
when I really started doing stuff on my
own I don't remember what order the
slicer and so we'll just see what
happens oh there's me and sum 41 so I
started meeting people online through
making the fan sites and the website for
bands and then I started moderating
message boards and the way that the
communities work then is sort of similar
to how they were now but they were much
smaller and you had to seek them out it
wasn't as easy to like find things and
so I ended up moderating message boards
for like the starting line and I was the
leader of the brand new street team for
all the street the state of Florida and
then I made friends with people that ran
street teams so I would enter contests
to win things which means they would
just give them to me for free um oh
that's me an else know if you like
wrestling you you get that oh so this is
one of the contests that i won this is a
video I don't know honey oh oh there's
steve-o from jackass how do I get this
to play whatever it's a video of them
thanking me for getting them on TRL I
didn't do steve-o from jackass oh
so then we're going to get to live
journal I'm friends with people that I
met on livejournal in 2002 that I still
talk to you today there's some people
than friends with that actually live in
the bay area that I haven't met yet that
I'm going to meet this weekend and it's
really weird to me um I was a part of
this is oh this is the one this is a
livejournal community that I made that
has over 6,000 numbers we're not going
to talk about what it is because it's
embarrassing but there was a lot of
people in it and I was in charge of it
this is the
first big community that I was a part of
online where it was it was easy to find
it was called indie it was a place
where people could go online and like
fine indie music and talk about bands
and it was before pitchfork so we
weren't that douchey except to each
other and yeah actually there's a
there's a really big gossip community
website called oh no they did it and
that is run by members of indie folks
and yeah a lot of people did stuff from
there also IRC I used to go into
channels on ethnic for like punk and use
xdcc box because that was the best way
to get music if you don't know what it
is it would take a RAR file and split it
up into a ton bunch of tiny smaller
files you could get it really fast and
this was like the best way to get music
before like soulseek or any like
peer-to-peer type stuff was happening um
I also met a ton of people that I'm
still friends with today on IRC
including one of my friends who was like
now the head of some like team at
Salesforce but it's weird does anybody
know what this is yeah this is a blog
publishing software that was made in
November of 2000 by this guy named Noah
gray it's written in perl and there's no
database is all local storage every time
you write a post it would rewrite your
HTML files um and it was awesome this
was I started having my own domain names
I started designing stuff I started
writing my own blogs which i'm going to
show you what you're really embarrassing
so this is this is one of my vlogs um i
was really into julian casablancas i
guess it was on my own domain name and
if you can see like the names of people
here I'm still friends with all these
people today like this guy had a
Kickstarter for a watch that he made
that was then sold at moma and then this
girl lives in georgia and she came with
me to a comic-con and then this girl
ended up living in like the next town
over for me in high school we became
friends so the Internet's really weird
and here's another one of my
so I discovered grunge brushes and
really likes them grunge brushes and
like silk screen pixel fonts and it was
really cool Ellen this is a this is like
the last one that I had right before I
went to college as you can tell by the
hair and the pink and the daughters and
hardcore music and stuff that's an
iframe and yes so now I'm going to stop
because between then and now I've done a
lot of dumb stuff on the internet I like
to fight with people a lot
unapologetically only because it's fun I
guess so um everybody knows what
twitches right so before twitch was
twitch it was justin TV and justin TV
when it was in its beta i was one of the
first 20 people on it so i was like one
of the first life casters and I would
play wow and stream it so I guess I was
kind of one of the first people that did
twitch the problem was i Justine was
also on there and she's really cool and
really nice except were vastly different
people so everybody tried to get us to
fight I would have my email spoof to her
she would have her spoof to me people
like who is my domain names and called
me and like would fight and it was crazy
and so from that I now have this
wonderful encyclopedia dramatica article
about myself which is them calling me
mean names and the video which it's just
an image so I can't play it it's
basically me reading it and thinking
it's hilarious that somebody thought
this was important enough to write an
article about but um what oh god no
um yeah so I've always thought with
people that's me and Kevin Rose I was
really into diggnation and then since I
was really into diggnation after that
went away I got into Reddit and here's
another great story uh so I was banned
from reddit for daxing a guy uh I was
completely valid in doing it I'm I will
stand by that I like to post on a lot of
like makeup subreddits because makeup
and like nail polish is really fun and
this dude went out of his way to come
into the community isn't be like he
women are covering yourselves in slime
and he made like his own subreddit for
really young girls to post pictures
themselves without makeup on so this is
before violent acres in the whole child
porn thing if you know about that if not
google it and then feel disgusted and
take a shower so I noticed that he kept
on posting pictures from his own domain
name and I was like okay so I who was
his domain name and I found his name and
I google searched him and I thought he
was a 60 year old man which no 6 year
olds are cool but not when they're
harassing teenagers so i posted online
and then I got shadow bands and i was
living in st. Louis at the time which
has a really great hacker community in a
hacker space and so Alex Ohanian and the
other guy whose name I can't remember
but his moderator name is karma not came
to st. Louis to do a Q&A so I was like
I'll ask them why I'm banned for doing
something good so it was like me bunch
of guys couple women and during the Q&A
session I was like yeah hi um I was
being harassed and so I outed somebody
and now i'm banned why I don't think
that's I don't that's very you know
right and they were like okay okay we'll
unban you um they didn't and then the
violent a curse thing happens and one of
my good friends is a game journalist for
game ranks and he heard that the verge
was going to write a story about reddit
and about how like it's ridiculously
misogynistic and there's a bunch of
issues and they were like oh you should
talk to my friend Rachel because she is
this thing that happened and then I
heard that they were going to write the
story and then all of a sudden I was
miraculously unbanned because I guess
they didn't want it to get posted
see I don't post on Reddit anymore cuz
it's gross I would recommend that you
don't either but you can if you want uh
this is a this is what I've been doing
since then i'm currently a software
engineer at Adobe I work for behance.net
i'm on the javascript team i also have a
problem with buying domain names
whenever I think of them and I think
they're funny and I don't do anything
with them so this is cat party calm with
forces A's this is one true God calm
with zeros as O's these are my cats and