yeah I am going to talk a little bit
about the thing that sits here and my
own software and stuff but like I said
this morning I've been asked to do
something different I'm I'm not the best
human beatbox in the world as you can
imagine otherwise I wouldn't be a
software developer anymore because human
beatboxing is just so much more fun but
if you're interested in how this works
and what you can do yourself you can
follow along so this is going to be like
a very simple explanation I'm going to
show three fundamental sounds of human
beatboxing the first one is the bass
drum it goes a little bit like this this
is not it could be louder but that's
probably fine and if you want to follow
along and you want to try this yourself
you should probably stand up because
it's it's kind of hard to beat barks
while sitting so if you want to you want
to do that nice and so there are there
few fundamental ways how you can do a
bass drum and it's basically two
different types of yeah sounds you can
make the first one is a little bit like
try that and it sounds unimpressive but
that's because you don't have a
microphone like a lot of human
beatboxing relies on the fact that you
have a microphone and the microphone
responds in a specific way to the sound
waves that your lips make and it sounds
dull like that sounds like nothing but
if you have a microphone it will sound
more impressive and the other one is
actually a D so you could do something
like
and at some point at some point you need
to start breathing and then things go
wrong that's that's totally normal for
beginners as well the next one is a
snare clap rimshot kind of thing and the
original human beatbox people mostly did
like like and it's like and it sounds a
little bit like a synthesized snare of
sorts and yeah try that again now the
interesting thing is if you get into the
breathing rhythm thing you actually need
to learn how to do this backwards so by
not pushing out air but to breathe air
in and this is I I'm not really good at
this so you don't need to try this
because it's hard it goes a little
something like this
and I'm breathing in ear air while I'm
doing that so it helps with a breathing
rhythm now the second one is a a clap is
really hard to to do with a mouth it's
easier to just clap and that's and
that's because a clap is usually a
couple of impulses that come like in
random order like if you if you see how
drum synthesizes synthesize collapses
it's relatively complicated and so what
you can do is a rimshot which is the
sound when the drummer hits the rim of
the snare drum so the outer rim and a
and it it's a it's a very harsh sounds
look like and it's really just and and
that one you can also do backwards and
now we have two sounds and that's
already something right and the last one
is the high hat cymbal and that's really
easy it's really just
yeah that sounds right so if you want to
turn this into a simple rhythm there's a
really nice like a really nice way to
say which is just and like I said I
really suck at this so here's a couple
of names to Google of people who can do
it really really well just look at each
YouTube and look at these people doing
things so much better than what I can do
here
cool nice okay so why am i doing this so
last year's j/s conf EU in Berlin was
really special for me because I
participated in the call for artists and
I've been I've been doing weird stuff at
J's confit you for awhile I for some
reason even opened up J's confluence
with another musician doing my live
coding stuff that I was doing back in
the time and last year we did music
during the breaks we did the
introduction we did a lot of things and
after the conference ended I was invited
to join live j/s which is sort of a
music group collective of audio visual
artists and you can find out more at
live jazz the network there's also a
live jazz slack if you're interested in
audio-visual stuff it's a very helpful
like it's an open slack very helpful
people with all kinds of info on like
modern WebGL visualization stuff web
MIDI web audio all of that stuff yeah
this is a picture from like a screen
grab from a youtube video that exists
this is me in the front there and we
were doing the introduction of last
year's live Jay Jay s con few I can tell
you that was nerve-wracking it was a lot
of fun too so this is most of life Jay s
in one picture there
our current lineup Ruth Tim Martin who
was here yesterday I don't see him today
Sam Matt Meadows Mehta's our New Zealand
representative which sometimes makes
travel a little harder than it should be
yeah and like I said I joined last like
I said we played at a couple of
conferences Jays continue we are going
to play Jays count of Asia this year
which makes me super happy and also a
bit anxious because I'm flying to
Singapore we played at a s last year we
played a cold front I think two years
ago we played at were Jay s which was a
lot of fun great great conference
maybe we're going to do something again
could be and yeah so I needed to come up
with a tool that allows me to quickly
improvised music with my with my
synthesizers and my computer and I was
doing like I said I was doing music life
coding before which was fun but also way
too slow I'm a I'm a bad slow coder I
I'm not very good at memorizing all the
shortcuts and I wanted to have something
that was a little bit more intuitive and
quick for me and I wanted to yeah I
wanted to build this tool which would
have a couple of features quick
workflows means that I don't need to
kind of go through a lot of menus to do
stuff needs to be all kind of a Tibetan
press it should be pattern based which
is if you know more about music it
probably makes sense to you if not
patterns are basically very small pieces
of music that you repeat over and over
again
and that makes it really easy to
more complex stuff out of them it should
fully utilize the Ableton push which is
this weird thing sitting at the side
here I'm going to hold it up in a second
and ideally I wanted to have it so that
I don't need to look at a different
screen I don't want to want it to look
at the computer screen because it's easy
to get lost in a computer screen and
like if you need to start like moving
your mouse around especially on a touch
pad or something you're already lost in
terms of speed I wanted it to be
built-in with web technologies mostly
because the whole thing is called live
j/s and not live C++ or live rust even
though Matt does have a performance
system that is built on rust but I mean
he also did awesome stuff in JavaScript
so I think that still counts and I
didn't really want to have a huge build
pipeline but that's just me I don't like
to fiddle around with web hacker and
whatnot and you know with modern web
technologies so to speak you can
actually do things like use JavaScript
modules without having a build pipeline
which is pretty cool the Ableton push
tube from the top looks like this it's a
controller that has been Bill
purpose-built for a music software
you're going to see the music software
in a second as well but this is very
like it it is very special hardware for
that very special purpose
but fortunately Ableton was kind enough
to completely open up the specification
of this thing and even though it has
lots of buttons that are labeled in very
specific Ableton ways you can kind of
use them to your own avail and it has
this awesome collection of 64 buttons in
the middle which are velocity sensitive
so you can play them lighter and harder
and get different sounds out of it
lots of encoders on the top which is a
fancy name for knobs that you can turn
endlessly and lots of buttons as well
and yeah
there's also a touch strip which is
interesting so it's this piece of
plastic and you can slide your fingers
across and get different values
depending on where your finger sits lots
of LEDs every button has an LED below it
so you can turn it on turn it off I
don't know something like 60% or so our
RGB LEDs so you can turn them into
different colors as well which is cool
the other half is just white LEDs and it
has a display and we're going to see
that this is interesting because well
with the buttons pads and Coda's and
touch strips and LEDs you can actually
like all the input elements just send me
D I'm going to talk about media in a
second but it's it's like it's a really
simple protocol that is easy to
understand easy to work with and the
LEDs of the on the other hand you just
send MIDI data to the device and it's
gonna display different colors depending
on the values the display is too big and
too high resolution that you could do
something with Metis there so we need to
figure out what's going on there this is
the official description so you connect
the whole thing by USB and use B as a
so-called composite device with a media
interface and a generic bulk data
interface used to drive the display that
sounds fancy right generic bulk data
interface what so use B yes we can do as
we know many things
it's called Universal Serial bus for a
reason so you can have storage devices
you can have so-called human interface
devices as we heard in the talk from
Raman earlier yesterday so human
interface device the keyboard mice game
controllers whatever and then you have
things like audio so you can connect
something that isn't an audio card and
listen to some music you can do media
quite surprisingly and lots of other
stuff and then you can also do generic
data around a KA vendor-specific crap
MIDI like I said is a ver
simple protocol media the media or the
original media specification is from
1983 who in here is born after 1983
interesting I mean that sounds like I'm
trying to brag up here but to be honest
like in 1983 I wasn't thinking about
like doing stuff with computers and
synthesizers to be fair because it's
such an old standard it's it's a basic
serial protocol for the most part in
modern API is its encapsulated in a way
that you don't have to parse out the
data yourself so for example from web
MIDI will you will get something like
this which is three bytes that probably
don't mean too much to you so there's no
like high level tagging or anything it's
just you I mean I'm looking at this now
and I know exactly what it does but
that's because I I've been breathing
this stuff for far too long and my brain
is mush with media but let's take a look
so this is actually a command that for
example a keyboard would send if you
press down a key so the first command is
the first byte is a command bite and you
can tell that because the 8th bit of
that byte is set you've seen that right
so I mean the value is over 127
basically so yeah every other thing
you're sending like every data bit byte
you're sending is only like with the 8th
bit not set so it's going to be below
hundred 27 which also means that for
most things you can only send like 127
distinct values which is barely enough
for the for the note which is the second
byte oh yeah and the other thing so in
the the upper four bits of a command by
it encodes the actual command and the
lower four bits encode the channel so
there's sixteen channels you can send
data on
which was more interesting when there
were like no when there were like only
like one cable connection nowadays like
every synthesizer has own USB connection
and turns up as a their own MIDI device
and so it's not that needed anymore but
anyway you have 16 channels yeah and the
next one is the note and the note is a
MIDI note number is corresponds to a
note in the twelve in the standard
twelve tone system that we have in in
western music so zero would be a very
very low C and a thirty six because it's
12 24 36 values above that is also a C
because every 12 I usually get to see
again and then like a 1 would be a
c-sharp 2 would be a D and so on so if
you know a little bit about music it
makes sense to you if not I'm sorry I
guess and the last value is the velocity
and that's just how hard I hit the key
so 100 is pretty hard given that we have
127 values if I play like if I touch it
really lightly it will be a low value
and so you can send this byte sequence
to a synthesizer and it will start
playing a sound now the problem with
this is depending on the synthesizer it
might never stop playing that sound
because that's the different commands so
you would send 128 to actually switch
off the sound you that's one of the
things you learn quite early when you're
playing around with me because suddenly
you have this cacophony of sounds that
coming from your synthesizing and no
idea why so that's me D let's talk about
the generic bout data interface and this
was a fun little experiment so this is
all from like most of it is from from
the documentation from Ableton so what
you do is you have this generic bout
data interface and you use
a library called lip USB which there's a
node module for it and so you're sending
you just send bytes to it basically
almost like a serial interface I mean
which is not surprising USB use
universal serial bus yeah makes sense
make sense and so you send it a frame
header which is just a thing that tells
the device oh there's some data incoming
I should take a look at it and it's just
the same 16 bytes every time yeah and
then you sent the frame buffer which is
you know data to display on the on the
display and then you do that all over
again you do that 60 frames 60 times per
second so you get 60 frames per second
if you don't send any data
the device will cache it for about two
seconds or so and then the the display
would turn black the frame buffer data
is organized in a slightly weird way you
have 16 bit per pixel so it's not like
your usual 24 bit thing it's a little
bit less resolution in there makes it a
little easier to send raw data over and
it's packed in a kind of weird way so
you have something like 5 bits for blue
and then for 6 bits for green and then 5
bits for red and that probably makes
sense for some weird color psychology
you know color physic physical reason
whatever I have no idea but that's how
it works
it's little-endian that's something you
need to know when you're sending data
there's bigger than bytes and for
reasons that I do not completely
understand but I think have to do with
signal transfer over over the actual
wire you need to XOR it with a specific
value for signal shaping I think it's
just to prevent things like zero zero
zero zero for happening on the data bus
because that would be bad for the the
signal quality I think so yeah so we now
know what kind of data we need to send
but where do we get them from and I mean
we're web we're on a web conference web
related conference at least and so what
would be easier than using canvas so if
you have a canvas of a certain size why
does that there you go okay so if you
have something like a canvas that is a
960 by 160 you can do something like
context get image data and you will get
actual raw pixel data from the formula
canvas which is really cool you have to
know in which way they are organized and
as you will note it's kind of weird
because we have we seem to have four
bytes in there but I only need three of
them what's going on here
so yeah the fourth byte is actually
transparency but I just discard that
because yeah you know I I just show you
like there's no hole in it so
transparency doesn't make any sense
anyway well okay so we have an
interesting setup where we actually can
use web technologies to generate the
display data but now we have to send it
over something like little USB which is
a node module which you can't because it
does have native dependencies on the
views B which is a C library you can't
just load it up in your browser that
doesn't make any sense there is a thing
called web use fee has anyone in here
ever used web USB the thing is it needs
to be supported by the hardware there's
a specific amendment of the USB spec and
I don't think the Ableton push does that
so yeah what you can do is just use
something like electron and then you can
require a native a module with native
dependencies in your webview that sounds
scary to me but it works so yeah I'm
just initializing the device and then
send the frame out and that's all so
that's how you end up with a display and
it actually it actually works quite well
it's a it's pretty responsive and yeah
like I said this is all drawn on on a
canvas as I can show you because I have
this whole thing here and now if I turn
this knob now if I turn this knob you
can actually see that also being
represented in the canvas element up
here it's just quite cool I have a
couple of extra slides I'm running a
little bit out of time so I really
wanted to talk a little bit more about
this so why this is a great question I
mean first of all because I can that's
always a good thing because learning I
really wanted to figure out this display
thing and I also really wanted to figure
out how can I build an instrument that
works for myself because that's kind of
the important part it's I built my own
instrument I can do whatever I want with
it it's not something where I need to
wait for like a new update to a certain
software to make it work better with my
setup or something and I have my own
feedback process so I sometimes talk to
myself and say hey wouldn't it be cool
if it would do this thing and I didn't
just implement it
and this actually does make a huge
difference and also I just needed to
build something for life Jess otherwise
it would be pointless yeah and I would
like to if I will show you a little demo
of what this thing can do and I would
like to close with this quote who in
here knows where this quote is from
there are actually two places so anyone
knows this yeah no no no no it's it's
like it's it's in two pieces of music
like one quotes the other the other one
is a little bit older than the other one
interesting I thought like last time I
did this there were very like a lot
fewer people so I thought maybe this
time someone would get it so the
original the original quote is from Bob
Marley and let me get the song I have no
idea I need to look that up and then
it's been quoted by come on
it's bigger than hip hop here pop there
press write nice so and it actually
starts with that exact line one good
thing about music when it hits you feel
no pain and I just yeah I just love that
so let me give you a quick demo and then
I'm done and I'm going to attempt to
play this overhead so you're gonna you
can see it and that's going to be really
hard so forgive me if it sounds terrible
yeah I mean the the square I promised
you to take a look at so this is this is
Ableton
this is I'm using this in the background
just to generate the sounds because I
didn't want to bring
to again like additional to this heavy
beasts I didn't want to bring like five
to six synthesizers to make sense so
this is all done in software right now I
can do both this sounds better than
external synthesizers because it's
easier to build like this massive
collection of synthesizers and effects
so yeah this is what's going to generate
the sound but the whole sequencing
everything like you're gonna see on
comes from the other software and yeah
it's going to be driven by this thing
[Music]
[Applause]
any questions
oh there yeah go ahead
good point the question was is this open
source let me answer that question wait
a second did I oh there you go
so yeah that's the github URL so yeah it
is open source if you want to take a
look at it it doesn't make any sense
without enabled and push right now I
really want to bring other controllers
to this as well because the push is
heavy to lug around and it would be nice
for conferences like this if I could
just bring a smaller thing yeah yeah
it's a thing that is on NPM like always
but I wrote it
[Laughter]
so yeah so there's I mean there's Lib
USB but I actually like implemented the
whole data mangling to get it in the
right format and stuff like that yeah
yeah ah interesting point it like did I
ever use this with my beatboxing not
really so Ableton does have some looping
functions and I really would like to try
that out one time but the thing is that
I'm so nervous when I'm doing this life
music stuff every time that I don't
think that with an additional I don't
know something like 10,000 hours of
practicing I would be confident enough
to try to add my own voice to things
yeah anyone else yeah thank you very
much
[Applause]