ah
so I have no audio and I have no
internet connection so it's going to be
a slightly different presentation and I
planned what I think I'm going to do
first is show you a little bit of
processing j/s which is hooking into
WebGL so here we have is it takes big
enough will show make it bigger bigger
bigger okay parents know what
how about that so good okay cool so we
have a basically this is Java syntax it
gets converted to JavaScript and then
runs a bunch of canvas functions and
WebGL functions so you have your setup
function and we're going to call OpenGL
and then the draw function and we're
going to translate across the canvas and
then we're going to have rotate why a
frame count is a global variable that
just keeps ticking over every time the
drawer is run and the door is actually a
loop and then the box which is the width
height and depth for the box or we can
just knock it down and just give it one
argument and it will handle that for us
there we go that's actually using the 3d
hardware in the browser on the canvas
and that's how easy is to start playing
with 3d with processing jeaious so it's
a it's a lot more tricky getting started
we have just JavaScript so you can do
things like color 250 500 which should
be red
excuse me it's Phil
so we have a red box and that's this is
something I've been digging into I'm one
of the guys hacking on the processing
Jas team and so we're at the moment
we're working on the WebGL part and
we're working on some audio stuff as
well to actually read the audio stream
in and write to the audio stream in and
out of firefox and i'll i can give you a
demo of that but I don't have any
speakers but i'll show you it anyway so
what i want to show you something I've
been working on over the last couple of
days and it uses a combination of WebGL
it uses a canvas 2d uses jQuery and
jQuery UI to for the interface and then
i'm using some SVG filters to add some
effects to that so this is a WebGL
running at the moment and basically
these sliders here I have control the x
y&z properties and I'll just show you
how I did that
where are we phottix
so I'm adding these hooks in at the top
rotation x y&z and then I give it a name
and I give it kind of variables that are
going to hook into jquery-ui well and
then a function for the slide event
which sets the value and then the beauty
of that is I can have all these
different visualizations with different
hooks and you can add hooks and
eventually I'm going to make it so you
can hook 1 the output of one piece of
code to the input of another piece of
code and you create all these sort of
generative visualizations so I'll give
you a little demo of how that works so
I'm using SVG filters here and what
that's doing is allowing me to do to
apply the blend modes like come like
multiply and screen and darken or
lighten if I do screen you can see the
other thing running in the background
which is a box and I can change that
around as well give you an idea of how
this looks you do different things to it
and then I can switch these around as
well and render them in a different
order and so then so I'm using SVG to do
that and you can't actually do it in SVG
at the moment in the way that you should
be able to do it what I've had to do is
put both of the renders in one div the
inside another div that has overflow
hidden then I've had to grab the SVG
image and then slide it across and apply
it because you can you can't mix and
match different Dom elements from the
CSS thing at the moment with the filters
so here's a little bit of control over
some of the filters this is a filter I
set up for adding some bloom which is a
typical effect in computer games so I go
that's the standard deviation just like
the width of the gorge and blur so it's
going for a gorge and blur and then it's
going through a component transfer which
basically what I'm doing is I'm upping
the gamma and then I'm laying that back
over as a screen effect so you kind of
blend between the gorgon blur and the
the original image and you can get some
really cool effects with this and so let
me play around with some stuff and show
you what it can do so this is a tree
visualization from the original
processing thing and it's cool because
you can then just dump all these
different visualizations into the
library and start messing around with
them to see what they do so if we take
let's see where we go let's try sad some
text
we multiply that these are using to do
three girls okay the two you're seeing
at the moment it using the 2d canvas the
other ones were using the 3d canvas but
it's using but the SVG stuff doesn't run
through hardware I think the filters are
just applied for your software
and then here's an object I was messing
around with today let me just
mr. Moser and that's running kind of
slow the reason it's running slows
because I am the way I've done it is
i've done it inside the processing code
which is using evo and it's using with
so the code isn't traceable so when it's
going for all these loops it's taking a
long time it would it's going to be much
quicker at some point actually that's a
good point i'll show you how to how you
can just make a 3d objects and export it
if I do do strood faces
if I export this is blender 3d which is
an open source 3d animation and game
making thing which actually they just
they've just started working on a
plug-in so you can export from blender
3d you can export to WebGL so we'll run
on the 3d cameras which is really cool
so you can I think they're going to go
and extend it to the point where you can
actually make games with that so
it's going to be test object so I'm
using wave front here because it's a
really quick and easy format to to
render so hopefully I go into object
up here I'm loading the objects so I'm
going to load in test the object here's
why slow code is it be
so hopefully this should work
here we go straight into the canvas
so one more thing I'd like to show you
is the audio if i put the audio thing in
here we have two boxes which are going
to respond to this audio element and
this isn't sort of plan to be in any
releases anytime soon but it's something
that we're working on in the processing
j/s channel Dave Humphrey has done the
the adding the hooks between c and java
script and then the rest of us have been
hacking together and making demos and
writing beat detection code so for play
this this is actually doing beat
detection right now so it's listening to
the samples of the audio it's getting
them into an array and then it's just
processing the array looking for the low
frequency and then it creates an object
which you can query and find out which
beat you're on so three it is
interesting to kind of play around and
merge these different technologies into
one sort of interface for sort of
testing purposes just to have fun with
it see what could come about so that's
about it any questions
enjoy so you running your own machine so
which is heavy how slow with BR a
regular gene it's not it's a lot slower
on my laptop and my laptop's kind of
crummy though the WebGL stuffs really
quick the thing that's really hitting
the performance is having the two
different layers and then doing all the
SVG filters are nice that seems to be
slowing it down a lot is the hardware
acceleration stuff that's coming into
Firefox gonna give up the performance of
this thing sorry is that the hardware
acceleration is committed to Firefox
gonna how about with this the
performance of this sort of work the
witch stuff I thought that we're getting
hardware accelerated graphics like I 9
is
for 2d or 3d as well I don't know well
this is actually free d and this is
hardware accelerated okay into he's not
currently available i I'm imagining it
must it must go them of it at some point
yeah any more questions