oh alrights just verifying am i heard
yeah okay it's going to keep this coming
close to nut all right all right so
hello everybody I'm tab Atkins I work
for Google I am a member of the CSS
working group and a number of other spec
working groups and I've been doing specs
for six or seven years now it's
disappears to be my passion is a number
of links up there and whatnot if you
want to follow the slides there's a
couple of useful links in them that you
can click on I don't have the URLs
visible so you want to click on them
that's the talk today or you just go to
slash talks and choose the one with the
right date so I'm going to once this
talk today about the future of CSS this
is a smaller screen so it's even more
here than you even know or at least a
little bit of it a lot of specs that
I've worked on that I have been excited
about for the last several years and I
have a lot of stuff and not a lot of
time so we'll be going through pretty
quickly here this is not meant to be a
let's learn about lots of stuff deep
dive it's just a here's a bunch of cool
stuff I will mention one sentence about
each of them more or less and you can
learn more about them later just to get
you excited let you know the landscape
of the stuff i swear i can get this
working oh that's better okay cool so
we're going to start with image values
this was actually my very first spec
when i started working on CSS it was the
thing that got me into the working group
I was like web kits original gradient
function is I can make a better
grammar for it and I did and they were
like why don't you just write the spec
you basically already done so so some of
the new things are showing up here
exciting one is the image function a
souped-up URL three examples of
functionality right here that lets you
do just a small bits that are worthwhile
the first one shows off fall back to a
color if you have so you have a light
website background dark buttons with
white text on them you're using a dark
background image so that the white text
offsets nicely but if that image 404s
you're screwed white text on to a white
background because there's no nothing
the contrast against anymore you can use
the image function once it's implemented
to say if the
image doesn't load just go ahead and
make a color for me it's good enough so
instead of a dark background image that
you would like you'll have a black
square better than nothing the second
one is just straight-up color images
easy way to generate if you ever needed
solid color images right now you can do
so with linear gradient you just repeat
your color twice and it kind of
generates it but that's a kind of a
weird hack image lets you go more
directly you just leave off the URL and
the color that's left there will
generate a solid color image for you in
this particular case I am blue tinting a
background by putting a partially
transparent blue image on top of another
background image the third one if you've
heard about everybody's used image
spriting at some point this shows off a
syntax for media fragments that lets you
do image spriting directly this rather
than having to do weird hacks with
background position and background size
you can literally say load up this
sprite sheet food up PNG and give me the
rectangle with these coordinates that's
the image I want gives you the correct
size let's a repeat etc the problem is
though that if a browser doesn't support
media fragments it'll just show you the
whole sprite sheet will mess everything
up image requires the browser to
understand the syntax of the hash or
else it will just fail so you can use
this kind of thing safely older browsers
will just ignore it ones that don't
understand the fragment syntax if we
introduce new fragments in Texas or new
types of things to images in the future
same thing it'll let you do fall back at
the syntax level very nicely next up is
the image set function this has been
around for a while it was introduced by
WebKit in the before chrome forked from
the codebase if you're familiar with the
picture element and the image source set
attribute that I've also worked on a bit
this does similar functionality there
right now it does just the basic stuff
you give a URL you give a density it
chooses which one it wants to load based
on the user's screen and then
potentially other things their
connection speed etc in time it will be
upgraded to match picture fully in
functionality similar functionality to
what sizes and the W descriptor does you
can already use media queries
just naturally in CSS to get the same
functionality of art direction that
picture allows etc the crossfade
function lets you smoothly fade between
two images this currently already works
in WebKit and blink a safari and opera
and chrome slightly older syntax and
what's presented here and in the spec
but will change to it whenever we
unfreeze fun thing is this is used
already by the animation CSS animations
to do animation between images what I'm
showing right here is literally just an
animation going between for background
images and it uses crossfade to
automatically give you the transition
behavior I don't let's not install all
right cool image rendering controls how
an image scales there we go the original
image is there I blow it up by two times
in each dimension the original they like
normal behavior using a bilinear scaling
looks freaking terrible because this is
pixel art this kind of scaling algorithm
is designed for photos and nice smooth
things new values pixelated lets it keep
the big chunky pixel look so it looks
nice when it scales up pixel art crisp
edges has the potential to do even more
advanced things it's allowed to fall
back to the same as pixelated but it can
use advanced pixel art scaling
algorithms like those pioneered by a lot
of game emulators and what not to do
smoother things this and i forget what
exact algorithm this is an example of
but it's able to infer angles and colors
and whatnot for you automatically
alright next spec is flexbox everybody
is hopefully heard of flexbox hopefully
you're already using it it's pretty
widely available now so you don't have
much excuse unless you're still on ie6
who knows i'm not going to talk too much
about this just up the main reasons for
it flex box plus the next thing i'll be
talking about solves basically all your
layout woes there's still a few cases i
want to hit up but this does ninety
percent of everything you can lay out
things in any direction left down
upright with flex flow you can change
the order of things without messing with
your mark
putting things in nice accessible order
with your content first and add second
and then just swapping them around on
display you can do vertical and
horizontal alignment including sintering
if you're still making jokes about CSS
centering you are several years out of
date by now and finally flexibility
allowing things to grow or shrink to
fill the available space very important
there's a lot of fun examples which I'll
have a nice link to in a little while I
really wish I could do an entire talk
about flex because I love talking about
that but that's not for today so the
partner to flex is gridlayout flexbox is
designed for linear layouts anything
that's one dimensional perhaps broken
across lines because you can do a
multi-line flexbox but it's still
essentially things in order grid is
designed for two-dimensional layout what
is really going on for pages basically
all the things that you could do with
table layout grid makes it possible to
do but ridiculously easier and not
terrible markup and maintainable
everything's great so quick example here
is one possible layout of a little game
design thing title score stats board
controls everybody can probably imagine
how they might mark that up use floats
or what not to put it into place but
with grid it's literally nothing more
than using a bit of ASCII art on the
container to define your page markup and
then telling each piece which section of
the ASCII art to go into the title goes
into the block a here's the real magic
this is a portrait orientation taller
than it is wide if you want it to handle
landscape as well really easily like
this layout same stuff just in a
completely different arrangement all you
have to do is change your Styles a
little bit give a different layout
they'll all sit in the same tile so you
can just use a media query to
drastically change the layout of your
page adapting to different sizes layouts
orientations etc rather than the
ridiculous series of hacks that we have
to do today to get the same thing if
you're following along on my slides
here's a bunch of great links you should
follow rachel andrews grid by example is
a wonderful compendium of a lot of use
cases like real world places where you
might use grid and how to do so
examples Phillip Walt installed by
flexbox is the same thing but for flex
box and then CSS tricks has great grid
and flexbox guides you can just google
for those or follow along these links on
my slides the selector spec selectors
level for the first specs that was in
level 4 but that's kind of not even a
big thing today we have a bunch of them
so touch on a few of the more
interesting additions the inth child
pseudo-class now does selector based
indexing that first selector li foo in
the child even doesn't do what you might
think it finds list items that are dot
foo and that are even not the even that
foos you know it doesn't let you count
particular things just elements
themselves so you can now move the
selector into the selected part that you
want to be counting on into the argument
of the imp child and this will now find
all the lig foos and then only grab the
even ones of them skipping over
everything else not implemented yet but
should show up in WebKit are yeah and
WebKit soon so I think Safari will have
this first the matches function lets you
do branching in CSS I've written this
kind of code all the time long selector
i need to change one bit to apply it as
well I have to repeat the entire thing
bad for maintenance bad for reading just
not a good deal all around using matches
I can capture the fact that i want a TD
or a th in this case and just put it
directly in write a single selector fun
thing to once this is well supported
sass can start using this for its extend
support and finally get extends to work
exactly like it's supposed to right now
they have to do a lot of heuristics and
they drop some edge cases to avoid a
giant selector explosion but matches
lets them do the semantics exactly right
without any explosion whatsoever you can
do extend in a single nice selector
without a bunch of duplication variables
I've been working on variables for quite
a while they've been a request for
forever in CSS fun thing they work right
now in Firefox if you want to
load up modern Firefox and try using
variables like this example right here
it will work you declare a bunch of
properties custom properties using
whatever name you want the only
requirement is they have to start with
two dashes give them whatever value you
want and then on any descendants of that
element you can use that property's
value with the VAR function in this case
i'm declaring some colors for my page
using them for the a and it's visited
and then also using them on my h1 that
way if i want to change my main color at
any point i don't have to go search and
replace hope I hit everything that
requires it etc and I have nice names on
my values and that's really important
for maintainability as well oh we head
back real quick like I said it works
today in Firefox it works in safari but
it's prefixed chrome removed our support
for it that was done in WebKit because
it wasn't very good and we are currently
replacing our CSS parser as soon as we
do that we will be able to put a good
implementation of variables in so they
should show up in chrome soon ish I'd
say within in 2015 we should probably
get one do to do to do the color spec
I've always been fascinated with colors
if you know me and you follow my blog I
have several posts about color stuff
because math and colors are just amazing
so I've been working on the color
spectrally a few additions that have
been done from author requests for and
eight digit hex colors so you can
specify your alpha in your hex you don't
have to change to the RGB syntax and
convert your hex back into decimal just
to get a partially transparent color and
this functions in general are a little
more consistent now alpha values except
percentages right now if you specify
your alpha its of number between 0 and 1
rather than a percentage no idea why
just people did weird things when we
first invented the color functions the
hue values also even though it's a
degree around a circle they accept just
integers right now and assume it's
degrees so the new functions will accept
real angles so you can use the turn unit
or radians or whatever you want if you
feel like it
there's a few new types of colors as
well HW b is a more intuitive variant of
hsl easier to use you just declare your
hue and then how much white and black to
add to the color to get it to a
different tinder or whatnot if you've
used Chrome's color picker the input
type equals color that color picker is
an HW b picker you choose your hue from
the ring then you have a triangle with
the hue of the white and the black on
each corner and that's exactly the color
space you'd be working in with HW b the
gray function lets you specify grades
that repeating yourself because they
have r g and b all the same you can use
a percentage or specify a 0 to 255 value
just like you do today in RGB and then
the color function which i might
probably tweak the syntax of a lot takes
all the as much of the functionality as
i can justify from sasses color
adjusting functions and bakes them into
CSS this is especially useful when
you're using variables in CSS to store
colors because then you can take a few
base colors and produce an entire suite
of colors for your site based on making
them a little bit lighter a little
darker etc media queries so one of the
big problems with dealing with mobiles
have gone along is how to convert over
hover based sites and detect when you
need to do an alternate solution media
queries are trying to level up to make
these kind of things easier to do when
the most important ones here are the two
queries pointer and hover which are
showing up in chrome now I believe
they're being implemented in Firefox
they should be around very shortly for
everybody in particular the pointer
media query has two values course which
means some it's a big fat pointer like
your finger can't select very accurately
or fine like a pen or a mouse pointer
and then hover is can you hover or not
yes or no and a few examples of the
types of devices you can handle here the
great things about this is that if you
handle a coarse pointer properly just
making your touch targets bigger making
sure there's enough separation between
links etc anything with a coarse pointer
a touch device or if you're viewing it
on a wiimote or you have using connect
to
never get the internet or whatever
they'll all work nicely breaking things
down by nice features rather than by
devices makes it automatically more
accessible to interesting devices on the
outskirts of your use cases there are a
bunch more in the spec for example
looking for the ability to animate you
can tell if your view being viewed on an
e-ink device that can't animate very
well it can change values but it can't
do constant gradations because it takes
too long to update the screen so you
might scale down or drop your animations
in that case there's a bunch more in
their luminosity queries you can tell if
the phone is being used at night and you
might want to use a different color
scheme to prevent it from being old
brighten your eyes and if you have any
other ideas for things that you need to
know in order to design your webpage
appropriately responsively let us know
email us on dub dub dub style at w3.org
and tell us what it is you're trying to
do and maybe we can craft a media query
for this some new things out of
animation who hears heard of the web
animation spec decent number not enough
all right everybody is homework look up
the web animation spec just google for
it it's taking all the functionality and
ease of use of CSS animations and making
them useful in javascript using a syntax
pretty similar to jquery animation if
you're used to that gives you all the
hardware acceleration etc that you get
from using a CSS animation for certain
properties but rather than having to
deal with strings and the crap that you
have to do right now to try to use
performance CSS animations you just say
element animate food to bar it's very
simple another very interesting one
again if you're following the slides you
just click that link is the new motion
property that was recently proposed and
being implemented in Chrome and Safari
right now SVG has always had a nice way
to animate something around a page two
dimensionally you can technically do
that yourself just by using transform X
and transform why but it's ridiculously
difficult it's not something that you
could actually do by hand unless you're
doing the simplest of things straight
lines maybe some diagonals you don't do
a curve around and try to set that up
with easing functions on the x and y you
can't do that with you
means computers can do it for you but
it's terrible motion path just lets you
specify the path you want to do using
the SVG path syntax and then you just
tell the element I want you to be at
this position and animate over to this
position and it will follow the path for
you automatically and finally we come to
the real future of CSS what I've talked
about before are features that are
coming up in the near future the medium
future things that we're giving you
Polly filling CSS is where sees us we'll
end up with you giving things to us no
language can grow forever it CSS is
already an enormous language we have
over 400 properties and memorizing
everything is ridiculously difficult and
we're only getting larger every day we
add something new the cycle time between
us finding a need in us creating a spec
and then it being implemented and then
it being usefully implemented across
enough devices for you to use on sites
is too long flex boxes cycle time was
about 5 years and that's not a typical
it's pretty normal there and that's
ridiculous we can't deal with a
five-year cycle time between I have an
idea I can use the idea on a website so
there's a lot of places where we can
open up CSS to poly filling to
JavaScript based approaches that still
hook into low-level browser primitives
the things that CSS is affecting in the
first place but let you tailor things to
your own solution one simple example
probably one of the first that will show
up is poly filling media queries I'm
going to start with a wrong thing doop
doop doop starting with a sea thing oh I
can get that all right cool small screen
too small for me creating custom media
queries just to give names this is more
or less variables for media queries if
you'll notice as well i'm using a nice
fun syntax 500 pixels less than or equal
to width etc that's a new syntax and
media queries because we never really
wanted to do min-width and max with it's
a little bit confusing we always wanted
a nice relationship operators like
you're used to a normal programming but
10-15 years ago when this was first in
to XML was harder to work with nowadays
we don't care we can use less than and
greater than signs pretty freely so
that's fine so this just gives a name to
a longer media query you can you make
one that's just for a small screen for
example that has that maybe some other
media queries stacked on give it a nice
short name use that throughout your
document again so you don't repeat
yourself also the script based syntax
for this lets you do more advanced
things you want to how many people use
moderniser so moderniser works by
setting classes on the body this means
though that you have to use a relatively
inefficient selector to style off of
this doing body dot animation or
whatever does and then a descendant
selector relatively slow instead that
kind of thing could be set up as media
queries which don't require searching
over the document for it set up true or
false set up new values for what you
want if you're using some new API on the
web on some mobile device that isn't
exposed into CSS yet but you want to
style your page based on that you can
set up a custom media query for that
with whatever values you want and you
just use them in your page like any
other media query would there's a bunch
more that we could do here to a basic
list here the most important one though
is down at number five custom layout
that's one of the things that has the
longest cycle time right now I said flex
boxes have been a five-year cycle time
from me starting to work on it to it
being usable across everywhere and
that's only because I started from a
spec that already kind of existed
everybody already recognized it was
useful grid has a similar cycle time a
lot of ideas are smaller than this but
layout just takes a long time it's
extremely complicated to get right when
you're trying to design forever so
recently I was in Sydney for a week with
the chrome team down there and we spent
the entire week talking about how we
could make layout customizable very
difficult because it's very perf
sensitive it's very easy to slow down
the entire page if you don't do things
carefully we think we have some
solutions for this and we're getting
together with other browser vendors our
next meeting in February will be with
Firefox ie
in Safari to talk about exactly how we
want to design a custom layout system
that lets JavaScript create layouts that
respond well to CSS because of course
you can create layouts yourself right
now you have JavaScript drives some
absolute positioning etc but you're
stuck with the container being usually
fixed size because CSS when it asks hey
what size are you you can't respond well
you have to just give a definite answer
this kind of thing will make custom
layouts work well within CSS and make it
much easier to say I want something like
flexbox but a little bit different
details just go write it yourself or get
someone else to write it for you rather
and then if it's a really good idea
afterwards we can come along pick it up
look really smart because we're
designing something great but you don't
have to wait for us to do it first
there's no more asking permission and
that's the big ideal here just letting
y'all all of y'all in this room and
outside work on the web in CSS the same
way you do with JavaScript the same way
you do with preprocessors etc and
continue on there so that's the end I
think it's probably time if we do have
any time I can take questions but I
don't know if this is a question e-type
place all right cool no questions talk