my name is Guillermo ouch i'm the
creator of socket i/o also co-founder
and CTO of a startup called Lauren boost
in the education space so I assume as
many of you might be aware of socket i/o
is a way of doing real-time applications
on every browser also a server now with
a simple API that resembles WebSocket a
lot so so far we've seen a lot of
adoption and many applications deployed
to production with it and many projects
created with it and with that we've
learned some lessons and we've finally
come up with a speck of how other people
that might want Sokka Dale and the saga
do protocol on other servers and other
languages might go about creating it so
they go for the next release of socket
i/o that has been already pushed to get
having an alpha State is sort of
implementing this spec implementing sort
of new features that are going to be the
foundation of socket i/o and so that's
what I'm going to talk about today first
of all I made some architectural changes
the like I said the prodigal the socket
a protocol which is what we need
essentially to make web socket and long
polling or other transports converge and
maintain sessions for users so they we
can for example buffer messages from the
server and the client we have we have
made some API changes so that it's
easier to get up and running we haven't
a new way of doing tests which basically
is I created on node client that I'm
going to use to test the node server and
vice versa so before each time you would
run socket i/o you were limited to
storing every message and every user and
every session ID
on one process of one computer so if
that process were to die or you wanted
to use two computers to handle a number
a higher number of messages per second
or a higher number of connected users
you basically had to create a message
you basically implement a message
dispatcher yourself you would subscribe
clients to a Redis set or pops up or you
would use RabbitMQ so today so k is
going to take care of that for you and
also another important thing is many
people have different needs as far as
how much latency they can afford for
their applications so some people might
want to just completely ditch the flash
transport because it adds a lot of bloat
and they can afford to use long polling
and said fallback transport so I've made
the hell shake process and it made the
socket interface is more configurable so
that you can easily decide what
transports you want to use and other
options I'm going to talk a little bit
about the new API so I we made some we
made it easier to run a socket server
that is not tied to a particular HTTP
server so before you have to instantiate
it yourself now you can simply call I oh
listen or pass it a port and you'll have
your own standalone socket i/o server
before you would have to pass this huge
object of options with nested objects of
options and now we have expressed like
configuration so we can have you can
have different settings for development
and production which for a project like
Sokka do is extremely important
sometimes your clients might be dropping
because of network latency or you're
testing a mobile device so you want to
make sure you know why a certain clients
dropping is it because a heartbeat
wasn't received or is it because the
client is too slow for this for your
settings so you can customize things as
the logger the log level
so like I said up until today you were
constructed to one process in one server
we made some changes to make that more
flexible so by default you'll still it
is going to continue to store everything
in memory the main reasons that not
everyone has requirements to set up
Sokka do in a cluster or perform worker
process replacements with tools like
cluster or multi-node like like I said
it defaults to memory and one thing that
we have to change in order to make this
two modes of operating compatible is
that every signature that before was
chance accessing memory now is an async
call back so from your socket i/o
instance if you needed to access a
client list before you would go sacate
other clients and now you're going to go
suck at a the clients and positive
function something really useful as well
is the ability to associate data with a
particular client so when someone
connects we can for example set and
nickname and that's going to leverage
the same existing storage that you're
using for your messages and for your
message queues so if someone connects
and you want to sort the nickname
they're going to have for the session
you can do that directly from Sokka do
as well another thing that is really
important is the ability to send
messages that can be dropped and should
not be buffered so for example if you
are creating an application that
displays tweets or you're creating an
application that you want to show the
latest stock prices to the users you
don't want it and you're retrieving
stock prices every second but you have a
client that is only taking messages
every five seconds or so you don't want
to buffer every single message you you
want Sokka do to drop some of them so
that you always receive the latest so
that's what the volatile flag does and
it's really easy to use so before you
would you would say sockets and and you
would send
message to the user so now by simply for
fixing it with volatile you can make
that message forgettable so if Sokka do
cannot write it to the user which is
important for example for long polling
where the client is opening request and
response cycles and we're only able to
write data to the user whenever they
open their request but between between
two requests and sorry between a request
and response we cannot write to the user
because it's not server push so those
messages would be dropped while the user
is temporarily not connected another
flag that i'm adding is called Jason so
before Sokka do was smart enough to
detect that you were sending something
that was not a string and serialized it
into Jason so the problem is that even
strings can be serialized in to Jayson
so if you want to force one hundred
percent Jason encoding you can also use
the Jason flag and you can combine them
so if you want to send Jason as a
volatile message you just concatenate
them and I really useful thing is
acknowledgments so sometime so the way
that WebSocket works you write a message
you never get a call back unless you
implement it yourself so you can send a
message that is prefixed by an ID and
then have your server respond with that
particular ID so you would get an
acknowledgement that your message has
been received by the server so i built
the machinery for acknowledgments into
the socket 80 protocol and implementing
it as a developer as a user of the
library is extremely easy so every time
you send a message if you pass a
function as the last parameter that's
going to send that that's going to
append an ID to the to the message that
is being sent through the wire and the
client will respond and it's also
symmetrical so a client can send a
message that has a callback associated
with it and the server will respond with
an acknowledgement another thing that it
was actually requested many times
it really doesn't add any blow to the
prodigal and that's the main reason that
it's been added is the ability to define
your custom events so you can still use
Sokka do as a unconnect on message and
on disconnect but certain applications
will fit other semantics better so if
you're creating a chat application you
might want user connected user joined
Rome user sending private messages so
now you can define these events and they
are sent through the socket a prodigal
in a very lightweight way so instead of
going sorry here is not io on chat
messages socket dot on chat message
essentially you can define chasm the
event emitter is overridden for sacate
oh so you can define your custom events
and omit custom events for events that
are user defined the parameters that you
send our JSON encoded that means that
you can send objects you can send
strings dates on it or any other in co
double entity so like I said events have
no protocol overhead they are optional
you can still use socket i/o as a cross
browser web socket if you like constrain
yourself to like the three basic events
and again it's compatible with flags and
acknowledgments so like I said it's
always events always use JSON but if you
want to send that volatile event so if
you're listening on a Twitter stream and
you want to send a tweet event and you
might want to drop some of them you can
do that by prefixing the emit by with a
volatile flag and something interesting
is that an acknowledgment from an
implementation point of view is just the
server sending us a packet back that is
basically an empty string but sometimes
you might want to acknowledge with
actual data so you might want to you
might want to say amid a nickname event
and as as part of the result get get a
response of whether the nickname could
be said or not or if it was being used
by another user in the case of a chat
application and that's also something
that is
empower essentially when you when you
emit an event if the function arity
meaning the number of arguments that are
defining the function that you pass it
as a callback for the acknowledgement is
greater than zero so in this case I'm
setting and emitting a nickname event
and the function expects at response
object so Sokka do will know that your
function the server side has responded
with data so in this case I'm performing
in a synchronous task which is checking
for the availability of that nickname
and this is really powerful because
there's many semantics that do not
require acknowledgement and do not
require data back from the server so for
example publishing a message to a stream
but there's many that do and events give
you this functionality now so finally
moving forward with the project one
thing I would like to see is people
creating reusable applications and not
just frameworks so today we have
frameworks like D node and juggernaut
which are awesome but if if we want this
to become mainstream and we want to
really enable people that are creating
web two point O applications doing start
inserting components of the real time
web we need to make sure that we can
distribute pre packaged applications and
to that end we need to solve to
basically one problem which is
preventing collisions and if you have a
particular eye socket AO instance you
need some machinery for two different
applications to share that without
having to initialize two different ones
so if two particular parts of your
website depend on web socket that's fine
you have two connections but if they
depend on long polling depending on the
browser and how many resources are being
loaded and how many people I've sockets
are open you might end up with like four
different connections just for your two
sockets so the idea is that we want to
be able to reuse a particular sicario
instance but be able to namespace it
and to that end I added the ability to
like sockets subscribe to channels
without the user knowing or having to
particularly subscribe or understand the
pops of kind of mechanism and the way it
works is really simple so by default the
when you define a socket it's going to
subscribe to the empty namespace that's
the default again you can continue use
Sokka do with as basically a WebSocket
it all the messages go through the same
stream but you can also define a
namespace just by prefixing your event
listeners with four so that part to your
socket for the news endpoint is going to
act as a standalone socket even though
it's going to go through the through the
same TCP connections a multiplexing is
automatic even on the client side if on
the clients that you define the same
hostname the same port and the same
protocol but you only change this
resource part of the URL then
multiplexing will be enabled for you and
packets that signal connection in this
connection of events of this socket will
be sent which means you can actually
disconnect the chat socket and keep the
new socket connected and that means that
every single event or every single
message that you send is constrained to
that particular namespace so this also
fits really well into how you could make
your own applications even if you're not
reusing third-party code so you might
have an event called item or an event
called message but they are actually two
different things in two different
namespaces and as far as where what
we're working on right now and what's
coming for the project so it it's
obvious that expresses the mainstream
web framework for node is the framework
that the community chose and we need
that really easy way to leverage and
connect session data with sockets so I
really
need is like okay so someone connected
through a socket and a particular page
but I want to retrieve what's his
username or what's his email from the
database and to this end the solution is
really simple by having a token of
authentication that expressed and Sokka
do can enter exchange they you can know
on what page the user is when what part
what particular out and who the user is
so this is a separate project that's
coming for express users another thing
that is challenging right now is testing
different browsers so every time you
make a change to the client in the order
server we need to see if I six works and
today to till today it's been largely a
manual process combined with really
simple unit testing and obviously unit
testing is not enough considering the
many quirks that browsers have so one
thing I'm going to do is set up
automatic cloud testing on selenium so
that we're going to be able to as soon
as we push to github we're going to be
able to test on all the browsers who
want to support there's been also many
problems related to the flash fallback
that range from sometimes increasing the
latency to a really high memory
consumption to RIT slowness when HTTPS
and ssl are used and also the fact that
Sokka do without flash is around 8
kilobytes and with flash is like I know
like 200 kilobytes and that's a problem
so we're going to be working on our own
flash fall back and we're probably not
going to be supporting as a cell with it
because that's what adds the most bloat
to to the Flash movie is the fact that
the ssl crypto libraries are not built
in into action script
there is also an upcoming WebSockets
back that browsers will be supporting
soon including Firefox 4 and as soon as
a major stable browser supports it we
want to support it and so that's it you
can check out the repo for the latest
code and if you have any questions so
you're asking if it should be connect al
or so yeah that's a great question and
so the session middleware which is one
of the things that we want to connect
with Sokka do is basically connect it's
not expressed so to that end we yeah and
there is a project already for that but
my other thing is the ability to create
to connect the templates to real-time
events and to that end we need to make
it express and there's also the fact
that not many people use connect without
express while leveraging the session
middleware you might want to use Kinect
if you're like just serving static files
or static pages like HTML and some
images you might just want to use
connect but when you're actually
leveraging the session middleware you're
probably using Express so I just went
with express today oh so he's asking
about how we're going to do
cross-browser cross-platform testing so
for a company we also have the problem
of supporting multiple browsers and we
want to have acceptance testing that
where that makes sure that things work
on WebKit which is the presser we
develop on but also Isaac's so we
created an adapter for node called soda
what soda does is implement selenium and
potentially if you want to use sauce
labs sauce labs is a starter that
provides a service for automating
testing with selenium on the cloud in
the cloud so instead of you setting up
your own cluster and you're like set of
computers running Windows and ie and all
the different variations of combinations
you can use sauce labs
and you pay per minute and it's also
free for linux and firefox so you can
get started doing acceptance testing
with that way and that's what we're
going to leverage so we're going to
write unit tests and we're also going to
connect to like a fixed socket i/o
server and we're going to just basically
produce output to the add page then
selenium will connect to that page and
check for a number of positives and
negatives and if it fails sauce labs
will give you a video of what happened
so you can know exactly like okay what
test failed or what's the output or
what's the JavaScript console saying
he's asking if it's been difficult to
keep up with the WebSockets back and the
answer is actually no because at first
we had up so in the very first node days
we there was no HTTP upgrade event so we
had to implement WebSocket as net server
so the HTTP parser and the HTTP note
implementation didn't give us the hooks
to have a WebSocket server without a
patch so initially saucony you had to
like patch node to have a WebSocket
server on top of the HTTP server
otherwise you would have to run it in a
different port so then we had to support
the initial spec which was draft 75 and
after that shortly after we had to
support draft draft 76 and since then
the spec hasn't changed at all now it's
going to change and it's going to change
in some pretty major ways but the
struggles with WebSocket have not been
mostly implementing this back it's been
for example the fact that they are
supposed to bypass proxies that's one of
the design goals of the WebSocket
protocol was what we need to make this
thing bypass proxies that are in on the
Internet today which is not the case so
WebSocket fails so socket i/o needed the
machinery to determine oh I couldn't
connect with WebSocket i'm going to try
something else so on that end it's been
a difficult decision to make WebSocket
the first choice because long polling
ends up being more reliable for most use
cases but hopefully that's going to
change now with a new spec and it and
that should be a definite one that
Firefox expressed interest in
implementing and so that's Chrome and
Safari and ie9 so I nine has the same
ambition to implement this aspect and
today they are doing it with silverlight
or through like labs plugins but
hopefully it's also going to be part of
by nine alright thank you so much yeah
I'm going to post the slides to Twitter