you
so in case you miss it the miss the big
yellow break sign this is the
hitchhiker's guide to yu xing with aux
ER and in case any of you don't know
this is me and me so my name is christy
welsh and i'm the lead ux for a company
called back base and we handle like
basically the front end for like a
financial institutions like ABN amro and
stuff but precursor to that i'm also
pointed their cloud nine idea luminoso
was there Liam you x over there as well
before I started there and my background
is in working with development teams to
really try and build great stuff and
this is what I wanted to talk about
which is sort of like the big elephant
in the room as i like to think about it
I'm gonna check more anymore yeah I am
in control okay so this is a big
elephant in the room and this is a here
right this is what I hear over and over
and over again I want to build great
things I start with really great
intentions but it always turns out
rubbish what happened and this is a
story I here and it's so so prevalent
and it all the different teams i work in
and this is how it happens is that you
start at Point a and you want to build
the best app you want to build the best
product and your little startup team and
you need to get to point B and you think
this is the way to do it as quickly and
as fast as possible that's not
necessarily the best thing because
you're great experiences and you're
happy users and you're easy interfaces
kind of live outside of that fast
approach if you want to build great
things you kind of have to live a little
bit outside of the fast approach to
getting things done and getting things
done kind of looks like a big wavy line
like this if you want to do it really
really well
by the way you to panic about it and I
want you to worry that you can still get
things done you can still do it in the
right way without having to take the
faster with all the time and this is
really what I want to talk to you just
now so I have about 20 minutes so you
gotta kind of keep your hat on because
we're going to be going really fast is
that I want to take you through how
important it is to have a vision and you
just need the one you don't need many
just have a one vision I want to see how
you help you think like a user help you
help your users why you should wireframe
at all and how to do it how to make
something throw away like a prototype
that allows you to test some of your
hypotheses laser to test whether your
ideas even good at all how to evaluate
that and lastly when you should scrap it
if you need to scrap it because ooh slow
sync because the journey of a thousand
miles always starts with one set and for
those of you who like journey and have a
ps2 is the slice for you know one
awesome one person of the back I like
you okay okay that's not good
yay ok so the vision do you have one for
your product if you don't have one I
would ask why not so whenever you start
today with them an idea of what you want
to make you tended to think a lot about
what it should do and what it should be
and it's very important to keep that in
mind because if you tick I set aside and
you take a step away from it you what
you get is feature creep and you get
lots of things being added in they don't
necessarily adhere to what was going to
be the great thing in the first place
Queen had the vision one with a very
nice record for those Queen fans and I'm
going to Queen the fun excellent so this
is what I want you to do and this will
keep you honest when it comes to your
vision I want you to print this out and
I want you to put on your wall whenever
you're going into your development
environment what one thing do you want
your product your service you're
offering to do well just one you can
have ok i'll let you have one or two but
it should really do one thing really
really well it should do one thing
awesome and you should know what that is
and it should be visible to everyone i
have made for my entire team to see in
the wall every single day and it's 80
does not like a for like second off it's
really massive and make sure that
whenever we do something it always we
reference us back all the same because
it should be simple until you make it
complicated the thing that you're
building the startup you have it should
start simple because it's very easy to
add complications in it's very difficult
to keep things simple so starting with
the user do you know who your users are
when you start with your products when
you start with your service do you know
who they are do you know what they're
doing do you know what they're trying to
do you know why they're doing it and if
you want to be good at us and you want
to do this with aux are this is one of
the top tips I can give you and that is
really think about who your users are
writer who will be using application or
your web
right their age their education and then
finally I want you to name that person
in this case we've got Arthur dance here
for those like Douglas Adams yay booboo
bunny slippers coats funny t-shirt
anyway this is who the user is and when
you do this they become real so whenever
you think what would Arthur do in this
situation would he want this we do you
want this feature if you're adding
something new in so why crazy lady are
you making me named imaginary people
that's the second thing I get a lot from
developers why am i creating imaginary
people right of nowhere and why are you
making me do this because I want you to
do this I want you to fight for your
users and I'm mixing metaphors but your
users are what's going to make you
popular they're going to make you
successful they're going to use your
application they're going to use your
products they're the ones who are going
to make it awesome for you and your job
and they're going to they're the ones
that keep you in your job they're
probably the ones with the paid
subscriptions you've got to fight for
them and less or the businesses more for
the user so this is how simple your user
persona and we call them personas in the
UX industry but it won't bog you down
too much with this can a technical
details but this is an hour third less
attractive older brother called James
this is james then 32 I've written down
some kegels for what he is he knows what
he wants to buy and his behaviors he
gets bored very quickly so don't serve
them fluffy product descriptions and
doing overwhelming too much of a choice
because you're going to lose them so
this is basically if you have a website
or service and this is just a very
simple example of how a personal in our
hair a user that you can reference can
be it can be this simple ok I'm going to
stand next to my computer because my
remote just lost connection so what does
it look like in real life
well it can look like this this is a bit
more complicated but there's no point
I'm trying to illustrate is a really no
right or wrong way to do persona work it
can be a couple of different ways or is
this right whatever makes sense to you
wherever you understand the best a
couple of these have some benefits over
others but it really depends on how you
understand your users and how you want
to you how you want to do it next thing
I want you to do is start to worry Finn
so before you touch a single piece of
code with your awesome idea and your one
vision and you know who's going to use
it I want you to get hit the pen and
paper if you can do this you can really
get to grips with what you should be
building and wireframes are not about
pretty pictures they're a bit getting
the functionality right about what
should be in there and why on earth
would you do that well there's a couple
of key benefits to wire framing I can
tell you really really fast early things
out super fast imagine a wall of just a
four sheets you can pull that together
in 30 minutes 40 minutes you can s rate
on that and even faster our mount of
time it's super super easy to see
everything that you have and you can
iterate on it you can pull stain
redraw it put it back up again you can
have this whole process doesn't have to
be long and it doesn't have to be
involved but it will help you get things
right and it'll help you get them right
before you waste time and money on code
because it's cheaper than changing code
changing pieces of paper so much cheaper
than changing code paying for a
developer to have to redo things if you
can hit it on the paper then it'll save
you a lot of time and effort so again
this is about ideas and this is about
iteration and I was kind of trying to
illustrate a point which is having one
idea super great I'm glad you have one
unlike right behind you in your corner
clapping iteration and one idea even
better you've taken that one idea and
you've taken a couple of steps further
and you've made it you've made it you
takin it to the pinnacle of what it can
be but you get a couple of ideas going
you're a tree on them
and you can get something that is just
super cool ready for the vision that you
had in mind in the first place you str8
on something and you go over a few times
and you build it you can have something
which is exponentially better than the
very first idea you had never ever hit
code if I can give you a 10 piece of
advice with the first idea you get
percolate and they go over a few things
first so what the wireframes look like
well i thought i would share one of mine
and the point i'm trying to make is
they're not pretty and they're not there
to be pretty they're there to be
functional and friendly you have used
Clayton an ID in the past this was one
of the dialog boxes I had done for cloud
nine and it's a complicated piece of
dialogue box with lots of bits that you
can't read in my scribbling handwriting
but trust me it's all golden and what
does it turn into well with a visual
designer can turn into something like
this before a programmer works on it but
it just means that whenever you start
work you've got it right the first time
imagine having to iterate on this three
four or five times before you get it
right the developer would be me
in the back if I turned my back on them
for too long but what if you really hate
paper you're allergic to it you
absolutely can't stand it or you had the
really bad experience in art class and
you never want to touch a piece of paper
again well don't panic you can use
software to their software like balsamic
FNA who knows balsamic oh you're just
damn awesome I love you who likes it
less people okay right so this is
balsamic and later to do some very fast
iterations on layouts and designs you
can throw things into there and you can
export it as PDF or PNG and that allows
you to do multiple things print them out
put them on the wall use them as a
prototyping like screens together do the
whole heap of things you can do with it
this one again so Clayton an example and
it was doing a flow diagram for how you
can actually get through from one screen
to the next and what you actually have
to show each stage and there's lots of
little virtual sticky notes because I
like sticky notes so some wireframing
tools that you can use so you're not
limited to pen and paper or balsamic
there's actually a whole heap of things
it depends what you're comfortable and I
guess and there's no hard and fast rules
as long as you do it at some point and
that is pen and paper would be my number
one because it's super fast and super
cheap and if you're allergic to pen and
paper you can use balsamic and if you
really hate balsamic you can go back to
Phantom favors most of the room seems to
do and there's that clear as well but
that's super expensive it's like six
thousand euros or something like that
for its year so unless you're a
corporate company I would avoid that one
and then there's your usual photoshop
illustrator so I'll tell you if you're
going to show wires to a client or wire
frame to a client never ever ever show
them paper never ever they will not
understand that I have two stories for
that i showed the clients and paper i
spent a whole week doing these really
great markups and I was thinking they'll
get it they'll understand this the idea
is golden and solids they looked at
paper and why are you writing on paper I
don't understand what we paying you for
conceptually they don't really
understand that so if you're going to
shoe a client something try to go as
high fidelity as possible and by high
fidelity I mean like as visual as you
can with it but i also have a story
about that i showed a client once a
really high fidelity wireframes because
of that first experience and I went I'm
not going through that again so I went
into its really awesome photoshop like
wireframes and these things were cool
and you know what happened they like the
wireframe so much i ended up being here
it would look so the wireframes in
greenway i kid you not was what they
wanted to produce at the end because it
was so high fidelity so i would take the
middle road not one or the other or
you're in dangerous territory at the
other end and envision app who knows
envision of couple of people start to
bring the back if you
no way it's really great you can link
flat screens like PNG's or and JPEGs or
whatever you want is really super cool
and you can create like little
prototypes for yourself and you can
share those with people so you can link
those bad boys up and that's going to be
good so what does a prototype look like
well you know how i made you do all
those wireframes earlier and you've got
all these bits of paper well guess what
you can do with them you can make puts
of types with them and you can actually
shuffle those bits of people around ask
people to click on them ask for feedback
so do you know where you're going give
them a task to do give them the paper
and you move the paper arraigned and see
if they do a task now if you're
wondering how that what that looks like
it looks like this so you have little
pieces of paper they can be drawing so
you don't have to be Prince I it's just
in case you're wondering and you just
shuffle them around and you ask people
to use your finger as a mess and you can
click on things and this is a really
nice easy fast cheap way especially if
you're a bit strapped company very cheap
to do this and this is kind of people
working their way through their wire
frames and you can see some confused
faces you will see that a lot if you do
this but you will also catch a lot of
your problems in your functionality by
doing this very small step and actually
showing something earlier there's a
great and cool I said I heard and that
was if you're uncomfortable showing your
work you're at the right stage to show
it so if you're uncomfortable showing it
that's the point where you should be
doing it because you'll catch all the
the bugs and things earlier in your own
designs and this is envisioned app so
this is what I was telling you about so
if you want to link those screens and
you have flat screens already great till
to do it creates little hot spots you
can click on things link them together
works really well what's really cool and
if anyone wants to see these things I
have live example so i can take you over
to the hallway right there and then i
can show you stuff as well if you really
is you really curious about it so so far
I've made you print a vision on a wall
what you're all very happy you've got
your one fashion just like Queen you've
got you know who your users are and you
can reference them you've got some wire
frame
that you've turned into a clickable
prototype know what you're going to do
well I want you to evaluate your own
work I want you to put the shoes on of
that James Dan Arthur is less attractive
older brother and I want you to think
like him whenever you look at your work
it doesn't have to be about just trying
to point and and when you think about
them I want you to really see if you can
be that person be that user and evaluate
your work it's great to get other ppl n
or segment groups but that's costly and
this total talk is about bootstrap
startups and how to get started quickly
so put on the shoes of the user evaluate
your work other ways you can do to
gather data there's a great tool it's
called usability hub it's a camera based
system so you evaluate other people's
work they evaluate yours and you get
really really awesome feedback and it
helps em and this is not a very involved
process but it is testing and it's good
testing and again you can use these kind
of fluids and diagrams and EP splits to
actually get some really cool stuff
going so this is why we're doing all
this right it's because greatness and
real true greatness does not take
shortcuts and it's true it doesn't
there's no quick way to e to be but I
can get the process down a lot shorter
and smaller so that you can get to
greatness a lot faster but it does
require a bit of work in a bit of
thinking so what if you can't evaluate
that work fairly yourself what if you
can't you don't can't conceptualize and
you just can't evaluate what you're
trying to do you look at it and it looks
okay to you but you get the feeling it's
maybe not so what happens if you can't
do it by yourself you need to find a
friend maybe not these friends I don't
think Courteney Cox is going to value
your application for you but if you have
a friends bring them in try not to tell
them anything about what you're doing
and get them to sit down and use what
you're building if you're uncomfortable
showing what you've got you're probably
doing it ray because you're getting that
feedback early
and this is somewhat what it looks like
so you've got to set the back and send
nothing and they're going to set the
front and they're going to do a couple
of tacit you set them or they're going
to talk to you about what they think
about what they're seeing and then you
get to write down or you get to say
nothing but just take notes and the best
advice I can give you is to sit and do
nothing and try to give nothing away
because a user will try to please you so
someone that you get n even your friends
will try to do it right and that some
that can be dangerous because if you're
they'll want to make sure that your
product is good but what you really want
is fear feedback so the list the less
you say at this point the best the
better so what really happens when it
doesn't go as expected so you've done
all this hard work right and you've got
the evaluation back and actually the
evaluation gave you something like this
probably because you didn't stay true to
your one vision you've had one two three
four visions in there or something and
you've got a bit of a Frankenstein's
monster of a product or service that
does nothing really very well well at
this point you really need to think
about your own work right so you need to
think about this so you're going to keep
it or are you going to bin it and this
is when I was trying to tell you about
earlier is that it's a process and if
it's a fast process and you can get to
this point a lot faster is that there's
no point in spending six months your
life developing something that isn't
great or isn't going to be great and
it's much better for you if you've been
at earlier than it as if you keep going
so please don't get too attached to your
projects they can some things feel like
your little baby that you have your a
golden channel that's going to become in
the next Jesus but it's probably better
that you are able to evaluate your work
and see if it is good because the next
great idea could be just raining the
corner for you as well so
is this everything I have to tell you
about user experience oh no need a whole
lot more to it than this but if we're
talking about getting the basics right
and we're talking about building
something really really super awesome
then this is going to help you get
started really quickly really well it's
going to get you to the point where you
could probably hire a professional and
to do this for you and that if I can
make any recommendation to someone is
that they don't do it themselves you
actually get professional in but if you
do if you have to then please do these
steps so here's what we just covered in
a very fast lightning style fashion
which is how important it is to have one
of your visions and pin it on your wall
and make it visible so that everything
you do you reference back to that how
you can think like a user which is take
those steps to write down who they are
name them please reference them whenever
you think about your features I want you
to think about wireframing I want you to
think about getting the functionality of
what you're trying to do right make sure
all the steps in place if you need to
think about the edge cases please do but
make it work for the eighty percent of
your users first and then the last
twenty percent you can make work with
the edge cases how to make a throwaway
prototype which is use those wireframes
uses paper reuse them and actually make
a finger clickable for a tightly can use
how to evaluate your own work which is
take a step back and really think about
your user and f it fits their needs and
finally when you need to scrap it which
is after the evaluation process if it
didn't go well you need to really think
about whether you should carry on so so
long and thanks for all the fish I will
be taking questions so I think I did
that in super fast time so I'm free for
some questions or not yes okay couple of
minutes anyone have any questions with
all that lightening fast speeds there's
a hand behind the camera man hand you
can go
yes okay
okay so what you're saying to me is that
whenever someone you're saying that
clients need to see something of a high
fidelity or kindly to see low fidelity
because then they understand it's going
to take longer to build see that that
sent like a workaround for a different
problem that's someone showing low
fidelity because it can't explain to the
client how long it's going to take to
actually build so that sounds more like
a communication problem than what you
should actually do with your user
experience but when it comes to little
fidelity the benefits of our that it's
throw away and it's fast high fidelity
takes longer to do so whenever you do
things a higher level of design is ready
to be built is ready to pastor developer
but you should be getting that feedback
much hair lair on if you're talking
about clients then you should be getting
the feedback for what you're building
and a medium to high fidelity stage if
you sure something to finish like I was
saying in my earlier example they
actually think that's what they're going
to get because the design hasn't touched
it yet that something is what you end up
building but my advice would always be
and what I just stated which is used a
little fidelity internally use it for
yourself it's not for shoes to other
people when you get to a medium or
you're iterating on that to look a
little better and it can look a little
better in like balsamic or any kind of
digital tools little fidelity I consider
to be paper medium I consider to be
balsamic or like lanes and boxes and
illustrator and when it comes to high
fidelity I consider that to be almost
finished designs in photoshop so i would
take the middle part and i will show
that clients that would be my advice hi
chris how does it have a question
what are you in your experience the
signals that tell you whether UX design
from a development perspective there are
other signals but from a UX designer
design is a throwaway or it can be
improved like what what's what are the
markers you
if every single user has turned brain to
you and said I don't understand what I'm
doing I don't understand what this
serves or what purposes is then that
would be a surefire saying that you need
to stop what you're doing because no one
is getting it the ones getting the idea
of the vision but if people are saying
oh I see it now i can get it comes down
to the feedback it comes in to
interpretation of the feedback that you
get so if you get some positive parts
inside the feedback then you can carry
on but if everything you're getting
comes back negative that would be the
point where i would say this is not
really going to work or they don't get
what i'm trying to do so maybe what
you've done doesn't quote doesn't go to
the vision of what you were trying to
create thank you you're welcome more
questions yeah so we philly at the end
when you finally get around to making
like an actual prototype because I i
follow this model before and I find it
quite waterfall like it gets to stage of
the bells and by the time you get to end
of the build everything's had to change
because of various things of this and I
tend to find when you get to stage where
you're making like a clickable prototype
these days most people can make it just
as fast in something like bit strut and
make something that's actually real I
most people have worked with in UX or
find that a lot better to do it that way
yeah actually make something real so
people can use a computer click around
as opposed to just a mud and what it
might be like yeah I'm with you there if
you're actually much more versatile you
have a dedicated UX professional that is
the way to go if you don't have that
then I would much recommend you don't
have to do a clickable prototypes you
can do them on paper before you start
the development cycle if you don't have
someone like me in your team but I work
in agile team so it's not this waterfall
we is an iterative process you do go
through in fact I've worked in link
teams before we are on your own even but
and the answer to your question is if
you have a dedicated UX person then what
you're describing is absolutely one
hundred percent too if you don't have a
dedicated person which is what this talk
is for then these steps will help you
keep things honest keep things good also
you can use topcoat staff bootstrap you
can use lots of things you can love you
lots of frameworks
we're not exclusive I I've got a
question shapes miss selfishly jump in
how do you feel mobile impacts this do
you guys do like mock up some wire
frames for like all the possible screen
sizes when you're in your building stuff
out and the answer is I generally do
depends on what you're building f it is
cross device if its mobile tablet
desktop then yes of course you have to
factor that in and there's actually
really cool things if you're working in
paper there's post-its I've now got the
mobile size because they understand that
people use them though whenever they're
wireframing so you can even get posted
some tablet and mobile now and you can
just draw them on and they're the right
size for you to work on so you don't
even need to like work out what the
sizes are anymore so the answer is yes
and there is lots of strategies and for
UX to work on which is mobile first
which is a popular one but I would
generally work if it's cross-device yes
of course I was working with the core
functionality would be in put that in
the smaller devices first but you've got
device appropriateness as well which is
some things are not appropriate per
device so for example if you're doing
I'll just give you a recent one loan
application forms not appropriate for
mobile however information on loan
application forms are more appropriate
tablet desktop so it's sometimes you
have to not always go well this is
essential for mobile but what's
appropriate per device as well and that
factors into the UX process too so I
don't know if that answers your question
or not totally ok cool more questions oh
yeah last last question I think last
question and I'll be out in the hallway
for any more questions if you want me to
look at anything I'm here to help you so
if you need any advice so you're talking
about the user personas and breaking
that down really on digging into who
your user basis do you have anything to
say about when you're seeking feedback
how best to or if it makes sense to go
after specific representatives from the
that user base yeah there is a more
involved process where you can go after
the segments that you've described you
can go after that 30 year old value
hunter for example or something that you
really want to go for and you have to
make your own judgment as to
you you categorize those people so yes
of course you will get better results if
you do that but it's better to get any
feedback than none so it's better to
just get some feedback than no feedback
no feedback is the death of whatever
you're doing but some feedback will help
you and even better than that is exactly
what you described which is targeted
feedback but that takes a long more
involved process and again if you don't
have a dedicated professional than any
feedbacks better than none awesome Thank
You Chrissy you're very welcome