so it's called jelly stains thoughts on
JavaScript Lisbon play so this is sort
of a a personal you actually you're
probably wondering with number one why
is this presentation called jelly stains
and why do I have pictures of zebras
hopefully by the end of the talk he'll
still be confused so this is sort of a
personal story on my own journey through
JavaScript Lisp and some some notions
about play I'm not going to spend that
much time in JavaScript this is Jay s
Kampf after all I'm gonna spend a little
bit of time on Lisp and then I'm going
to spend a lot of time on this this idea
of play so this talk is you might this
talk was sort of advertised as being
about closure script and I will show
some closure script but I think the talk
is about bigger ideas than enclosure
script in particular so I came to
JavaScript in 2005 I was living in New
York City I ended up doing some a lot of
front-end work in JavaScript I ended up
falling in love with the language as we
all know JavaScript was created by this
guy he took some interesting ideas from
a minimalist functional programming
language called scheme he took some some
ideas from a minimalist functional
programming language called self and he
took some syntax from this language
called Java which supposedly was
supposed to be the next big thing and
maybe it's turning out that on different
languages gonna be the next big thing
so as JavaScript developers on the front
end and increasingly on the back end
we're asked to solve very hard problems
I think I was very surprised when I was
doing sort of rich interfaces just how
hard front-end development really is so
we often grow tools to address
deficiencies in our tools I might be MIT
building libraries building frameworks
whatever but the big idea in this talk
is that programming languages themselves
are tools just like any other and we're
going to sort of look at the
implications of that so so the the big
idea here is you know that you know we
grow tools because we really can only
manage seven plus or minus two things in
our heads Alan Kay likes to talk about
this a lot I'm going to quote him quite
a few times so it's it's unfortunate
when tools and software methodologies
steal these precious seven plus or minus
two things because we can't focus on
making insanely great stuff so that
brings us Lisp I think
ashle Lisp is an insanely great idea I
had messed around scheme in 2003 but it
wasn't until summer of 2008 I was in
between client projects and I was like
I'm gonna really figure out what this
listing is about and so I spent three
months in my Brooklyn studio just
messing around with this so the list was
invented by John McCarthy in 1957 to
tackle the problem of artificial
intelligence I think he was a great
computer scientist I think still to this
day we haven't really fully understood
the implications of of what he invented
it's sad sad he passed away last year
and this this talk is sort of a bit of a
personal mission to make sure that
people don't forget the ideas that he's
contributed to our craft and art so this
is a page from the list 1.5 programmers
manual this is the bottom half of this
page is often celebrated by Alan Kay as
the Maxwell's equations of software
because of the bottom half of this page
is eval and apply and that's all that
you need to bootstrap lists that's it
we're done right so a lot of our tools
and a lot of the things that we use do
not have this level of clarity or
sickness or without sacrificing some
amount of power so John McCarthy was a
mathematician so he had a very different
take on programming languages and I
think a lot of us do so he understood
that we often want to run programs you
give an expression to the computer we
get a result you know add two numbers
get two but being a mathematician he
really realized that he wanted to
occasionally or often symbolically
manipulate the program right it wasn't
just good enough to ask the computer
what to do sometimes even sometimes we
want to take to an expression and and
modify the expression before we evaluate
it so a very basic thing is that is that
Lisp as is home iconic right the source
is defined with his own data structures
so we can modify the syntax using the
same functionality we use at runtime so
quote here says don't don't run this
give us the list that has the symbol
plus and some numbers in it and this is
a this is I think a very profound end up
insanely great idea so another Island
key analogy is that I think if we if we
lack these really good deep ideas I
think software development ends up
looking a lot like this I really love
JavaScript I think JavaScript is great
but I think still to this day a lot of
projects architectural II resembled
it's sort of a brute-force kind of thing
we don't have the insanely great thing
to sort of a design better software Alan
Kate
you know points out that an insanely
great idea was the arch right this
radically changed what we could do with
art with our materials and the kind of
ideas that we could have so thinking
about this got me thinking about you
know how is it that we come to insanely
great ideas I think there are many paths
I can't assume to know how they
everybody arrives at them but for me I
think a big way is is just by playing
around just just by playing and so this
takes us to the final and sort of
longest part of this talk which is about
play so this this part of the talk sort
of starts for me about a year and a half
ago I was in raleigh-durham at the first
closure conference and I recall being
tired and falling asleep and I just
cracked open this book called the reason
schemer and I wouldn't be here today if
I hadn't opened this book it had it
really influenced a lot of my thinking
so before we dive into that and we are
going to dive into that I want to talk
about two ideas I think really framed
this this section the first is this
image which was making the rounds on the
internet a couple months ago and I love
this for me it's sort of encapsulate so
much of my philosophy about software
development so everybody knows that Lego
was Lego was selling these these these
pre-made frameworks that you could these
sets that you would buy but of course
that's not how anybody actually played
with them you get a couple of sets they
go in a big box and when you play with
Legos you dump the whole thing on the
floor and then you actually learn how do
I put something together right that's
when we actually learn how do we
architect something and play is often
really messy I love the fact that this
image has all these little pieces on the
floor right this is how we play with
Legos Legos isn't the pre-built stuff
the other big inspiration for this
section of the talk is this quote by
Richard Feinman so there are many ways
to play and jazz comp is amazing it's
just what people do with JavaScript
blows my mind it's great but I think
it's also important to really think
about playing with this really the
bottom level the substrate I think it's
interesting and curious that human
language is so flexible we're constantly
growing it naturally yet we tend to use
languages which eventually become
obsolete because the syntax isn't really
again growable so fineman's quote goes
like this then I had another thought
physics disgusts me a bit now I used to
enjoy doing physics why did I enjoy it I
used to play with it I used
do whatever I felt like doing it didn't
have to do with weather was important
for the development of nuclear physics
but whether it was interesting and
amusing for me to play with when I was
in high school I'd see water running of
a faucet growing narrower and wonder if
I could figure out what determines that
curve I found it was rather easy to do I
didn't have to do it it wasn't imputed
important for the future of science
somebody else had already done it that
didn't make any any difference I'd
invent things and play with things for
my own entertainment and I think as
working programmers I think we need to
make more time to do this kind of thing
that he's talking about so of course as
it turns out clay is actually often very
pragmatic there's often very serious
things that that that come out of play
so it's often play has really positive
consequences so I'm going to switch
gears I'm going to talk about there's
sort of two sections on closure script
I think clojurescript actually offers
quite a bunch of nice things for
JavaScript developers and I'll
demonstrate a couple of those I can't
talk as much about closure script as I'd
like because I don't have a ton of time
so switch over can we sorry okay
all right so here we have sublime text -
and you don't need Emacs to play around
with a list so here I can type here I
can type some expressions sure it's
alright
okay so so I can type some s expressions
and we see that they evaluate that's
cool so what's interesting is I can also
place my cursor right here at the end of
a form and notice again this is Lisp so
if Lisp oriented list oriented so I here
I can actually grab what looks to be
like a body tag and it prints at the
repple I can actually extract all all
the nodes out of that out of the a body
tag right here in my repple notice that
it's printing we're not in we're not in
a browser so something strange is
happening here and what's happened is
that closure script actually gives us
back one of the most powerful thing that
javascript has which is that you can
modify types that you don't own so
somebody created to type and you can
modify that nobody does this anymore in
JavaScript because it's dangerous for
Interop so closure solves this problem
in a fundamental way by namespacing
everything your modest your
modifications live in a namespace so now
we have suddenly have the ability to
bring the Dom and all this all all this
complexity outside our software back
under our control so I'm gonna pull back
the curtain here for a second
so I'm actually running live against
Chrome I can whoops and get a reference
to the box I can change its height I can
make it blue you can make it red I can
make it a hundred pixels so this this
should remind you a bit of the Brett
Victor inventing on principle talk which
if you're a small talk program or a lisp
programmer
it's basically old hat it's something
that we've been talking about for forty
years now right there should be no
distance between your ideas and the
software that you want to develop at all
so we we saw that a little bit of a demo
again I can't I don't have time to get
into all the cool things that closures
trip pads I look in I love JavaScript
use JavaScript all the time but
clojurescript has lots of neat things
and we avoid some annoyances some of
these things are less what like for
example zero and the null the empty
string or not fall see we have let
scoping today even in loops dynamic this
is not really a problem in in in a
language like closure script because
it's based around functions and it is a
sort of object-oriented but this always
gets passed as a legitimate argument
it's immutable by default and there's a
lot of active work in the closure script
community to make these immutable data
structures very efficient so I don't
have to worry about somebody changing
my model or my data structure without me
knowing it the others that the other big
idea here is often people rely on
libraries like underscore to provide
some sensible no-scent notion of
iteration which doesn't really exist in
JavaScript so clojurescript
solves this problem and it solves it for
native types in a safe way the other
thing we have are real namespaces so
there's a sort of pattern which I which
we have we have to do in JavaScript even
though it's annoying which is we create
these function closures and we put all
our stuff inside to avoid polluting the
global namespace there's no such thing
as the global namespace in closure
script so you don't need to do this in
fact hiding things and functions would
destroy the interactive programming that
I demonstrated the other important thing
which I'm going to show the implications
of is that we have macros so a big idea
here is that the language is global we
don't have to wait for a committee or a
beat at be DFL to decide that some
features should or should not be in the
language so this takes me to the I think
the more playful part of the talk the
part of the talk where I don't even
understand what the implications are so
this is the reason schemer I was written
by Daniel Freedman William Byrd and all
that key slid off it came out in 2005 so
I found this book to be pretty shocking
because it's only 187 pages long that's
a bit of a tough read surprisingly if
you think you're a clever programmer I
double dare you to get this book and try
to understand it at the end you will
understand and it's pretty profound but
they show you how to basically create
most of prologue and about 200 lines of
scheme and not only do they do that
but the prologue that they show you how
to build is actually very efficient so
you know there's a lot of talk these
days about functional programming and
auditorium programming and as JavaScript
developers we sort of get the benefits
of both worlds right javascript is this
nice language hybrid language where you
can engage in both philosophies about
software development I think what we've
we've lost sight of is that logic
programming is actually really powerful
a lot of these things that seem esoteric
to us or seem like in the realm of
experts things like type inference are
actually really almost trivial to
explain once you understand logic
programming and just to show you that
that's true I'm going to sort of rewind
the clock so things like type reference
are really they're all problems of a
similar domain so we can go back to
December 17th 1962 to this time Life
magazine and they had this
said who owns the zebra and there are 15
sentences in this in this magazine and
you're supposed to solve this puzzle the
sentences are like this there are five
houses the Englishman lives in the red
house the Spaniard owns the dog coffee
is drunk in the green house the Ukranian
drinks tea the green house is
immediately to the right of the ivory
house the old gold smoker owns snails
and so on and it ends with the question
now who drinks water and who owns the
zebra so this problem is defined in such
a way that there are five houses and the
five houses of five properties the first
one is what's the nationality the second
is what are they smoke the third is what
do they drink the fourth is the pet that
they have and the last is the color of
the house so as Peter Norbeck points out
given that combination there are 24
billion candidate solutions right so in
his book the paradigms of artificial
intelligence programming he showed in
1992 how to build a prologue in common
lisp how to make it efficient and he
showed that oh on hardware at the time i
can solve this problem in seventeen and
a half seconds which at that time was
probably really really shocking that you
could solve such a hard constraint
problem in in 17 seconds i'm gonna show
you the we can solve it way faster and
we can do this right in chrome oops so
we're back here just scroll down so we
sort of left the clojurescript world
this library that i built is actually
called core logic it's a faithful and
movement implementation of the system
found in the reason schemer which is
mini cameron and so this is where macro
is really like shine because i'm able to
take a very customized syntax this is
not even just a DSL this is an entire
embedded programming language paradigm
stuck right into closure script so here
i can basically define the rules of
verbatim from the from that page right i
can say i can represent the five houses
as a vector which is closure scripts
versions of arrays i can use blanks for
the things i don't know the answers to
so this first line says we know that
milk is consumed in the the middle house
the first house is occupied denote by
the norwegian next to their own
norwegian is the blue house to the right
of the ivory house is the green house
the english man lives in the red house
the cool smoker lives in the yellow
house and so on
you notice the answer returns very
quickly and we see those in Norwegian
drinks water and that the Japanese
person owns a zebra how quickly it's
about 48 milliseconds and I've
benchmarked this in all the night leaves
it's about the same regardless of where
you're running into WebKit nightly or
Firefox nightly which is pretty cool
so you know the first question you
should be asking yourself what is it a
toy well the first thing I said was the
constraint thing that we're solving is
so so it's so similar to type inference
so it's already the type of thing that
we're already doing and this other thing
that we should think about is what did
McCarthy say isn't it really beautiful
when we can have both the execution like
look at our programs immediately execute
and also has things that we manipulate
so what if you start manipulating our
programs with the system like this
what's possible so maybe it's a toy or
maybe it's a deeply concurrent tool for
reasoning about the meaning of our
programs I actually don't know the
answer to that yet I've been working on
playing really literally playing with
the system for a year and a half now and
it's been fun watching other people see
what does this let us do that we
couldn't do before so again this is this
whole sort of experiment for me just
made me realize that we really do need
to play more and I put this talk to
they're just sort of you know encourage
other people to play more as well so
again JavaScript is fantastic but I
think as programmers we need to think
about more about languages what's
possible in different languages which
one of those things do we want to bring
to JavaScript or you know maybe we want
to program in a language like closure
script there's a really great service
that I recommend it's on Heroku now call
him Mara which provides a closure script
repple so you can try a lot of the
things that I've shown right in your web
browser which is pretty cool
so some closing notes so above all
really really this is about community I
mean none of the things that I that I
showed I came up with it was all
everybody else's years of research and I
said wouldn't it be awesome if I could
do this in a book in a web browser so I
really loved this photograph this a year
and a half ago I I didn't even know what
logic programming was I never read the
reason schemer a year later at the
second closure conference William Byrd
and and Dan Friedman the authors of the
book came because I emailed him and said
hey I implement your thing in closure
and they were like what the heck is that
that's cool and then and so they came
and they want
talk about it Dan Freeman meeting Dan
Freeman was particularly cool because
you know he's been programming list for
about forty years now and you know
that's longer than I've been alive to
the to the left is Azure is this guy
Ambrose who was this young guy and and
this is another sort of aspect of
communities so I was working on this for
a long time and pretty much everybody in
the closure committee world was like
you're nuts
we're functional programmers who cares
about logic and so Ambrose was this guy
who was in doing Java at university but
he was curious about closure it was like
logic programming that sounds neat and
so that actually kept me sort of going
through and finishing this project so I
think community is really not about
specific languages specific tools but
it's really about a community of shared
ideas and and playing with stuff so
right when it gives you think some
people first off I want to thank rich
Hickey for making such a neat neat list
I think it has a lot of affordances that
were used to whether you're coming from
JavaScript Python or Ruby or some other
modern programming language definitely
thank Dan Friedman and William bird they
sort of got me playing with realizing
there's a lot more left to play with in
computer science
definitely the closure community for
putting up with my my logic programming
rants and I've definitely want to thank
the JavaScript community for inviting me
to come here and talk about this stuff