thanks guys is this everyone can hear me
fine yep good so my name is Steven and
let's talk about some JavaScript flow
control with set timeout set of media
and process next tick and I'd like to
point out i started this talk with this
amazing slide background it's just like
it looks so professional right my goal
was do the whole thing like that and
that didn't happen so a little bit about
me I'm from node Orlando I have a kid I
live in SF now i really like javascript
because it that it's awful if you watch
the wat videos or any time like you're
you know trying to debug node which is
sometimes impossible and you're like i
just think i hate this thing
that's why i like it i don't i don't
know why i moved here originally to work
with CJ she abandoned me kick cambridge
also abandoned me i love those guys
right now i'm typing computer things at
Netflix and and I'm very nervous and
later on you can ask me why I gave this
talk at bay node because Ross k said hey
anyone want to talk about process next
tick and I said I have no idea what that
is but sure and I gave the talk and he
said I think if you polish that talk up
you would have a really great talk so
the plan was that I would do that and
then present it here and this is not the
greatest talk in the world like we had
originally planned this is just a
tribute so let's get started it's
dangerous to flow control alone like
let's take this set timeout concept look
don't take set timeout you heathen
dinosaurs you don't use that for flow
control in JavaScript the way that we
have these like really powerful tools to
do so we're actually not really going to
talk about that will show why it's bad a
little bit later but let's talk about
set immediate like recursive deferral
with set of media this is kind of a new
thing that's come up recently in node
not super new but if you guys all want
to just take some time to read all of
this there may be a test later I'm
kidding there's the important part is
the while the order is preserved for
execution of anything that you use set
immediate for other i/o events may fire
between any two scheduled immediate
callbacks and I've got some code
it will go over for that but the
important thing to remember is that set
immediate you should use that if you
want to cue the function behind whatever
I owe events callbacks that are already
in the event queue so I've got this a
couple code examples here by the way I
would like to take a second to thank
node botanist for loaning me a laptop I
had a huge fiasco where I thought
December 10th was Thursday all week so
I'm standing in line to to go to Los
Gatos to work and then I'm realizing
like oh I have to be in oakland today
not los gatos so I was not prepared for
this so stack overflows if you've seen
them like we have a real simple function
here it's just going to recurse a whole
bunch of times and then when it does
throw we've got this process that on
uncaught exception that's a really good
code practice I'm told and then this
particular error throws what I like to
call nearly perfect messaging I think
that's TM so you might yell at me later
Isaak will sing so if we fire this up in
the console here it recursos a whole
bunch of times and then it just says hey
range error maximum call stack size
exceeded and you're like great that is
actually nearly perfect messaging I know
exactly what to do with that right and
another thing that we can do here with
the get my bearings here real quick
continuous compute so stack overflows
are bad in general I think I just heard
somebody from and yet talking about how
they were having problems with that and
I do apologize and learning how to use
this new computer there we go is it
going to go to someone there we go so
let's say that we have this this this
problem in our in our application where
we want to be able to respond to HTTP
requests but we also have to do some
like long-lived compute function if we
recursively call this compute function
like we're just going to get the same
thing we're just going to get a stack
overflow it's going to block we're not
going to be able to respond to those
HTTP functions so if you wanted to you
could do like a set time out and just
say like hey every you know 1000
milliseconds run this compute function
that's going to do some
thing in the meantime you can answer you
know HTTP requests and do continuous
compute here you'll see over there we're
running our server and it's like kind of
got this ongoing thing and we're still
able to respond to these requests that's
like probably the worst and most
inefficient way of doing that so I'm
really struggling with the alt tabbing
here we go I turn go back over here and
kill this and I feel like it goes back
to keynote when I really want sublime so
if we use a process that next tick like
it used to work a long time ago it is it
doing that that's not just like me and
being jittery or so we'll go back to
sublime and then I term there we go and
let's restart this continuous compute
and we don't we don't even get anywhere
so it's like oh hey by the way you're
done like you use too many process next
sticks and I just don't want to do this
but it gives you some nearly perfect
messaging that says like you should be
using set immediate in this version of
node because we're not going to be using
process next tick that way and I'll show
you an example of what we would use
process next stick for later on the way
that we actually want to do this so we
got this set immediate where the server
is going to be allowed to work as much
as it can but we do want to allow it to
respond to these requests you'll see
over here we're still able to ping the
server but obviously it's just like
firing off a whole bunch of times over
there so we're we're no longer blocked
by by that process in the event loop
that's the general purpose for set of
media and process next tick now we'll go
back to our slides here
and we'll get into the actual
differences here between process next
tick using call backs versus set
immediate so we're going to use process
next tick to effectively cue the
function at the head of the event queue
so that it executes immediately after
current function completes so in the
tinkering file here there's a couple
different examples that I've got and
right now we've got this these two
different functions here one is going to
be maybe synchronous sometimes and one
is going to definitely be synchronous
all the time because we're going to use
process next tick and then a couple of
functions that we call in different
orders so right now if I call maybe sink
and I pass in false and give it that
callback and then I call bar does anyone
know what the terminal output here is
going to be
ok
I thought that would be a good play on
the hold ojs thing and then look the
more I read it I'm like loads d loads
that doesn't even really you know like
anyways so we get this deal edge and
then loads just like oh hey I fired and
you're like okay nice so what happens if
we change the arguments and now are our
statement it basically changes the way
that the function is going to run they
come out in a different order and you're
like a weight so programmatically I want
to change like some logic I didn't want
to change the order in which the program
ran and that's why you would use process
next tick so as you can see here in the
definitely sink what we're doing is
we're basically just saying hey like we
we want this to perform the same way
every time so if we come down here and
we pass in false Hey look it came out in
the order that we might expect and if we
pass in true comes out in the same order
so it starts behaving a little bit more
the way that our end users of this API
would expect and it's going to be
consistent and that is actually where I
get into like what is this what is this
sorcery and there's like again there's
really long thing that you can read on
stackoverflow when I first dug into this
there's like a whole lot of like older
node stuff and newer node stuff and they
kind of give misinformation but this
stack overflow post seemed to have a
pretty decent amount of good answers why
should you use this this actually comes
from Isaac's blog post which he points
to another blog post and he very
adamantly says like four or five times
in one paragraph go read the other post
right now you absolutely have to read
that do you still kind of stand by that
or yeah so you should probably go read
both of these if you haven't i'm going
to assume that most of you have at this
point if you have an API that takes a
callback and sometimes it's called
immediately and other times it's called
at some point in the future then you
render any code that's using this API
and pow
symbol to reason about and you cause the
release of zal go I actually don't
really understand what that last line
means but I think it's bad I think it's
really bad so oh and here's a note
botanist see if i can not expose
anything that I'm not supposed to hear
this so when I was digging into this
talk the first time at begnaud I started
to think like well this is like really
you know loads and D loads yeah perfect
it makes sense it's a real world
application right you guys do that all
the time that's like wait nobody does
that like what's a an actual example of
what we can do you know to to take
advantage of these when we're
constructing our our modules so that
people can use these and not have to
worry about how it's going to perform
later just based on on the logic
conditions but they just know it's going
to perform the same way every time and
this example is the one that I landed on
so we have two constructor classes here
and they perform entirely different and
you probably run into this I would think
at some point but the the cigarettes one
is really just a constructor and we call
that we say hey we want a new sink and
it's going to say hey I'm gonna park
some options for that and then I'm going
to initialize and immediately after that
it does its initialize things and it
says hey I'm going to omit some events
and and then I'm going to be done in
this example so if we run this block of
code here that says hey you know I want
a new sink and then I want to listen to
the data event and I want to listen to
the end event when we actually run
I need to block this out there we go
we're getting back to the wonky behavior
so we were on that block of code the the
other logs that came out for what we
thought would listen to those events
never actually never actually get there
and I ran into this a few times and I
had no idea why I was like we I thought
I attached an event matter and then
sometimes it would work later on it was
like okay so it's it works sometimes I
don't understand why but the async
module that we wrote here does one thing
different instead of initializing right
away it just says hey by the way I'll
finish up my initial at some point you
go ahead and finish everything else that
you wanted to do and then when you get
back you know process next tick I'll get
my initializing done there so we have
the same block of code for our end users
of this module but they actually get to
use immediately what they would want
programmatically so you can see right
here like it initializes the module fire
some initial events and we capture those
events later on in the code and then you
know we can we can actually use the
module at this point has anyone ran into
that when they're using like third party
stuff where you try to attach one maybe
two a couple i did scratch my head for
you know like ours like I don't
understand what's going on here so and
since I'm doing the whole like I'm
nervous and I'm going super fast and
we're all ending through or like we're
almost done don't worry I did do some
micro benchmarks there's apparently some
performance benefits that you can get
here obviously micro benchmarks are
super important and you can learn a lot
about programming concepts if you only
do micro benchmarks
let's see here i'll just show you these
and i'll show you the results but
essentially what we do here is I just
use a for loop and either you process
that next tick or set immediate or set
timeout to show you you know what the
performance values were there and it
came out again like really super
important micro benchmark information
yeah that's that's useful right what
I've heard though is that said of media
actually can be a little bit more
performant when used properly I've had
some coding challenges in the past where
they just use that to like overload a
whole bunch of stuff that you do and you
have to kind of like you know positive
stream and all of that but you can you
can really wind up the node process with
with set media if you use it effectively
so yeah that's that's all I got
javascript flow control it's it's kind
of complex if you use these concepts use
them right you read the right blog posts
I think you'll do it right if you guys
want you can follow me at spr j RX on
twitter i say a lot of really stupid
things and they're not that funny and
i'm learning how to behave better but or
you can check out my website at stephen