hey so my name is Dave Ulmer I with this
framework called Joe because I figured
there weren't enough mobile frameworks
out there in the world right now based
on html5 actually sorta development on
this about a year ago so it's been kind
of percolating behind the scenes you can
applaud early this that's okay that's
fine okay so yeah I've been kind of
lurking in the JavaScript community for
for some time now so this is my first
open source JavaScript project mostly I
get paid by people to do things that you
know stay proprietary and hidden behind
the scenes see I've been programming a
while pretty pretty much a geek so I'll
just move on so yeah what is joe joe is
a application framework for mobile
devices most of the cool smart phones
today have either webview with web kit
or something very much WebKit like so i
took a look around at some of the older
frameworks that have been kicking around
some of the things that I've done in the
past and kind of wondered what would an
application framework specifically a UI
framework look like if you just started
from scratch and said well if I don't
have to support IE six seven or eight
you know can you write a smaller
framework can you leverage some of the
cool stuff that's into css3 and all this
thing that we're calling html5 n turns
out you can end up with a pretty small
library so Jo has a pretty robust set of
widgets a simple data layer and gzip to
minified it's kicking around 12 k and if
you want to do how to work with
basically anything except IE anything
before ie9 it's actually working value 9
pretty well these days it's designed to
work with phonegap so how many people
are familiar with with phonegap for
mobile development all right okay
brian's brand arose very happy so Joe
was designed to sit for mobile
applications on top of the phonegap so
as you may know with phonegap
basically what it gives you is sort of a
baseline compatibility layer between all
the different mobile OS is out there but
what it doesn't ring to the party is
sort of all the cool native like widgets
and controls for for putting a nap
together so Joe is designed to sort of
sit on top of that or the great layer so
no this is you know a pretty typical
block diagram of you know the
architecture pretty simple Joe is a very
lightweight framework so you don't have
to use it for everything if you want to
fill it with the Dom directly because
you have some last-minute hacky thing
that you have to do for your app to get
it out the door go right ahead Joe Sri
they're not going to get in the way it
has no other no dependencies on any
other libraries so the big plus there is
is that you don't run into any
incompatibilities so if you want to mix
in other lives to get your app together
Joe's not going to get in your way if
you're using phonegap with iOS and
Android basically for those that haven't
used phonegap allows you to create
installable native ish mobile apps use
html5 technology so on these platforms
iOS and Android phone taps will give you
sort of a web view and then sort of a
native app wrapper and then inside that
webview you can put your your JavaScript
html5 CSS app and then some other mobile
platforms so I work at HP that's my day
job how many people are familiar with
webos okay cool cool that's actually
yeah all right that's a lot of hands
cool so let's go about webos is
something like PhoneGap is there mostly
as a compatibility layer webos native
apps are basically web apps or at least
they use web technology so kind of
another flashback to when the iphone
came out i was a big fan mostly because
apple got up in front of everybody and
said hey does anybody remember what they
said right right right web app so
basically Apple said the web is the SDK
this is you know new breed of smartphone
you don't
special SDK all you need our web apps so
it was all on board with that and got
well underway writing if you absolutely
sort of came back a year later and said
well web does the SDK except for this
new thing that we're calling the actual
sdk for for apple so I still bear maybe
a little bit of bitterness towards that
and so when webos came around and
actually said the web is the sdk and
then actually you know came through on
that promise that definitely attracted
me over to HP to work on that Joe is
also open source has a freebsd license
so you can pretty much do anything you
want with it and i'm really hoping to
actually get a lot more code
contributors i've had a few so far who
have mostly done a few bug fixes out a
few pieces here and there but Joe is has
reached the size where you know to sort
of get it out there and get it to beta
and have a go live definitely like to
find a couple more folks who are you
know really enthusiastic about the
approach that I'm taking with his
library and have a little spare time on
their hands to to chip in so I'm going
to go over real quick the the basic
philosophy behind Joe because it is it's
a little different so just sort of show
of hands like how much how many people
are familiar with say sencha touch okay
it's not bad sencha touch is relatively
new what about jQuery Mobile okay
actually about the same about 5050
between the two so to me these sort of
represent sort of the two polar extremes
of what we have out there right now with
sort of html5 based mobile technologies
we've got jQuery on the one side which
jquery mobile does pretty much you know
what you created except they have like
sort of a mobile widget library laying
on top of it and you know if you code in
jquery mobile you spend a lot of time
more on the HTML side and then you sort
of add the javascript kind of as you go
which is that's so that's one approach
and then on the other end of the stream
you've got something like sencha touch
which is similar to you say
sprout core or even going back to dojo
which is more JavaScript centric so
using javascript to creat your app the
fact that there's sort of a dominant in
there is sort of sort of a means to the
end rather than than a focus so Joe
leans a little bit more towards the
sencha touch side but I can do this in a
second here but yeah I'm going to skip a
slide and come back so what a lot of
these frameworks that are very
javascript heavy tend to do is come to
come to the play come to our platform
saying well javascript parts of it are
kind of hard you know prototypal
inheritance is tough and gosh you know I
we come from a better language that has
proper classes and things like that so a
lot of frameworks will create these
really sort of intricate patterns and
machinations to sort of create a what I
call a sort of a language experience
inside JavaScript you know these
libraries do some cool stuff but that
that's never really set too well with me
I happen to actually love JavaScript at
its core it's my personal belief that if
WebKit were more up to snuff today we
really wouldn't need sort of any UI
frameworks whatsoever and even though I
wrote 1 i'm i'm actually genuinely
hoping at some time in in the next five
years or so well i'll be using vapor jas
basically to get our apps done so
between now and absolute adoption of
vapor jas we have something like Joe Joe
has a lot of the things that I like one
of the things that I really appreciate
about jQuery is method chaining took me
a little bit to really enjoy that way of
doing things but it's very handy i also
have a constructor nesting in here now
i'll show that off in a minute when we
get to the code stuff but basically a
lot of stuff that's in Crockfords you
know javascript the good parts show of
hands everyone should know this book
right
javascript a good parts okay yeah so all
of the good parts stuff Joe is pretty
much in line with i agree with about
ninety-five percent of what is in
Crockfords book and so a few old
favorites like observer pattern which is
all over yui particularly yui too and
for those folks who are big fans of
binds i support it if you don't want to
do that all of the event handling you
can pass in a context s in an optional
parameter so joe tries to be pretty
accommodating so in addition to not
trying to fix javascript you know rather
than having a bunch of Java scripts you
animate things on the screen hey require
css3 use the transformations and the
transitions that are built into it and
the reason that's important particularly
would go with mobile is you have slower
machines they have less memory available
for you to do funky things like manually
move things around not to mention some
of us is out there kind of throttle the
the timer interval that you can use in
your apps so you might find that you can
only move things you know ten times a
second for example if you're too you
know manually go through and move things
around yourself another goal with Joe is
uh keep the code light is absolutely
small as possible without making it
completely unreadable so the car service
coming up I like to think if Joe were a
person Joe would be Indiana Jones
basically all the cool stuff you can
think about Indiana and then then maybe
yeah maybe that'll get you sort of in
the mindset basically face you know like
in the smart flexible lightweight and
dress up if he needs to you know anyone
wear a tux you know if the occasion you
know requires same thing with Joe if you
want your app to look extremely you know
special and yours and branded and all
that other cool marketing speak just go
to the CSS and tweak it you know make it
look the way that you want you don't
have to just use all the
default styles that come with all the
widgets and get the job done again as
quickly as possible so having said that
and this goes back to what I was talking
about a little bit earlier today it's
more like young Indiana Jones basically
showing a lot of promise and i think
when we get into the code and some of
the examples you can definitely see that
it's it's off to a good start a little
bit rough around the edges again
definitely trying to run up some more
code participation in this to help take
it right now it's pre-beta so at least
take a debate and hopefully get it
shippable okay we'll do a quick
comparison so this is the obligatory you
know size comparison chart and for those
of you who are not in a food coma
because we just ate lunch may notice
something mix little fishy here this is
using my favorite size comparison metric
which is the number of bytes that it
takes in the name of the framework so in
this case you can see Joe only takes two
bytes or two characters for the Unicode
folks xui very lightweight takes 30 5
and on down now I think Joker emo
jquery-mobile would have been a lot
smaller if they left the word mobile off
of it the same thing was with sencha
touch but in all seriousness so this is
a bit a bit more us here in comparison
this is sort of give you kind of a
mental map if you're familiar with the
mobile framework landscape that's out
there so on the top of the chart we have
more more minimal sorts of frameworks
in-depth oh and and Xu I are sort of
what I would consider to be sort of a
jquery light they're very very small and
if what you want to do is manipulate the
Dom sort of by hand in your JavaScript
these are fantastic libraries for doing
that across platform and then sort of on
the opposite end of the spectrum you
know you've got to essentia touch sprout
for dojo mobile s come out recently they
tend to be a bit bigger
they tend to be a bit more ambitious as
far as what they're trying to do and
they tend to sort of take the approach
of here's how your app is laid out and
sort of inject your your logic into our
framework so they tend to use the word
framework very seriously I tend to use
it more in terms of features rather than
trying to direct the way that that you
code your a pub so I like to think of
Joe sort of occupies kind of a sweet
spot between those two spectrums and
then over here you've got a jQuery
Mobile jQuery Mobile is is a bit bigger
than something like Zeppo and xui but
they're trying to do a lot more they're
trying to support you know not just mart
phones but you know feature phones and
not just installed apps but you know the
browser's on these different phones
which can vary wildly in quality but
again they have a very different
approach in the way they do that so
anyway move on and so let's get into
some code examples this is actually a
really terrible example but it gives you
an idea of you know how where you would
start with Jill basically you're setting
up an empty index HTML you're loading in
the CSS and then if you have application
CSS on top of that you load that to you
load in the framework and then you've
code up your app which is pretty simple
it's like when you example you'll notice
I'm using the new keyboard I happen to
like it I happen to like prototypical
inheritance there's a some really nice
built-in stuff in JavaScript that deals
with its its natural way of handling
well not really classes but classes and
inheritance so I'm a firm believer that
if you're writing JavaScript you
shouldn't break things like instance of
which can be very very useful so I'm
going to pop out of this and into an
actual editor
and while enduring that do we have any
any game throwing like a couple of quick
questions if anybody has it has one not
yet okay you want to see the code first
I understand yeah slides are not enough
okay so and by the by all this stuff so
I don't I didn't know how good our Wi-Fi
would be actually it says I have to say
this is bet one of the better Wi-Fi
situations I've seen in a conference
like in the last year so that's really
cool ya round of applause for the Wi-Fi
but i am prepared so if for some reason
you can't get it for whatever reason i
have flash drives to pass round with all
of this stuff on it okay cool so let's
pop up say a really simple sample
everybody read that do we need to bump
the font size up a bit okay someone said
yes so I'm going to comply how about
that readable anyone can't read put your
hands up awesome so they can either read
it perfectly or the too embarrassed to
put their hands up either way it's good
for me okay cool so here we have sort of
the shell and this is an old example so
those of you who are actually paying
attention don't look at what I just
deleted the old doc type for a one
strict good old 401 strict right yeah
okay so we don't need that anymore so I
have a lot of funky stuff in here which
I've set up in this index.html basically
all of these meta tags here are for iOS
and a couple of them for android and
webos actually uses them to this sets up
the viewport and make sure that the app
actually shows up at the proper
resolution and all that type of good
stuff
so we have the standard style sheet with
joe i have a special style seed sheet
that i did for the sample app which are
show you in a second and i'm going to
move this guy up here and for those who
actually are using iOS and want to take
this from a web app and make it a an
offline running web app yeah there you
go it's a little icon to do that so
anyway just tagging on to unload here
because I'm lazy and I'm calling my app
load and then I've got the jo Jo script
and then I've got the YQL GI script so
the index HTML page on that page but the
file is actually just sort of a sort of
an empty shell empty canvas and puts all
the pieces together and okay cool so
this is the actual business end of this
app the way that I chose to code this
one up is using sort of the the the
object literal or the singleton pattern
Joe doesn't really judge joe doesn't
really care how you write your
application if you want to do your app
all based on if you wanna make it
functional that's fine if you want to
use sort of this pattern that's fine if
you like the module pattern that's great
like Joe doesn't really care so as far
as hitting up your applications
architecture I mean that's up to you I
mean it's I really don't feel like it's
a frameworks business to tell you you
know how to put together your app I feel
very strongly about that so singer call
to the same called Joe load and then
I've got Joe has a built-in control
which makes a little bit easier to make
yql calls how many people for me with my
key well you know who's awesome query
language service you can shout and Cheer
because it is awesome yeah mallu okay
other for you so we've got two two boots
for that so what YQL does is it sort of
like sequel but for but for the web so
any sort of data that's out there
preferably XML assured or jasonich it
can sort of put them together data from
Desperate Reese resources put them
together into something that
your app can digest more easily so here
basically setting yql select and it is a
lot like sequel so select title from RSS
wear and I'm giving you this URL and RSS
happens to be a service it's a comes
bundled with YQL basically it'll pull
the data off of any RSS feed did you
give it and so this particular example
I'm doing sort of long-form so in other
words i'm sort of creating each element
as i go along and then putting them
together later again Joe doesn't care if
you want to do it sort of this way and
i'll show you a slicker way to do it in
a minute so here i'm creating a new list
widget so new Joe list and I'm passing
in yql Joe yql is a it's an extension of
a base class it's in Joe called Joe
datasource and what that does is
essentially basically two wraps an array
of objects of whatever that you want so
the list control happens to accept a
data source so in this case we're
passing in YQL and what that means is is
that whenever YQL the response goes out
and then comes back with the data this
control this list controller we've just
defined will get notified of that data
and then it will be told to present that
data the next line here we've got list
dot format item equals blah blah blah so
if you if you want to do this sort of
you know the right way you could create
your own application specific version of
Joe list which I'll show you how to do
it and second basically if you're
familiar with the extend method to send
JavaScript the good parts it's really
similar to that but if you're really
lazy you can just make a new Joe list
and then sort of over right it's it's a
form an item function and so the format
item method basically takes data from
each of the each of the array elements
and its job is to turn that into some
time
nodes or an HTML fragment for the list
view itself to turn around and present
pretty straightforward I've got a button
that we're creating you notice here
we're starting to get a little bit of a
little bit of our chaining so we've got
a new button we're giving it a title of
go and all these widgets have different
types of events that they that they
publish button has one called select
event so I'm going to subscribe to that
a select event and I'm going to tell it
whenever that happens I wanted to call a
method that's in my app called refresh
and because i don't really like buying
that much i'm going to pass along a
reference to this app object up here
even more lazy coding so adding to the
chain here i've got a set style so this
is an example of you know a lot of you
know the sort of foreign extreme of
widget sort of oriented frameworks they
don't really mess once you messing
around with sort of the nitty-gritty Dom
elements they want you to use their
widgets and do things the right way and
you know extend it and add stuff to it
and things like that Joe is perfectly
fine with letting you sort of fiddle
with things on the fly this in this
particular example this wouldn't exactly
be what you call production code but if
you're trying to put together a quick
prototype and you have to make a quick
tweak because someone from your product
team or you know your consultant your
client run walks by and says gosh what
would it look like if we change the
color blue you can do that really
quickly without having to fiddle with
your CSS okay so setting up a new button
so that's everything we need to do for
setting up the button we're setting up
just a empty variable right now for
input and this is an example of
constructor nesting that was talking
about so sort of like method chaining
in that it's a kind of slick it can look
really cool if you know what it's doing
and it can look mildly confusing if
you've never seen it before but the
advantage is is that you when you're
done you actually get a feel for the the
structure of your UI so this would be
something akin to if you did this with
the templating language or with straight
HTML you'd actually sort of see the
structure of you know what elements
contain what etc etc so here we're
creating a new screen screen this is a
defined by default to sort of fill the
interior area of whatever container it's
in so in this case we're actually just
filling the window itself whatever size
it may be we're creating a container
within it and then we have the same
called flex row so flexible x ro just
uses the flexible box model so again one
of the nice things about doing mobile
apps is you tend to have more feature
support for a lot of the newer css3 and
things like that doing the input and
again another little site style just for
fun and lists so if we look at this main
thing Joe screen will see that we're
passing in really what this is is just
an array there's an array of different
widgets that are being passed in so I'll
show you real quick what this looks like
okay i'm going to rescind the phrase
real quick and just downgraded to
shortly okay okay cool so we open this
up and we get something pretty simple we
don't have any scrollers set up so it's
using whatever native stroller you
happen to have on your system so if
you're setting this up say on iOS inside
a one webpage you just have you know
your page which is sort of scroll from
any and as you can see in the browser
we're just using the native scroller
really doesn't do much beyond that
allows you to change this who has an RSS
feed they don't mean to pull up short
has to be short what shorter this was a
bad idea i can't type any of these
things okay i'm just get that yes
basically give it a RSS feed it runs
through yql using the joe yql wrapper
class that we have and then pushes it
through DUI that we have defined so
that's a pretty simple example any
questions so far in this one because it
had introduced a lot of joe joe isms and
yet okay you want to see more code I get
it all right
so this is the sort of old kitchen sink
sample and if you notice of doing this
we're actually writing mobile apps right
now even though we're sitting inside the
browser the nice thing about that if
anyone who's done mobile app development
debugging on device or even an emulator
can be challenging particularly in some
cases using web-based technology
actually even getting console.log to
come out and see what's going on much
less being able to step through and
debug things so the nice thing is is
that you can get your app most of the
way done inside the browser and then use
the debugger that's built into Chrome or
Safari Firefox okay so this is a pretty
simple sort of kitchen sink you know so
we've got our little physics based stuff
all that's done with css3 and really all
that Joe is doing is altering the class
name of the elements that are being
scrolled around the big advantage with
that is well one using css3 it's going
to in many cases use hardware
acceleration it's built on to the device
so you're gonna get a lot smoother
action out of it and the other thing too
is is that you can alter the way the
physics sort of that you set up in the
scroller by tweaking the CSS rather than
digging around in your JavaScript so
this page it shows off some of the
different widgets this is like a
pulldown widget this is sort of a toggle
on or off this is a pulldown it has you
know arbitrary fields whatever you want
to put in it we've got buttons etc etc
this one looks rather boring unless you
see what it's doing underneath what this
is doing is it's loading in HTML
snippets from another place so if you
wanted to say do help system you
basically give it an HTML file and tell
the to render as one of these cards so
back up a little bit here
options basically he fills it up however
you want text fields work pretty much
like you you'd expect and all of the
stuff is the mobile and skinnable
completely in css3 for the main project
CSS for Joe I use less CSS anybody from
a row that one it's kind of like kind of
like SAS okay so some hands I assist CSS
compiler makes it a little bit easier to
do things like themes and such
expandable text area blah blah blah
fairly simple table control basically
has event handlers for when the user
interacts with it like as a tap on a
cell and such like that you can set up a
you can subscribe to that event with any
methods that you want you uses a an
event model similar to Yui to which is
sort of the observer pattern so you can
have as many controls there's many
arbitrary hunks of your code subscribing
to any anything that you want basically
and you can sort of chain up behaviors
based on that here's an example of using
flexbox type stuff do you like say it
the TV remote app ignore this part down
here and then this is the example of an
on-demand view again this page is kind
of boring unless you know what it's
doing behind the scenes which I'll show
you real quickly so Joe has a sort of a
convenience wrapper for defining
something like a card view or a set of
UI widgets without actually having to
instantiate them until you need them and
so I'll show you that in a second none
first pop-ups you have to have pop-ups
in any library alright so let's going to
the code I'm actually not going to do
the whole code for this because there's
kind of a bunch but I'm a touch on some
of the more interesting bits
so in this particular one setting up
using the more of the module pattern
bum-bum-bum lots of comments explaining
what's going on lots of commented out
code so this is your original kitchen
sink demo so there's a lot of commented
code that's been commented out so here's
an example of creating a new card called
in this case menu I have defined I did
VAR menu up above so I'm just putting
this in line two so we're create a new
card inside that card we have a list
inside that list we have this data we're
just coding it in line because it's its
static we're setting a title for it and
so that's our menu and then we're
setting up a handler front whenever this
menu gets activated what we want to do
is to tell it the list to deselect
whatever item was selected last time and
that that basically gives us this card
right here that code we just looked at
setting up our screen using a flex
column now what the Flex column does is
allows us to have distinct sing at the
top and the thing floating down at the
bottom which can be interesting on iOS
basically needs a lot of hacks out there
some of which involve giving up and
doing native controls for you know any
of the headers in the toolbar down below
but you don't have to do that Joe
scroller actually performs very well in
iOS so it works pretty well ok defer log
in ok so these are more sort of static
things to do it today ok here we go so
here's that that you I mechanism of us
talking about where you can sort of
define a hunk of you I without actually
instantiating it until you need it so
there's a thing called Joe cash and you
can set basically you give it some sort
of name string and you give it a handler
function that gets called
the first time that this particular hunk
of you I is requested with the geocache
get and then the stores are respond to
that so any subsequent calls to it it'll
just return whatever whatever reached
her was returned from the first call
does that make sense nobody raised their
hand ok so I'll show you real quick
here's a couple more Joe kashish set so
whenever whenever you Joe cash get okay
I get text area so we can use something
well look it's about that typo so
something like if we have our Rui stack
we can push this on to it and what
that'll do is since we designed this
thing down below text area the first
time that this gets called the stack
push Joe cash get it's going to go look
up our property for text area and it's
going to say well I haven't this isn't a
call before so i'm going to call this
function and the function all the does
is return some sort of UI widget in this
case we're returning card another thing
to note 2 i'm just going back into the
hole you know Joe isn't trying to get in
between you and and getting the job done
the common unit of currency that you'll
see being thrown around with all this UI
stuff are basically Joe widgets and Joe
views they can just as easily be HTML
pieces so you can you can feed it a dumb
node directly and it'll sort of roll
with that as well so if you have some
sort of thing that doesn't really match
any sort of control that's something
that you sort of created on your own you
can feed that in as well and it'll it'll
handle it it would resolve all that for
you
so a little more stuff here but again
you can see more of that that's sort of
a inline sugar for for creating these
things now you see this type of
structure in things like sent to touch
but what they do is sort of create sort
of a JSON blob with a lot of properties
and some string flags and things like
that in there I kind of like I like the
structure but I prefer to be closer to
the middle so if you notice we sort of
have that the nested structure but we're
actually creating these objects on the
fly so we're still actually coding in
java script we're not pushing it through
some sort of framework and in fact if
you wanted to code this up without
putting it in the sort of hierarchy
network it's perfectly fine you can
create each of each of these pieces and
then you know inject them in whatever
fashion suits your coding style cool
this is the remote thing okay all right
make sense so far I saw two people nod
ok cool ok so
so let's take a look at a quick sample
app that does a little bit more than
these are these little prototype things
mmm see again in some more applause for
the Wi-Fi that worked beautifully that's
what the sample app does is it looks up
all the traffic incidents that are that
are centered around a particular area in
this particular case we're looking for
anything it's with it within 100 miles
of say New York City because we want a
nice decently sized list to to scroll
through and when you tap on one of them
you get sort of this detailed view in
this case we're pulling down a view from
google maps if you click on that and
actually pulls up the google maps page
itself not as impressive on the browser
so in here you're a mobile app it'll
actually typically able to launch the if
you have a map application that will
launch that map app all right a little
more stuff here if you notice we've got
so you can manually refresh it all out
of there kept it good stuff so the same
app and I have I don't want to go
through all the different platforms but
basically you can take the same map and
run it in a dozen different places and
by places I mean different sorts of
platforms including a few that you
wouldn't expect so after the talk
sometime later today if you go to Joe
app calm and i'll have that roll up at
the end i have like a 10 minute video
that does sort of a demo of the same app
pretty much the same app running on
about eight different things and again
the same code underneath so sort of
right once well i won't say write once
run everywhere i'll say right once in
debug everywhere each platform has like
a little some eccentricities one of the
design goals with Joe is to limit most
of those eccentricities on the CSS level
and it's been largely successful with
that so let's take the same app
alright so this is a the same app and
I've got folder setup for running the
browser for android dashboard widgets
will show in a second running on iphone
ipad mobile safari this is slight tweak
in the index HTML for that and then
webOS and I happen to have the emulator
up for webos which is of course my
absolute favorite mobile platform
disclosure i work for HP but i was
actually a huge fan before i started so
i feel fair and honest in saying that ok
cool so we have a simulator running a
webos 20
alright so we package it these are some
command line tools for getting apps
basically built builds the app package
and then installs it on the device or
the emulator here we go these are
commuter up so again same app running on
two different platforms Joe also does
some other things to some platforms will
require a back button others won't for
example webOS as a web loss to anyway
has a back gesture on the device which
so you notice it won't actually put it
back button and will maybe show another
example of that in a minute
ok
actually how much time do I have left
I'm about done I'm about done so um let
me go back or a quick okay Q&A session
so any questions why on earth would I do
this um that sort of thing yes up here
questions have again it worked with
backbone I have not played with it I I
don't see why it wouldn't work with it
so and I think somebody over at night
Toby was talking about playing with that
so somebody somewhere has it working
with backbone just not me yet any other
questions Oh what about any oh yeah so
any oh is a really cool framework that
HP's put out Mac McNulty's team is
putting that together at over at HP Enyo
is really designed for i want to say
larger more enterprise type apps that's
a very comprehensive framework and it
has all the pluses and minuses that you
get with a larger framework like that
generally if you're doing larger apps
you would probably want a larger
framework to get the job done there's
some conceptual similarities and yo the
same thing as joe you know you start
with an empty index HTML and JavaScript
pre all the stuff okay so that this is
actually yeah so the question is is uh
any 0 vs vs really you're talking mojo
for those for those that started with
webos when it first came out there's a
framework called mojo please do not
confuse Joe with mojo in any shape form
at all mojo is something that we're
trying to move away from at HP you know
we really appreciate the developers that
started working with it but any o is our
official framework than it's a heck of a
lot better but yeah it was as far as Joe
versus n yo Joseph's lighter weight and
it's it's geared I think more for
different types of apps and different
types of coders any others
anymore anymore okay cool I think I am
done thank you guys very very much if
you want to get more info go to Joe app
com and see me after if you want to get
a copy this again it's if Wi-Fi is not
working for you cool thank you did you