my name is Thomas on troop I'm working
40 I'm currently living in Seattle but
I'm
originally from Poland I'm focusing on
back-end systems mostly and for the past
few years I've been working a lot with
no Jas so I spent a lot of time working
on cloud computing software for
microsoft and HP for my last few years
of Microsoft I we need to signal jas
into the Microsoft ecosystem after I
left Microsoft I stayed with no Jas and
I continue that work with 0 of 0 right
now I talk was about sandboxing know Jas
code which is a topic relevant for
anyone who's building a multi-tenant
system that executes custom code on
users we have I think there are few
interesting trends in technology over
the past couple of years and you are
only going to see more of it one is the
entire software landscape getting more
polyglot before using more languages and
more technologies over time also the
barrier to entry is getting smaller and
smaller one thing I know to one
interesting thing I noticed he not zero
is how many external systems we are
using to deliver our service it's about
50 external components so software
development going forward I think will
be mostly about putting together
existing building blocks and gluing them
together rather than huge infrastructure
investments section my second time in
Buenos Aires I've into a month ago now I
love this place is very it reminds me of
my home country of Poland study similar
in many respects of course this is a
different hemisphere so for me
personally coming from snowy Seattle
right now it's a nice change I've always
liked like Jess conferences they're just
different from from all the other
conferences I've been to I mean at three
J's conferences in the reigning in the
US and here in Venice iris and there is
a common theme theme running through all
of them people are just coming to learn