[Music]
hi it's me again
so yesterday noticed I'm into pretty
formal computer science II stuff and I
wanted to show you what you can do with
theoretical computer science and plants
so I'm not going to dive too deep into
it but you can describe plant growth the
way you describe human language with a
grammar a plant is basically just a seed
that grows and we start with the seed we
have one leaf then we have a couple of
leaves and the end we might have a tree
every step of that growth is a legit
plant so we can describe that with so
called generative grammars generative
grammars are grass that generate
sentences or other structures that can
be interpreted into sentences or plants
if you want to google that later you
should search fall into Maya systems or
else systems how does our grammar look
like we've got one thing that's called
the axiom that's the initial word or the
seed of the plant in our case and we
have replacement rules they describe how
the plant grows this is a replacement
rule you replace every occurrence of the
symbol on the left hand side with the
symbols on the right hand side not like
it's written here but the other way
around
I'll show you so on the left side we
have rules for SLR
our first word is the s in the next
iteration we replace the s with LS then
we replace the s and the new word and
the L in the new world and so on so the
board or it gets longer every step this
is not really a word yet and that's not
a word that we can understand but we can
apply a transformation function that
translate it into something that we
understand that might be actually human
words but also can be plants so you
could write a function that draws this
word onto canvas into a frame or WebGL
so the theoretical foundation for that
is the same and the cool part would be
how to translate it into a tree and I
want to show you one way to do it with
canvas and so called charter graphics
how they work if you never heard of
title graphics before just imagine a
turtle with a pen and the turtle with
the pen is following directions so for
example an S would mean draw straight
line and L would mean turn left and then
R would mean turn right so for that word
we have here first would be drawing a
straight line that we turn left draw
sight line again turn right turn right
trust right line turn left again and
draw a line I had started graphics and
I'll show you how this is actually used
by someone this there's a repository by
John Bravo for Lindenmayer systems in
JavaScript that has some nice code
prints you can play around with and also
it's super accessible and super well
documented this is the first iteration
the first part of a tree the grammar is
here on the side it's not super
important how it looks like it's a bit
complicated if you've never looked at
this before but just to show you what
you can do you see that shape that goes
to lines up and one to the side and from
this shape the whole tree will grow and
I'll just show you by increasing the
iterations that we're going or we can
actually draw the tree with it and
that's Lindenmayer systems that's a way
to describe plant growth with grammar
[Applause]