everyone a marquee on 11 sometimes
and the people we met at the next I'll
festival the organizer of the festival's
here as well I prepared a few like 20
different demos and like i'm playing i'm
doing like playing with a lot of toys
and make what I thing is toys and
general so on this is one of them and
i'm going to show you kind of like the
journey and look how and why i guess i
got when i got so um yeah i can so this
is my simple setup this is usually what
excel all the products with so on there
was a great brave talk on creativity by
john cleese and he compared basically
creativity to a playground so like you
come you can be stressed you can't have
a deadline if you have to just like
caesar and display with whatever you
like playing with and then you actually
come up with new stuff like the same
thing the same way like i don't i don't
learn from books I like I dream learn
with my hand so I have to look play with
something I work on something long
enough that it actually becomes a thing
to starting with this setup I was
playing those are the skills those of a
dragon cube I can't do a full product so
on this is the same thing same setup
then you can musical loader yeah so this
turn learn through the fool like Twitter
visualizations to what happens I can
visualize any Twitter account so I'm
life from Twitter API and I can see I
can show all the connections between any
account so i think they s dot la it
should work as well yeah so I'm with
this out strengthen videos that will
happen if we see every single follower
and we see that what happens will apply
from one to the other then place another
session playing with another titanium
another cube I was changed we had a
client called product bio we try to
visualize connection between the series
of products and how everything is
created to in this case you goddamn
thousands of items creating database for
the city and also explains here is the
scale
so connecting this list and also one
thing I really like is a Pinterest so
I'm with this with all the sources of
fifth element with kind of anime or like
all the other references I ended up with
this project what it does again I'm
taking them reload I'm running all live
demo so uh always a bit risky yep
aftereing it ain't happening so what I'm
taking I'm converting all the Twitter
Twitterverse universe whether we call it
into an infinite city using the trees
using the system and using these
references and what I kind of like the
idea of turning a twitter handle as I
just a shoe so it's kind of tattoo it's
kind of if you think about any kind of a
God in this universe and you've got your
followers so I'm obviously like the
bigger you get the more photos yes and
look especially right now I feel like
this is kind of rather than on top of it
yeah it's a for infinite city so yet
i'll let see what was interesting also a
key like I really like yes this is a few
of those resources I'm running what we
are any of the projects I made in web
deal people can step in to do with this
one like she's actually flying through
the city to seeing it from the inside
but what I wanted to show you is in a
way I don't make thing for them I make
tool so in this case I and also I've got
a very good I didn't plan this anyway
make him too so I i make i made a setup
I make this system but people have to
fill it up it's kind of like interests
of ours right now it doesn't happen
without the person inside someone has to
trigger it and if you give people simple
tools to make something they claim it
like ooh look what I made the cod eyelid
if you everyone tries to create art but
it's really hard but if you make
something race
simple people claim it like look what
I've made to speaking of this i really
like creates more world and sometimes to
complete abstract sometimes the base
from the Credo location this is a really
fun project this will all live demos by
the way this is a this was a very fun
project for a mountain next to San
Francisco when we were collecting
people's stories the people climbing can
actually leave the photos the videos
deafening speaking of stuff based on
real life I mean what everyone makes at
some point like a big skier make it at
Earth so like I really like make like
making what I look like to destroying
them as well yeah it looks like apricot
inside I guess speaking of this around
the same time there was a nefertiti hack
to always I only the same thing I think
it looks in a bag of bread um let's see
how to enter Cristal is go online then
yeah the one thing I keep coming back to
I always put most of the stuff I'm
talking about it's going to relate to a
product I'm going to later but this is
like a main keys I really like making
living things so I'm for a while like
I've always trying to create some living
creatures living something just somehow
respond to you so this is 11 that
version it sees you you can see her she
sees her reflection inside as well i'm
using kinect amazing both camera and
depth camera and gestures to its
response to your gesture and sea view
and follow through so it's kind of like
a station acquiring you can kind of play
with him tap taking this further we had
a client called braintree and one of the
main things was did we like asking
really developers you want to be cool
and do stuff with the developers so I
serve a simple demo and then and one of
the pitch decks are so on page 7 like
one of the screen and ideas was what if
we visualize bug bug is bug you call
them bugs would have
what do they look like and then what if
you take a side what if you visualize
all the code as creative so what we did
I will start looking what would a code
code code quickly look like what was at
generating it also have a lot of gundam
powers references variation life or it
is a symmetry with my movement you've
got different stuff and we make project
called the code ology so this is a
visual that visualizes any github repo
created so what it does I go through
projects and I find languages or use so
for example JavaScript Python c c++ d
mustard and they all create all the
different parts of this living creatures
and the some of them look like we're
spiders some of them look like a
facehugger from alien some of them are
just big monster what's really
interesting project is on github as well
so the project can visualize 3d or the
project can visualize itself also this
bunch of like easter egg different
rendering mode different stuff um it was
really fun and again i use the same idea
than the same concepts from before so if
you go yeah if you go on Twitter it was
the same stuff people claim it like ooh
look look how I also we want a golden
lion for it who look like look how my
cold is looking look look look arise me
and it's kind of fun to like let people
create something from three much nothing
took from that actually what I mean what
if you do it high res do like I started
playing with a high-res version of
generation then um my turn the freed
crude drawings to put some drawings on
it would look like wood paper something
then I was taking how it looks with this
a lot of lot of them the variation the
term then what are they all just fly
through space
and again you got a load of them I use
this for music visuals for a container
and they're OK in San Francisco it makes
really good music visual things again
all JavaScript things through the how
the API all generating to the actual be
and then I sewed painting by passing
ability he's a he's actually in san
francisco and i hit him up because for
some reason i really like the scale I
relax is completed by also looking at
the migration of things on being a whole
place looking at it and with this
reference in mind I made this project to
this let me generate all the creatures
all those environments and use them
later so you can modify any of them this
infinite amount of them as well so if
you look at the white one white and
black on in the middle if i scroll down
its grow up it doesn't exist anymore the
old they were all generated in one frame
their own instance and this was a really
cool website but it was about our
independent web PR came over look what
if i connect HTC vive to it so you can
do it with the controllers MVR another
the same time I start doing a lot of VR
event and then I realize we are in a
headset and the event is not refund its
separate people rather than bringing
together to water to distil touching
some positive next next out event what
if you bring like this the gr outside of
the headset so in this case you've got
multiple people that can interact with
the VR environment at the same time and
people will pretty much dancing to it
and each like everyone everyone concrete
again create something play with it but
also everything is going to be saved
into 3d files the 3d printed or shared
online so it saves everything every
minute and all the other objects are
available online for anyone so yeah
after this I start teaching so like I
editing web PR and I started
worships in up to 6 hours people the
coded simple javascript stuff were
making their own beer environment and I
had a lot of people coming to it it was
a fun to this was some examples of what
we created in class in couple hours all
of the stuff working by oculus and
cardboard some of this looks pretty
intense but in you know you should try
stuff and you know it's just break it
and that maybe it's not better this way
this was one of my classes and there was
a time around the time that mr. Dubois
in town so he was he actually came to
the class and pretended to be one of the
students but they found out afterwards
mr. Dubey the guys created the whole 3d
library i'm using the pjs earned the
same time ago by travis scott and i
really like i had the contact me today
making new website and then we like
shiny stuff and I like some shiny stuff
kinda make something of a two days so I
did it in one evening but I had all the
resources from the class I was shooting
this was one of the first website for
people released he didn't know where we
are but it worse than we are and then I
started working with action later he's
an Indian artist he does a little crazy
3d and he we want to go into the movie
are spaced and yeah this is this is a
few demo tube you can check out in the
other room they're really colorful also
i try to step away from a low poly
system was kind of bored over to I felt
collaborations a lot of different
artists at the time and a lot of them is
getting pretty interesting to get a
collection of different world this one's
kind of blade runner in New York it's
all rainy the rain and double check the
rain is done by Lucas ever so I just use
the existing library but a mixed it with
VR with three days of all the stuff and
kind of good stuff fun it was November's
all training a lot of San Francisco
but yes especially after this I come to
look at rain anymore because I kind of
see how it's made now you shouldn't
admit you had a pretty good run with it
we're moving invite to a lot of
different we're actually traveling and
traveling art exhibition came with mass
migration the other one with moving
invited to a centre pompidou to
festivals in brazil in serbia and couple
other places this year is going to be
playin tennis but here we're going to
come back to somewhere to Los Angeles in
March there's another event next arc the
real Luke authority after this following
the ER what will set up this was them
Archie like this was the vision how
would how we visualize an artificial
intelligence which we try to mix data
and all the kind of abstract 3d graphics
and all of the stuff again worked in VR
and it works on its own as well so I
like I polyfill through whatever device
you have to investigate but something on
mobile is a gyroscope and NVR is that
whole world you can walk around and then
at some point every a sec actually do
really good projection mapping devices
do we started hacking them and uh yeah
my friends were pretty good we had a
light table for a bit oh no ah so this
is very funny again like the predictions
on the side of them they don't even see
it so they have to improvise they will
talk to each other like now you defend
now you do something and actually from
the trick are going to work from the
audience I'd and works really well and
here we had a few solution it's gonna be
a moving exhibition and I'm going to hit
some festival soon as well but different
modes different variations and we
turning into a whole piece so speaking
of three days one political i should
mention with obscure digital we work on
projection for election night so on
nothing if you will know that but
all this that we see the whole data that
we had live data feed JSON data feed of
whatever is actually happening and also
JavaScript so I think this was like a
biggest canvas JavaScript read so far
it's all running chrome or like insane
side but it was pretty well so we had a
big as a designer set up we had done 40
different projectors split into three
rows this was a top middle and bottom
and this this whole park is a DJ this is
all just a browser in portrait mode so
then I started working actor working
more into intricate installation through
the huge patch screens as well to this
is again one browser split across for 4k
displays running from three different
graphics cards on like one machine that
has for graphics cards and to process it
and it's run its kind of crazy so
following this okay we like this wavy
stuff so I went more into the twice
can't we just make first for Christmas
experiments I agreed we collaborated
with john-boy Berber with this fight
with gloom and made this very thing we
like dark and gloomy I don't really like
Christmas do it kind of hit it up a bit
on a dark side and yeah so the last
thing I was working on though at some
Maggie skin is all i ever do spiders
kind of follows you it was in VR as well
so you can play with a pit fighter and I
realized finally my creatures are moving
and they finally have a character the
one this is the where I'm right now so
after the whole environment of those
things walking and hanging out we follow
my mouth for Mac things it fully
generated the one I've got a fake
physics engine that can calculate any
number of legs between 42 and a lot and
I'm working on some tails and working on
some hands more bodies and
come here can be pretty fun and I think
that too much it for now yep Oh which
code would you like I think I've got the
yeah I can show you this or nothing
about it actually it's all jealous good
so I can show you the animated think so
oh this was like the whole presentation
was at the browser window but I can show
you yeah so the one was automated cube
different all the animation happens in
two lines so I've got a simplex mode and
select know it is running on X Y Z and X
is the position of the cube actually you
know I can probably run it yeah so this
is it right so if I just about this yeah
and maybe divided bar with ya so if you
change some parameters like this one
and maybe even quicker seizure so with
the simplex notes you probably want to
look x and y you can spread them around
so for example if I cut it in like this
simpler if I cut it more into pieces now
sideways this one is more intense and if
I cut it even more it's just going to be
noise and just cut this more yeah I
think this might look kind of cool yes
after which chief to work my phone now
oh yes it does he has all Morgan some
setups how you can run tax quiz without
touch screens and with a pretty good
remote and our pocket
[Music]
the so i think i mentioned before like
why I don't like learning and like I
don't like I don't learn from books I
don't like I can select play with it
there's an example for every single
thing part of the engine so and all the
examples also so through whatever you
thinking of making you can find a full
example online and you can just even if
you want to make a product is and find a
few examples gluten together you've got
a project but also if you want to get
into it find something closer to what
you think of making and play with
variable see what happens when you
change three to three thousand
[Music]
they are denying it and so mobile things
based on all of the every single example
you've seen it works on mobile each one
of them and as part of its part of the
polyfill i'm going to use so in the
future where we are is a placement lot
of people different computers of
different devices are going to eat but
they will have different capability you
know if you have leaked motion if you
have leap motion you've got fingers if
you don't have the motion maybe that
control it we don't have controllers may
be just the thing phones have read the
gyroscope to for example is actually
considered copious multi-touch you can
use location capacity me any optimized a
new phones are ready for we are
especially the new android phones all
the Bajan ready for a break from but
each of the examples I felt it was
iphone 4 plus and it's all for the
browser there's no app is nothing
um I'm using a lot of random library on
the girls look if I need something for
everything library so for paranoid on
keeping library for some shader stuff
the greatest thing is difficult to
contain community like I'm pretty
confident but I'm trying to make a cube
that's more and does something if I look
up cube the boss and does something j/s
I'm going to find it and it's gonna be
open so the money even the framework for
it cube thing goes there I'm working on
the project right now see if I can hey
I'm working on the project with connect
so you can stream in next culliton and
I'm mapping it to bone so this last have
you seen was well for the creature they
all running bowline system from map you
connect bowl into the actual bones of a
character you take over control of the
character so you can map it easily you
can I could you know two legs and two
and two legs and two hands but maybe
you've got two legs and the character
edge length yeah yeah yeah
[Music]
I like yeah I like making living things
but some way to control it one way or
the other like the restaurant directly
don't be kind of interesting also like
out-of-body experience especially for PR
[Music]
so new VR headsets are going to have I
tracking the group they're going to have
fun while tracking so you can have you
can smile ending dr you cannot see some
of smiling because right now the kind of
emotionless pockets and kind of funny
yeah complete gonna be really
interesting later
[Music]
Oh