well everyone glad you're here and not
learning about the namespaces and Yui so
or dojo so just wanted to start off and
say this is one of the best conferences
that I've been to in the last week or
two so actually this year you guys the
content here is wicked I don't think
anyone here has said Ajax and not been
sort of sarcastic about it I think
everything that is going on the
JavaScript space pretty exciting and
yeah you guys all rock so it's cool to
be here so I'm just going to quickly
talk about NATO because they pay me so
that's important to me it's found in 98
it's 15 guys it's a really small company
we're in Vancouver just Canada we're an
early player in JavaScript air and
lately we're really into the mobile web
which is something we think is going to
be pretty big and I'm going to talk a
lot more about that we have two main
products they're both open source and
are both based on JavaScript there's
complete UI which a set of user
interface components data grids and rich
controls and that sort of thing and then
there's what I'm here to talk to you
about today phonegap so phonegap
I think I got back to the hotel last
night like three after eating empanadas
and I edited my slides and I have no
idea what I was thinking I added this
one but it's pretty good so oh yeah
that's right so um the mobile web is
huge and it's growing really fast I
think there was something like three
hundred percent growth in just the last
month on queries on Google from an
iphone that's insane if there's a
billion television sets and there's two
billion web enabled phones that speaks
to the opportunity I don't need a bar
chart to show you how much of an
opportunity that is but there's a
problem right now with mobile devices
and that problem is best illustrated by
a really complicated chart like this one
or table so there's obviously a lot of
platform fragmentation we've got the
iphone with which has objective c which
it actually it is pretty cool as a
language i recommend learning and i
think it is interesting you've got
android which is also really cool kind
of a beautiful version of java running
inside of it called dalvik which is
quite performing it's just plain old
java objects really simple the program
against theirs blackberries take on Java
which is about as about as easy to use
as their keyboards or their browser for
that matter windows mobile whatever
nokia nokia is actually really cool
nokia does a lot of stuff they just
don't do any one thing very well which
is what happens when you do a whole
bunch of stuff that they do have web
technology called wrt which is jQuery
base so it looks pretty cool and it's
quite interesting problem is nobody has
nokia phones in north america a lot of
people in europe do so it is worth
watching it's kind of interesting then
there's the palm pre which is coming up
soon it looks like they may have nailed
it with their programming model which is
HTML CSS and JavaScript
so you know we've seen this kind of
thing happen before platform
fragmentations not not news to web
developers and well it's you know it's
never going to work so what do you do
well you use the web to solve this
problem this slides awesome because
check this tank has a greater than sign
yeah right and that's like the
internet is really like like it's kind
of like you know C programmers will
speak to Rizzoli about your little web
app or whatever but you know writing and
c is really cool and it's really
performant and it has a time of place
but that time in place it's got nothing
on this tank man like a weight's
whatever so i thought i might be a first
guy out of the wall cat and it's kind of
bitter that I wasn't but that's okay you
know people say shouldn't have a walk at
your presentation that's lawl
cats are awesome so yeah anyway so we're
pretty sure that this internet thing is
going to work out and and so when the
iphone was released that was like this
marker got thrown on the ground okay
here we are the mobile web is finally
arrived I've been waiting for this
forever they roll it out and they're
like hey you're going to do all your
apps with web technology like oh my god
this is fantastic this is exactly what
I'm looking for and then the whole
community went no we want to do native
apps we want to do with Objective C and
we're like wait no no we don't want to
do that actually but people did and so
our team was actually really
disheartened by this because a lot of
work are going to WebKit to make it
quite powerful we think Apple was
planning on releasing a lot more
features into it who knows it's all
speculation but when the SDK came out so
i'll go back so the sdk came out we
started to look at closely and we're
like you know how can we still do web
development with the iphone but take
advantage of the native features and it
turns out a lot of this stuff is built
in
and so beer being a primary motivator
and I Toby this is Brock wit and he's
one of our main developers and he came
up with the whole phonegap concept at
iphone dev camp and they had free beer
so he got a lot of work done and that's
where phone calf came from so our
philosophy with phonegap and this is
probably a little bit unintuitive to a
Western audience but it's like an
Eastern Zen philosophy Taoist kind of
thing we we don't actually want this
project to have to exist and if it
ceases to exist will have been
successful because what we really want
to see happen is web technology to be
treated as a first class citizen on
devices right we know it's never going
to happen in the short term so
we have to do it ourselves I think I
wrote this slide last night too so
phonegap lets you access the data
features on the phone and by native
features I mean pretty much anything
that the phone can do we want to expose
back to JavaScript and God I think I was
trying to remind myself that yet so it's
open source it's MIT licensed we want
you to take our code we want you to fork
it we want you to work on it we don't
want to have any barrier to adoption we
want to see people use it and change it
and modify it and do whatever so why
would we do that it's kind of crazy it
makes no sense at all the reason we're
doing it is because we're web developers
right we want to see the web succeed and
well you know that's that's pretty easy
to say because it's probably going to
work out like I said before this whole
internet thing is obviously not going to
go anywhere but progress the state of
the art Ford and we all win in that case
so here's phonegap right now we have it
working on the iphone the Android in the
blackberry with identical api's BAM it's
my only animation I promise you this is
this is phonegap really soon so we're
do I see that again yeah i'm going to
make up for lack of content with effects
so we've got on the iphone the android
the blackberry we're looking at you know
what else is cool too about this that
you have to note is that web kit is on
all of these devices except for the
blackberry so that makes our job a
little bit easier and it also gives us
better rendering engines and I'm not a
WebKit fanboy it's just the reality okay
so let's move on actually you might have
a question about that you're thinking
windows mobile has WebKit and actually
yes you can build web kit on the windows
mobile the thing is nobody really owns a
windows mobile phone so no one knows
that you can do that Microsoft talks
about how they ship so many of these
windows mobile SDKs because they count
visual studio is a shipment of their sdk
so and they it's a free download with
the.net framework whatever so another
way to look at this too is site-specific
browsers which is kind of an interesting
thing there's lots of ways to do these
things maybe the browser vendors should
also be considering giving us better
access to our devices and for example
like if I could use my phone to take a
picture I can use flash to take a
picture and all of our laptops have
cameras built-in well you know why can't
I do that with JavaScript it's an
interesting question so I don't have an
answer for that by the way I don't work
on browsers but so this is also another
interesting recent development Apple
came out with an app store facebook went
oh why didn't we do that and then all of
a sudden all the other mobile carriers
jump on they release app stores and now
Nintendo just announced they're doing an
app store which is cool and interesting
because the d/s is a mobile device so so
there's a lot of opportunity there too
and you probably don't want to develop
your app that many times
to get it to market right so how do you
make money as software developers we
probably this is the last thing we think
about half of the time but it is worth
thinking about actually it turns out so
you can do advertising your apps and all
these app stores that there's you know
apps that have examples that there's
freemium apps which means you know apps
kind of free but you have to pay for an
upgrade of some sort subscription based
apps we don't see in the app store and
they're discouraged but there are ways
around that such as releasing a single
app for everything like there's you know
10 comic book apps or something like
that so it's kind of like a subscription
value-add type apps had no idea what i
was thinking there who knows you can
probably come up with something I the
app store right now is full of these I
fart type apps and this is just an
unfortunate fact of the market that if
you're going to develop something for
the iphone you're going to run into a
lot of barriers with the time cost to
development and then the price is
getting so low that you wouldn't want to
develop something that has like a
six-month Deb schedule with a team of
five guys you're not going to make any
money and that's just an interesting
thing to note using web technology you
can actually take that time way down and
you might be able to build more
competitive apps and you don't have to
worry about the I far pricing model
something we're seeing happen recently
and it's kind of interesting there's
niche type apps coming up now and
bineesh apps I mean apps that are really
narrowly focused for specific audiences
so one example I saw recently was a
terrier decorator app and you can drag
around like couches and and plants and
it was like 10 bucks right and I would
never buy that but a lot of people
probably would because they like to move
their coaches no yeah and then the last
way to make money is to write apps for
other people which is what you're
probably doing or I'm doing so well one
other thing to note about phonegap is a
good way to look at something is talk
about what you're not going to do and so
we're not trying to build hardcore game
we're not building another browser and
we're not focused on substandard devices
so invite substandard devices I mean
anything that anything that isn't going
to be able to compile and run an
instance of a browser our goal is to
stay as close to the html5 spec as
possible which is a moving target and
also html5 that doesn't really have any
do a JavaScript but it does kind of
right so things like geolocation but I
don't think the guys at w3c are thinking
about accelerometers even though every
computer has one so it's kind of an
interesting thing so we're trying to
make our API as close as possible to how
the web itself will probably evolved so
let's get into some code I put this
unicorn up here for you Tom this is a
really simple basic example of doing
geolocation with phonegap we start off
with the debugger which will come back
into apples xcode so we're going to get
your current location we start you know
and a pass you can this person user or
can this app use your location well
that's what's going on we say navigator
done notification or activity start
we've got a success callback or a wind
call back and we've got a fail call back
that's it that's how access to your
location of a phonegap it's pretty
simple accelerometer was the next thing
that we added pretty much immediately
and I don't think it it can get much
simpler than that there's a function
here called round number which i forgot
to strip out but it was just like a
helper function inside this method as
these examples go on you'll see that
I've got pretty much we have the same
convention all the way through we will
say navigator dot whatever the feature
is and then I you know callback function
and love success a failure function and
then
any options which is an object literal
we've recently added contact support
it's still a little fuzzy but it's also
quite powerful and interesting we just
returned well the first time we added it
all we did was return an array of
objects that made a lot of sense and
then this guy hit the mailing list he's
like well I have 6,000 contacts in my
phone really dude I've got like
eight but so we had to think that one
through because you don't want to load
that many people and do into an instance
of web can it just takes forever so
we're we've reworked the API with these
constraints in mind I don't even know ed
i added this because i thought i'd be
funny last night apparently whatever so
you can do other stuff with phonegap we
have a whole bunch of notification
events the different devices have
different ways of notifying you
different stuff and so that's a really
complex sentence for a simple idea
you've got like on the black bear you
got all these little lights that you can
make blink for whatever reason if you
were you know inclined to do so android
same kind of thing we can play almost
any audio in the iphone sdk there is a
restriction that we can't play anything
more than 30 seconds so you could loop
and you can get clever with that there's
obviously ways around that but we're
trying to keep phonegap within the
sphere of apples legalese which is a
labyrinth amazed at best but it's an
interesting thing and you can play most
video files as well which is kind of
cool so a phonegap is quite adopted we
don't know how adopted exactly because
it's MIT licensed when people do want to
promote to us they'll tell us we know
there's a minimum of 50 apps in the App
Store so that's kind of cool and rather
interesting there's lots of forks on
github so if you're if you're on github
I encourage you to get up there and take
it for yourself so web apps are pretty
easy to build when it's just a
client-side code and that's all you have
to deal with when you're building a
phonegap application so I could really
get deeply into this but I'm fairly
certain most people here are comfortable
with HTML CSS and JavaScript so I'm just
going to talk quickly about some of the
neat capabilities oh yeah and and I'm
going to do a little WebKit fanboy bit
here a WebKit is winning it's it's just
a fact it's it's an amazing browser it's
fast it's got a tiny footprint and it if
you build your app correctly you cannot
distinguish a web app from a native
application with WebKit and that's just
a fact and the quickest easiest way to
build a web app right now is with dash
coat how many people here have even know
dash code exists yeah right it's kind of
interesting because Apple spent a lot of
time on it and it has a way to publish a
web app it's not just for publishing
dashboard widgets and when you do it it
does it to the dimensions of an iphone
and it's got libraries for all the
native controls that you have on an
iPhone but done with javascript and HTML
CSS so that's kind of an interesting
thing that got overshadowed when the SDK
came out nobody noticed this it just
came out and i think they announced at
the same time and I ones like oh yeah
whatever dash could I can't wait to get
into this objective c man it's going to
be awesome so it's worth checking out
it's the only problem with it though is
if you build an app using dash code it's
not going to work the same in android
and it probably won't even build a load
inside of whatever browser that
blackberry is currently using so that's
something to note I you I I I like I you
I I think it's really cool as developed
by Joe Hewitt who you have to respect is
when probably the best mobile developers
out there it it
really hasn't seen any love it doesn't
take advantage of CSS transitions and so
it it looks sort of know if you've seen
an iui up it looks choppy and clunky and
it's based on linked lists which gets
boring really fast if you're just like
going through like list after list after
list like okay that's it that's all
there isn't this out so it's worth
looking at there's a new one called
magic framework it's jQuery based it's
pretty simple and it's a lot like I you
I it's worth looking at if you're going
to build a mobile web app jqtouch is
probably the hottest one right now that
everybody's getting into using it is
also jQuery based and it's quite fast a
problem with jquery on the phone is that
it's huge and that's not such a problem
but it takes a long time to load and you
you pay that a performance penalty
upfront for that when it loads that
JavaScript into the interpreter there's
just almost like a shrug well that phone
gets used to the idea that it's got all
this code inside of it and so you don't
actually need a lot of that code unless
you're using something like jqtouch we
developed our own little mini solution
to it which we called xui and it's
experimental it it's almost identical
syntax jquery except for its 2k instead
of 24 K or whatever jquery g zips down
to and that leaves you room for your app
logic so you could load your app really
quickly you can build whatever it is
you're doing in a familiar way because
we're just using jquery and you don't
have the performance overhead of it
something else worth doing if you
haven't is and this seems like heresy I
think everyone should try and write
their own framework before they jump
into using a framework that's you know
why would you do that that's crazy well
as a practitioner of the craft of
building web apps with the lingua franca
of Frank whea whatever that word with
the with JavaScript it's your it's
almost your job to know it and
understand it you know if you don't know
about query selector all you're missing
out it's really cool technology it's
interesting you don't need sizzle half
of the time if you don't use document
get element by ID then you probably
don't like typing and I don't blame you
but you should try rolling your own at
least once something else it's tricky to
build web apps for the iPhone because
the screen resolution so small the
emulators are really not good at
emulating what the phone experience is
exactly like and so you do a lot of this
sort of build and then test on your
phone and build and test on your phone
if you write unit tests up front you're
going to save yourself time later and if
you're using fire bug light embed it
inside the browser you can get a good
idea what's going on that's all I have
all right so
somebody was talking about hoverboards
last night which is kind of cool what's
coming next with phonegap oh yeah so
it's not just about phones that there's
a lot more than mobile devices and then
then just phones in the Tendo d s is a
pretty good example of this it has a
browser it's a little mini platform unto
itself we're seeing the internet kind of
pervade areas that we hadn't thought it
would or at least we didn't know it was
going to and we want to be cognizant of
that I don't know why there's new walk
there something we're exploring is gecko
rendering the reason for this is because
WebKit is winning so we're looking at a
potential of using gecko and making it
the rendering engine and making that
transparent we've had some success with
the iphone not so much with Android you
can build gecko to Windows Mobile which
is cool fennec is a browser for Windows
Mobile that's based on firefox so that's
something we're looking at I more
devices blackberry please oh yeah I had
a blackberry because we've been we've
been trying to get ahold of someone at
blackberry and asked them why they don't
use a real browser and they won't get
back to us on that so maybe they will
open toolchain something else we're
looking at adding right now if you want
to build an iphone app you need a mac
and you know like mac users just such a
minority we want to make sure that we
can also help out our friends in the
windows world linux to uh yeah so this
is also something cool that we've been
working on recently and i'm going to
jump out and we're trying to name it I
wanted to call the stimulator but nobody
was into it
no spaces there we go so this is pretty
cool actually this is the the phonegap
stimulator if I want to like watch the
accelerometer we can use this little guy
over here this is an adobe air
application by the way I would have
built it with or we would have built it
with titanium but you can't do this cool
paper vision of 3d like rotation stuff
with titanium at least not yet to my
knowledge geolocation is not going to
work I think it beeped yeah it's not
very exciting whatever vibrate blank you
know I mean this is pretty basic stuff
is like a nifty way to like move it
around and get orientation change events
we can change the skin to like an
Android to get an idea of like what
that's going to look like you know or
you know we're a masochist we can also
change the skin to blackberry bold which
you know that's probably how it will
render in a blackberry the palm pre oh
that's hot yeah anyway so back to the
old iphone i think yeah we've got some
other demos in here too so like this is
and i can show you the source code in a
second can you guys yet ball in there
it's not showing up super well but we
can we built this little game with like
hardly any JavaScript at all and you
know that's not very exciting this is
way cooler this is actually hard well I
have a difficult time with it but yeah
i'm using the accelerometer to navigate
this dude around and if i hit the spikes
at vibrates so that's pretty gnarly this
is this thing's going to be completely
open source to we're going to release
this on github let anyone work on it
we're embedding Firebug light inside of
it as well so you can do
any kind of debugging that you used to
probably in that side pain and then just
use the other side to interact with the
code for that first demo I mean it's not
the most beautiful code but that's it
right there so all we're doing is watch
I have no idea what's going with the
indentation all our day is watching the
accelerometer we never fail apparently
and yeah then we just move the ball
around using this method right here
there's no frameworks there's there's no
real magic it's just simple simple HTML
CSS and JavaScript here's the the other
game with the vibrate built-in I mean
that's not much code for the effect and
it's pretty hard to tell once that's
running on the actual device that it's
oops pre hard to tell that it's just
HTML CSS and JavaScript so it's pretty
cool we're working on a whole bunch of
interfaces right now for phonegap and
really we're driven purely by a need to
try impossible and so we're
looking at adding speech API google
android has this or the new sdk has a
speech API but it's not real time and so
that's not good enough we're looking at
adding a couch like SQL Lite wrapper be
even cooler if we could add couch itself
Chris we're looking at adding a socket
API file i/o you can already send
telephone events back through phonegap
so you can invoke like the phone
interface and an SMS interface just via
a href so you just do tell colon slash
slash and telephone number boom you'll
pop it open so it's kind of cool we want
to actually make that even more
interesting and add programmatic access
from JavaScript
so you can build gnarly auto dialers or
something I don't know another friend of
ours back in vancouver added Facebook
Connect which is neat so you can you
know do your authentication with
facebook as well everyone has it i guess
this is the last bullet here is really
new and i didn't even know it was coming
until like two days ago we had a fork
happen a friend of ours in vancouver
decided to just go gonzo and he added
half of the native controls that are
available and you just add them back
into your phone gap application using
CSS so if you want a native tab bar you
can just say class tab bar and then a
list items inside of it links will be
the links that you can use them like the
bottom tab bar it's a little bit of a
tricky one though because you can't do
that kind of cross-platform stuff the
controls that are native to an iphone
are native to the iphone you're not
going to see those on an android so we
want to be cognizant of that you're
doing development that some people just
don't care they want to build iphone
apps so here's some resources i'm gonna
put these slides online anyways you'll
be able to find them you don't need to
like quickly jot all this down we need
your help guys weren't you know we're
not a big company and the the project is
ambitious at best we especially need
documentation tends to be a problem test
specs code ideas we want to see people
fork it on github and take phonegap in
directions that we don't expect it to go
in and that's that's where all the cool
stuff happens to us so you know please
do take our code and do something with
it and let us know about it more
resources and yeah that's all I got for
you yes it's in android there is no SQL
Lite support side blackberry
iphone and android yeah yeah oh so the
area the webs are cool but the problems
they don't work when you go offline low
bandwidth go to the Metro what I support
is that there's full offline support for
phonegap in so let me show you and
probably pursue a delay right yeah
partly I'll just pop the whole tree open
so when you download the phonegap source
can you guys see that that's what it
looks like it's pretty straightforward
we've got a Java scripts directory which
has a whole bunch of interfaces so this
isn't implemented this is just an
interface so let's say you take a
picture of the camera for example and
then it gets implemented different ways
for different platforms in the case of
the iphone we have a WWF older that
example app that i was showing this is
it right here it's all offline and so
yeah you yeah yeah you could if you
wanted to you'd have to code that into
your logic when you build it but it's
fully doable some people just use this
HTML file as like kind of a shell and
then they'll keep all their assets in
SQLite database and eval them and the
phone starts up and then you could do
like a call back to the server say hey
is there a new version cool update this
database boom run the app so offline is
fully supported there are any other
questions yeah is so when you're running
an application from gap is when it's
being executed as it actually be thank
you
yeah it's an instance of it's an
instance of WebKit so every application
building this is everything the Franklin
yeah are they are you guys going any
options to like say we will have this
build down to man code well it uses the
SDK the iphone sdk so at the end of the
day it is native code i guess underneath
it all but i think what it is like the
like i have actually run applications
and go on gas javascript in a becks to
patrol because it's the language that a
maze a little cleaner maybe that just to
see ya in it but actually have that
compiled down to the native application
that broadens that's not the morning to
WebKit it's actually well that that is
how it works like it's it's a native
springboard app it's a chromeless
instance of WebKit with native features
just injected it like we pollute the
javascript with you know awesome
basically yeah so you're you're looking
to support free when it comes out
totally hopefully soon yeah obviously
it's already or it's going to be built
on that same stack so i guess well
phonegap basically just a simple little
train one what's the benefit of using
phonegap of your target yeah so we're
ready me a ship for the the Mojo SDK so
that your code would be portable between
from iphone android free so that's
that's our approach there there any
other question yep yeah as i
understanding you go to build a web app
you can i'll down install just that app
kind of isn't is a native pump through
the store save me working with i say for
targeting the iphone yeah but if you say
want to use it more as a platform is
anybody any of you guys and you know
what you do is you bridging the gap that
the operator that the native browsers
don't allow you access to the to the
native services sure you know there's
movements to try to try to push that to
build with like basic building code web
apps it can kind of do the hybrid man
ninja provide this is buddy or has been
able to get through say the apple store
and more of a platform type of
application that will allow you to say
had if you had multiple yeah business or
multiple applications that you wanted to
code to that api in a sense you can
install in a browser yeah like a wrapper
of some kind yeah there's there's a
couple examples of this where people are
because phonegap work since there's two
ways when you're actually building the
app you can point at a remote URL or you
can do offline and there are apps in the
store that like point to a remote URL
you could use this in a shady way right
you could like you know have your
kitten's app and turn it into like nasty
porn app and a week if you wanted to but
no they gate no one's done that yet but
they're there have been examples where
people progressively enhance their apps
over time and added like new
functionality and features and you could
you can almost turn it into like a mini
portal for whatever specific yeah so
yeah it people have done it and you
could do that and apples let stuff
through that is like that okay this was
wondering i mean one of that one of
these we're talking some folks recently
bad is to doing that install an app that
kind of starts with a single focus that
they get add more capabilities to it
essentially becomes more the launcher of
their own private suite of mobile
application so it's totally doable yeah
there any other questions yeah that's
all face on that which of my nursing me
was the apple / stricted you from
running anything with a lot of amenities
like stories they do except for they
ship with web kit which is gut um
javascriptcore or scroll whatever so you
can your it's fully allowed by the sdk
is there another question yeah is there
going to be a feature detection billions
in the API so for instance you're saying
some of the phones to support sequel
life is be some sort of a Lillet is
saying if the sequel lights accordingly
than do so so yeah totally we've got
device and platform always return back
and you can do you can test against that
although it would probably make more
sense if you depend on a specific
feature to test the feature returns null
or something like that so be depending
on I'd had to say if you not that Gator
blackberry than SQLite is not usable
instead of SQLite support is equal to
Teresa yeah yeah it'd be Europe it'd be
up to you to do that although i would
like to entertain better ways of doing
that I didn't really good it is it is
did you wait we should make your
application with poem yes you I use are
you installing a new browser on the
phone or is it I'm using the browser
that's already on using the browser
that's already on the phone are using an
instance of the browser that's on the
phone so you're building it like a
native app and it'll have like an icon
on the springboard in the case of
Android and iPhone apps and it'll be
just like another native app except for
it's really just a windowed browser or a
chromeless browser so if you want to
explode more data functionality it as an
app out there you can drop down to do
get see you right there yes yes and we
encourage people to do that totally and
it's really simple the way that it's
architected you you can add the features
and it when you call them from
JavaScript it just mimics the
objective-c so we look for a call if
it's not it's almost like a method
missing and Ruby similar kind of
delegate approach