blessed be talking about mastering the
command line with nodejs so without
further ado I'm Phil that's Mike and
both of us work at Adobe and we mostly
work on web stuff but generally we work
on project called phonegap and it's
Apache sibling called Apache Cordova and
we just want to share a few points with
you guys about how we've converged on
building command line tools we converged
on these patterns the hard way which is
basically a nice way of saying we've
failed several times and want to share
the failures with you we think shrank
failures is just as important as sharing
successes and for about four years now
we've been building these tools to
assist a project phonegap and not
surprisingly most of the tools are used
generally by people you download
something you want to interface it with
it right away but I guess to our
surprise some people started integrating
the tools with other tools into larger
programs build automations whatever it
is so while building these tools and
interacting with our community to evolve
them we've kind of found a few qualities
I guess you thought you could call them
of command line tools that we think are
useful when we want to share with you
guys so we've chosen four of these
points and we'll walk through them one
by one and since we've written these
tools in nodejs we love javascript and
we're at JS con we might as well show
you some node.js based code to go along
with it but of course I mean these are
just kind of suggestions just what these
two dudes converged on might be wrong
don't take them as absolutes
cool all right let's kick it off with
the command-line interface with respect
to testing it in the node community it's
really interesting that we're very
diligent for testing our modules will do
unit tests or will do behavior driven
tests for the public interface to our
module that we're providing to our users
but we rarely do that when it comes to
the command line interface we dumped
dozens or hundreds of lines of code into
a file and we release it and that is
often the public interface to your
library for most of your users if
they're actually using your command line
interface and your command line
interface has a bug you have no test to
cover it and your users will be seeing
that as a bug towards your library not
necessarily the command-line interface
and this is something that we've really
struggled with Phil and I for both the
past year or so we have no idea really
released for the past year we had no
idea how to write good test for a
command-line interface we really
struggled with this originally we were
going about by testing through shell
execution so we would write unit tests
or behavior driven tests we would
execute a given script and then we kind
of like poke and prod inspect what the
results were but the end result is that
things weren't really slow you're doing
a ton of file i/o and you're actually
executing a lot of code and your tests
end up being extremely vague so if you
dive into just this one example here
this is just a simple behavior driven
test where we're running the command
jazz conf create with a given path and
the test itself should create a project
so on line 7 you can see we shall exec
to a given command that command is jazz
conf create with a path and then
afterwards we're kind of going to poke
and prod and see if maybe the result was
what we wanted so first off we expect
that the result status code is 0 0 means
things probably went okay assuming that
we actually use status codes
command-line tool and that's not broken
we inspect the output the console output
so we can match a couple words and see
if maybe the word created and not err
appeared but that's again or extremely
weak what if we have just a conditional
bug and we're always saying the
project's been created when it actually
hasn't and so then we can also go even
deeper and we can start checking whether
or not certain files certain folders
were created and so this is where the FS
exists Inc is and equals true downside
there is that what if the file existed
before the test ran or you would
actually have to have before and after
tests to do clean up each time which
means you're doing a ton of file i/o and
people who don't have a solid state
drive results in tests the run extremely
extremely slow and in the end it's still
not a very deep test ideally what we
want is to programmatically test deep
CLI the same way we programmatically
test the rest of our library we can do
very deep and very intimate test that
way so we want something such as this
which is on line 7 we would simply say
we expect some function to have been
called with some argument at least now
we have a much deeper test running at
that specific time well it turns out
that we can actually do this and we can
do it very easily by simply treating the
CLI as a module instead of as an
executable script and to actually go
about doing that the first step you have
to do is just simply slim down your bin
script instead think of it as a proxy
into your CLI module or an interface
into your CLI module so what we're going
to do is actually go into the bin
directory we have the J's conf Chason
typically here i mentioned people would
be dumping dozens or hundreds of lines
of code where they parse argument
parameters and decide what they're going
to do but instead let's just get rid of
all of that and instead require a CLI
module that we've declared on line 8 i'm
actually parsing the process argument
values i'm using optimist but you guys
don't have to if you like the raw
process args then go nuts line 14 is the
key right there with our CLI module we
call an entry point and we pass those
process args so
my entry point is RV and pass arc V and
so that is all that this would do you
could write three simple script tests if
you really want to know that this entry
point works but after that at least
we're moving into real code now the
second step is actually the CLI module
which is going to consume our main
library and so if we go into lib an easy
way to organize this as silly as it
sounds is just create a CLI directory
with an index like Jas and size nice and
clean that lot that modules of course
going to consume your main module in
this case we're calling it Jas conf and
from there you can actually treat it
like a real module so you don't need to
have this gigantic bin script instead
you can actually start to abstract and
move things into different files and it
looks a lot cleaner to work with and the
benefit of all of this is that now we
can actually test that CLI as a module
and we're binding really close to the
metal of the actual command line
terminal because we can just fake the
process arg v value but everything else
is going to run the same so we have high
confidence that our programmatic tests
are actually testing the same interface
that our users are actually going to use
so if you jump into the spec and you
jumped into the CLI if we want to
actually write a test for the create
spec we can actually now accomplished
something much more detailed we can
again include our CLI module and we can
again still test the the J's conf create
paths we can still say it should be able
to create a project but on line fourteen
we actually call CLI dark B and we pass
in the exact same command that the user
would have ran on their system so create
space path to the project the benefit
those and now we can actually test
details so we can actually say what's
the entry point to remain library JS
conf with the create function was it
actually called yes awesome was it
called with the correct path yes awesome
so at least we know that the CLI is now
parsing things correctly and of course
we can take it even a step further and
this is always important is to keep the
CLI as silly as it sounds doing the CLI
logic only but the benefit there isn't
now we can actually use mocking so we
can mark out that mean lie
the J's conf la creme Lee fast so we can
jump into the spec the CLI to create
again and now on line 7 we're actually
mocking up the Jazz conf create so very
basic for testing but now these tests
are running lightning fast and are not
altering the file system they're not
doing anything but testing that CLI
interface and ensuring that things are
being parsed correctly we've already got
rock-solid tests for the Jays conf
create function so things are now tests
on both ends and with that we actually
have a testable CLI so without doing
anything fancy again it sounds trivial
but it's taken us well over a year to
converge on actually this using this
pattern and works fine a ruby or node it
doesn't really matter what you're doing
so point two is command line interface
should be helpful and it does actually
sound like a silly point but it's people
that are using a tool mostly not i'm
missing gods so people generally need a
little bit of hand-holding especially
early on to kind of figure out how to do
anything and so having meaningful help
output you know actual usage
documentation to help people out is a
big win and unfortunately that's not the
case for a lot of tools out there
documentation seems to be generally
neglected by developer community and so
at least what I've found trying to dive
through code for a lot of modules out
there is that usage documentation or
documentation in general is hard-coded
straight into logic so you get end up
getting these massive ugly strings in
the middle of your code and they're hard
to find hard to contribute to hard to
fix and also you forget you just forget
to update them a lot of the time so
let's take a look at one back to our Jas
conf tool I I see this kind of pattern
if you're lucky enough it'll be in its
own module sometimes it'll just be
randomly
kind of sprinkled all over the codebase
but you see something like this so a
giant array of strings that are then
joined with a new line pretty clever but
say you add a new command and you have
to update this and you forget a comma
that'll break so instead we found a
better way of doing documentation an
easier way a way that is much simpler to
contribute to and it's pretty obvious
how to do it we just use plain text most
of the time individual files that map to
specific commands our overall usage and
it's easy to find them it's easy to
contribute to even straight in github
since it's just plain text and it's
worked for us so in our imaginary j s
conf tool we actually have a top-level
folder for documentation which again
isn't the norm i would say in there we
have a CLI folder and we have individual
files for different aspects of using the
tool here's an example of the top-level
usage the help text standard usage
documentation nothing you wouldn't
expect when you run the command from the
tool with help flag or something like
that and by setting up a structure in
this way all we have to do to kind of
wire it all up appropriately is righted
a little bit of logic that will find
read the perfect file and spew it up for
a user so this logic is fairly simple
let's take a look at one example that we
wrote up so in our help module here it's
probably the biggest code slide we have
but essentially what's going on is we
just take the arguments that are passed
into the command using the pattern that
Mike touched on earlier between lines 25
and 28 there we append a txt extension
onto it join it up with dots and then we
try to read that file if it exists so if
typed GS com helped create it will put
together a file path that ends in help
create text for example probably need to
do a little more than this like air
checking making sure the file exists
that kind of stuff but it's simple and
really it's it's very similar to routing
in a web server kind of the same idea a
request comes in with a bunch of
parameters and you end up your web
server does all the work to route it to
the appropriate view and put in all the
data appropriately and that kind of
stuff so it's the same idea except the
parameters are a lot simpler just based
on the commands you type into your
console and I mean you can get fancy
with this too if you really want you
could use templating or actually the guy
who came up with this general pattern of
documentation Gord Tanner from ex
blackberry ex tiny hippos now at thalmic
I believe he he was the first one that I
saw that used this pattern but he ended
up going one step further and using
markup for his documentation so he sorry
I marked down and you know so he has to
include a markdown parser and all that
good stuff but it worked point number
three so a bit of backstory between Phil
and I oh that we're part of the Apache
Cordova phonegap project for the past
year the tooling has been starting to
develop in that project that's a huge
pain point right now and in the past
year we've had to build a number of
tools but we've also been consuming a
lot of command line tools provided by
SDKs and one thing that we've quickly
realized in the past year is that
command line interfaces should be
bipolar and what we mean by bipolar is
that sometimes it's nice to have a
verbose tool when something goes wrong
so you run j/s comp create with my comp
as your path but you provide the verbose
flag it's really helpful to see what
files what directories have been created
when an air goes wrong it's going to
just flip out and print as much as
possible which in
in the end actually is incredibly
helpful for your tools that you're
building on they're consuming these but
also just as a user but at the same time
sometimes it's nice have a quiet tool
actually most of the time it's nice just
to have a quiet tool when everything
goes right so in this case we can do the
same thing but with the quiet flag and
it spews out nothing that's awesome but
how do we implement that into our own
CLI tools that's kind of something that
we struggled with the command-line
interface module doesn't really know
much it knows how to call jayus conf
create who knows it's about to create a
project and these are going to succeed
or fail but it really has no clue what's
happening in between and if we start to
put a lot of those messages into the
actual module then we're going to result
in a bunch of console logs hanging out
inside a library that other users might
be consuming not from the command line
interface they might have to deal with
these ugly console messages in some form
so we thought about this quite a bit and
we've converged on event meters they
actually work incredibly well and they
provide all the functionality you need
without any additional dependencies
which we like a lot and the idea is that
the main libraries is verbose as
possible it's a chatty kid always
talking telling you absolutely
everything that's doing but the catch is
that you don't actually have to listen
if you don't want to so inside the lib
directory inside our J's comp directory
for our create command we can actually
have a global emitter so inside the util
I've created this emitter module and
we've instantiated a single singleton
actually of the event emitter provided
by node and then any command can
actually require that and constantly
chat about what's happening so it can
emit a log event and give a message it
can even MIT and a warren event if maybe
some folder already exists but it's just
going to plow through and use it annoys
and it can emit an air event if if
goes wrong and so these are incredibly
useful because now the CLI module can
subscribe to these events or choose to
unsubscribe
from that chatty kid and also
third-party libraries who are depending
on you can actually choose to subscribe
to you if they happen to be integrating
you into their their continuous
integration service or something like
that they may want to know what the hell
is going on so implementation wise we
can go into the lib the CLI in this case
I'm going to my argument parser so I
called it the arg v and at the very top
I'm just inspecting what were the switch
is provided so what's silent or quiet or
q provided if so let's set our V dot
silent to true and for verbose if
verbose or V were provided let's set
verbose the true and if verbose is true
let's bind to the log the warren and the
air events and just route those into the
console belt law console dot warrant or
console the air and of course is more
elegant ways to write this code but to
appease everyone in the crowd this is
the most obvious way and so now we're
able to actually subscribe to all the
details the nitty-gritty details are
going on inside our library only if we
want to and we can unsubscribe at any
time too so so it's just a beautiful
little approach that we've came up with
and finally the last point we wanted to
touch on was that a command line
interface should be interoperable so we
were all taught hopefully to play nice
on the playground with other kids and if
you're building software the story is
the same be nice so like I mentioned the
very start we might have been surprised
by it but in hindsight other tools
consuming our tools seems pretty natural
when these programs really evolved the
kind of build on each other and
eventually you get to something that's
really useful or really good and the
only possible way to have this kind of
tower of programs that are authored by
different people are different groups to
work well together is conventions and
good communication between all of them
so essentially when I'm getting into is
that exit codes are
ortant don't ignore them let's take a
look so to build on Mike's previous
point let's go into that argument parser
that's part of our magical program and
say that in verbose mode we wanted to
halt the program's process immediately
if there is ever an error message
emitted so dropping a simple process
that exit with a nonzero exit code does
the trick here whether someone's
consuming your tool at the command line
level or as a node module it'll still
work out the same way sometimes you also
want to be able to talk in ways that
other tools can understand at least
easily so perhaps we want JSON output
like so or we just want tabs and we can
do that too so just thinking about these
sorts of ideas allows us to create tools
that work well with each other and I
talked about interoperability would not
be complete without mentioning windows
the kid that's always picked last so
these sorts of problems there's really
two or three major points here bit us
early on where we iterate riddick really
quickly on our tools and it worked great
on mac and linux and then we're about to
release some and someone's like hey
let's check them out on windows and
everything's broken so simple rule to
follow is don't hardcode paths let's
take a look in this create function that
we have in our J's comic program you
might need to shell out just just an
example but at least in our project
happens a lot so the top example there
has a dot and a forward slash both of
which will blow up a Windows machine so
you don't want to do those instead you
should use your trusty friend path the
standard lib or the node standard module
to join it all together and then execute
that instead
simple tip but it saves us a lot of
hassle environment variables are a good
way to kind of figure out a few details
that are sometimes necessary to work
with when you're building command-line
tools so I'm going to show an example of
a technique to get to the user's home
directory which is sometimes useful if
you need to download stuff on the fly or
save stuff you need to get to that
director because you know you can write
to it so here we use the environment
variable one of two environment
variables depending on the platform that
the program is executing in and it will
return a proper path on that environment
and so this line actually works well and
takes into account the latest switch and
windows is that right so from windows 95
to windows 7 your home directory was
located in a user profile direct your
environment variable but in the latest
version of Windows it switches back to
home as every other st. operating system
does so this conditional least handles
that case but it's like very simple kind
of patterns that help you build
compatible tools everywhere and
thankfully node uses NP m and n p.m. is
awesome and windows friendly and one
interesting thing that took a little bit
of documentation hunting to find out was
that any dependencies that you have in
your package.json if they have binary
interfaces or command faces for their
modules NPM will add all of those
binaries to the executive search paths
before you fire any of the npm scripts
so let's take a look an example this
will die on windows because you're using
a dot and using forward slashes
essentially the situation here is say
you have some awesome test framework
like jasmine node and you want to use it
to execute respects usually you want to
type npm test in a node
jewel in a way goes your test execution
but you don't have to do that you can
just refer to Jasmine node the binary
name on its own and NPM figures out the
rest because jasmine has this binary
executive bowlin so it's it's a neat
little tip to kind of ease development
and that's it those are four major
points that we want to share with you
guys and hopefully it will improve your
command line tool authoring and thank
you very much we have a five minutes if
you guys have any questions yeah awesome
hey that's good yeah for the video he
was just pointing out that if you want
live input extending that initial proxy
interface the support streams of
standard in standard out that kind of
thing you can achieve the same
testability with more advanced CLI
Thanks yep no we were debating if you
guys want us to push that up we're cool
with it there's been like requests over
the past not not the base of project off
of but just purely as a reference we
actually used it for a co-op that we got
in the office and it got him off the
ground pretty fast but yeah if you guys
want it we can provide it I'll update
the slide deck and tweet out about it
with the link but it would be just up on
github yeah yeah front row yeah well
let's came up when we were making this
talk why aren't we talking about
libraries and libraries come and go
there's commander there's CL ijs there's
a bunch of others we've tried a lot of
them and you neva get to the point where
you want to do something slightly
different than what they're doing and
then you end up going right to the very
beginning so commanders awesome oh and
any of those other ones are really nice
but you have to buy into it 100%
otherwise you're going to start from
scratch again but even simple things
like when you want your help dialog to
appear they're very restrictive with it
so just spend an hour two hours like
hacking with and seeing if it does what
you want but I think a lot of what we
point out here would apply regardless
because too many people right there
higher code in that bin script and they
can't test that will commander can be
tested if you just treat it like a
module yeah there's someone a little
further back we had a question as well
Oh awesome okay got another question
over there
yeah so the question was if we have
deeper hierarchy and more dependencies
how do we deal with that event emitter
message with verbose and quiet for now
I've settled on just the singleton which
actually works the best if you're for
some reason your library needs instances
then it gets a little bit more
complicated but yeah so far it hasn't
been a problem at all but I definitely
could be if you start to deal with
instant space one's cool I think we're
out of time so we'll publish these
slides on this link and then shortly
you'll see a github URL with a template
as well thanks guys