um give me a second all right working
good um hello good morning uh we're
going to go from systems programming to
tech money and politics so I think we're
aiming for like hundred percent audience
alienation is the goal here so who here
and this is going to be a question that
I want to start by making you
uncomfortable who here writes code for
money I do yeah I know we're not
supposed to say that we write it clearly
for passion but um also for money who
here writes code for money at a tech
company I do not everyone does um who
here uses products program data tech
company say github or nvm who pays for
products that are programmed at a tech
company who makes products that they
sell to other tech companies that's the
thing i do not everyone does that either
tech company tech company tech company
money money money money money so tech
companies make a lot of money and
they've made a lot of people very rich
some of those people they've made rich
through profits off of sales of products
directly but not very many that's not
the typical model for tech company money
making these days mostly those profits
come from a large exit event such as it
like an IPO or a sale not such as those
are the two exit events um and the
profits from those events I don't know
why they're called that but that's what
people say the events are split between
the shareholders who own part who own
shares of that company us can be
employees it's often in some part early
employees but it's usually mostly
investors people and firms who have
given those product makers money in
exchange for a share of the company in
the hopes of this large event happening
we call early stage investors venture
capitalists um because it sounds like I
don't know an early like a victorian
cowboy novel I don't know why we call
them that but it has to do with the writ
like the risk involved and the early the
earliness of the investment I wanted to
find that because I'm going to be saying
the word
see a lot so when we work at these
companies as many of us do as I do and
many folks who raise their hands do our
labor is going to grow the investment
that these people have made some of it
may be going to grow our own investment
but its share between those things and
when it does pay off the money that's
made out of our labor goes to these
people and they use it for other things
some of that is other tech companies
increasingly more and more it's been
spent on political campaigns and races
so there is a lot of national investment
from tech companies into politics Barack
Obama certainly has gotten a lot of
money fund raising money from tech folks
lobbying if there's been almost like a
hockey stick style growth in lobbyists
paid directly by tech companies national
candidates to four million dollars was
spent this year on a house race in San
Jose trying to electro Khanna to the
house representatives as sort of a tech
company friendly legislature national
priorities tech money-wise are usually a
i'ma guard sort of immigration tax
policies cyber security and net
neutrality I am NOT going to talk about
immigration because some things are
sacred and that's absolutely a third
rail in our community so I'm not I'm not
touching it tax policy generally is the
same as everyone else tech companies
don't pay it either cyber security and
net neutrality are things that other
people have talked about and talked
about better I'm so I'm not going to
talk about national priorities in tech a
political spending I'm actually going to
talk more about spending on local state
and regional levels I believe that this
kind of political involvement has more
of an impact on our day-to-day life I
believe we're seeing more and more of it
and it's changing rapidly right now so I
want to talk about it so those are the
things that tech money cares about in
the national level what does tech money
care about on a state and regional level
so who knows it six californias is who
has seen like a badly night joke about
six californias six californias as this
plan to split California in 26 States
you know small government and all that
it's completely unworkable it's insane
it doesn't make any sense um
it was a ballot initiative they missed
the deadline in 2014 and spent so
gathered signatures for 20s their dau
gathering signatures for 2016 they
collected a million signatures to try to
get on the ballot in 2014 missed the bat
ended up being about 750,000 valid
signatures so about three quarters
actually isn't bad which says a lot
about California and initiative politics
they missed by about 50 case they're
looking to put it back on the ballot in
2016 this is Tim Draper he is a
billionaire venture capitalist he is the
son of another billionaire venture
capitalist and he's the grandson of yet
another billionaire venture capitalist
he's the founder of draper fisher jerger
and Draper associates I also believe his
son is avicii um some of his investments
are skype hotmail Tesla baidu which is
like the Chinese search engine twitch
and an unaccredited University named
after him and San Mateo offering degrees
in entrepreneurship he is the sole
funder of six californias he poured five
million dollars to buy those eight
hundred thousand signatures to get on
the ballot and he's going to pour more
into get it on the ballot in 2016 so you
know wacky rich guy right that's in by
the way this picture was taken in his
University this is the seating at Draper
University in San Mateo ah so you know
was a crazy check story right here's the
thing it's not is actually his first
political venture in two thousand there
was another time very recently where
people were making obscene amounts of
money and then investing it in local
politics I know we've forgotten that
that ever happened and and refused to
talk about what happened at the end of
it but in two thousand in the first tech
boom he sponsored a proposition state
proposition called proposition 38 prop
30 proposed to give every student in the
state four thousand dollars to attend
private school no regulations are
constraints whatsoever no means testing
nothing it was essentially a proposal to
privatize public education at the cost
of about three and a half billion
dollars to the state of California Tim
spent 23 million of his own money on
this proposition his dad threw in
another two and a half million
it was believed to be the largest
contribution by an individual to a
ballot proposition in California history
at that time so large amount of money
this was to be fair pretty beanbag wacky
that's very far to the right of even
like the most ardent voucher prophecy
proposals and it failed it did not
succeed not before the opponents of it
spent another 30 million opposing it so
this is still in the realm of crazy guy
doing crazy things in politics but he
actually was fresh off a stint on the
State Board of Education he Tim Draper
was appointed by governor pete wilson in
1998 to the State Board of Education his
main is only qualification was having
developed a business simulation game for
kids and fundraising for Pete Wilson of
course the Board of Education sets
education policy in California it orders
textbooks it's sort of adopts policy and
writes the actual practical
implementation of policies that's quite
a bit of power for someone who went on
to then propose privatizing the entire
education system Gray Davis a Democrat
was a replaced pete wilson discover 1999
Tim Draper was not reappointed in his
place however Reed Hastings was and you
probably know Reed Hastings as a CEO of
Netflix he's also on the board of
Facebook he was on the board of
Microsoft he was already rich when he
founded Netflix from a 750 million
dollar acquisition of a previous company
he helmed he was and is a major major
major Democratic donor nationally and
locally and he was a special supporter
of the newly elected governor Davis and
he stayed on the Board of Education much
longer than Tim Draper through the
beginner beginning of Governors for
teenagers term and he actually was the
President of the Board of Education for
four years and Reed had a big-money
school bell on the ballot in 2000 as
well prop 39 reduced the threshold for
local school board initiatives to pass
from sixty-six percent to fifty-five
percent so it said to pass a school bus
school bond local school bond measure
you only need fifty five percent of the
vote previously it had been sixty-six
percent and this had a big effect on
bills getting past actually to fund
school dist
locally I passed easily um partially
probably because they outspent their
opponents 621 they raised three point
flat through 30 1.5 million dollars to
pass proposition 39 and 2000 Reed gave a
million dollars of his money personally
the main Thunder was I mean then the
passing this bill was in big part thanks
to Reed's buddy and the campaign
co-chair John doar John doar is the star
partner at kleiner perkins caufield &
byers that is a very very powerful
venture capital investment firm in the
south bay they made their substantial
wealth by investing in google amazon AOL
into its son EA Genentech Zynga lots of
things have been funded by kleiner
perkins um John doar the partner gave
six million himself uh kleiner perkins
gave a million from the firm there was a
couple other partners that gave a total
of 1.5 million more than eight million
dollars basically made from investments
in these companies went to pass prop 39
so like well I got to be thinking like
all that just to lower the voting
threshold for these school bond bills
that seems like a lot of money to spend
turns out there was a provision of prop
39 that didn't have anything to do with
bond funding charter schools are private
organization some prop nonprofit and
some for-profit that run public schools
they're funded by taxpayer dollars
they're funded per student the way that
public schools are this has been a
growing movement over the past about 20
years as a way of reforming the
education system basically taking the
government out of it well not their
money um there's a proposition a in the
bill prop 39 that requires that public
districts provide charter schools with
space reasonably equivalent to those
used by non charter schools in the
district so they have to lease if they
have space they have to give it to
charter schools if they ask for it
basically and it has to be identically
furnished and located in the area the
charter school wants to locate in and so
different school districts have done
this in different ways LA Unified School
District has to fill this request
through colocation which means putting
charter
schools in the same actual building and
facilities as non charter schools which
is a very literal reading of what the
bill is asking for it's incredibly
controversial it doesn't go well very
often and charter schools are not happy
with it generally so this culminated
recently in a series of drawn-out
lawsuits against the LA Unified School
District by the California Charter
Schools Association probably wondering
where I'm going with this guess who's on
the board of the California Charter
Schools Association Reed Hastings is
recently appointed to the board there
Reed Hastings is also a co-founder of an
a major investor in aspire public
schools which is California's largest
charter provider he is on the board of
the Kipp charter school network which is
a massive nationwide network of charter
schools he's on their board along with
the CEO of Viacom he's also another
member of that board is the managing
director of Bain Capital you may
remember bain capital from the mitt
romney a presidential campaign but but
you know besides ridiculous christmas
parties with Mitt Romney and bad photo
ops they've also found it they've also
funded things like Optimizely rent the
runway and LinkedIn big pretty big tech
investment arm of Bain Capital he's also
on the board of and a major investor in
the rocketship k25 charter network which
is known for its incredibly aggressive
growth plans they have their own real
estate development agency to buy land
and build facilities for themselves this
is a really tak friendly organization
the former CEO John Danner with is a
man-made wealthy by a check by out in
the first boom the investors include the
CFO of skype sheryl sandberg from
facebook dave goldberg who's the CEO of
SurveyMonkey Arthur Rock who is a
legendary venture capitalist who
invested in fairchild semi he invested
in apple in vasant and tell their
partners from menlo ventures which found
it which funded uber and Warby Parker
accel partners who led run lead rounds
for etsy and Dropbox benchmark capital
who's founded snapchat Instagram Yelp
and then the aforementioned the kleiner
perkins and John Doerr all of these
people are major investors in we're
talking 1 million plus in rocket ship
um that's a lot of tech people that's a
lot of tech investors there's actually a
lot of money coming from tech to fund
what is often cast as a grassroots
Charter movement right and actually once
you start noticing this this is
everywhere you look Laurene Powell Jobs
is now after her husband's death has
been sort of lauded for her newfound
philanthropic interest and she's done
she's been giving massive grants to
charters vihar Emerson collective
education fund the CEO of co.org
recently gave a huge chunk of cash to
support a measure to establish charter
schools in Washington State Mark
Zuckerberg um 100 million dollar
donation to Newark schools which has
been kind of a clusterfuck was actually
focused directly on charters it was a
main tenet about 100 million dollar
donation there's a lot of money there
from tech in this movement and in these
organizations what is it being spent on
so at a certain point within the last
couple years the folks funding these
movements have turned their focus from
state propositions all of those still
exists and there's still political work
being done on the state level in favor
of charters to local governments and
there's there has been an absolutely
unprecedented flow of money from
political action campaigns into school
board elections which are you know
generally even in big cities kind of
tiny Affairs in Oakland in 2012 185
thousand dollars was spent by tech
funded packs on school board elections
here 150 k this year in West contruct
West Contra Costa County school board
election this year 350 thousand dollars
spent by one pack in a school board race
$250,000 in Santa Clara against Kennedy
and a song who's never even had outward
opposition to charters it's across the
country it's happening all over the the
focus has turned to school board races
so why is that so these are a couple of
quotes from Reed Hastings recently the
first one he's basically saying what's
the problem with school districts
definitely their democratically
school boards um apparently they're
getting a little sick of having to spend
all this money to keep candidates in
there um it's he outwardly said that one
goal of the charter school movement is
to get school board is to shrink school
board um power and this is where the
opposition that happens the school board
generally happens at the school board
large schools generally happens at the
school board level this last quote is
really instructive right it's like why
why right this is this is a huge amount
of money and a really like widespread
movement why do it and this quote ear
says basically how Reed Hastings
envisions the role of a school district
in this new model of Education is to
bring charter schools to town like a
chamber of commerce would develop
business okay I think that's a really
instructive quote why is all this money
going to charter schools so rocket ship
that I mentioned is a huge proponent of
the concept of blended learning which is
classroom time that's really focused on
it's backed up by a computer based
instruction and all of these a lot of
these charter schools are very tech
focused there's a ton of online work
that happens it's bringing tech into the
schools there's in fact there's in fact
some schools that are entirely online
doing online education what that means
is that there's a lot of software to be
made and there's a lot of software to be
sold to fulfill these needs for for for
online classes and for online education
and online tools and in fact there's an
entire new sector newish sector called
ed tech which is growing hugely it
focuses on a couple different things but
k12 ed check in particular has been a
market that's gone up hugely in the last
decade last even two three four years
it's become a huge focus of folks it's
stuff like online classes apps to drill
for tests things like that and it's it's
broad and there's a ton of money going
into it some of it directly by some of
the folks that i mentioned earlier who
investing in these charter schools
dreambox is a math online math education
program that Reed Hastings and John
Doerr recently bought for eight figures
and it's used by
all the rocketship schools it's like an
official tool that they use John Zenor
who was the CEO of rocketship actually
left to develop an app that's now used
by rocket ship schools there are VC
firms that only focus on ed tech there
are accelerators now there are multiple
ed tech accelerators some of which are
focused directly on k-12 education um
there are some challenges and investing
in ed tech as our favorite Twitter
thought leader has pointed out here in
Marc Andreessen he was also a major
venture catalyst famous for his
investment in netscape I think this is a
really interesting quote because Morgan
Driessen does invest in EdTech despite
this quote he's not saying he wouldn't
invest in EdTech he's saying these
conditions make it difficult and so one
approach to that is doing some of the
things that I talked about earlier which
is changing the way that public schools
as they're conceived sort of exists so
that you can change how they procure
things and in fact andreessen horowitz
recently hired as a political consultant
adrian fenty the ex mayor of DC who is a
very famous charter school advocate and
that's that explicitly adds a political
consultant to help them with political
interventions for their portfolio
companies another way to do that is to
create markets outside of public schools
which is tech could be you could and you
could sort of sell the charter schools
of that but even things like just last
month andreessen horowitz invested in a
new private school chain completely
private venture funded schools is kind
of an unusual model in anything there's
a thing called there's some for-profit
universities have also seen investment
from tech companies there's also not
sort of bypassing the school's
themselves and selling directly to
students and parents um there's been a
big wave of free products recently that
are designed to enhance learning and as
we know when you have a free product
from a for-profit company what's what's
being sold there is not the app itself
but it's the data and in some ways
having some sway over regulations about
the use of student data can be
really really lucrative thing for
investors so what okay so let me say
this let me just cut off a conversation
I'm not interested in having after this
talk you don't need to come up to me and
tell me about how your little niece is
in the best charter school and it's
amazing or teach for america saved your
cousin's life or whatever I don't care
and also I don't think it's actually
relevant to the point I'm trying to make
right the charter schools sort of
argument or discussion is complex right
if there's I'm by no means trying to
suggest that all of the thousands if not
millions of students in charter schools
and teachers and administrators who are
working very hard to give students good
education are evil or are scheming for
profit right but this is going on and
we're basically having a private
infrastructure built under our nose by
people who are openly advocating for
less democratic processes in order to
serve their own economic interests and
that bothers me I find it disturbing I
think that's reasonable to be mad about
that right public schooling has been
concerted considered a cornerstone of
our democracy forever right and you
might ask agree or disagree with this
particular approach to education reform
but our ability to have that
conversation at all as being usurped
right and what's more is to like to us
it's being you served with our own money
with our own labor right with with money
that we're generating so I think that's
worth paying attention to and it's worth
caring about another thing to note is
that there's something that we know
about tech companies and investors they
copy right you get for every goober you
get a lift sometimes the the models that
are copied go on to be far more
successful than the original you know
you do get things like Facebook out of
my space I want to wrap up by talking
about a way that I think that this
pattern which has been pretty successful
so far is starting to be applied again
who knows who this is yes say it say his
name if you say it three times in the
mirror he appears covered in blood this
is Ron Conway we were not going to get
through a presentation in the Bay Area
about tech money and politics without
Ron Conway um Ron Conway okay Ron Conway
is a a
like very prolific tech investor he's
invested in Airbnb in Google very early
on to so he's made a ton of money Airbnb
Google paypal Twitter Zynga Facebook
BuzzFeed reddit pinterest mint square
over 650 companies I guarantee this
morning you have interacted with a Ron
Conway investment product it's I there's
no way you didn't um every for a while
every y combinator company he was buying
shares and I mean he gets around and
he's made an absolute almost
inconceivable amount of money uh early
stage in early-stage tech investing this
is maybe his most impressive purchase to
date the entire political apparatus of
San Francisco and I am in no means I'm
by no means exaggerating and this is all
very public it's not hidden there's
articles about it i'm not going to go
too deep into it but i encourage you if
this is newer a little bit unfamiliar to
you to look into it because it's pretty
fascinating basically he in 2011 I
believe stepped in to negotiate a tax
break to allow in the way it's phrased
is to keep Twitter in the city which I
have a lot of any way we could talk
about a lunch um he negotiated a massive
tax break for Twitter and other
companies in the mid market area he
basically decided that was great I like
that let's do more of it he spent six
hundred thousand dollars getting the
mayor of San Francisco elected likely
reelected many for the just two weeks
ago the like main opposing candidate in
2015 basically said I'm too scared of
Ron Conway to run against Edley he also
bought five or six seven possibly
depending on how you're counting
supervisors on the board of supervisors
including the president the Board of
Supervisors and he's so be like this is
and this is an order to enact laws that
are favorable for companies he's
invested in and he in fact was so
blatant about buying the recent
short-term rental law in favor of Airbnb
that Airbnb competitors are suing him
for shutting them out um pretty
impressive this is Greg Suhr Greg Suhr
is the chief of police in San Francisco
he's often described as an old friend of
Ron Conway I've never found a picture of
them together but still lookin um in a
couple years ago there was a widely
publicized $100,000
donation to SFPD from SF City which is
Ron Conway's coalition of tech companies
donation is kind of an interesting way
to put it that money actually went to a
member of that coalition in order to
develop an app for SFPD and it was the
access that wrong call my has that was
made it made it possible for that
public-private partnership to happen it
was an app to access the city's crime
data warehouse in the field so he
basically engineered this way for a
company under his umbrella to be paid to
build something for the SFPD just at the
beginning of this year he announced a
series of gun safety challenges for
entrepreneurs this is in response to
Sandy Hook he came out saying you know
this is the next new thing this is where
I'm focusing my philanthropic efforts
philanthropic is an interesting way to
put it not that gun safety isn't an
incredibly worthy cause but he also has
said he's looking for the next Mark
Zuckerberg or Larry Page of gun safety
it's an entrepreneurship challenge which
he's offering to invest in tech in
technological solutions for gun violence
this is both for this a huge market
admittedly and this is both for the
private owner market which in this
country is very large but also for the
public in the last challenge in the set
of four focuses on the euphemistic
community safety which generally is
understood to mean policing a quote from
a partner of Conway's in this sort of
challenge that they've enacted there is
money to be made gun violence is
expensive to society and there's a big
potential market for solutions Ian
sobieski who's a partner in I don't even
want to say this out loud in a VC firm
called band of angels kidding me yeah
said that at those sort of launch for
this set of challenges that's really
interesting because sobieski is an
investor in SST Inc and if you've ever
done any reading into sort of military
or government contractors you know that
they're like Vegas names are the most
terrifying things assistant used to be
known as ShotSpotter oh yes if you are
an ugly resident that may be familiar
two hundred and sixty-five thousand
bucks
of Oakland money was spent on
implementing this shot spotter network
of gun supposedly audio gunshot
detectors um the police recently came
out and said yo this doesn't help us at
all well I don't like we we generally we
know when someone gets shot um to vote
ShotSpotter was on all the time not just
when it it wasn't activated by anything
it was just on all the time and recorded
voice conversation may have been a
feature not a bug um Oakland has also
been investing over the past few years
11 million dollars in the domain
awareness center which is designed to be
a surveillance hub for law enforcement
collecting things like ShotSpotter data
traffic cameras police reports stuff
like that social media posts into one
hub running it through things like face
detection software and data mining
software and you know alerting software
what I'm getting at is that that 11
million dollars was going to software
companies right again this is a market
and that 11 million it's been it's I
mean it's been scaled down somewhat and
there's been a lot of opposition
understandably because it came out in
public records requests that the overt
intention of it was to spy on activists
basically the money so far has gone to
military contractors but Google actually
put in a bid to use some of their
services in building this domain
awareness center google has products
surveillance products I they call it
something else there's some euphemism
for this like Intel or like communica
it's always community that's how you
know the techno police community intel
something like that um because they have
products that they do sell to other
municipalities they didn't you know they
didn't win this bid this time yet but
this is a market that exists it's
growing the legal sort of barriers in
place to prevent it I would argue are
possibly more more more easily
surmountable than the ones that we've
seen have basically been steamrollered
by the charter school movement so
this is kind of scary and I think if I
was a betting woman I would start a
terrible firm with a terrible pun name
um no um I suspect that what we'll begin
to see is the very valid and
understandable calls for police reform
start to be engineered and funded by
some of the folks who funded the school
reform movement and buys when I say some
of the folks who fund the school reform
movement I mean the people that we make
money for so I'm not saying this to
scold I work at a company funded by Ron
Conway I've worked at I think three
companies funded by Ron Conway I've
worked no company I worked out we've
covered in all the names that I've said
probably ninety percent of my salary has
come out of some of the names I've said
here this is a fact of life we pay rent
we do what we do I an argument you could
make is that this is the same as other
industries certainly other industries
lobbies certainly other industries have
political involvement my concern is that
while that may be true um we have very
little skepticism about some of these
initiatives particularly around ed tech
which I find troubling we're smart
people we can get our heads around this
I believe in us and part of that is just
paying attention there I did a lot of
research for this presentation but I
wasn't exactly like filing Freedom of
Information Act requests and combing
through obscure things I was reading
articles published by journalists the
stuffs out there and we should be
listening because this is our blood in
the game our skin in the game finally I
was going to open this I considered
opening this talk with a moment of
silence inspired by um Darrell hopwood
did this recently at a conference I was
that in st. Louis I thought it was very
moving and I saw sounded like make a
slide for it was just like a a moment of
silence for who like for you know like
Eric garner who recently the protests
have been focused around for Alex nieta
who was shot by the SFPD for Alan
Blueford for a local person and then the
CIA torture thing came out and when I
came right down to it I think we have
enough silence in the tech industry I
think we've
you did more than our fair share of
silence so there's a lot of chillin sort
of effects of some of this stuff I think
people feel like maybe their jobs are in
danger or something but I think that
some of that is just cowardice and I
think that getting our voice is as
people who a are making money that's
being used to implement things like this
and be you just have a lot of privilege
by the fact that we're very well paid we
should be the one saying things and we
should be paying better attention so