oh my name is Amanda glosson and I've
been pushing pixels around screens for
over 10 years now mostly what I mean
when I say that is I've been writing
software for a while but I've also
worked on my fair share of design
projects along the way recently I found
my way into pixel art which is actually
how I ended up here in front of all of
you today talking about thinking inside
the box thinking inside the box white
box am I talking about what's in the box
I should I go back the box i'm talking
about is one that is bounded by
constraints constraints are just defined
as limitations or restrictions imposed
on your project and the space inside
that is our problem space that's the bit
where we get to work and solve a bunch
of problems in the case of my pixel art
my constraints are very straightforward
pixels can either be filtered
transparent my canvas is eight pixels
wide by 16 pixels tall and recently I've
started to limit myself to the NES
palette javi very nice and neat looking
128 pixel canvas for my problem space
this isn't an awful lot of work with
when I first started out nearly every
sprite I drew felt impossible at first
how am I going to draw a drum set this
is not the right form factor it's not
even going to fit tires are round they
are not rectangular dinosaurs are really
really big
I usually only work on pixel art during
my train commute and as time went on I
began to notice that I was drawing
faster instead of only drawing one a day
starting it on the way to work and
finishing it up on the way home I was
making two a day so I made three a day
and then I was making for in I was
finding that I was more quickly finding
creative solutions inside of my problem
space and I started to suspect that my
familiarity with my constraint set was
helping me get better at this but I
wasn't really sure because there aren't
a lot of people out there who are like
yeah constrain yourself dream really
small right no one says that ever so as
soon as I started considering these
constraints I was immediately reminded
of a presentation I attended at this
year's California extreme about the
arcade game defender so this is an
arcade game that was developed in 1981
that was a long time ago it's a 2d side
scroller where the player flies the
starship around this alien terrain and
you're trying to protect these
astronauts from some aliens the talk at
California extreme was given by two
defenders developers Eugene Jarvis and
Sam dicker they were there to talk about
the constraints that they faced and
their design process when working on the
game when they started development they
had never designed a video game and they
didn't know anything about hardware so
they were like well let's get the best
cpu available now again this is 1981 so
what they got was a one megahertz
motorola 8609 with an 8-bit processor it
had some 16-bit operations they
12 kilobytes of ROM 48 kilobytes of DRAM
single frame buffer and 16 colors this
was actually pretty good at the time but
they were so really constrained by their
hardware and these constraints inform
the design throughout the development of
the game so for example Eugene Jarvis
chose to set the game in space because
he thought the abstract setting would
help to obscure their simple graphics
the landscape see at the bottom is only
a pixel wide and that's mostly because
the hardware wasn't powerful enough to
generate anything more detail again
instead of creating assets in the game
CM dicker wrote some particle effects to
generate unique explosions so that was
pretty cool powerful software at the
time because these hardware limitations
cause their graphics to be somewhat
simplistic they had to focus on their
gameplay to make a good game no no one
was going to look at this and be like oh
wow incredible even though they did have
16 colors which was kind of a big deal
of the time so they created a bunch of
characters and projectiles and each sort
of had its own personality the
personality emerged from some simple
rules based AI that they've developed
and when they're on the screen together
you ended up with a sort of notoriously
punishing ecosystem so this team of guys
with limited hardware limited hardware
knowledge developed a game which since
its release has become one of the
highest grossing arcade games ever so
they get to the end of this talk and I'm
like these guys are wizards like do
people even write software like this
anymore like I'm at work complaining
that I have to support ie7 like I having
I have incredible resource to be honest
at first I sort of dismissed this story
even being about the constraints I sort
of attributed their successes to be more
based on their programming genius so I
kept digging for other examples so I
started thinking about we're now so to
create his parent ease jiri uses the
existing melody rhythm intonation and
rhyme scheme of the original song and
uses new subject matter to illustrate a
completely different message these are
pretty intense constraints when you talk
about a song that's nearly everything so
in the case of eat it he removed one
letter of Michael Jackson's beat it to
transition a song about walking away
from violence into being one that mocks
the idea that eating food keeps it from
being wasted so his entire career has
been exploring this framework of musical
constraints and certainly he's created
on an original content but he's most
known for his parodies so okay maybe
weird owl is also a genius he's a
musical genius so I kept looking so in
nineteen sixty 54 years ago bennett cerf
that co guys all fifty dollars that he
wouldn't be able to write an
entertaining children's book with only
50 unique words you might know Theo
gazelle better by a pseudonym of dr.
Seuss dr. Seuss won that bet with his
story green eggs and ham since the
publication of green eggs and ham it
sold more than 200 million copies which
makes it the most popular of his works
and it's one of the best-selling
children's books in history so here's a
list of the 50 words that were used
that's all of them you too can go home
and make green eggs and ham so at this
point I now know that defender eat it
green eggs and ham
we're all created under heavy
constraints I think okay so there's
clearly some relationship between
constraints and ideas we've already
defined constraints as being limits or
restrictions so let's also define when
an idea is for the sake of this
exploration I want to define an idea as
being a connection between two pieces of
knowledge that you have in your brain so
you have piece of knowledge a piece of
knowledge be and the link between them
is an idea a B if we follow along with
this pretty simplistic definition of an
idea then looking for ideas is really
reduced to being a search problem that's
pretty cool so we know how to do thats
right some pseudocode so for every node
in your knowledge compare it to every
other node let's make a link and just
for complete list completeness let's
make sure it's not the same one and we
have idea ap so the efficiency of the
search is defined by the set of
knowledge that we're talking about and
if you're interested in Big O notation
you already know what the complexity of
this is but I put it on a slide so you
can take a look at it so by using this
simple definition of an idea we're able
to see that perhaps adding constraints
to limit the set of knowledge that you
have to search over for ideas could be
of a benefit simply from an efficiency
standpoint so we certainly don't want
all of the ideas and we shouldn't be
satisfied with just having relevant
ideas what we really want are the good
ideas actually scratch that we want the
creative ideas so what's your creative
idea a creative idea is a new idea that
is also useful generative or influential
useful meaning it's a new idea that
solves some sort of problem generative
meaning it's a new idea that leads to
other ideas so if you think about our
loop before maybe you make a B and you
throw it back in your set of knowledge
that it gets very messy and complicated
or it's influential meeting it's a new
idea that changes the way people think
so how do we choose our constraints how
do we do this in such a way that we are
able to narrow down our search to be
able to create these to find these
creative ideas from our previous
examples you might think oh gosh maybe
we should just add a bunch of random
constraints and see what happens but
that's actually probably not what you
want to do so let's take a look at a
paint-by-number to paint by number
Hamburg the problems faced with a
paint-by-number is totally filled with
constraints 100% the starting place is
the burger with a bunch of numbers in it
I fill in spaces spaces labeled one with
the paint that's labeled 1am and I do
the same for two and I do this until all
of the areas fill so if you and I both
do the same paint by number and we
follow the rules because we're rule
followers our pieces would come out
looking the same a coloring book page is
only a slight step up there's still not
an awful lot of room for creativity here
especially because this is horse
skeleton there are constraints that do
not promote creativity but instead
promote conformity so we need to ensure
that our problem space is actually not
well defined there needs to be some room
for the unknown and we also want to
choose these constraints strategically
if chosen correctly a constraint can
push you towards the goal that's paired
with it for example you want to promote
the expansion of real
xicon write poetry where every syllable
is going to count you have to pick the
right words you want to promote
cross-browser compatibility don't use
browser prefixes don't use bleeding edge
features or maybe only use ie8 promote
contrasts you can maybe only use black
and white for your slides so there's
also more common constraints that we're
going to find that we're not going to be
able to do a lot about for example we
need to make our clients happy we needed
to have it done yesterday regardless of
what sets of constraints you end up
stacking up they're going to create a
problem space for you to move around in
and it's probably it's probably not
going to look as nice and neat as this
it's going to be more messy it's going
to look maybe more like this your
constraints are going to overlap you're
going to create some weird spaces a
weird framework for you to work inside
of maybe after a while that space
becomes something that you fully grok a
space that you can quickly move around
and because you know where all of the
boundaries and barriers are in a space
where you start making your way into the
smaller nukes when you get wedged up
into one of those you're going to be
coming up with ideas that are generative
you're going to be looping them back in
your for loop that we talked about
earlier you're going to be creating new
ideas with them you're going to be
informative other folks that you work
with are going to pick up your ideas and
it's going to change their mind and
they're going to have new ideas with
those and ultimately these ideas are
going to be useful you're going to be
solving problems with them you're going
to be turning on creative ideas maybe
you begin to identify common constraint
frameworks in your work and they become
familiar and supportive is old friends
even if you don't become best friends
with your constraint
I hope that you'll take away some of
these ideas to help you identify
appreciate and use your constraints to
your advantage in discovering creative
solutions in the projects that you're
working on you can feel free to find me
on twitter if you want to talk about
constraints but just be sure to keep it