Good morning everyone, my name is Ali Tabibzadeh from Iran.
I'm currently living in Tehran.
It is an honor to be among you here virtually.
Today I want to share with you a very enlightening
journey I had in learning what community and
inclusiveness are all about.
This journey is by attending this very same
conference back in 2014.
The time that these concepts didn't really
mean anything in my country.
And as you can see, I've kept this T shirt
which I love very much.
To give a very brief introduction about myself,
I started my career in tech from design.
Then doing frontend development for years.
But now I have shifted towards the business
side of technology.
I've had the privilege to experience a lot
by curating three tech related ventures with
my friends over the past decade.
Currently alongside my capable partners and
colleagues, I run a little sort of focused
on digital transformation products in travel
and single finance.
The goals I want to achieve from this talk
is to give a new point of view on community
values from a perspective that has not experienced
it before.
What valuable impacts and different profits
the communities generate within themselves
and on their outer ecosystem.
And most important of all, the openness of
technology related communities that makes
them for other sectors.
It makes us appreciate the efforts more and
even do as little as we can for the communities
we are in.
And one interesting point, if it wasn't for
community, this presentation wouldn't be possible
as my good friends provided me with a camera,
a microphone, and, of course, above all, the
support.
I will approach this from two sides of the
argument.
First, how I learned about community building
for the first time in Berlin four years ago.
Important that JSConf EU had taught me and
how I witnessed and helped in partially developing
communities in my county.
Second, with two real life examples I want
to proudly say that the synergism and volunteer
work in tech related communities should inspire
other sectors to take community building more
seriously in order to evolve to a more vibrant
ecosystem.
So, where did this all start?
I used to watch JSConf videos for education
purposes on YouTube.
And once I said so myself, I wish we had something
similar in our country.
I visited their website and read online that
they are open to let us do so.
Then, maybe we should run a JSConf in Iran.
Unfortunately, back then, and still now, we
do not have safe and easy access to international
payment methods.
And then telling the curator team about it,
they surprised me by inviting me to the event.
They're so loving,aren't they?
Attending JSConf EU 2014 is where this journey
began.
Where I learned how volunteer work benefits
everyone in all important aspects of life
and business.
Because, believe me, if you are not familiar
with it, this may look or sound a bit weird.
Some words were really bold in the JSConf
sphere.
Which I didn't understand.
First was inclusiveness.
And I was like, what does it mean?
What is inclusiveness?
I had only heard about exclusiveness in my
country.
It was as if everyone was trying so hard to
get an exclusive privilege to get ahead.
Even most prominent companies and products
advertisements showed big, exclusive words
attached to them.
So, you can see my perspective.
Other words that confused me were labor of
love and not for profit.
I was wondering why someone would run this
huge event not for getting direct profit.
Because, honestly, it was the other way around
in my country.
The curators taught me a great deal about
their experience curating and running this
conference.
Explaining the experience and principles of
JSConf community and how they would use the
sponsors' support to upgrade the conference
quality and in all these matters.
Meanwhile, I was experiencing the conference
myself.
Meeting wonderful people, exchangeideas,
talking about collaboration opportunities
and receiving valuable insights and offers
from world leading sponsors and many more
fulfilling moments.
It was starting to make sense.
The pieces of the puzzle were coming together.
And the last piece was this sentence.
It is not just a conference, but a community.
You should first build the community, then
the conference would mean something.
I still remember very vividly the friendly
and productive talk I had with Christine that
when she was telling me about her experience
in creating a running the up front meetup
community with her co organizers and the CSSConf.
As you may have noticed, I also missed this
year.
So, I came back very pumped with a crystal
clear vision.
I gathered a couple of people who I thought
would be interested and they were in.
Back then the Iranian system was at its infancy,
the startups, just starting to build one with
baby steps.
First the Iranian sort of accelerator was
founded six months after my return.
So, back then we had to approach more to additional
entities and venues.
Unfortunately, we didn't find much luck and
we got some empty promises that were never
fulfilled.
There was only one tech meetup back then.
The Linux user group, which were mostly hosted
in software companies.
I attended a session right after coming back
to Tehran for the first time.
It was quite a lovely community.
They had their own benefits and own challenges.
But more importantly, a bit far from the web
community.
So, there was no room for the specific topic
of JavaScript.
We continued attracting support, explaining
the vision and talking about the community
which will have the comprehensive conference
with the JSConf.
We got some interesting answers in return.
They were like not for profit conference?
What are you talking about?
And sometimes they didn't have an answer to
that thought.
It was our passion, but [audio breaking up]
the timing is not right.
Maybe we should try later in the future.
During this time, I was working on my second
startup to figure out what to do next.
And this they urged me to get back to business.
The time passed.
In one and a half years, the Iranian ecosystem
grew significantly.
Suddenly you would see a number of businesses,
accelerators and community events were starting
to pop up here and there.
When I was so caught up building our new business,
I was thrilled to hear that my friends were
finally able to do that and curated a community
for Tehran called Tehran JS.
This wonderful meetup by these three people
that you see their pictures.
Tehran JS meetup has been held averagely every
two weeks since early 2016.
It has now almost 1,000 members and new members
joining every day.
I was glad to see they had the right principles
and a lot of good work was being done in this
community.
And you saw a few pictures of them.
This is where the second side of the argument
will begin to conclude.
As we were new in tourism and pursuing niche
markets that no one had entered before, we
thought that maybe it's best if we created
a community for the travel industry to make
a positive impact.
We wanted to apply the community building
principles and create an inclusive platform
for everyone to benefit from.
So, we started tourism up in August 2016.
Here you can see a few pictures of our events.
This event was held on a monthly basis.
And over the six months we had the pleasure
to host more than 300 participants in two
chapters in Tehran.
Now, I want to do an honest comparison between
these two community building endeavors and
sharing with you what happened to them and
why.
Tehran JS was thriving.
It was fulfilling every aspect that the community
promises.
When I contacted my friends in the organizing
team to talk about joining forces for running
JSConf together, they were open to any forms
of collaboration.
So, this is very beautiful.
This is where we talk about openness and inclusiveness.
In the community side, it was exhilarating
to see how people were submitting talks, to
volunteer in running the event, offering each
other projects and companies were finding
talents to hire.
Benefits for all.
This is, indeed, where it is worth the effort
to curate the community.
On the other hand, despite putting tremendous
efforts and resources into this, we couldn't
achieve the same thing in tourism app.
Where the technology mind set was involved.
After a few events, we had to try so hard
to find speakers.
When creating task forces for joint community
projects, people would volunteer, but unfortunately,
not deliver.
We do not blame them at all.
We have to accept these as facts.
Because, despite Iran's potential in tourism,
the industry is not yet advanced.
And it is suffering from traditional ways
of doing business.
People were so occupied with their daily hustle
and so under the impression of inclusiveness
in projects that they were unable to see the
benefits in community.
We accepted this failure after six months.
And we thought maybe it's best to temporarily
shut it down so the industry can evolve and
then we can come back.
When no one could benefit from this community,
it was no longer good to waste everyone's
resources and time on this.
As we went through a comparison between success
and failure stories, I think this is the only
sentence we can get as the conclusion.
Proactive participation by all is key.
And technology is built by the very same spirit.
That is why there is less burden in applying
this in technology communities.
No single entity can run a community.
A community is formed by effort of the many.
Last year Whitney Williams said in her speech
that leadership in communities are by the
many, to the by the few.
So true, isn't it?
I am proud to say that the JavaScript community
is thriving in Iran by many people's contribution.
And we are starting to find forward thinking
sponsors.
We hope to hold the JSConf Iran conference
in the next year with the help of its international
family.
And we strongly hope we can see you here in
Tehran someday soon.
To wrap this up, we all know that the small
actions create big impacts.
This might take time.
So, does every sustainable and long lasting
result.
Our small actions and giving back to the society
creates social capital.
A meaningful concept that can help us in every
aspect of our lives.
I believe I am talking in a place that everyone
knows and appreciates the values of this.
But it is worth sharing this side of the story
for more encouragement.
This feedback, I believe, are what drives
us to be active community players.
We all have learned a lot and given back to
the open source community.
But I think there is more to OSS than open
source software.
Let's think of it as the open source spirit.
This is why we should be proud of ourselves
that we are community builders.
Not lobbyists.
Thank you, everyone, and I hope to reunite
with you very soon whether in Iran or at any