hello good morning a little early for
those of us who came from the west coast
or further timezone so thank you for all
being here this is jas comp if you're
not sure if you're not in not supposed
to be in Jas calm please leave now
there's the door you still have time to
get out before we unleash the drones too
late so I am dead program in the real
world my name is ron evans but that's
not very important right now I'm the
ringleader of hybrid group so this other
guy here is a DS ankush also known as
Adrian's ankush in the real world but
most interestingly he's the serious
programming guy at hybrid group so that
means he does all the work and I take
all the credit which is nice that's a
joke or is it we'll discuss that later
it's about so we're with the hybrid
group were a software development
company based in Los Angeles California
home of the flying space robots that is
not a joke if you're a fan of either the
jet propulsion laboratory or SpaceX you
know I'm not actually making this up
we're also the creators of kids Ruby
which is an award-winning free and open
source tool to teach kids programming
but that's not very important we're here
to talk about javascript robotics this
is Maria I thought was a lecturer but I
was confusing my mythologies amarilla
she's the leader of a robot proletarian
revolution but that's a whole separate
talk let's talk about that the future is
already here but it's not very evenly
distributed at least that's what the
author and futurist william gibson's
it's really true isn't it when was the
last time you went to an apple store you
can buy drones there you can even buy
robots at best buy there is a lot of
amazing hardware happening but the
software has not really kept up with the
hardware even though you can buy all
these cool and interesting devices
there's no easy way to hook them all up
to do something useful that's why we
created Cylon jas Cylon Jas is a
JavaScript framework for robotics
physical computing and the Internet of
Things or as i like to call it the real
world web except that doesn't flow off
the tongue so it supports multiple
hardware devices different hardware
devices and multiple different hardware
devices at the same time so cool this is
all thanks to the amazing concurrency
that we can have via nodejs and the v8
engine so Cylon j/s makes programming
devices as easy as web development well
you're going web development easy yes it
is really easy compared to the sad old
days of the 90s when we all use gopher
thank you thank you for the history
buffs so what programming devices has
just been really too hard and so Cylon
jess is a framework designed to make
that as easy as web applications are
today so it has a built-in API because
of course without an API you can't
program your internets over the
intertubes and that's no good you need
robotic internet control devices right
it has test-driven robotics built-in we
think this is really important I know
that some people claim TDD is dead I
think they're a little confused if
Toyota for example yes I own Prius if
Toyota they have only used test-driven
robotics as part of their brake system
just imagine if GE or GM you know GM
with their ignition system I mean
there's a lot of examples where people
do hardware based development and their
idea of testing is flip on the switch
and then step back hoping that it
doesn't bite you on the way it's kind of
dangerous so test-driven robotics and
the command line interface
because CLI is the new API you don't
want to be using GUI tools to program
your devices or they get them started
you want to be able to use a command
line interface to do all the normal
things that you would do fact we have a
name for this we call it robot ops it's
DevOps for robotics we have a whole
separate website for this at robot ops
com our CLI is actually a separate set
of tools from our robotics framework
it's called Gort you can check that out
at Gortat I oh so Gortat I 0 for the CLI
tools robot ops com for DevOps for
robotics but let's get to the actual
demo you guys ready to see some real
robotic devices yeah oh hell yeah so
we're going to start with the canonical
microcontroller the Arduino so the
Arduino is a very very simple
microcontroller you can buy them
everywhere radioshack even sells them
yes the shack is back if you need parts
go there so here's a very simple example
of a Cylon program so the first thing we
do is we say var Cylon requires Cylon
which as everybody here probably uses
notice how you bring in the main Cylon
module then we declare our robot Cylon
has a declarative syntax as opposed to
an imperative one so you define the
things that you're going to use and then
they just work so we say our salon robot
has a connection to an arduino using the
fermata adapter on pork dev TTYL ACM 0
which if you're using Linux is your
default serial port so we have a single
connection then we have a single device
which is this led which is using the LED
driver on pin 13 and then the work that
we're going to do the work that we're
going to do is every one second we're
going to my dot LED table which will
cause the led to flash on and off and
then last we tell the robot to start up
so we see here the three important
conceptual ideas behind Cylon j/s the
first one is connections which are using
the adapter pattern which is a software
design pattern similar to the way that
object relational map to use different
kinds of database back-end engines
without changing your
ode Cylon jess allows you to use
hardware devices different hardware
devices but using the same code by
changing the adapter and then the driver
we're using the double adapter pattern
so we have adapters for our connections
and then we have separate ones for
drivers so the code for an LED is
exactly the same whether you're running
it on the BeagleBone black or a
raspberry pi or an arduino so here's our
some video and so we have here the
arduino and it's plugged in to the
largest LED that we could find
conveniently and so what an adrian runs
the code here it's going to be
communicating using the serial interface
and yes it is blinking gratuitous
applause applause for a two thousand
five hundred dollar lamp so it's using
the fermata protocol which is running on
the microcontroller itself this is the
same way that Johnny Five and a lot of
other similar robotics tools work it's
actually communicating from the computer
to the microcontroller via serial
interface so let's look at another
device the tehsil who here is hard of
the tehsil alright so Tesla is a
JavaScript powered microcontroller you
actually run JavaScript that's been
compiled into Lua on the device itself
so we brought one of those let's take a
look at the code the code looks almost
exactly the same as the Arduino okay we
once again we declare Cylon we say our
Cylon robot this time the connection is
to a tehsil using the tehsil adapter but
otherwise it's exactly the same we're
still using the LED device the work that
we're doing is exactly the same every
one second we're going to my LED toggle
so will not everyone has actually have a
chance to look at one of these little
guys there i believe shipping on monday
that's what the email said so so this is
the tussle it's plugged in to exactly
the same bread board with the same Led
you know because we're trying to save
money
also you know mercury led there's a lot
of nasty chemicals in your electronics
don't just throw them in the trash
properly recycle them all right moving
on so we're going to run the exact same
code and this time however we're going
to compile the Cylon code and it's going
to execute right on the tehsil itself so
example 1 we were on the computer
talking to a microcontroller example 2
with the tassel we're going to do the
exact same thing and yes tehsil blink
okay see now we're down to much more
reasonably cost flashing lamp yeah just
so just so you know the previous example
with the Arduino my computer was
communicating to the Arduino through the
serial interface this one the code is
actually running on the board itself so
with silent jsu can actually write your
firmware that runs on this
microcontroller itself so you don't need
a computer at all for this so the only
reason why I'm plugged into this is for
power so if i had a battery pack or
something this could be completely
isolated somewhere with the firmware
running written in silent jeaious
somewhere doing something controlling
some led somewhere exactly somewhere in
the world and LED is blinking alright so
now let's move on to the BeagleBone
black so the BeagleBone black is a
single board system on chip linux
microcomputer it's very similar to a
Raspberry Pi but better if better is
defined as more processor more memory
and more capabilities so the BeagleBone
black we have Cylon j/s running on there
let's look at the code should look
exactly like the code you've already
soon right in this case once again
require Cylon we're making a connection
this time using the BeagleBone adapter
and once again the same our friend the
LED driver but we named the pin a little
differently and Cylon Jess we have
mappings so that whatever is labeled on
the board is what you use in your code
so no more looking through data sheets
trying to figure out the mysteries of
naming and it turns out this one is 43
but that one's actually p to underscore
12 or in this case p 9 underscore 12 so
we make it a lot easier for you to just
look at how it's labeled write the code
the same way plug it in and it should
just work let's just take a quick look
is again the tehsil code here is the
arduino code so arduino code tussle code
beaglebone black code same basic code
just with little tiny tweaks you see a
pattern selling the form alright so
let's take a little look at the
BeagleBone it looks very much like all
these boards tend to look it's a surface
mount components with some heathers the
BeagleBone black has I believe 68
digital i/o lines that can be used for
general purpose i 0 for analog for i
square c which a lot of devices like
lcds and accelerometers and other things
use and so adrian is going to tell us
what you're going to do allow me to
explain so so we have no Jas running on
this beaglebone black so this computer
this is actually a full fledge ARM based
linux computer so these two previous
examples this Arduino is a
microcontroller that we are
communicating with over a serial
interface remotely controlling the pins
this tehsil is a microcontroller that
runs java script directly on the board
so this has no operating system just
running pure code this is a full linux
computer which are writing a Cylon
program that runs on the computer so you
know it's three different use cases for
how you control pans and that sort of
thing so let's run this program really
quick he's SSH tin and so he's actually
executing the code on the BeagleBone
black itself or you would be if it hit
run this is how you know it's real and
it blinks yes
all right hello I'm going to do a
karaoke song not just kidding all right
so this is the perfect time for the
choose your own Hardware adventure yes
choose your own Hardware adventure
because we came provisioned with all
sorts of awesome gear from our wonderful
friends in case you're wondering how we
got so much of it so this is your
opportunity to get some of this so to
win a sphero 2.0 to win the spirit two
point oh just go on the Twitterverse and
tweet go Sphero and Cylon Jas okay so go
straight on silent yes if you want to
win a sparrow two point oh if you want
to win a pebble smartwatch tweet pebble
and Cylon Jas and if you want to win a
BeagleBone black tweet beagleboard org
kind of long eagle board oregon's hi
lenge so those twitter names again to
win the Sphero tweet ghost Pharaoh and
Solange is to win a pebble tweet pebble
and Solange is or to win a BeagleBone
black tweet beagleboard org and Solange
ass all right on with the show spero
plus leap motion alright so a bunch of
people have seen the Sphero it's a very
cool we call it the Minimum Viable robot
it is a toy it looks like a toy it is in
fact a toy but it does have a few
interesting characteristics one of them
in has input it has a built-in
accelerometer so we can detect
collisions the other it is that it has
two different forms of output one is
that it can roll around it has a
built-in accelerometer as I mentioned so
it can auto stabilize the same way as a
segue or a myth or some other kinds of
robotic devices and it can change the
color of its built-in RGB LED so let's
take a look the code here is a little
bit more complicated we can see now an
example of using two different devices
at the same time so we have two
connections we have the leap motion
connection and then the Sphero
connection so the leap motion the leap
motion is a gestural controller that
plugs directly into your computer and
then allows you through its built-in
camera and infrared projector to figure
out where your hands are positioned and
use those as a way without any wire
at all to control some kind of device so
it puts out to data via web sockets and
so you can see here's the poor that's
running on then the Sphero the squirrel
work it's a Bluetooth device but we're
using a Bluetooth to serial connection
so again our old friend this case it's
RF calm 0 which is the typical port used
by Linux again if you're doing robotics
and you're not using Linux you're
probably doing it wrong but that's a
whole another rant so then we have two
devices the leap motion and the Sphero
then the work that we're going to do
we're going to turn on the tail light of
the sparrow so we could tell which way
it is pointing or pointing away from
then here is our event syntax it looks
exactly like the kind of event syntax
that you've seen as a no developer
because in fact it is so on my leap
motion dot on hand we grab that data
from the hand and we scale it using some
of our built-in scaling functions since
you have to do a lot of scaling when
you're moving from for example the leap
motion to a servo or something of that
sort so we scale the hand x and y
coordinates to something that the Sphero
can use then every one second we're
going to roll the Sphero or we're going
to sorry we're going to set the color to
a random color then every point 01
seconds we're going to look at that data
from the leap motion and decide which
direction the roll around in the reason
we have to do this is we need some way
to manage the concurrency the leap
motion puts out data a lot faster
because you can wave your hands very
quickly and they could detect that a lot
more quickly then the physical device
can respond in this case the Sphero and
then last we Cylon dot start so let's go
back to my camera so we was this way we
can kind of see both his hand so he's
waving his hand okay that's better
look ma just a hand this is really fun
oh we by the way we have a table in the
makerspace area along with the node BOTS
team and the node rockets team and the
bunch of other cool people so what if
your are wandering around and you're
bored of the hallway track and you just
don't have the attention span you know
come on in there we have lots of parts
and you can play with this stuff we have
a leap motion that each person could use
but you can't keep them or else working
to get in big trouble all right so Spiro
plus robo so we're going to show
something completely different now with
this Pharaoh who here knows Conway's
Game of Life all right so only a few
mathemagical people so a brief
description so there was this guy named
John Conway not John Connor that's a
fictional character John Conway John
Conway a man completely obsessed with
mathemagic specifically he keeps looking
at these flocks of seagulls and he knows
seagulls are not especially intelligent
and yet they fly in these amazing
formations he can't stop thinking about
it like off mathematicians and he sits
down with a piece of paper and thanks
really hard and solves a problem that
problem becomes a whole new field of
mathematics that we call cellular
automata or more popularly artificial
life so he makes this game known
popularly as conway's game of life and
it's normally played on graph paper
which I highly recommend you go out and
get the pad a graph paper because it's
an amazing tool for creativity all good
ideas start on graph paper you don't
have to stay within the lines you can
just know they're there and it makes you
feel nice all right so Conway's Game of
Life these little circles ourselves and
the squares are an absence of cells so
each one of them follows the same basic
set of three rules so the first rule is
if you're RSL and you have less than two
neighbors you die because of loneliness
if you have exactly two other neighbors
then a new cell is born
into an empty square and if you have
three neighbors then you die from
overpopulation so with these same basic
three sets of rules you go through each
one of the squares and depending on
whether it has a cell or not you apply
these rules so first move would look
like this and the second one would look
like this so we thought it'd be really
cool to create conway's game of life but
with robots just take anything in the
universe and add with robots and see
whether it does it's kind of fun so but
we realize that we're going to be a few
changes we'd have to make first of all
we don't have a really fast 3d printer
that can create news Pharaoh's on the
fly in case you're wondering how we get
new ones to be born working on that also
they have no eyes they can only detect
collisions by way of the built-in
accelerometer so because we are all
family use something called an inverse
Fourier transform which basically allows
us to take a slice of time and then
using the number of collisions we detect
within that slice of time we create a
number which corresponds to the
approximate number of neighbors all
right you guys got that cool moving on
so here's the code so what we're going
to do is we're going to run five
sphero's which we've named Thelma Louise
grace Ada and Mary but Mary is supposed
to be Missy which stands for Missy
Cummings first a female fighter pilot in
the United States Navy and an associate
professor of human-machine interfaces
and I believe Duke anyway so each one of
these Pharaoh's is going to be running
the exact same code so let's see what
that code is so our Conway robot we have
a connection and a device which we're
going to fill in the port number when we
start them all up then they're born when
they're born we set the number of
contacts and age 20 they have life and
they have movement so when they move
they move around in a random direction
that's a little bit different there is
no randomness in the original Conway
game but we're very random people so we
thought it'd be fun so when they come to
life they are alive and they turn green
when they die they stop moving and they
turn red if they have enough contacts
then they can stay alive so when one of
these robots has its birthday
we tell it happy birthday if it has
enough contacts and it's not alive
meaning already dead it comes back to
life zombie mode zombie robots it's real
otherwise they die if they don't have
enough contacts and so then the work
that we do is we connect start detecting
collisions we detect them and we keep
this counters every three seconds we
move if we're still alive every ten
seconds we have a birthday so life is
hard short and spherical in Faeryland
and then we're going to start out for
each one of the bots that we declared
initially in that first array we're
going to go through and we're going to
see here's a new conway robot we're
going to tell it which port and what
name it has and then we're going to
start it out and then this line here
we're going to turn on Cylon j/s is
built in API it has an express jsapi
built right in and we also have a single
page web app built using angularjs
called Robo so similar to the way your
router has an admin page that's just
built right in we have Robo built right
into all of the Cylon Jas code that you
write that way you can test to see only
my case my code is not working but why
that's the interesting question we can
go in and we can use Robo to figure that
out so first of all what's is the rather
still armed it says its own wee brother
on Wi-Fi something to do with not trust
in conference Wi-Fi can't imagine you
doc disconnected you didn't pay your
AT&T bill it says it's my mifi oh I
didn't pay my bill what's now it's back
on oh well we saw the ATT cell tower
here it's in a truck that's parked
Connor on the back 40 this is not the
joke we can show it to you later if you
don't believe us what if you want
cellular signal just kind of wait don't
move all right
he's going to connect you'll know that
they're connected because they stop
flashing we take on the sustained color
standing by their thinking think think
think think
just imagine when you're in orbit and
you're waiting like we're waiting
houston we're standing by yeah exactly
45 minutes later when you ping Mars and
your it didn't work hmm 45 minutes later
you ping Mars again that's weird it
worked this time all right well four out
of five all right they're rolling around
they're looking for love in all the
wrong places they need to clogged with
each other actually with anything some
people have said how do you tell when
they only collide with each other and
not the walls well a wall is a sphere of
Taurus Pharaoh and it's going to restart
it really quick okay okay
standing by
the death star explodes that's a very
interesting question he asked when does
the death star explode that brings up
the question was it contractor failure
or were they partisans who inserted a
design flaw intentionally we could
discuss this at the bar later but I'm
original trilogy for life keep that in
mind almost there we're going to go to
the next demo if you don't get it this
time I'm getting bored I mean I don't
got all day so little to do so much time
wait strike that reverse it yes not that
that one didn't count do not look at the
Sphero behind the curtain something's
not going alright I'm ready to move on
to the next mo well they're not playing
well with each other actually we have
nothing to do with this game there is no
human robot yet alright so let's move on
to the next demo if you want to see the
Conway's Game of Life is Pharaoh's come
find this in the hackerspace alright
let's get into some drones because since
we didn't have the swirls working not
having the drones working will be so
much more interesting so we have support
for the ar.drone thanks to the hard work
of the node copter team which we wrap
around like many of the library's we use
if you haven't noticed we support all
the same hardware plus a lot more it's
because we are standing on the shoulders
of giants not on their toes so we're
going to show an AR drone with opencv a
ps3 controller and the neuro sky so what
is this all about so the ar.drone it's
the popular parrot ar.drone that if
you've been to a node copter you've
early flown we're going to be using
opencv which is an open source computer
vision package that is very very
commonly used for
things like facial recognition or edge
detection we're going to fly it around
with a ps3 controller which we're using
I believe we're using a library that was
partly created by Andrew despot and then
we're going to use the neuro sky
brainwave r either we're not going to
fly the drone with the brain that would
not be a very good idea because most
people do not have enough brain control
to even fly without the brain controller
instead we're going to monitor the brain
waves of our pilot and if he gets really
nervous will know all right so put that
on here let's take a look at some code
while he's getting ready so once again
VAR Cylon requires Cylon that's how
everything starts out and then we
dynamically include the modules that are
needed for whatever Hardware you're
using in this case we're using three
connections we have a connection to open
CV we have a connection to the DualShock
3 joystick and we have a connection to
the ar.drone itself then we have four
devices the first one is the matrix not
the matrix you're thinking of this is
the matrix that's used by opencv for its
optical recognition then after that we
have the window so that we can actually
see with the drone sees we have the
controller for the do shock 3 and then
we have the drone itself flight
commander so we can control it so we
have a little helper the validate our
pitch so we don't flip over then the
work that we're going to do is we're
going to grab the data and we're going
to show it on the screen okay so every
time we get a new PNG file from the
camera we're going to display it inside
of the window then based on the
different controller we're going to
either take off if you press the square
if you press the triangle will hover if
you press X will land etc then every 0
so if you ever use set interval you
probably wondered at its API because
it's really confusing we didn't like it
so we wrote our own little helper around
it every 0 does something as quick as it
can but asynchronously so every 0 we're
going to grab the joystick info and then
based on whether you put it left-right
turning or pitch or y'all we're going to
change those
then some similar fashion we're going to
do the same thing for the rotation and
then if we lose control we're going to
hover now here's the code for the narrow
sky headset we're running another little
separate Cylon program we're just
grabbing the neuro sky data and then
we're going to log it so let's see if
this works here oh wait I got to run my
code
okay there's Adrienne's brain on
JavaScript so we could tell if he's
getting really nervous the door is right
there under the tables works the battery
life of the ar.drone is maybe seven to
12 minutes of full flight good to know
right and this way we can kind of see
not we really are standing by standing
by
standing by yeah everyone turn off your
Wi-Fi just kidding
banking working working working
uh-huh let's go see what his brain has
been doing this whole time looks kind of
erratic bro so now you're trying to
decide should i watch the drawn or watch
his brain
there is a lot of interference in your
brain or the drone if it crashes into
you we're really sorry
so Cylon ps3 AR Drone and neuro sky ooh
no humans were injured alright we have
one last demo and then we got to get out
of here because there's a lot of other
cool people doing a lot of other cool
things so now we're going to show you
the mother of all demos we're going to
show you a pebble watch that's featuring
our to controlling an AR Drone with
opencv doing facial recognition then
controlling some sparrows and the digits
park running on the drone itself in
other words are too so let's explain
very briefly so what is r2 r2 is the
same idea Cylons yes but it's written in
Ruby we call it Ruby on robots because
we love many languages so we're going to
use our to communicating with a pebble
smartwatch here's the code same exact
idea as what you saw we don't have time
to go through the whole thing but it's
the same basic idea of what you already
saw but in Ruby same design software
architectural design pattern in this
case we're going to detect when the
button pushes and then we're going to
start the whole thing off using the API
alright so then we're going to
communicate with our drones running
Cylon j/s in this case we're going to be
doing the facial recognition part so
that's why we need the matrix again so
we're going to look at your face and if
it's recognized based on a generic human
face so any human will work basically
when we detect that face if we detect a
phase we're going to send an API command
to another microcontroller that's
running on the drone itself so we have a
very very small little USB powered
microcontroller called the digits park
which is plugged into the USB port
that's on the ar.drone and we have this
led plugged into the top of it attached
via either electrical or duct tape
depending on what was available so um
when it detects that it's going to send
a command that we're going to flash the
LED on the top of the drone so when it's
looking at a human than the detects it
the LED will start to blink the sphero's
will start to go crazy and you will be
able to see a green outline around the
human face through our Universal video
adapter and so we're controlling the
we're actually running code on the
ar.drone itself it's actually
board linux computer of its own and
we're using go bot which is our go
language framework so we're basically we
have our two is going to tell the Cylons
to command go bot if everything goes
well and here's a some go code if you
haven't looked at go this is the go code
that we're running on the ar.drone
itself that's basically it's that same
blink that you saw before but now
implemented in go and communicating with
the digis park all right so now he's
waking them up everything all at once in
one massive demo what could go wrong
nothing could go wrong especially if
you're sitting in the back you're pretty
safe normally we choose a volunteer /
test subject / target but now that we
can start it all off through the pebble
that means he gets to be both the
serious programmer and human subject a
human subject it sounds really nice
you've got humanity you are the point of
the whole thing how can you complain
it's all about you ma'am
how many devices can we use all at once
we could probably add a few more but we
don't have enough time like we're losing
devices rapidly device attrition you
started out with like 40 and you end up
with 3 there could only be one think
think think think think
all right let's do this do you need me
to increase the screen size when it runs
ok all right so you get in front of the
drone you get between me and the drone
all right
goes
where's the video there are this oh it
would spotted somebody else behind you
quick throw yourself between him and it
so you see the light on top is flashing
every time that you see the green square
because when it recognizes a face
friendly or otherwise we're stripping
the humans in this room alright the
mother of all robotics demos what's that
fun you guys have fun did you enjoy that
I certainly did thank you so join the
robot evolution not revolution that
those usually don't work but the
evolution seems to work fairly well
given our current status so join us
solange is calm or Cylon j/s on Twitter
are two dot IO or are two I owe on
twitter if you prefer Ruby go bot I 0 or
go bot I oh if you'd like to explore the
exciting world of concurrency in the go
programming language thank you very much