[Applause]
I'm really excited to be kicking us off
today and I'm very excited because I'll
be talking about tamagotchis and es6
generators so quick recap I'm Jen I'm a
front-end architect at a company called
the wing we are based out of the United
States and we build co-working spaces
that are women first if you want to
reach me the best place is twitter my
handle is girl code girl with a u and at
the end I'm definitely gonna post these
slides so if you miss something do not
worry the slides are gonna be posted ok
how many of you had a tamagotchi
ok a good number of you so if you aren't
familiar with what a Tomahawk is it was
a really popular digital pet in the
1990s it was a handheld device like this
and the game was that a Tamagotchi would
appear on the screen in a shell it would
break out of its egg and then you were
responsible for raising the Tamagotchi
to adulthood so it would go from a baby
like this to a teenager to an adult and
then when it became an adult you didn't
know what type of Tamagotchi you were
gonna get so that was like the fun
surprise of it now I had a Tamagotchi
growing up in fact they were even banned
from my school because they made a
beeping sound when they need something
from you and unfortunately that meant a
lot of my Tamagotchis didn't make it
rest in peace but I really really love
this game growing up and I decided I
want to make a web based version of it
so my web-based version includes an SVG
shell for the game the controls are
actually made out of divs and then the
screen is made out of the canvas element
now if you've never worked with the
canvas element it's really easy to work
with you're going to query the Dom for
the canvas element and then to draw on
the canvas you're going to request the
type of context that you want so in this
case we want to D not 3d and then you're
gonna
an image to draw and some XY coordinates
that I'm really not going to get into
right now because they don't matter as
much and you're gonna do draw image that
image to the screen so you can see that
my Tamagotchi is drawn to the screen and
then for the animations in the game I
decided I want to use a sprite sheet so
below is the sprite to bounce the
Tamagotchi so if you go one two three
I'll go up so if I need to animate this
I need to draw it at zero and then 200
and then 400 pixels so that's going to
bounce the Tamagotchi up and then I
would do those coordinates the opposite
way to go down now you'll also notice
that I'm using context clear between the
drawings and that is to avoid this
situation so if you don't clear between
your drawings they just draw right on
top of each other so you always draw and
then clear and so the way this code is
written this this isn't going to work so
I'm pressing one of the controls and as
you see the Tamagotchi is just one of
the frames being drawn and that's
because we're drawing and clearing the
contact so quickly that you only see the
last frame being drawn you're not gonna
see the other ones so what I actually
need to do with this animation is that I
need to delay it so the original game
has this really old school like choppy
animation so that's what I want to do I
want to delay it like that and I can use
set timeout to do this and this works so
now you can see the Tamagotchi is
bouncing up and down I'm going from
frame 1 2 3 and then back for a full
bounce but you know this has actually
created a problem for me because now all
of my animations are async so you know
how do I know when an animation has
completed how do I know when I can
safely kick off another animation
without overwriting the previous one the
truth is I don't I'd have to sort of
measure and keep track of how long these
animations take and that's just not
sustainable for a game that is full of
animations
what I want is to resolve an animation
and then handle another animation and
this sounds a lot like a promise
now promises represent eventual values
so I can animate inside of a promise
resolve it and because it's a venable I
can then kick off another animation so
for the first version of this game
that's exactly what I did
I used promises for every animation I
made a general purpose animate function
that takes in a draw function and the
milliseconds for the delay so animate
always returns a new promise and inside
of that promise an inner function runs
the draw function and we delegate
resolving the promise to the draw
function so if the draw resolves the
promise and returns true we're done
otherwise set timeout is called with the
inner function and another loop of this
occurs so here we're going to use the
animate function to create a bounce up
animation we're gonna pass a function
that draws the correct frame it's gonna
clear the context it's gonna increment
the current frame and when the current
frame is greater than the frame count
the promise is resolved and we return
true now this would stop the function
from setting another loop via set
timeout so now we can create a simple
bounce function using our bounce up
animation and it bounced down animation
using the same animate function and as
you can see our Tamagotchi is bouncing
now with those animations out of the way
what we need to work on is creating the
main game loop so when you're not
interacting with the Tamagotchi it goes
through a loop it sort of bounces up and
down moves a bit this way moves it that
bit that way it bounces up and down and
this is what it's doing when it's idling
when you're not doing anything with it
so to setup that we're going to create a
loop function and we're going to call
the idle animation and when that
completes we're gonna call the loop
function again
and I thought this is great totally fine
except I actually created more problems
so the first issue that I noticed is
what I refer to as Venable hell so once
upon a time we used to use async calls
on the front end with callbacks and this
created the dreaded triangle of doom aka
callback hell but one of the issues I
noticed when creating this game was that
promises actually don't alleviate
callback hell you're still in hell it's
just a different looking hell so you
know the left side is a more realistic
version of how these animations might
work I mean might need to pass in some
information to functions or check
information to make a decision and this
gets just as unwieldy and as
unmanageable as callback hell you know
this doesn't resolve that issue for me
and you know I actually really love
promises I think they're really great
but when you're using them for very
large-scale async work the ease of
promises really tends to break down so
you know the point of the tamagotchi is
that the user can interact with it and
this is where we come up with our second
issue that I found because Venable hell
is one thing this is a completely
different thing now it's it's looping
it's idling I need to interrupt that at
some point because you're gonna have to
feed the Tamagotchi at some point or
play with the Tamagotchi to up its
happiness the whole game is actually
about you interacting with the
Tamagotchi so what I need to do is I
need to suspend the idle animation in
favor of a user-generated event so if
you want to feed the Tamagotchi I gotta
stop idle and then you can feed the
Tamagotchi
so here I've added an array to hold
pending events the loop function is
going to check if there are any pending
events and if there are the handle event
function is run and the loop is
terminated so handle event is going to
take the first event off the queue and
it's going to run it and when it's
complete we're gonna restart the loop
and if there's another event in the
queue
handle event will get called again
otherwise we're gonna continue the loop
until the next event and unfortunately
the problem that I found was that this
just doesn't work so I'm requesting to
feed the Tamagotchi
but the feed animation is actually
delayed until the idle animation
completes so this can be upwards of
seven to eight seconds and this is not
going to work what I actually need to do
is cancel the promise that runs the idle
animation except you can't cancel
promises promises are unbreakable vows
you can throw errors and promises and
you can catch those errors but you can't
actually cancel a promise all the
attached then functions are going to
fire what I want actually is to pause an
animation and then yield to an event and
this sounds a lot like a generator so
generators are amazing because their
code that can be paused all of the code
that you write is run to completion
except for generators all the code that
you write usually once it starts it just
goes from top down to the bottom even if
you're doing async work it's thrown on
to the event loop and it's going to come
back around you can't cancel it or pause
it
but with generators you can do both so
let's take a look at them this is a
generator and I know it's a generator
because of the asterisk next to the
function keyword so that turns a
function into a function generator now
inside the function you're going to
notice a special keyword called yield
and yield means pause in the generator
world to use the generator you're going
to call it and that's going to return to
you the generator object and on that
object is a method called next and when
you call next you're gonna get back an
object with two keys on it value and
done if there is a value to the right of
the yield statement it's going to return
that as the value done is going to tell
you whether the generator is
or not and in this case it's not because
there are more lines to run okay so
we're gonna call next again see now
we're not actually yielding a number you
don't have to yield a value if you don't
want to yield just means pause generally
so in this case the value is undefined
and again we're not done yet so done is
false we call again
now we're yielding back three so the
value is three but done is still not
false because we've paused at yield
three so once we call next again now the
generator is gonna say yes we're
actually done so we didn't yield a value
and now done is actually true now you
can also pass values into a generator
and this seems a little bit weird at
first because you'll notice that the
first time we call next we're not
passing in a value we're actually doing
it in the second call now the reason
that this happens is that inside of this
generator function once it hits the
yield statement it pauses and that
includes assigning things to variables
so Const num equals hasn't actually been
called yet it actually yields it pauses
before you actually assign the variable
now when I call next again if I provide
a value to it it's gonna take the place
of the previous yield so now continum
equals that yield is replaced with a2
and now we've assigned the variable and
then we also run yield 2 plus num it
pauses there and gives us back the value
for after that yield 4 plus num and now
we're getting back the value 6 then we
call next and we're done
one of my favorite things about
generators is that you can create
infinite generators so here to avoid
having to call next and the next again
and passing the two we can just straight
up pass in as an argument for the number
two so right away when we're calling the
generator we can pass something in and
you'll notice that inside of this we
have a while loop now normally doing
while true is going to run continuously
and crash our browser I know because
I've made that mistake more than once
and but in this case actually that's not
going to happen
so this is really interesting the
generator is actually going to pause the
while loop and it's not going to run
continuously and crash our browser and
every time that this gets called next on
it
we're running the while loop again so it
pauses it and when we call next is going
to resume and because while is true it's
going to give us back the number now I
can just keep calling next on this for
as long as I want there we go
it's just gonna keep generating numbers
for me it's never going to stop until I
explicitly tell it to stop but you can
create infinite generators that always
gave you something back now you can also
call a generator from inside of another
generator to do that you're gonna need
the yield star expression to illustrate
that I have a function a generator
function called outer and a generator
function called inner and you'll notice
that outer is calling inner with the
yield star expression in front of it so
same as before I'm going to call the
generator to get the generator object
then I'm gonna call dot next on that
generator and the first time this you
know totally makes sense what we expect
to happen happens we're yielding one so
we're getting back the value one and of
course we're not done yet
but when I call next again you're gonna
notice that we're not yielding back a
function what we're actually doing is
we're going inside of the inter
generator so yield star is a delegate
and that means when it encounters a
yield star with a generator next to it
it's actually going to start calling dot
next as if that generator was part of
the outer generator
so now when I call dot next I'm actually
getting yield a value a from the inner
generator and this is going to continue
until the inner generator is complete
and then it's gonna go back to the outer
generator so it's a seamless calling of
dot next even though you're putting
together two different generators now
the other thing that's really cool and
the thing that I really wanted out of
the generators is that you can cancel
them and you can do this one of two ways
so the first is that you can call from
the outside denied that's right sorry
I'm having a hard time with the clicker
so here again we have a while loop so it
should say while true and it should run
for forever but I'm actually going to
cancel the generator from inside of the
generator and I'm gonna do that with the
return statement here so the first time
I call next we get what we expect but as
soon as it hits a return statement in a
generator it's gonna cancel it and
you'll notice that it just goes straight
to done true and of course we're not
yielding a value same thing when we call
dot next we've cancelled this generator
so there's no way for it to keep running
anymore this is actually done completely
now the second way to cancel a generator
is from outside of that generator again
a while loop this should run for forever
but as soon as I call generator dot
turn on it it's going to cancel it so
you can see again that done is now true
and this is really interesting that you
can cancel a generator from inside or
from outside of the generator because
resuming the generator occurs on the
outside of the generator only so
generators are paused via yield and
restarted via next but a generator
cannot call next on itself if I never
call next on this generator it will
never yield to and this is something I
really struggled with when I started to
convert my game from promises to
generators because I wanted to know who
runs the generator if control happens
outside of the generator something has
to be telling it to resume itself who's
pulling the strings and that tie learned
about co-routines
core genes are really cool I'm a big fan
of them they are a general control
structure whereby control flow is
cooperatively passed between two
different routines and this doesn't make
a lot of sense but it will soon because
the generator can't resume itself you
need a cooperative partner to help out
so something has to take control away
from the generator but then also hand it
back to the generator to run its own
code so this function is a basic example
of a Co routine so it's gonna take in a
generator and it's going to call it
which returns the generator object and
then the inner function next response
calls the generators next method so this
is going to actually start up the
generator which will run until it
encounters a yield statement at that
time the generator is going to return an
object with the value key and the done
key and next response is going to
evaluate whether the generator is done
or not and if it's not it's gonna call
itself with the value from the
generators response and the loop is
going to continue until the generator is
done so
the co-routine is the cooperative
partner to the generator the curb
routine function passes control to the
generator and when the generator pauses
control goes back to the co routine and
these two functions cooperatively pass
control until completion so now I can
rewrite the bounce up animation as a
generator and use a KO routine to
actually run it but this code actually
suffers from the same problem I had in
the beginning so it's just gonna go too
fast there we go so you can see it's
doing what it did in the beginning which
is just it writes too fast and that's
because generators aren't really gonna
resolve my issues with set timeout and
promises I actually still need them to
be able to handle delays but generators
don't really care if you're using
promises so it's not gonna wait for each
promise to resolve and then resume
itself it can't resume itself but a
cooperative partner could so I can amend
the KO routine to handle async requests
instead of calling next response we're
gonna call it a handle async function
we're gonna pass it the value of the
generators response which is a promise
and now we can actually prevent the
generator from resuming until the
promise is resolved and when it's
resolved we're gonna call next response
which will resume the generator so with
our amended KO routine these functions
are now equivalent previously we change
promises together for the animation now
we can yield promises and our
cooperative partner the KO routine is
going to handle resuming the generator
when the promise is resolved now you can
do more than yield promises with
co-routines you can yield all sorts of
async things including callback
functions you can also yield generators
themselves and there's a really great
library called ko if you want to play
around with this it's highly recommended
Kuro jeans are very powerful and the
reason that they're so powerful is that
they allow you to think
sequentially about async code so because
the co-routine is your cooperative
partner in handling the messy business
of chaining promises together you can
write your code as if it ran
sequentially so for the second version
of this game I rewrote all of the
animations with promises and generators
so what you're seeing here is the same
idle animation but with generators and
promises and it's run by a KO routine
and I had two goals with the rewrite I
wanted to be able to pause animations
and I want to take advantage of thinking
sequentially about async code so to do
that I started with rewriting the
function that delays the animation so
this is our async function and it
doesn't need to hold the animation
itself it just needs to delay with a
promise that's its sole responsibility
so when this function is called it
returns a new promise that resolves when
the timeout is complete I also broke out
the context clearing into its own
function and the drawing of the image
into its own function so now we can
combine these new functions to replace
the previous animation function and
we're gonna do so inside of a generator
so we'll clear whatever was previously
on the canvas then we're gonna draw the
new frame and these get to occur
synchronously there's no problem with
these needing to be a sync they can
recur synchronously but what we is a
think about this is the delay so we're
gonna yield the delay that's the
asynchronous part and then we're gonna
pass off handing it to our co-routines
so our ko routine will be handling the
asynchronous part of this but this feels
very synchronous
and now I can redraw the dislike
animation so this is an animation that
has two frames so you can see this gets
a lot cleaner than the code that I had
previously and then here is our
Tamagotchi saying like nope I don't like
whatever's going on I'm running out of
time but very quickly we're gonna
rewrite the main game bloop so we're
gonna take advantage of canceling the
generator our loop generator function
will be run by a KO routine so we can
rely on that to handle the asynchronous
stuff we're going to create a variable
to save a status of the generator is it
done or not and we're gonna preset the
animation to idle we'll use a while loop
to create a never-ending generator and
this way the game loop can continue for
forever if we have a pending user event
we're going to delegate to the event
using yield star and whatever the event
yields will be passed to the co-routine
otherwise a second while loop will
handle running the animation so as long
as the animation is not complete and
there are no pending events this loop
will yield to the generators values to
the KO routine to handle and these are
promises so the KO routine is going to
handle the chaining but if the animation
is done or there's a pending user event
the loop is going to terminate stopping
the animation generator from running
again and we're going to reassign the
animation to an idle generator so it
starts from the beginning and we're
gonna reset done to false so on the next
iteration of this loop pending will be
true and we'll handle the user event
instead so this is the generator for the
feed action it's going to evaluate if
the Tamagotchi is hungry or not if it's
not it's going to delegate future next
calls to the dislike generator which
will run the dislike animation otherwise
we're gonna decrease the hunger count
and use the yield star we delegate to
the eat generator that runs the
animation okay so now we need to see
everything together so we're idling
riding we're gonna feed the Tamagotchi
give it a good burger and you can see it
canceled the idle animation straight
away and you got to see the time I got
you eating right away then it goes back
to idling and then we're going to feed
it again
and this time we're gonna give it some
candy great immediately cancels the idle
animation and runs the candy animation
feeding it candy one more time we're
gonna try and feed it one more time and
it's not happy it does not want a food
so you can see this now works and that
is all I have for you the code is at
this github if you want to check out the
code itself I'm still in the process of
writing the Tim Tamagotchi but you can
check out what's there already and come
see me at the break if you would like
some stickers I have some use react and
wing stickers that are react focused if
you use react and thank you
[Applause]