when I was asked to NC I've never done
this before and I actually as I
mentioned before never been to CSS comp
for CSS conference so I was really
excited to come and and I was trying to
think like well how would I end such a
great like group of speakers and and I
don't know I just I feel really inspired
and and I was going to talk about like
my wish list for like what I want in the
future is CSS but I realized I feel like
we've tapped out CSS as a language I
think we've done it all and I my
backgrounds started in academia and then
I worked in sports media tech at the NBA
and a couple of the main thing I learned
from working in those industries is how
to monetize things so I figure like
instead of talking about like what i
want for CSS i would give you some of my
ideas on how maybe we should monetize
CSS so that's what i'm going to talk
about and so I have a I have a couple
ideas bear with me they might sound a
little crazy but like I was going over
my slides before and now I'm sorry to
think like you know what I think I've
got like a good couple of ideas rolling
and what better place in CSS confer we
have all these great minds here that
work at really cool places that can make
decisions and make these things happen
and who here would think it's a cool
idea if we all made more money yeah so
important is the first thing I want to
talk about originally my wish list or
CSS is to get rid of important important
causes me a lot of stress and it
probably does for you especially when
you pull in third party libraries that
have CSS files and they used important
on all of them and you know it's a pain
the butt but like instead of getting rid
of it like we could just make it harder
for people to use by monetizing it like
and so like how can we monetize in
Horton's like what is important it's
like some weird like social construct
that we can totally take advantage of so
I said I propose that we introduce some
politics and bureaucracy into important
so like we can create the sort of like
government of CSS politicians who pass
laws on what can be important and what
cannot be important and i put democracy
and scare quotes because really like we
don't know how to do that sort of stuff
but like some people might say like oh
well good the w3c like we can handle it
but like I feel like they're a little
distracted right now so maybe like we
can just do like a total qu and take
over ourselves and create another group
we all know like the more groups you
have deciding the same thing obviously
is like the best approach so figure we
should contribute to that and like in
terms of bureaucracy and these are all
things that I learned working at
Montclair CA and MBA like in order to
like make it difficult to do something
we actually make people apply for it or
put it behind a paywall or we can create
these loose rules and never-ending
debate between our cool little democracy
and bury people in paperwork before
they're able to use important in their
code and of course like but the great
thing about politics is that it always
means more jobs and more money not
necessarily distributed to us developers
but the people in power because when you
have power you get money and when you
have money and power e of respect and
this is something little kimsin telling
me since 1998 so it obviously is
something we should look into z-index
this is my favorite CSS property because
i love like math and the Z plane and all
that cool stuff but we can totally
monetize the z-index the more money that
you pay the more stacks you can have I
mean my default for Z index is like 99
999 up until like even beyond what a
computer can technically handle it with
32-bit integers so like if we charge
people for how high their z-index codes
well if you have a lot of layers you
know you're going to have to pay more so
and I mean I don't know exactly who
they're going to pay like us wherever we
are but I figured that's a good idea
yeah that's that's all the money that
we're going to be making if we do this
my favorite subject ever SC oh right
yeah how can we monetize with SEO well
like SEO just automatically means money
anyway so like I have this I actually
wrote some code I hope you can see and
like it doesn't really like to the when
you're viewing in the browser doesn't
actually do anything like this code is
useless but if we can incorporate like
search optimization and box and stuff so
like Paul like see me later we can
discuss how Google wants to work this
into their roadmap but like why don't we
just like class name stuff everything
and then like everyone will definitely
go to my site that's styled by the CSS
and like you can inject like your name
and like all this sort of stuff into CSS
you put into client projects and then
you get more clicks and then the
internet gives you more money because
that's like where this money is coming
from the internet javascript and CSS so
like on the JavaScript developer yeah
boo and like we all know that like CSS
really don't need CSS is a language we
can do everything in CSS or JavaScript
so I mean let's just get that out there
performance and all that other stuff
like aside like you know JavaScript can
do it but like let's turn the tables on
JavaScript developers like let's create
a syntax and CSS where we can put
JavaScript into the page so like I mean
I I've come from a background in PHP
development so like why don't we use
like PHP to parse this and inject it
just seems like it's totally easy and
not tasking it also we can do that and
make money through CSS that has
javascript in it so like how would we do
that well let's rebrand it people
whenever you like your work in a company
that
markets things and like this happens at
sports seems all the time to let go you
know ticket sales aren't so good like
what should we do like oh let's change
the name of the team and that will like
totally like blow it up and it usually
works that way so like let's rename CSS
with JavaScript syntax inside of it and
called script we can have like t-shirts
and like framework Wars because all of
the money that I make off of web
development is actually from arguing
about code on Twitter so like we all can
get involved in with this rebranding I
mentioned in the beginning of the
conference that CSS is a line language
because you know what you see on the
document you end up looking at your page
in the browser and it turns out it's
just full of lies so I feel like if we
want to be taken more seriously a CSS
developers and therefore make more money
we need to sort of stop being a big fat
liars all the time and I treated this a
couple of days ago I was actually really
stressed out I was working on a project
where we were sorting a column and
there's CSS triangles pointing up when
you sort of sunday and would change down
and I'm struggling with that and then i
was like thinking like why are we
calling these triangles like they're not
triangles like if you take a look at
this code it's only hiding parts of this
box you know so like I'm standing behind
this podium and you don't see my legs
you're not going to call me someone who
doesn't have legs so like why are we
lying about triangles it drives me
insane like this is that triangle and
CSS and like why don't we just use like
HTML which this is obviously more
semantic I take a look at ampersand hash
x.25 be too and I'm like oh that's an up
we're pointing solid triangle so and
it's like so much less code and you know
and yeah we might have to memorize all
these entities but like what else are we
going to do so that's a little taste of
my upcoming talk a deprecated CSS cove
where we just get rid of all CSS so yeah
NHL mods modernization is really easy we
just introduced politics bureaucracy and
just like basically not use CSS at all
also like again like let's stop calling
them triangles
and just like doing whatever I say it's
I feel like anybody that's listen to me
like usually gets it right along the way
so I don't know and also like on a
serious note let's just based on all the
talks today like keep the web pretty
funny accessible and experiment friendly
and I'm really happy to see based on
what everyone's been talking about today
that we're doing exactly that with CSS
so I wanted to keep it brief because I
know you want to party you've heard me
talk all day but I want to thank you um
i'm on twitter it gets that's a real
email address that's a real site um and
if you like don't want to read serious
stuff I do right on medium olive like my
joke ESAT tire thing so and we're
sponsored by soundgarden so thank you
for thank you for bringing it and
they're literally playing in New York
City a week from today I just learned
that I also don't really like
Soundgarden but don't know that um but
really on and just to take it seriously
which from me it sounds funny i'm sure i
wanted to say that seeing all the talks
today like there's like talk certain
people have never spoken before that
sounds so eloquent and are doing such
awesome stuff and I feel really honored
to sort of be in the group with all of
you and I want to thank nicole and all
the organizers and chris and laura
williams for organizing this really
awesome event like I really needed this
I really did so I want to thank you all
for letting me make a nice out of myself
all day I love to do it and I love to
see all of you my new friends so thank
you very much