so as I said how to get rich quick with
JavaScript so present to you a new
JavaScript framework and together with
it an opportunity for you hello it has
all kinds of features so it has XM l HX
SQL it even has Wi-Fi and it's licensed
/ app so you pay fifty thousand euros
per app that you create with it and
peruse it as uses the framework another
five euros pretty cheap so we make a
7030 split so that means you just create
one app that has 100,000 users and your
have almost half a million euros cool
right wait a minute what come with this
is or to put it more bluntly what the
hell are you talking about okay I have a
confession to make I lied so this
doesn't really exist but imagine it
would exist in this parallel world where
our tools that we use to create
applications would be licensed for
device or per app or even for users
imagining for a moment if you used
phonegap and you had to pay let's say
100,000 years to use phonegap per app
just imagine it for a while that's not
that wouldn't be a nice world right
instead we have a wonderful world where
you actually have free tools and even
more you have ecosystems that are
created and enabled by those free tools
think back of all those great projects
we have we have no look at the ecosystem
around node look at the one around
jQuery
our own annual around phonegap look how
much we have there so just back about me
I work in the webos and annual develop
relations and i love the web I love
communities and also mobile so this is
about the tools that we use to create
our software and it's worthwhile to go
back and see how did we get here so go
back to the age of Metro works Borland
Clarion and so on I was actually when I
think he works for used to work for
metal works back in the days those were
sold to and used to buy specialists
they're pretty expensive 3,000 euros for
professional license or if you were
lucky enough to be a hobbyist you might
you might have only to pay 200 years
maybe that's actually cut off as he did
expensive tools and only used by
specialists and those were closed tools
no open source proprietary licensing
which meant that writing software was
limited to those specialists and also
you had to actually find a fan so on to
you have to pay someone to ride you the
software I don't think anyone would just
go out and say let's spend three
thousand euros on software so i can do
stuff and as we marched on in time this
also led to a kind of when door locking
where we just said okay this is truly
this is how you have to use this you
have to update it to get the latest
feature fevers forward we started
packing the time if you remember in the
browser Wars time Netscape versus in the
next floor where the web started to rise
and you might remember the attempt to
control this open web to make it
proprietor again we met do you remember
activex back in the days so luckily we
didn't and we didn't stay in that age
because what actually happened was a
devil creation of the web the creation
of software for the web websites those
shifted from the specialists which they
were created in beginning to everyone
everyone was able to create a website to
create software for the web what
happened the web was open source by
design it had built in a really cool
tool which was hidden in many on her and
view source so you could actually view
the source of every website you visited
this led to communities this led to open
exchange where people shared their
experiences thanks to view source
because then you said well I have
nothing to hide here's my code look at
it look how I made it this led the web
to become an ecosystem where we exchange
information where we created tools built
on the web where we created services
built on the web it also meant that he
no longer had to be an expert to program
the barrier of entry for programmer was
really low if you look at HTML CSS CSS
and JavaScript and how they were
standardized so many people could write
software the development tools were
basically free all that you needed was a
text editor and the browser which both
were free and available
even in source it around the same time
we also saw that the infrastructure that
built the web was starting to become
open source languages operating systems
databases web servers all this start to
become open source so let's fast forward
today to today we are in the age of
mobile clearly if you look at it re in
the war of browsers again second coming
well it's probably more a war of
ecosystems where we have everyone tried
to lock them into their world Apple
Google Microsoft and so on what's the
role of the web in this mobile first we
have the evolution of HTML CSS and
JavaScript which we collect if you call
html5 but we also have this epic you
ubiquiti we have all kinds of connected
devices all over the place that can
access the web and on the other hand we
also have this expectation of people
let's say I just want to access my
content my data anywhere peed in the car
on the phone at home the role of
JavaScript also in mobile it's important
it's a big bootys every browser ships
with JavaScript and as we say I already
saw every device has a browser it has
even moved to the server so we have
client and server with the same language
and it's easy to learn which leads us to
native vs web so I have to talk about it
a bit I know it's like beating a dead
horse I will do it anyway but i'll try
to approach it bit from another
direction so my question is what if the
web what if web is native water if there
is no distinction between web and native
if you look at projects like Weber's
chrome eyes forever folks always that we
saw today there the web is native
what if all out our Epsom are on the web
are we stick are we still talking about
native 10 and also brings me to another
topic eps must die why are we stuck in
this why do we like back in the
mainframes mainframe days start an
application to do something why don't we
do more just in time interaction for
example i want to interact with
something p the device or a service so i
have to go ahead and download and it's
still gonna install an app that specific
for that device then i use the app and
then I probably don't use it anymore I
forget about it and then after a while I
have after have after I've used every
service or every place on this world I
will have 1000 apps installed and I
don't even know which one I have to
start anymore why do we do this where
will this end up so what about I want to
interact with something I have an
automated discovery that finds out
what's out there it will serve me a web
based app I use it or interact with that
I forget about it and it's gone and
thanks to the weapon thanks to all the
infrastructure that's open will have
rickety this is getting with on top of
topic so let's go back to the
development tools that we have today in
mobile development in mobile negative
development we have three tools you
don't have to pay for the development
tools with xcode eclipse and so on and
so on or also a visual studio but are
they really only an entry into an
ecosystem of the mouth of the
manufacture their free as beer but
they're really to really do they really
give you freedom think about
in web development most tools are open
source and I mean that in a way of free
and freedom as I mentioned before alo we
have a really low barrier of entry for
new programs they can go and start with
javascript HTML and CSS as and we have
the browser and JavaScript everywhere we
have a lot of communities around those
products around the web and just
interesting to see good communities that
form orpha our founded on mutual respect
by the entity that puts out the tool and
the ones that use it because for both it
means respect each other and also
voluntary engagement if I use it or even
if I commit a code to the project also
these days if you don't have a tool with
a strong community I don't think it has
much relevant anymore so with all that
in web development the free tool
ecosystem is key so back to the
beginning one app 100,000 users easy
four hundred thousand euros but now used
you came here to find out how you get
rich where's the money the role of tools
and frameworks is shifting they are
shifting to become an enabler so instead
of just selling a tool you're using it
to sell services enabled by those tools
and we also see that a framework or tool
becomes more than just the framework or
tool because you start to offer support
and consulting you might
even offer and integrate the development
environment together with the tool or
even a build environment think of phone
get built for example or you might offer
cloud api's that enable to do more with
a framework or a tool so this is where
you can make the money let's look at
some ecosystems as an example i will
look at three of them phonegap in your
our own and jquery the ecosystem around
phonegap is consulting and also lots of
services on top and for phonegap just
look how how it has enabled us to write
applications and look how many big-name
committers we have that contribute to
the code is that here is the codec you
can use it and we give it to free to the
project now think about it if they had
said let's charge 100,000 for for using
phonegap what would have happened
nothing it would disappear no one would
use it let's talk about our own
framework this is a sponsored slide so
you might not know what it is it's a
JavaScript framework called any ojs it
was open source in 2012 it uses the
Apache License so it is free as in beer
and also in freedom and its goal to
build native like applications with
JavaScript across platforms I invite you
to check it out this ends the sponsored
slide here again what's the ecosystem
about around that new tool why should hv
and not say well let's charge just that
much for the license and that's it no
again we say it's open source and it's
an enable for us to provide services and
also even more important it will enable
other companies to build services and
applications based on nu
there is also already a big community
around it where people for example
submit their component components that
they made for Nu and I again I have to
ask if you would go ahead and say yeah
you to use it you have to license every
up you can read you have to pay that
much I would work you wouldn't use it I
wouldn't use it jquery which is a bit in
all the project just look what we have
in terms of jquery how how big the
ecosystem is we have jQuery jQuery
Mobile jQuery UI we have thousands of
plugins we have theming services again d
the ecosystem around this is mostly on
consulting and services built with on
the top of jQuery again if they would
have decided back then i think it was in
2006 to charge for it what would have
happened i don't think people would use
it and look how much it's used these
days in how many applications in how
many websites so to wrap up a bit
ecosystems by freedom it's there is so
much more value than just selling a tool
you could say ok let's sell the tool
will probably sell it to that many
people will make that much money if you
give you the way for free and let it
enable other people just look at the
value of that is so much bigger than
just telling it and it's also
interesting to see we'll have probably
have not in network effects the more
people use it and the most people i will
create services and this will increase
the value even more so i urge you to
keep the web development ecosystem free
and in freedom open source all the
things love the web javascript and be