the script Mallinckrodt ingestible I
work every right webrip i love what mr.
Brendan Eich malaga internets we write
about technology and bad dolores park
basically what am I talking about it
that's to ride out for keeping it real
big goes to joy you painting off big
just to my room then you get up I seen
infested route yeah that's my first
slide stop you cannot because I heard
this one before / odds if you want a
copy to install packages use the module
system it was good so uh this is my
first slider here this is actually the
default image for this scene right here
and I had to include it because it
looked cool and it's a ducati so yeah so
yeah I'm not the best programmer ever I
kind of just like a kind of make it up
as you go kind of guy and so that's why
I'm on the B track and not over there I
just like that like put modules together
and try to make them work so I love
github can see I've like 57 repos and
dub it's a lot of crap actually okay so
these are just pretty much all the
modules that I use on a daily basis for
all my different projects and it's all
about standing on the shoulders of
giants I really like that phrase because
it's like all the good people are down
here
so I add these some of the modules i'm
just going to like give you a look at
you probably already seen it before or
maybe not they're really good to have in
your arsenal though so you got coffee
script by does anybody know how to
pronounce his name Josh kennice Josh
ganache alright second chain saw my sub
stack Express TJ Holloway Chuck reddit's
by a Salvador then send Phillip bow now
jazz request by Michael and discovery to
the shameless plug that I wrote like
yesterday and I decide to throw in here
it's my first npm not module so alright
and that does not really fit on the
screen okay anyway this is CoffeeScript
and no one here has already used
coffeescript before ok so like half
about essentially what it does is it
like JavaScript the good parts will only
let you use like the non crap parts of
JavaScript like it will pass like jslint
like strict mode on everything so you're
like actually have good JavaScript
without really even trying and that's on
the left side there that's like the copy
script and then on the right side is
like the what it evaluates to and like
normal JavaScript and then you'll see
that like over here like Eddie yeah it
puts everything in its own scope so you
don't have any global variables which is
pretty cool alright the next one is a
sec this is part of like flow control
subsec wrote this and essentially what
it does is you'll see that you require a
sec and then oh is this home awesome
okay so you require sec right here right
and that means sequential power is
parallel so it does the first one right
and then after it executes that it has a
little thing inside of it says okay I'm
done go down to the next one but if you
parallel one it go does both them at the
same time and it passes both of these
guys right here as these guys right here
and so it does a sec on do two of those
right there after both of them are done
at the same time so you don't have a
bunch of like callback and stuff like
that you can just do flow control code
oh and it over here you can't really see
it cuz it's up the screen it's a dot
catch which is awesome because like
normally you'd have to do like a catch
on each one of these but if you have a
catch up there that it'll catch any
errors you have in here so you only have
to have one catch statement to catch any
air you have in that whole spiel over
there there's another example of the SEC
modulator just using different stuff and
you can see at the bottom that's taking
a B and C and doing them all at once
alright this is express it's a pretty
much the backbone of every like web type
of thing that I do it just gives you
like really simple dsl kind of like
Sinatra if you guys are familiar with
like Ruby Sinatra so you just have an
appt up there they can't really see
where you just require Express and then
you just create app we didn't doing a
new create server on your Express object
and then you just listen on a port and
then it's just really simple you know
get post whatever your method is
whatever the route is and then your
callback alright chainsaw this is really
cool mod I actually built my module
using chainsaw what it does it's for
creating modules so you can use flow
control in your module when you create
it so this is an example of a function
called add do and it has two methods add
and do and it over here is an example of
like it works so you you do add do you
instantiate it with a zero so it sets
your thumb up there 20 and then you add
five and then it does some plus equals n
so adds five to it and then it goes to
the next one so it's like okay I'm done
this is now five and it's like add 10
alright so it's like 15 now and then
they do it actually gives a result of
some back from your this new method
right here where it says a saw nest so
it returns that back into your thumb and
it's like okay if sum is greater than 12
then add a negative 12 so subtract 12
and then add two and then back down here
do your some and it's like five or
something like that redis this is one of
my favorite libraries in the whole world
well actually the whole system of Redis
I'm coming from Ruby so I use this a lot
in Ruby it's pretty much just a key
value store so like if you want to set
like a string you just do set the key
the value
just persist it to the disk so you can
what I should persist to memory and then
like X amount of Rights later you can
sit in the configuration file you can be
like okay after like five thousand right
or whatever then like persist it to a
file but uh you have different things
like hashes and sets and lists and it's
really fun to like do just like in
memory storage stuff it's kind of like
memcache bit different actually my big
issues for this I don't even put up
there is like pub/sub it's like for like
inter process communication like I'll
have one process go okay anytime one
event happens I'm going to publish like
hey yo this happened and then the other
process will have a listener on it and
it will accept a subscriber over here
and say okay that happened and then do
something else so i can have stuff on
like two different things going on like
so I've architecture shredder classic
like the whole system or whatever and
then they're all talking to each other
in real time and they can all just be
event driven using the pub sub
capabilities of brightest okay now Jas
is anybody ever using out Jason here
alright it's kind of a new library
alright like three people so anybody
heard of stock and I oh okay so this is
like an abstraction on top of socket i/o
so ressaca diyos you know there's a
server in the client and it talked to
each other well this is for the server
the client also but it's a lot more
shorter as you can see right here like
on the server side you just do okay now
Jas eagles require now everyone it's
just kind of like magical variable that
stores this namespace inside of it so
everybody is synchronized so if i do
like everyone dot foo equals bar on the
server all the connected clients now
have everyone up foo equals bar without
actually explicitly like telling the
clients to set that so everybody is in
sync so everybody has the same namespace
variables so like this is the defining a
method right here so like everyone now
get server info in a function callback
would
so what I can do on the client is I can
do all right now dot get server info and
I'll look on the client say okay do I
have this function defined on the client
and if not then automatically looks on
the server for that function in and
execute it so it kind of blurs the line
between having a function on the
client-side and server-side because
essentially to the client they're all
the same so you can do some really cool
like real-time stuff with like multiple
people doing that kind of thing so
here's an example of like server-side to
client-side suicide to client side so on
the server side you define distribute
message in then everyone now namespace
and then on the client side you're like
all right now not named prompt what's
your name and then they click the button
and then it does now that distribute
message and see since it's not set on
the client automatically jump it up to
the server and xq set function with this
argument and in it we turn down value
and then everyone got nada shouldn't
matthew so that's on the server side and
then it calls the received message was
set up there and then receive message
down here so regardless of what side
it's set on you can call it from
wherever so it I use a lot for like
games and stuff like that request this
one's by Michael Rogers it's just a
really cool utility for doing like HTTP
requests on stuff so you can use like
the standard like nodejs HTTP library
but uh I like this one because one of
the big things that does it follows
redirects so if you get like a 301 or
302 it'll automatically follow that and
here's some example code of how to use
it so like requests and you can put the
method in there in the URI and you can
send multi-part messages and then it's
just an array of what
what you want to send it and then
there's a response body so it gives you
three different variables in your
callback and you're going to evaluate
those and do different things depending
on what they evaluate to all right this
is a module that I made using chainsaw
so you can kind of see the flow control
up here so what it does is you just
require the module and then non-black
equals discover and then what is doing
is it's looking for the the RSS and atom
feeds in the main page all is looking
for like the link rel equals application
Adam XML application RSS xml but instead
of doing like callbacks you can just do
the fine method and then when you run
that this is what you get so it looks
goes to the first line look ma no
blocking and do another stuff now so
you're not blocking or halting up your
execution I mean one of those and then
at the very end where it says dot do
feeds four feet of feeds call it's a log
feeds is this what it outputs so just a
really terse way to kind of just like
process stuff and this is written in
CoffeeScript right here so it might look
a little bit different if you're not
used to seeing CoffeeScript syntax oh
yeah and this is this slide is for max
yeah all right I'm probably like not
even close to be in 30 minutes but 15
minutes good anybody have any questions
or anything
what do you mean by feet aggregation
we have some things like we'll have like
a big list of like a couple thousand
feeds where we go through and we splice
all of them together to make one big
feed it's kind of like all the current
data from like all the different foods
we have been different topics and then
we can look at what's going on with that
but that's like not so open source
first slide yeah
so I were because ed and I always felt
like all these scripts is going to be in
my ass that's valid or not I think it I
think it depends on like your style
right like if you like the syntax and
like it feels good doing it like do it
and if not then not and because I mean
it's like they're kind of saying for
CoffeeScript just coffee script which is
JavaScript so like it evaluates the
JavaScript so it's not like a different
language or anything so I mean it's just
way of generating JavaScript so like if
people don't like it like I'm not trying
to like proselytize and like tell them
that they have to use coffeescript like
it just whatever feels right you make
some extra copy strip goth chick and
regular yes what not really everything
that I write is a mostly coffee scripts
so all these examples I just copy and
paste it from the like the website for
the example code because I didn't really
want to make my own code since it is
already there so uh so yeah like as you
can like on my module like that's why
it's coffee script because like that's
pretty much all i right just cuz I like
the the syntax of it I didn't notice I
was like that's all true yeah yeah
par seemed like how to find what the
feeds were whatever um I did it's a good
question i use the sum I forget what
libraries I can pull that up real quick
actually yeah it was a 10pm librarian
producer share
it's a nut module called HTML parser is
what I used and this is all coffee
scrutineers this is the library itself
is not that big so like right here I do
like where's HTML parser handler new
HTML polisher default handler right here
and let's do it creates a Dom element
and then I just can do a select on that
dumb for link elements and then I do a
for each link and it gives me element as
my return and then just a regular
expression match for RSS or atom and I
yank out the the hof for that in and I
return it in a an array yeah
yeah yeah i've used step in sec I like
sec a lot I haven't really used it in
anything in production I just played
around with it before oh because sec is
for like actually riding your program
whereas chainsaw is made for writing
your modules so like it's one that's
like different sides of the same coin
this soup select like a bloody of HTML
parser or oh yeah super select is a it's
a weight cuz like HTML parser gives you
a Dom element like right here and then
select is worth soup so that comes in
and it just allows you to easily select
your Dom elements so it gives you really
like terse way to just too I just do
select Dom blank for each and then that
will go through every dump for every for
every link element just give me the
properties for that without having to do
a whole lot of code RV vision jizzed on
g4 now right
we mean like
yeah I'm going to say probably I mean I
haven't really used that library just
because I needed a quick Dom element and
I read on like some blog that that was a
quick way to do it so I'm really played
with it enough to know like how fully
featured HTML parser DOM is but I mean
since it's a dominantly one of the
dependency of dependencies of it is
probably J is dumb and that's probably
just the Jays Dom element but I don't
know for sure anybody else got any
questions comments or concerns yes ooh
good question um well the guy who wrote
it is here yeah it it should if if it
doesn't you should give him crap about
it