hello and welcome to one of the last
talks and before really get started what
I wanted to kind of walk you through is
is kind of some applications that we
would typically write today and what do
they all have in common so for example
if we had a game such as as this what is
it really doing well let's see we have a
time loop or we're obviously reacting to
events here if I can actually figure out
what I'm doing here all of these sorts
of things we have timers we have
animation we have all sorts of things
whether it's that even edge detection
for example what do these all have in
common you know even even simple things
like coordination of of events together
or real-time data analysis or or for
example just a simple simple drawing
mechanism what do all of these have in
common you know even anything like Super
Mario Brothers or or tutu MVC so
hopefully that will come true and I
cannot knock that off my list
but text editors animation and even even
even video players for example what do
these all have in common
you know this for example streaming live
data really kind of cool kind of
thinking but all of this is based upon
and then especially here is based upon a
very very simple simple concept and that
is the observable and and reactive
programming which we will talk about
today so as I said there are a lot of
different ways about thinking about
these large applications that we're
building today and so what we're going
to be doing is really talking about how
some of
the larger corporations in the world
have solved some of the really hard
problems in a particular way by thinking
very differently about how they write
their applications whether it's Netflix
slack or Microsoft or anyone else they
all have some the same problems that you
all do but they fought very very
differently about how they did it so if
you want to follow along at home you can
you can do so there the slides are
available now now the way I always like
to start off with a talk is just to kind
of give an alternative title for example
I always stopped worrying about
asynchronous programming and started to
learn to love the observable so like I
said it's going to be a little bit of a
mind shift on how we do that and just
because I love concurrency jokes and and
who doesn't or I thought to myself I'll
solve my problem with promises and
events now have now problems - I dang so
many people may wonder why I'm wearing
this hat well I am a principal of
software engineer at at a fairly large
company but why wear this hat is is
because I call myself an open sorcerer
and what I mean by that is the fact that
for the longest time at Microsoft I've
been doing open-source in such a way
that I've worked on such initiatives as
getting node supported on Windows to
open sourcing a large part of nets and
that's been a lot of my
behind-the-scenes work and this
particular company and yeah I love that
logo I really wish we had that one still
to this day but this one is from 1981
it's a real logo but I like to think of
myself as putting a little bit more
metal into into Microsoft so if people
saw me last night I was talking about
this particular project so if people
want to talk about running note on
phones you can come and talk to me
afterwards I think it's a lot of a very
interesting project about build
the pure web and I think it's very very
affable applicable especially at
conferences when Wi-Fi can be scanned
but the vast majority of what we're
going to be talking about here is is my
work on the reactive extensions now this
is a thing that's we've been working on
so since 2009 at Microsoft and really
it's a fundamental shift on how we think
about asynchronous programming it has
its own history in which we were trying
to solve problems with asynchronous
programming before a lot of people
actually had those problems this is 2009
before before promises really existed we
were trying to invent our own style of
how we were to express both events and
asynchronous callbacks in a simple way
and so what we called ourselves as the
Riyad we are a part of a larger program
called Volta but we then shortened
ourselves to reactive extensions or we
just call ourselves rx pushers now what
I really want to talk about is Netflix
in particular and how many people have
Netflix heard of Netflix I'm fair a fair
number so there their goal is is fairly
simple stream stream movies from any
device and if you think about it at
scale you're talking a lot of data
you're talking one third of the u.s.
broadband traffic I don't know where
we're at what it is in other countries
but that's a significant amount of
things that they have to worry about so
this is really a story on how Netflix
Microsoft and others have sold some
really fundamentally hard problems and
building those large systems by just
thinking a little bit differently about
how they deal with with events so for
anyone who actually has the Netflix
player it's fundamentally asynchronous
everything about it the last thing you
would want to do is have that little
spinny thing of death that Christian was
talking about in terms of error handling
and
fourth so everything's app startup the
player itself animations and the view
model binding is all done asynchronously
no blocking involved but that introduces
a good number of problem that you're
going to absolutely have when you're
trying to do that whether it's memory
leaks because you have so many open
event handlers to race conditions where
these two events have to have to happen
in a certain order or this asynchronous
callback has to happen in a certain
order I that can be very very complex
and not only that but this notion of
callback hell is is very very real and
it's not just because your your code is
walking off the side of the page it's
more along the lines of your company
you're building these very complex state
machines and you're not quite sure
exactly where you are in the code
because somewhere within all the
callbacks is your state and you're not
quite sure where you are in the
computation so in 2014 they finally did
a complete and utter redo on where they
were so when they started in 2011 they
had they had seven different platforms
seven different languages all to
describe doing these asynchronous
operations as I showed you each one had
its own way of thinking about it for the
data binding for the data access and so
forth and so what they did is they
thought differently about how they were
doing events so they could standardize
on a single way of thinking about it
not just not just having one library two
libraries to do it but just thinking
fundamentally different about it and so
what they came up with is using the
observables which we'll be talking about
today as their base and what this is is
it's a very language neutral approach to
to solving asynchronous problems so what
they were able to do is port what we've
done already in JavaScript and on net to
other languages such as groovy Scala
Java
Clojure and so forth so regardless of
whether you were a front-end developer
or a back-end developer you could easily
switch between teams because you
understood the paradigm it wasn't
necessarily that you needed to
understand language you understood the
paradigm you understood the architecture
so quite honestly why is this so
important because real-time is
everywhere and what we're doing today
whether it's looking off of your phone
and getting GPS data seeing where you
are
SMS traffic any number of these sensors
well Twitter notifications anything how
do you keep up with that how do you
coordinate them all together without
just giving up and just shoving them
down your shirt it just it gets very
very complicated very very quickly
and unfortunately the given mechanisms
that we have in JavaScript are terrible
let's just face it I mean programming
asynchronously in JavaScript today using
events and using callbacks and using
promises aren't exactly great they might
be better in the future but right now it
shows an utter lack of coordination here
I don't know why the guy couldn't just
put down one thing and I will so it even
was a topic of concern even to the
highest levels of the US government for
example so that we'd shoot so President
Kennedy simply choose to solve
asynchronous programming and to do other
things not because they're easy but
because they are hard and then he
realized afterwards after saying this he
is like well maybe it is too hard and
let's just go to the moon instead so he
decided to go to the moon I think so
like I said callback hell is really a
thing and and like what I meant by that
is the fact that we have here whether
you're having a movie ticket and the
player error and then you're trying to
figure out where exactly are you okay if
the players not initialized and
initialize it and then try to finish
okay going in to try to finish that
I got where are you supposed to go from
there oh yeah yeah you're supposed to go
to that callback which might be
authorized movie it just gets very
complex and it turns into instead of a
pyramid of numerous anything like that I
call it a cow's head and I think it's
very very easy to get burned on on those
kinds of things because you have no idea
where your status is where you're in the
computation and you know if you're
looking at these your stack traces you
just get lost and it makes me want to
jump out a window sometimes quite
honestly and even when we're dealing
with raw events by themselves you know
we we still have to have whether the the
mouse is down or not and the and the
state that we happen to deal with well
what if we want to go beyond that what
if we want to add some delays to it or
or or call a an agent make an AJAX call
all of that then gets somehow lost
because now you're having to deal with
all of these three separate callbacks
and having to decipher where all of your
logic is going to be so yeah whoops
indeed I is is it really is an enemy of
the state and like I said all of these
events that you're trying to to
coordinate becomes very very hard to to
juggle quite honestly so so in our
infinite wisdom in JavaScript we came
out with the this idea of promises so we
would have this first-class notion of
instead of dealing with callbacks we
would deal with promises so with then we
could take the aforementioned example
and we could say player initialize then
authorize movie or else it's a login
error then play the movie or or it's an
unauthorized you're not allowed to do it
but you have problems with that and the
problems is the way that it was designed
in es2015 2015 or es6 as some people
call it is the fact that there's no
cancellation built right into the
into the promise itself there isn't any
you can certainly write it yourself but
by default it isn't in there and in fact
it actually became very much a point of
contention when when people were you
starting to use the fetch API and
realizing that they were using you know
xh the xhr like everybody else was used
to and then the right well so how do i
cancel that oops so they kind of left
that out and so this is a fairly long
thread here as you can see 21
participants and oh yeah 204 comments so
I think that kind of solves the problem
of how many engineers does it take to
cancel a promise and they still haven't
figured it out and not only that but it
also lacks a notion of finally so for
example if you have some sort of
resource that you want to finally clean
up at the very end ensure that at the
very end of your chain is going to be
cleaned up there isn't any so what I
considered is is that the the promise
itself is a very nice way of dealing
with a really fast car with absolutely
no breaks now other people think about
stream programming and think well that
maybe we'll solve our problem but when
people think about stream programming
they mostly think about node streams and
quite honestly at the beginning I would
say that node streams were pretty
terrible and the fact that just like
that poor kid the data started firing
before he was ready for it and you
couldn't consume just a little bit know
you know your if you're completely
screwed because pause and resume or
absolutely heart are hard to get right
and so they they had to come up with
four different ways of expressing
streams in the next version of streams
to with with transform readable writable
and duplex yay and then streams three
still adds more complexity with whole
bulk
rates and bulk reads so once again very
very complicated stuff in order to do
something that should be fairly simple
so let's go back to 1994 and I realized
probably not many of you were born by
them but let's go back anyways to this
particular book here design patterns and
this is a hallmark book that a lot of
people bought because it was this idea
where you took all of these design
patterns and finally put them in a
single book together and what they did
is they had so many of these patterns
whether it's singleton facade abstract
Factory you know all those things that
you use for java scale your java names
for four particular classes but two in
particular that were very interesting to
at least me at the time and us was was
the iterator in the observer but there
is absolutely no linkage at all between
the two of them but we thought that
there absolutely was so for example in
the iterator pattern which is now as
part of es2015 we can say get numbers
which returns us a an iterable iterator
in which we can call next which tells us
whether we're done or not and gives us
our value so we can go through there and
finally we get done and value is
undefined and the subject observer
pattern which we're all very very used
to for example on document add event
listener and remove event listener is
the subject observer pattern so we've
been using these design patterns for
since forever in in in JavaScript and so
when you move the mouse sure enough you
started to get the data now let me ask
you a fundamental question then what's
the difference between an array of this
kind of data and that Mouse movement we
just saw before well they're both
collections nothing more fundamental
than that in the fact that your mouse
your phone and an array of stock ticks
are both collections that you should be
able to treat as just the same kind of
thing
and as was talked about yesterday in the
functional programming talk when you
talk about functional functional
programming over these questions that's
exactly what we're going to do here so
the vast majority of the of the of the
coding that was done then I'll show you
is is all using very very few functions
but very very powerful ones for example
map which is the idea that you can
transform every single element in the
collection and project it to a new
collection so for in this example we can
take our circles and project them into
into diamonds and the same thing with
filter is to apply a predicate to every
single item to say I only want circles
so give me circles now flat maps a
little bit different and it's a little
trickier to think about although if if
you're used to two arrays it's no more
than just in a Cartesian product but
that's not good enough quite honestly
but what what it's really doing is it's
going to do a map like we did we showed
before and then it's going to start
merging the data back into a single
stream so it's going to start getting
multiple pieces of data as you can see
here for example the the red here will
project down into into multiples so it
starts based upon the time and the
reacting to it merge it all into a
single stream so yes I realize it's a
fundamental shift in the way that you're
thinking about it and you really kind of
need a smack to really kind of think
about it go a little bit differently
so let's actually walk through some code
and make it absolutely clear on how this
works so if I wanted to get top-rated
milk boom movies what do I do
well I start off with the the array of
the video list for a particular user I
go through and I took and I filter out
all of the all of the ones that
I only want the ones that to have a
rating of five and then I can go through
and pass in myself and and display each
movie now what if I told you that I can
turn that exactly around on its head and
say I can create a drag event with the
same exact code would you would you
believe me of course you wouldn't well
why would I be here so what you would do
is is here is you would take the mouse
down and flatmap or just the map and the
merge and then take the mouse move take
until mouse up so basically what you're
doing is you're saying mouse down and
mouse move together merge together and
take until mouse up happens and when
mouse up happens the collection stops
and no longer is a collection now
suddenly you get that zen-like feeling
you're right Wow just about everything
that I'm dealing with is a stream it's
something that I can query something
that's very tangible unlike events today
in JavaScript why because it's a
first-class value and what I mean by
first-class value is the fact that I can
both create one and I method but I can
also return one as well and where does
it really fit into the grand scheme of
things so when we talk about the general
theory of reactivity as it were
we have four quadrants here whether it's
single or multiple synchronous and
asynchronous we just have to think about
each one a little bit differently so for
example an object is fairly fairly
straightforward and es5 we added in the
ability to do filter and map directly on
our arrays so now that we were able to
do some fairly good compositional
programming styles using just plain
built-in objects then the promise came
along as part of yes yes 2015 although
it had been around for quite some time
before that in various forms but then we
now have a notion of a single values
instead of having to deal with a
callback we have the single value I can
handle to everybody and they would get
the right value
now observable on the other hand looks
exactly like array and there's a very
specific reason why is because in order
for people to actually start thinking
about thinking about asynchronous
programming you want to give them
something they're familiar with and let
me just clear something up that that
observable is definitely not object
observe it's not an event emitter in in
JavaScript nor is it an event target and
just as well object observed went
bye-bye anyways and that was the thing
that people are like oh this is great
we're going to solve all our data
binding issues with object.observe you
know I'll change something on there now
it ended up being a pig it ended up
being very very slow so it's gone so
instead everyone started to hop on this
idea of reactive programming and
unfortunately when I say reactive
programming everyone said react ah yeah
never mind the fact that there's nothing
to do with reactive programming and
react but you know they they kind of
stole the the the the moniker I've been
using four or five years oh well so what
is reactive programming anyways so you
know it's a very squishy term sort of
like the way that functional programming
is a squishy term you quite can't quite
define it very easily so I just went to
the dictionary why not
because Wikipedia had this really long
article and I couldn't figure it out so
it just says readily responding to a
stimulus okay and its components are
active and rallies ready to receive
events well we've already done that G
jQuery has been doing that forever and
even further than that I think the our
business analysts in our company if I
can laugh at us easily and I write you
noobs we've been doing reactive
programming forever
it's called Excel so you really want to
know really what reactive programming is
and where it came from there's actually
a paper that people can read on the very
origins of reactive programming by
Gerrard berry about how he created the
general-purpose language for doing so
and yes I know there there's a there's a
certain phobia of
reading academic papers because they
have a tendency to make you melt in
terms of their content and even the
smartest of us have you know that kind
of reaction to the technical papers and
and God bless the Germans for coming up
with an exact word for this of computer
vision shaft Academy sheesh Pepa phobia
I think there ya go
I love its yes I love having a German
German in there I love you guys that you
can shove ten words into one anyways so
yeah there's an actual I think term I
maybe I made it up I don't know and when
people start to talk about reactive
program they start to think about
functional reactive programming no no no
no no this is not what people are doing
when they think about reactive reactive
programming functional reactive
programming is a very precise term it's
a term that comes from Connell Elliott
and Paul hue DAC from the 1990s in a
language called Fran and it had very
precise meanings for everything that
they did and they called it that fart
pee so we're kind of stuck so they had a
very distinct notion of separation
between time continuous time whether
it's a clock versus discrete events and
it's just not important so you know call
us whatever compositional event
programming reactive don't care but what
I want to get to you is is the fact that
we have a very precise way of thinking
about asynchronous programming because
you have zero to infinite values either
by terminated by an honor or uncompleted
and
doesn't have to be obviously you can
continue infinitely you could admit a
couple and have an error you can
complete what you could never do is you
can never have anything overlapping and
you certainly cannot get values after
after it's been done so type-ahead
search is one of the most difficult
things that we've ever done I don't know
why but it just seems that everybody
tries to re-implement it and doesn't do
it very well so I decided to implement
it in jQuery
yeah just jQuery uh you know I had to
add it to bounce I had to add some some
checks I had to add in the xhr and retry
so I wrote more and did less so instead
I go you know I can solve this a little
bit a little bit better what if I could
say take the the Dom in Dom in key ops
the bounce by 500 milliseconds distinct
until changed did a search and bound
directly to the UI done I think I just
eliminated three pages of code now we've
already kind of talked about what the
observable is in terms of that contract
of 0 to infinite values but let's
actually go down to you know and we've
already talked a little bit about map
filter and reduce so let's actually go
into something a little bit more
complicated that a lot of people do with
their web applications so for example if
you're dealing with a phone or you're
dealing with something that's
constrained in terms of how much how
much memory and how much storage you
have you want to be able to only keep on
the screen what's absolutely necessary
on the screen and when when a as soon as
it goes off you want to completely get
rid of it get rid of all its handlers
and leave nothing around how do you do
that well first off you're going to
listen for the document scroll and then
you're going to the bouncer just a
little bit just in case people start to
you know scroll up and scroll down
rapidly and then they're going to
basically determine based upon the road
visibilities determine whether it's
weather
I hidden or not hidden and I'm what
you're gonna do is you're going to take
your rose shows and do an interface do a
poll polling basically and you're going
to get the row data continuously get
that row data continuously get that row
data until it tells you to hide it and
as soon as it tells you to hide it
everything goes away everything so it's
it's really a complicated kind of thing
and people can look at the code
afterwards but I think it's very magical
in the way that they were able to think
about it in very precise terms using
functional programming and reactive
programming together just like our
callback hell example we could actually
go a lot further than we did with with
promises by actually going down here and
authorizing and retry three times if it
fails and then we can also say if the
person who goes oh gosh no oh gosh no
cancel cancel cancel well we can
automatically stop that with the key
with take until so it's a little bit
more than than the burning sensation
that we got from callbacks
now slack for example slack for Windows
uses açaí uses rxjs
and what they use it for is very very
complex kind of interactions like an
editor should like for example if they
want to implement spell check what do
they do I'm not going to explain all of
this in particular but I just want you
to understand that they are actually
determining your language as you type
and being able to do that very very
easily using using this technology and
thinking differently about events now
they are able to think about these
things as objects and pass them around
and as Europe now allows us to think
about is now try catch finally becomes
very easy because I have catch and which
I can I can retry three times I can
catch and return some default data so
for example if I'm creating an offline
first application I can try and get the
data and if I fail for some particular
reason
three tribes and I can just give them
some default data and say here you go
and then finally at the very end I can
do some data cleanup now data back
pressure is also a thing that people
like to talk about and yes observables
can absolutely do that in fact we're
working on on a standard for exactly
that's called objective streams now it's
even more important that you want to win
friends and influence others so
obviously you want to work with the
react angular and ember communities to
do you know see how observables mix with
them and so what you've what we've been
finding in the community is that there
are literally twenty six different
implementations of flux written in
observables and there are about 20 s and
27 or 28 different bindings to react
directly from from from observables now
angular is its own special little beast
and why that is is if you're going to
use an angular 2 at all then
congratulations you're going to be using
observables because the HTTP stack
itself is an observable is going to be
is is rxjs today so they've already add
that in and what people have been
finding is that people want to use those
two things together because it solves a
lot of their problems they have the
retry logic they have attach they have
the finally all the things that promises
could never give them now what's also
very interesting is is not only is it
really interesting for for just doing
the basic kinds of things but I I would
say that's our notion of having this
swappable concurrency layer is also very
interesting so schedulers to me matter
and the fact that what I can do is I can
say where how and when something is
executed so for example I can take an
observable and I can generate using a
default asynchronous scheduler well
that's a problem in the fact that's oh I
just completely
turned my turn my machine into a
helicopter because the fan is just gonna
go off completely off its rocker but
instead if I could do something like
something like the the
requestanimationframe scheduler then it
changes how the picture apparently I
didn't swap out the picture but anyways
the it absolutely does matter because
now you decided to use instead of set
timeout or any other request set
immediate or anything else you've now
decided to move it to a
requestanimationframe
so when I said that Netflix is using it
for for animations that's exactly what
they do is they take a lot of their
asynchronous operations throw it on to
requestanimationframe and all they had
to change was one line of code they
didn't have to go through completely
throughout their their infrastructure to
do that now async/await is very
interesting in that it makes programming
very very easy in a very imperative
style so I can do try-catch and I can
treat it almost as if it were a
synchronous code which is absolutely
beautiful it's it's actually a stage 3
proposal right now for es2016 or ES 7 as
people call it and it actually ships in
the Microsoft edge browser today so if
you have Windows 10 edge and you can
turn on experimental features it's there
today which is kind of cool
now with observables you get also that
same kind of thing is because what we
have added is basic support for a CA
Cinco 8 so I can say when the text
changes I can ace a call an async
function on text and awaits the search
result which happens to be a promise so
that to me is kind of cool and so I
think it has a lot of promise especially
Mogan I just said promise
anyways so instead what we're going
going to see here is that I observed
are in fact coming to es2016 so if you
go there somehow something happened with
my slides but observables in es2016 are
absolutely coming I that hopefully that
they're in stage one right now and and
we're working towards stage two of
adoption but the idea here is that we
will now have complete and utter support
for for observables in your browser
directly so now you'll be able to do a
lot of the things that that for example
that's Netflix and others have been able
to do just by just by using your browser
directly that's kind of cool now let's
talk about the future a little bit so
the future is very very interesting and
the fact that we we have right now at
reactive - extensions rxjs but in the
future we're moving to reactive X and in
fact the the all of the code that's
being done right now is a combination of
Netflix Microsoft and Google all writing
this together it would have who would
have guessed that and five years ago
that someone would say that Microsoft
and Google and Netflix and even Facebook
are writing a library together well it's
true I yesterday during the functional
programming thing there was a comment
about rxjs versus or or CSP versus
observables so I don't necessarily want
to you know dog one or the other but yes
observables can absolutely do everything
that's that that CSP can do so let's go
back and take a history lesson here CSP
was created by Tony Hoare who works for
Microsoft Research no less in 1978 and
he wanted it for production systems or
they were kind of loosely coupled why it
was mentioned in a functional
programming context I don't know because
there's really nothing much functional
about this there's a while loop there's
a global channel
there's mutation all over the place it's
not really functional
so the imperative cat is not amused
because like I said there it's it's a
different definition of simple to me I
don't find this whole thing of a wild
shrew loop to be involved that simple
and in fact when I think about the
composition I think of that as a lot
more simple quite honestly so maybe it's
it's a personal thing but why
observables why not CSP well for example
I have determinants to clean up so for
example if I create an observable here I
not only get the on behavior which I'm
sending the next values but also when I
return an object I give it this handle
and which I can tell you to stop and
which and when I tell you to stop it
removes that event handler and so when I
call and when I start listening here and
then when I call unsubscribe the handler
goes bye-bye in CSP that doesn't work
that way also in CSP you have a notion
of there's no consistent air handling at
all so instead you have to throw it off
to an air channel and hopefully you can
listen to it but instead here we have an
air channel that's built directly into
the pipeline itself so it's very easy to
think about it when we can listen to it
on our air handler here and we can also
try & retry here and catch directly into
an end so there so with that I don't
know do I have sound here apparently I
don't
oh well anyways so if I can leave you
with anything today I want to say push
you know think about push collections
think about events very very differently
I am so with that I'll be glad to take
any questions Thank You Matthew
could you explain a bit about the
difference between arks extensions and
other libraries out there like vacant
Jas other laying with that deal with
reactive programming okay so yeah the
question was how does this differ from
any other library that does asynchrony
that does reactive programming well
certainly rxjs was the first one out
there since we've been out since 2009
there are slight differences when when
you talk about bacon and so forth none
of them have the for example the the
virtualization or notion of a virtual
time where you can just swap out the the
scheduler they don't do a lot of that
instead they tried to focus on
simplicity in terms of really you know 0
to 60 really really quickly instead of a
more comprehensive approach which we
took and there are a few fundamental
differences on how we we thought about
thought about hot versus cold
observables it's a long discussion you
can come and talk to me afterwards but
there are folks you know some
fundamental differences on on how we
tackle those problems but that's mostly
for the most part and we're we're fairly
friendly with one another in terms of
you know we're always you know trying to
one-up another in terms of speed in
terms of features and so forth I have
heard a lot of people complain about a
document of our says it's too
competitive especially for a beginner so
do you have any plan to fix in terms of
begin of stuff for beginners well we
have a lot of exercise so if you go to
reactive xio which is our homepage and
let's see if is it still up directly on
me so anyways if you can go to reactive
xio and take a look there we have a ton
of material in terms of our introduction
material and so forth in terms of why
why to use them but also there are lots
of other in
things such as reactive x io learn RX
there are interactive exercises there
that you can that you can learn if you
go to egghead radio did egghead io and
technologies rx there are a ton of
material there as well so in terms of
approachability the Internet is
fantastic here by the way sorry but if
you go to these particular sites egghead
radio has a lot of stuff that that is
particularly about new people coming to
2rx from from nothing at all explaining
the very very basics here I wanted to
get through the fact yes I could have
done a very introduction talk but but
it's more along the lines of showing the
real power of why people are using it
versus the oh you can you can do you