so about the
it's a silly way that I heard of when I
stopped start working on marketing and I
created different landing pages and only
done in benches people who are saying
like all the important information
should be above the fold which means the
user data scroll and all the extras
should be below so that meant for
marketing that if we want the user to
convert that means to fill a forum on
something like that then we must put the
form above everything an old information
below and honestly for me that didn't
make any sense because if the usual
dozen read what we are sailing we cannot
asked him over here to fill out the form
so i don't agree with the theory and I
don't know if you are with me who
doesn't agree with the theory you have
some people some people again not many
but I'm going to prove it wrong so and
let's chicken and then Wikipedia
Wikipedia we have a scroll through with
video or of our lives I mean high school
is full of it we scroll we know that we
scroll and then let's check out this
website which we all know about this
tray is khan website and according to
the above default theory this website
should be a massive fail because the
form is below the fold but on the other
hand it has sold out so what what's the
key point in this why did it work well
they engage the user basically
information and other stuff like the
terminal the countdown the other
countdown in the workshops again I mean
why did they put game in there I don't
know they just say I'm going to put a
game in there and it wasn't pretty well
it didn't make any sense I didn't have
to put a game in there but they engage
the user and
gonna spend like 30 minutes in this
website without getting bored and really
bad at it but some people may be better
and the nyan cat is like hidden in the
planetarium and then the suspicious
octopus another thing at the bottom of
the page that again it gives the
sensation of I want to keep scrolling
because I want to discover more stuff so
yeah if they ought to boost has nothing
to do with say yes maybe but it's
something else that you can add to the
website so for me really the about four
theories nothing man excuse for lazy web
design it's like I don't have much time
to do this I'm just gonna put the forum
over there and hope to the users to fill
out the form but now if you really put
and love into it you can make this
awesome website that the shades Khan has
made and then Troy us to paradox by whom
what has parallax to do with the
waterfall well parallax means scrolling
so if the user doesn't scroll he will
never enjoy parallax but parallax is a
wave of engaging the user while he or
she rolls so a current Wikipedia
parallax it's like moving the hbu port
which will be us but we are not really
moving we are giving the sensation of
the user moving so this trend when
design began with nike website in 2011
and it means moving different elements
in different layers along with scroll
base that means the user Scrolls an
element's move and this has the
sensation of perspective and depth that
you cannot give in any other way so how
do you do parallax in web design this
was one of the challenges when I started
with this talk there are so many ways of
playing parallax and I found for which
were like the best one is using jQuery
the other one is Suzanne
library CSS or something called pillar
which is not really parallax well I'm
option one is shake weary and let's
imagine we have this improper thing with
an image Powerpuff Girls and son info
about that we add some CSS to it what's
important about the CSS is that you must
generate overflow because without
overflow parallax really doesn't work
and then info which is this red thing
about and must be relative if it's not
relative then you will have this problem
that when you apply parallax the image
will cover the text and you will be able
to read it so they the info must be
relative or absolute in must have some
see index applied to it so and again we
must have this info element which is all
the information relative and wiped out
when we apply parallax in this in this
form we will apply it through transform
property it's a CSS turn for property
and we're not really telling the image
to be relative or absolute or fixed so
why does it cover the text well because
the transform property and create the
hips like position relative when Tim it
means that grace and us talking context
so that means its original space is
still occupied but with it this newest
talking context and it activates the see
index so even though the image is still
a static when we apply transform
property to it it's al aliy wicka wicka
and becomes relative it's a strange but
it does so info must be relative a list
or have AC index so when we have the CSS
then we apply some shake wearing any
version of jQuery
will do and then we write some jQuery
it's not that easier so this is one way
of doing battle axe Russia query which
is calling the scroll function on rapper
and inside that you call for a scroll
tube a scroll job is a function that
returns how many pixels has the user
scroll like 30-50 that so we create
something like this mmm that means we
ask for scroll top and we save that into
distance and then we tell the image
inside wrapper which is the Powerpuff
Girls to translate y half of the
distance that the rest of the content
and that as a result gives this so as
you can see the image Scrolls at a
different pace than the rest of the
content so yeah that's really all so
then we can apply a negative value just
a dash and we can make the image go up
as if it isn't working but and the image
goes up imagine something will fail so
yes it's often but there's a little
problem is that a scroll function
doesn't have really well performance I
mean if we are applying it's only to one
image inside of website is ok but if we
want to do everything with a scroll
function then we have a performance
problem so the right thing will be used
for qwest animation frame but you have
to break like a lot of JavaScript and we
have weird shapes from we have a lot of
JavaScript not really so I go for option
to rush up to our libraries well there
are many as four magic peril Akshay's
scroller and many more I go for scroller
what's interesting about it and you
don't require shake wary you don't need
to be an expert in JavaScript that's
awesome for me
and its massive realizing something
called data attributes data attributes
are attributes that you apply to the
element you want to transform and you
simply in provide an encore inside the
website when the element reaches does
that anchor the animation triggers it's
something like this let's imagine we
have a proper with information something
called move move along with this wording
circle and the more information we call
a scroller we initiate it and then we
have something like this if we apply
this thing so what is going on here well
we indicate this to and data attributes
one if data top and the other one data
button on that atop we tell the element
to be rather and rotate 360 degrees
which means more round and then that's
about on we tell it to be blue and not
to be rotated so data top applies and
triggers when the element reaches the
top of the page that's why we see it red
and the data bottom attributes applies
when we reach is the bottom of the page
so that's basically where we apply these
data attributes on the the anchors and
the animation three years when that
element which is that point something
like this you apply to an element when
the element which is that point it turns
to what we say and there are a lot of
data with tribute this is actually from
the github page of a scroller you have
all this and to like a cheat sheet you
can apply any kind of CSS to it because
it actually depends on CSS so any kind
of CSS you can apply there it will work
then and what if we want faster parallax
well
and we can just avoid a script because
we hate JavaScript or because just you
you don't want to bright JavaScript and
you will be able to create a faster but
lacks and that's option free which is
using CSS and only CSS and what's great
about doing paralysis you don't need to
worry you don't need JavaScript really
you don't need anything about it's pure
CSS here are here's some one of the
examples there and so we can see this
has this parallax effects effect on it
and it's only CSS is pure CSS do you
don't worry javascript jquery or you
don't need anything else bad CSS and
what you need to do this is actually use
perspective property in CSS that means
that suddenly Internet Explorer 10
doesn't read it but in the future it
will and this is another example we cssm
parallax this example is from scott
calhoun he created SS mixing in order
for every one of us to to have it easier
when we do parallax with the SS so you
can check this one out as well and then
another great example if this one that
comes with an article explaining and
step-by-step how to do this and it
worked like this you have those
different layers and as you scroll all
those layers are going one below the
other and it gives again the sensation
of reflective you because you are
actually using perspective in CSS
then this there's option for in case you
don't get along with CSS or you don't
get along with parallax in JavaScript or
you you just don't want to write one
line of code which is something called
Peter well Peter is not really parallax
is something called bigger so sometimes
it is confused like parallax that is not
parallax and it comes with well she is
it's a small thing only three claw bites
and he has many options for the
animations like the duration the delay
the duration many other cool stuff and
the only problem is that once you play
it you cannot replay it that's the
difference with paradox when I do
parallax when I scroll to the top again
the animations go again not here the
animation only triggers when the page
loads when the user Scrolls for the
first time but then everything remains
like that and it's actually what the
shyest conf website uses so it goes with
animation CSS which is something like
this and you pick animation like bounce
in up system working but you can check
it out a cure hmm well can't you get a
layer it works and then you are these
thing with cheese and well she is with
some brown loading images but what is
something like this and full of comic
sans and all that and yes it doesn't
require shake wearing or JavaScript nor
any kind of code you can create this ma
this Peter effects which is basically
this it's what the shades can we use is
when all the things appear out of
nowhere and as you can see as I scroll
the animations trigger but the only
problem is as I scroll back again the
animations don't we go again that's
different with parallax and it doesn't
give the sensation of perspective
because there is known perspective in
this but you don't write a line of code
in JavaScript or CSS additional so Oh
what our final recommendations for
parallax well first of all and
responsive first then animations them
parallax than everything when you apply
parallax to a website you destroy the
the organization and the flow of the
content because you begin creating
relative absolute and fixed elements and
everything's closed crazy so if you
apply parallax before making your web
site for mobile or responsive then at
the time you want you to make you want
to make it responsive you go Gracie
because I or the whole of your website
is kind of weird so make responsive
first and then up the animation of the
parallax but parallax and especially a
scroller doesn't work really well
neither on mobile devices and on touch
devices what can you do about it you can
turn it off with inquiries or and you
can use moderniser to turn it off on
touchscreens yes because touch screens
and parallax and especially scroller
like don't get along really well and
what else it's better to animate
transform property and opacity
transforming in scale askew rotate and
translate because those are cheaper and
they were better they have better
performance and opacity as well and if
you want to animate colors you cannot
use Excel SML and because you cannot go
through an f 20 there's no transition
between them you have to use our cpa or
hsl and simply because you can go
through 255 20 but no from f20 it
doesn't work that is simple changing the
mode the color mode and don't go crazy
over absolute position in because
there's this idea that I have two
absolution everything and
it's not really necessary because once
you apply transform the element will
have as the index and you can apply
relative the only problem with up to the
positioning it does is really like the
black sheep of the family because it's
and just like a rebellion in it and it
does whatever you wants so you have to
be certain that you can handle a lot of
absolute elements otherwise i recommend
you to go for a relative or fixed
elements but on the other hand absolute
and fitch have better performance than
relative so you can like go from one on
the order so and go soon and choose the
best implementation according to your
project needs simply there are thousand
ways of doing parallax and nobody's
going to tell you anything is you use
pillar instead of writing hundred lines
of JavaScript or if you use a library
and you don't use pillar whatever is
great for your project use it and please
try to keep keep a clean HTML because I
seen horrible things and I'm one of
those semantics crazy people so yeah try
to keep keep it clean okay well thank