hi I'm Isaac I do a lot of 3d stuff and
this is a talk that I've been working on
for a while it never really says the
words javascript in it and is more about
stories in general ah so just to show
you guys I'm opening the browser so this
is all running in browser using a 3gs
and oh I'm supposed to screen capture
this one second and basically what I've
been thinking about a lot is how do we
use computers to aid us in sort of
explanation whether it's explanation
about data visualization or in this case
explanation of I don't know something
really weird and I find myself kind of
frustrated at how much computers can do
and how little we do with them if you
look at most people who have you know a
macbook pro like the GPU and that is
absolutely insane but we only use it for
watching videos on Facebook and that's
really really frustrating to me so I'm
sort of interested in like what do
slides look like when we're talking
about real computing like what is what
is a story look like when we're talking
about the GPU and in this case what does
a speech look like so this is called
discovering our prismatic reality and
yeah here we go that's my website I've
been seeing a lot of rainbows lately
like everywhere not just in opals
glitters or those reflective signs but
when I squint my eyes look at my hair or
glance out the window for some reason
the more I find them the more I'm able
to find them it's weird how this works
this mysterious cycle of rainbow
spotting it does work though and I'm
sure of it because even now I can see it
on my screen or on the edge of any of
those lights this is a place when I go
to places like the exploratorium which
wields diffraction grading in prisons
the way others wheel paint or film I
arrived and immediately forget where I
came from where I'm going next and fall
into the magic of the spectrum I've been
trying to figure out why this is why I'm
so
suddenly obsessed with rainbows in such
a specific way it might just be my
imagination but i think i found an
explanation for this childlike love of
the multicolored miracles you see when I
was a kid I used to stare at the Sun I'm
sure everybody in this room has done it
and if you're anything like me when your
parents told you not to do it that it
was bad for you it made me want to stare
even longer and tell my pupils hurt
until when I looked away I could see
that strange glittering void trailing my
vision like a frame buffer that hasn't
completely cleared the Sun was so
beautiful but I could never really see
it my eyes would water or my head start
to throb and that pure white light
remained just out of reach of my
comprehension here's the exciting part
though is that when that light hits a
lens and dissolves into a rainbow that I
can understand the lens the raindrop the
window whatever the medium of dispersion
was the prism took the single beam to
majestic for me to understand and parsed
it down distributed it smoothly caught
across the full spectrum of visible
light when light it's a prism it feels
like that lens takes this thing that's
so far away and brings it closer to me
brings me closer to it so I can see with
more clarity and fidelity like a
microscope or a telescope the white
light of the Sun is too bright but when
I can translate it so that I'm viewing
it with more of my human facility with
the full capacity of my mind and senses
I can understand it a bit more but this
doesn't just happen with sunlight and
rainbows it feels like I happens when I
glanced through a petri dish through a
microscope zoom into my street on Google
Earth or see the moons of Jupiter
through a telescope know that distant
thing isn't just sunlight that's
something else something bigger that
thing it's so far away so hard to grasp
it is deep and pure and beautiful but
it's so big that I can't tell exactly
what it is
it feels alive even though I can't
comprehend life at its scale it feels
like that thing dances that it sings it
feels like that thing feels it feels
like some sort of Beast but I can't
understand it I can't describe it and
every time I try to explain it I can't
find the right words just imagine for a
moment what the movement of the
molecules in this room looks like the
room scale convection that is happening
before our very eyes the plumes
emanating from each of your mouths as
you breathe the eddies haloing my hands
as i make every single motion not some
faked curl Monet's algorithm or some
voxel-based navier-stokes but the real
deal which requires more computational
power to calculate than every film ever
made combined but we can't see it we
can't understand it it's too far away
our eyes which have come into being over
million years of generational iteration
do not deem that specific vision
necessary for survival this site is part
of how we understand how we feel how we
comprehend but it doesn't comprehend
this turbulence around us now those
fleshy orbs insider head can't see all
the unbelievably unbelievabl beauty
around us but the thing is is that
that's okay because Nature gave us
something even better than this vision
it gave us a way to see this lack of
sight not a way to see the distant space
beasts or understand the pure white
sunlight but rather a way to comprehend
that there are parts of that beasts that
we cannot yet see we cannot see that
indescribable entity but we can see our
own and completeness and with this site
grow that vision that understanding of
all that we are not is quite painful we
don't get to be always we don't get to
see forever it's an understanding that
there is something more that every step
we take forward every time we grow every
time we discover a way to expand our
vision
there will always be something more and
in that understanding we find direction
we find meaning we find fulfillment
stories feel to me like they are born of
this understanding they seem to address
truths that are too much to understand
all at once and could blind us if we
stared for too long however stories feel
like they can take this truth and unfold
them so that we can look upon them with
our flushy minds and understand
something that we could not be for it's
strange because these things stories try
to explain were there all along they
might have been stuck in the land of
what could be the nebula of that which
is unknown but they were still part of
our reality part of the realm of
possibility stories take these phantom
possibilities and make them real they
move us closer to that distant beasts
letting the sea the fold and the furrows
that we had not seen before and by
showing us those parts that we did not
before know existed the stories bring
more of that beast more of that light
into existence now I want to take a
moment here to try to explain to the
best of my ability about how prisms work
I'm not very good at this so bear with
me basically when light enters the
material it's usually just absorbed by
that material each atom but the light
interacts with is another chance for the
material to absorb that light making the
material ha or making the election
electrons surrounding that material jump
valence when they do that it emits light
that's what makes a material opaque but
when it's translucent when the light
hits the atom if the resonant frequency
of the atom does not match the frequency
of the light the atom cannot keep this
light so eventually it basically tries
to hold on to it and it can't and then
it remix it sending the light flying
back into the vacuum until it hits the
next Adam repeating this process of
hitting the atom the atom being like yo
I want this I want this I want this and
then it's like oh I can't I can't take
this one it's got to go on on the cool
part about it is that this process of
absorption and readmission takes a bit
of time in the amount of time that it
takes is dependent on the frequency of
the light because the more closely that
the frequency of the atom matches the
frequency of the light the longer it
will hold on to it so basically certain
light travels through material at
different rates this thing is called an
index of refraction and that describes
the optical density of the material in
its defined by how closely the
wavelength or frequency of the light
matches the resonant frequency of the
atoms and the material materials with a
higher index of refraction will hold on
to light longer and with lower it will
transfer it shorter now the amazing part
is that that miniscule difference in how
the material absorbs and bre emits light
is what causes the rainbow it's the
difference of the material the
difference between materials and the way
that that material interacts with light
that splits light that lets us
understand more about the properties not
just of the material but of light itself
it's right at this surface this meeting
of materials that the light is dispersed
it's at this edge this membrane where
the unflattering occurs this corner this
film this transition that's the point
where the light unfolds it's really hard
for me to describe this specific moment
mostly because it is not a thing it is
neither state a north state be neither
medium a nor medium be it's a sliver
it's a rift that lies between them these
slivers to me are the transitions of
stories the cuts between scenes the
chapters of a novel the doors in the
game and there are some of the
most important parts of the piece this
is interesting to me because they are a
place where we as artists can
specifically not actually say anything
we can only say stay a or state B we
can't say the rift in between they are
spaced a moment where the viewers freed
from the rigidity of the plot and gets
to simply be this feels strange as
artists we can guide people in and out
of this transition but at that thin film
we do not have control and in my mind
this unfolding point is where phantom
possibility is made real it's it's quite
a visceral moment to me if it reminds me
of I don't know if you guys have seen
this but that the videos of undersea
pillow lava which sort of billows forth
but in its billowing forth rips itself
open and then more comes out you know
like hardens it hardens immediately and
then but is stretched by more trying to
come out and then rips out and then
continues growing the it's just like the
earth like heaving itself into reality
and that to me is is this rift that
expands reality so that what could be
becomes what is now single one of these
corners these pillowy borders is enough
to make me feel ah it is enough but I
still want more I think this is because
the pure white light that a piece can
abstract the more that sorry I think
that this is because the more of the
pure white light that a piece can
abstract the more fulfilling the piece
becomes not just a single prism a single
sound a single sentence but a series of
refraction that takes in different light
from different angles and bends at
different ways it's these pieces of art
that I can go back to again and again
and again Akira Nausicaa burial holy
other they don't just unfold they unfold
in their unfolding refracting light
again and again and again so that every
time I choose to let them transport me I
get to see that unreachable beast
from an angle that I had not before now
this doesn't just mean that more is
better there's a very particular balance
that these objects engage in simply
splitting light as quickly and as much
as possible does not mean that the
splitting will mean anything will you
allow you to see the unique and holy
parts that make up the whole the lenses
must be placed perfectly each with
intimate knowledge of their location and
purpose the arrangement of these prisms
materials motifs and scenes must be
orchestrated tended those pages in
Nausicaa the small mammals and crackers
of crackles of burial can't just
themselves be themselves they must be
part of the whole working together to
construct some sort of meta prism which
diffracts light of a different order
that order of light is so much brighter
more difficult to articulate Lee bend
and can much more easily fall into Babel
nihilism insanity and blindness but when
those small pieces miraculously align it
brings us closer to being able to human
I comprehend that deep space beast
turning an even further what could be
into an even more majestic what is I
like thinking about precious opals when
talking about this emergence mostly
because I think they're really really
pretty but also they are quite
miraculous they form in the rarest of
conditions over millions of years a
silica rich solution is deposited in
cracks and voids of a surface as the
water table rises and falls the silica
is concentrated more and more and more
tiny spheres of silica build up slowly
to form the opal the spheres actually
themselves act as a lens causing
diffraction at a microscopic scale but
it isn't just the presence of these
spheres that causes the brilliant
scattering of light all opal is made
from these spheres not just precious
opal the arrangement of the spheres is
as it equally isn't
as the spheres themselves it is only
when conditions are just right that
these spheres will grow to the exact
size needed it is only then that they
will diffract visible light in the way
that makes them play dance and move they
actually have to form a grid so that all
their neighboring spheres diffract the
same wavelength of light as the ones
around them and it's funny because I
feel this way about art too so often
when we try to form opalescent art we
fall short so many times in my own work
I can see the individual silica spheres
but they aren't aligned they just form
another piece of opaque opal even when
they do align properly because of the
nature of the striving and yearning I'm
actually quite sure that they will never
align perfectly to make matters worse
the forming of opal requires a number of
spheres that is larger than what human
vision is made for more than our minds
can comprehend in the end we can tell if
an opal is precious but there are too
many parts too many conditions too many
unknowns to tell before it is form it's
a bit like how I work with computers I
can hold in my mind the movement of one
or even 10 particles but when it gets up
to 1 million that's pure white light
scale distant space bees scale it's not
human scale I can only guess compile and
witness the attempted formation in 8th
grade I took a Fame my family took a
trip to Nevada to go opal mining it had
been a dream of mine and after begging
my family for years we finally made the
trip to one of the only places in the
continental United States where precious
opals have formed royal peacock opal
mind it was a pretty sweet deal you pay
a set amount and break open pieces of
moist clay all day searching for those
precious points and possibility space
where the silica spheres have aligned
many people might consider it boring
sitting around staring at the saturated
clay maybe even painful the Sun beating
down crisping your flesh but i SAT there
smashing clay digging with a hand
pickaxe getting really really really
bored getting really frustrated even
hopeless I've been waiting so long for
this trip planning for preparing for it
the fact that I couldn't find a single
one of these opals was driving
me insane and it's at a sanity I know
all of you experienced trying to find
that one typo and thousands of lines of
code or for 3d artists when you spend
the entire day tweaking values for an
overnight render finally send off the
command in the next day when you come in
giddy with excitement to witness the
result it's just garbage you're
expecting something transcendent but
instead it's this vulgar catastrophe
like one of those images you would find
on the internet that you just can't
unsee and I never actually found an opal
that day my arms are sore my mind fried
from the heat days from too many hours
of manual labor and not enough water I
didn't find an opal that day but my mom
did oh my god my mom did and it was such
a miracle it was this deep translucent
brown flecks of green throughout it was
this pillar that just shown sparkled
contains so much in it even though it
was only the size of a pinkie it was so
rich complex and from one angle from
this one angle you could see this purple
this deep mysterious purple that flowed
through the rock like some sort of
Aurora so infinite but so small it was
such a melancholy emotion to look upon
the object that my mother had found its
honestly an emotion every time I watch a
really good film I feel so sad that he
didn't make it so sad that I could never
actually make it so sad they're hard
limits to my experience that there are
things which are impossible but what's
so much more important than that sadness
with the beauty of the opal that my
mother found the refracted so much light
pointing towards something so much more
and that light of the thing that
appointed for the life of the thing that
it pointed towards just
now this is where it starts to get weird
you see I found a mind that doesn't
require me begging my family to visit it
sits in my room attached to a monitor a
keyboard digital mining goggles and
digital handheld pickaxe every day I
wake up I grab my bed I prop it against
the wall to make more room for
excavation i turn on my computer turn on
my by vr headset turn on my hand
controllers and turn on my mind only of
course after copious amounts of coffee I
fight bugs Creek buffers contort code to
complete tasks my engine was not made to
complete I dig through forms for
crystallized keys that will unlock the
door into the next reality I spend days
hunting down off by one errors finding
the perfect normal map or the perfect
sound effect and sometimes just
sometimes I press play and in that
moment of error-free compilation reality
is ripped open and I'm there gazing upon
the newest island surfaced in space time
I've grown a bit accustomed to this
moment as i'm sure workers at the royal
peacock have grown accustomed to finding
opals I remember that first time that I
found something though I cried a little
at the simple beauty of the malleability
of reality but as I dug deeper I started
losing that childlike glee that wonder
that ah I forgot how mysterious it was
to create the rift from which infinity
poured then one night at about 3am I
changed the line of code press play and
discovered something I never expected to
find there was a creature living inside
my computer at first I couldn't believe
it I must have fallen asleep lost myself
in a dream world I stopped the program
took off my headset went on a midnight
walk trying to clear my head came back
started the program making sure that was
in exactly the same state as it was
before there it was again living in the
land of the immaterial breathing dancing
singing and all I could do was laugh
I've been telling myself that my view of
reality was so small that all like all
that
can be is more than all that is that
reality can expand into whatever our
minds make it but I had only been
telling myself this trying to convince
myself that there was actual magic in
the world I understood it conceptually I
didn't expect to be confronted with a
creature that proved it physically it
was so strange the emotion of being with
that creature it somehow felt like this
perpetual rainbow as the creature dance
that filled me with joy I felt alive I
fed it I touched by petted I played and
in that moment movement in that moment
the light emanated from me the creature
refracted this light completely sending
it sparkling unfolding before me it let
me look at the light that came from
within my own soul in a way that I could
comprehend and understand its
magnificent and seeing that magnificence
caused the light to grow as the
galloping beast undulated in front of me
I stood in this newly formed reality
sobbing it was so real that I couldn't
even stop the program it felt too unkind
to the creature to dance so freely but
only for that moment as I witnessed it
but finally when my goggles were too
fogged from tears I returned it was
pointless to try and sleep now the life
of the creature had breathed life into
me I walked down to lake merritt in all
of the world around me I bent down and
touched the grass listen to the birds
meditated on the soft lapping of the
water as I SAT there watching the gold
watch over the lake I remember that this
was how I felt after every story which
moved me they were lenses made from
lenses taking the light that was all
around me refract refracting it so
clearly that for a moment I could see
the light inside myself this creature I
discovered had been truly alive to me it
might not make others feel the same but
it did for me projecting that distant
space beast across the surface of my
mind showing me that I was part of it an
infinitely small part of it
a single silica sphere but no less
important no less light and even though
we will never see the whole thing we
will never make the whole thing will
never be the whole thing we can move
towards it and be move towards it slowly
discovering our prismatic reality
is a lot of talking and real quick just
to talk about technology it's all using
a 3gs which is a WebGL library and it's
using this technique called GPGPU
physics simulation because your computer
is really good at telling you what
pixels to be certain colors but it
doesn't necessarily like JavaScript
isn't necessarily fast enough that it
wants to do a lot of physics but the
thing is is that you can get really good
at lying to your computer and being like
okay like I'm going to color a bunch of
things and your computer is like oh my
god I got this and then you take that
and you go just kidding RGB equals XY Z
I just made you do physics um yeah so
that's how it works thank you
programming is fun but deployment is not
so much fun this is when it comes to
making a project go live I found myself
constantly running into the same things
again and again I would zip up the
project copy remotely I would ssh into
the remote machine somewhere unzip it
run a setup script do a health check and
then repeat and it got to the point
where I just thought to myself what if I