when you think about a conference you
can draw some parallels to what a
conference is versus our sort of daily
work that we do in some ways a
conference is kind of our Olympics or
its kind of our space launch or our
Grand Prix and I guess we all kind of
just win by being here together I mean
it's not every day that you get to
launch rockets but I think that this is
this is one of those such occasions I
think we should enjoy being here
together especially at the first CSS
come here in Asia which i think is
incredible because Singapore is
amazing and I am really really happy to
be here as well today my talk is not a
it's not about code it's about being a
coder I guess or designer I'm asking the
question what are we doing anyway and I
talked about the Space Launch is if that
was something that we aren't sort of
really doing you know we're often like
this is our environment we sit looking
at a terminal with a blinking cursor and
we're typing in there all day or maybe
we're hitting reload all day and
swearing at a browser and looking at the
box model and I think what's really kind
of interesting when you think about what
it is that we do we you know I mean
before the web was this intangible thing
you know when we had big CRT monitors
that sat on the back of our desks you
know it like we had no connection to to
the web but what's really interesting
about now is that we're just surrounding
ourselves in their screens and they're
just smaller they're in our pockets and
they're in out bags and there are no
tiny laptops and so we don't have
tangibility over our work really but
it's just closer so we tell ourselves
that it's okay and we're actually
building something visible or not
anyway I'll introduce myself super
quickly I'm Ben I'm from Melbourne
Australia I'd say that I was a designer
but I would be lying I didn't go to
design school I did art in high school
and that was about my sort of design
background I studied multimedia design
I'd say I was a developer but I didn't
study in computer science so i guess i
would say that i was i just build things
for the web i'm mostly self-taught like
probably a lot of you are I certainly
didn't start doing stuff for the web
because it was easy to describe to my
parents I just did it because I was
working on a computer and I was really
interested in how I created something
and I think that's probably true for a
lot of you here how many people are
self-taught wait sheriff you okay maybe
fifty percent i think i think you know
maybe we get into doing what we're doing
because we have this sort of dedication
to a creative endeavor or we're just
chasing a desire to learn how to do
something also i forgot to mention it so
I'm a contractor I work for sort of
maybe four to six companies a year I'm
one of the three founding members of CSS
conf Australia and I just try to build
stuff that I enjoy doing and that's
that's what my talk today about it is
about but the actual fact is that I have
no idea what I'm doing today I'm going
to talk about fun and goofy or fun /
goofy over profit so let's think about
that for a second what is fun and goofy
funds pretty self-explanatory but what
is goofy goofy means like fully ashore
just harmlessly eccentric and so I'm
talking about the the idea of building
things just for the hell of it just for
like the sake of learning or just for
having fun
so I would say im doing this but I have
no idea why I just am Brad bells at
cascadia jeaious said creative clewd is
an experiment with the goal of
surprising and delighting I think it's
much easier to say that something is
goofy but that's just me he also goes on
to say that when you do something that
is an experiment you do it because it
might make you a better engineer you
don't necessarily just quit your job but
you know maybe you should just take a
day off and try to build something so
I'm going to tell you a story I bring
water somebody's water I'm going to
drink it anyway tasty all right
so I'm going to tell you a couple of
stories today and they're just sort of
points in my career over the last 13
years they're not like the best things
I've ever worked on they're not things
that may be made more money than other
stuff that I've done but I think they're
interesting for the sake of they were
really fun but they were seriously goofy
okay one afternoon sometime in 2009 i
was i was actually putting together a
series of html5 workshops this is when
here smell 5 was a new thing we still
called html5 her for one thing I was I
went to a meet up and I said hey I think
I'm gonna maybe do some workshops she
would be interested in doing it it's
gonna be a whole day there'll be 300
bucks who wants to come 70 people in the
room with their hands up and I sort of
looked at the ground really nervously
and I said I'll get back to you and two
weeks later I put aside up and I sold
all of my tickets in like an hour
suddenly I had like fifteen thousand
dollars in my bank account and I had no
idea what I was doing I had a date I had
a venue but I still have no idea what I
was doing and I guess what I wanted to
do was I just wanted to know everything
I didn't want somebody to be able to say
well what happens when that doesn't work
in this browser or what happens in this
situation I didn't want to be blah so I
started reading w3c's facts and I just
wanted to know how does everything work
I'll just I'll just read
everything and nobody would be able to
prove me wrong and I started and I
quickly realized that w3c specifications
are not built for normal people they're
built for people he told browsers and so
I mean I was going to get to the
workshop eventually I was eventually
going to start preparing that I mean it
was only in a week and i had only you
know taking a lot of people's money and
by that point and so I was madly
researching I took like time off work
and I was just reading and researching
and trying to develop this content but I
stopped and I I just did something
there's a little hack project one
afternoon I went into devtools and I
started messing around with the
developer
improved like the spec information I
started changing margins and tweaking
the typography and changing the line
heights of everything just trying to
make everything more readable because I
didn't really want what i was looking at
and I thought hey this is this is pretty
cool maybe I'll maybe I'll show it to a
co-worker and you know maybe I'll make a
little bookmarklet out of this thing and
so I did and I tap you know quickly as
fast as I could in under an hour made
this little bookmarklet that basically
took this pic added these weird styles
that I decided were better than the
other ones for whatever reason and I I'd
showed it to my friend Anthony pushed it
took your hub and a day or two later I
just tweeted like oh hey here's some
user styles good luck does it I thought
the project was earlier and for the next
three hours I watched my phone explode
in ways that I had never seen my phone
exploited I have been working on open
source for a long time and I was kind of
building things that I thought were
interesting I wasn't really getting that
much attention and this thing that I
just kind of threw together when I was
just messing about you know
procrastinating essentially suddenly was
making my phone melt on my desk on the
fourth hour Paul Irish retweeted it my
phone exploited for this evening and the
next day paul got in touch and he
actually sent me a pull request and the
pleura quest was like oh hey I fixed
your fonts in Firefox because
cross-domain issues it wasn't working
whatever I said hey cool thanks Paul
George did I was like oh my god this guy
actually knows who I am this is super
cool what was one of my heroes and the
next thing was I got an email from him
saying hey what are you on gchat
suddenly pulled message mean he's like
hey what up no seriously the
conversation that was I'd look back
through my message history that was the
message he sent me friendliness guy ever
and what was really interesting was that
like like I said this was something that
I just threw out and I didn't think was
important or interesting even I was just
doing it for the hell of it but I wasn't
just pull other people kept coming out
of the woodwork other people from
organizations like W
see people like Steve Souders and people
who work for browser companies were
actually interested in the work that I
was doing people that I respected you
know it wasn't just dorks on the
internet these were like my heroes a
little while later this is a great shot
of me mid-speech I look much younger but
still be looking of course so this is my
talk from web directions 2010 so this
was a little bit longer and I was on
this whole tip about how evil the w3c
were that um what was really fun that in
in between those few months of me
throwing out the sort of bookmarklet and
this point here was that mike smith from
w3c got in touch and i actually went to
tokyo for a conference or something else
and mike said you want to grab a beer of
course i wanna grab a beer let's hang
out let's let's meet each other and what
followed was really interesting Mike had
actually been working on a specification
that he called html5 for authors and the
idea of hicksville five four authors was
that he took the w3c spec removed all of
the crazy browser implementation crap
and just shipped a much smaller version
of the spec it looked the same but it
was the content was slightly different
smaller and we kept talking and you know
we're you know chatting a little bit
from the same talk this is from you know
the same the same moment in time during
this talk Mike and I have been working
together and we actually took my my
styles and pulled them out of the
bookmarklet and fix them and worked on
it for a bit and you'll see this is Mike
here and what we did during this talk
was I mean he works for w3c any have
access to deploy stuff so we didn't ask
anybody but we just hook the user styles
and put them on his spec on the w3c side
and hit deployed from the front row of
my talk which I thought was the coolest
thing in the world
and I realized holy my work is
running on their domain I got pulled
down you should really want to but it
lost it a few weeks but some people
weren't so happy it was it was pretty
amazing a little bit later on after a
few months of nagging whole Irish
convinced me to start joining RC told me
a few channels to join and this
conversation took place I actually took
this from the logs from 2010 uh so in
hixson okay there we go there it is um
to kick see up here was like oh hey I
thought this was really cool the work
that you did what do you say we put it
on what's up ug so we did we we shipped
this month or so later he just gave me
access to deploy whatever I wanted and
here we are it's been online for five
years now it was the thirst w3c extended
spec that you know obviously what WG so
is kind of at that point but
that's a whole other story it was
offline capable so you could go into
your tablet and it would sink down to
your device and I was documentation
looked a little bit better whatever it
was cool but I had no friggin idea that
when i SAT there in 2009 riding a goofy
little bookmarklet that I scared to one
friend that this would happen months
later did I'd be working with these
people so as an extension of my talk I
wanted to talk more about commercial
versus fun and don't it's entirely
possible that you here will work you
know a full visit II busy lucrative
career doing good work for good people
and your impact on the world will
actually be minor you're not going to
disrupt an industry you're not gonna
you're not gonna fix anything you're
just going to build good stuff forget
people and that's okay that's totally
fine
one of the frustrating things about our
industry is that predicts die and when a
project dies underneath you you lose a
little bit of yourself too how many show
of hands how many times have you lost
something after three months of work not
too many six months 12 months like
entire products disappearing there's
couple of folks even good for dicks diet
I worked on a few projects that died
after investing a lot of time and money
into them and they've disappeared from
underneath me and I had no idea that
they even kind of came or left and I now
I guess you know I work for myself and I
am and celery and I'm I'm the person who
maintains my own happiness and I'm the
person has to pay my salary and my super
and worried about my next contracts
coming in if the contracts good and if I
need to like yell at my client for some
reason it kind of sucks but I think it's
really important that we focus for fun
it's this world so this is a project
that started in my office we were
drinking beer it was 35 degrees so it's
kind of Singapore ish we were in a
warehouse office that had no air
conditioning so it was 35 degrees inside
we were you know beating sweat down our
heads and we'd all been doing client
work for the day and we were all kind of
a little bit over it in the office we
had just bought a projector and so
basically we were projecting anything we
could onto the wall funnily enough we
started just projecting gifts because
gifts are here are the people who there
there's me eating a doughnut probably
wasn't eating a doughnut right down
there is Glenn Madden there is Tim Lucas
and there's Josh episode disorder myself
Glennon's him or CSS conf australia by
the way and josh is just a rad friends
that was so visiting the office that day
now we sat down and we started working
on this thing called gift city i'm going
to show you give city hopefully just
remember this is the internet and I
don't moderate this content so if
anything comes up that should I'll do my
best ok cool ok so this is gift city
gift city as you can tell is full screen
gets cool it has basically node features
except for this guy
so what gives city does is we take the
name of a tumblr and we hit the tumblr
API and we just look for gifts pretty
great right we have only a couple of
features we have the X button which if a
gift comes up that's a little bit rude
for the office it is tumblr after all
you hit X and it will remove that gift
and never ever show it again it's kind
of great and the gifts are random this
is one of my favorite tumblers code
classic but in the source we actually
know in source we actually keep a list
of a couple of our favorite tumblers in
here let's see let's find some good we
got some adventure time fans here no
want just right come on you're lying to
me adventure time is the best okay and
so what's happening here is it's hitting
the tumblr API for both the classics
tumblr blog and the adventure time gifts
blog it's found that many gifts and it
just keeps traversing through the API
and trying to download more and more and
more gifts as you'll notice the URL bar
updates and the query string shows the
tumblers that we actually have in there
so if you wanted to you could actually
get the URL actually go on edit the URL
just put anything in there it goes and
downloads them it's pretty good
everything else okay
we set a couple of rules for the for a
gift city we want allowed to use any
JavaScript libraries we went allowed to
use any JavaScript to do the like little
pop down thing for that we're using the
CSS target selector because why would
you use javascript because we're CSS
badasses of course and we didn't wanna
use libraries we just wanted to do fun
and dumb JavaScript you know Smashing
API and put your API key in the source
code of course that's gonna be amazing
we focused on fun and so a couple of
things happened like we were doing this
in our office and drinking beer and
hanging out is pretty great and when
somebody else would come in the office
we would just start like putting gift
city on and showing them gifts and
playing music and you know just inviting
people into our office to hang and we
kept going okay cool we kept going and
we thought we were really cool we
started going to hack events and camp
JSE's and stuff like that and there was
one point where we at a New Year's Eve
party we were projecting gifts 40 40
foot high on to a factory building
across from the rooftop that we were on
which we thought was pretty cool kind of
dorks I guess we took a projector to a
camp and dragged out a cable that was 50
meters long the power cable and started
projecting onto trees it didn't really
end there for like Tim and Josh and
myself it ended there we were done but
Glenn wasn't quite done Glenn kept
hacking we kept as I said going to
parties and playings too often hanging
out and blends like you know what to be
really cool if the gifts were synced to
music would not be great wouldn't be
great if we could like hook it up to a
turntable and like have an analog
control for the gift so we could scratch
it backwards and forwards would not be
great would it be great if we could like
put the gifts in 3d and shoot pixels of
gifts at the camera wouldn't be great
will be great if we could like just have
like gifts decoded in the browser
wouldn't it be great like
it just kept going and we humid him for
a little while but to a point we were
like Glenn I we need to work just please
leave us alone and Glenn kept just
writing code more code and more code and
more killer he was experimenting a lot
doing weird stuff and he was somebody
who had never written JavaScript before
not much anyway little bits Glenn went
on and he wrote something called X gif
which is a web component that actually
implements a tag in the browser called X
give it has only a couple of options you
can set a gift a loop you can set it
playback speed and you can do some other
interesting things he made it as a web
component he experimented with doing it
in react and angular and using basically
every library around to try and go on
this pursuit of learning web components
learning Audio API is learning how to
break down a gift learning how to I
don't know what his obsession is but he
I think his business card what does it
say no so if you if you don't know how
to decode a gift in a browser I think he
calls you a gift enthusiast but he's a
gift pro anyway I'm going to show you a
little demo of X gives anyone seen
excuse before lunch flirts cool ok so X
gift takes a gift you add a tag to your
browser just like you would an image you
say here's the source of the gift and it
plays it just like an image then some
other cool stuff happens you can
actually change the playback of the gift
so you can do this ping-pong effect and
then you can even do other stuff like
how many times do you want the gift to
play through just once tempos and that's
all implemented as attributes on Elm
pretty cool you can set the speed
you can set speed so you can say like oh
hey me really fast crazy stupid fast or
just one France then he started working
on beats for a minute and he figured out
you could actually sing some audio
pretty rad so Glenn is super rad he's my
buddy he's the CSS comp guy as well you
should definitely say hi to him because
i'm using his demos and I'm kind of
getting to play music look cool but he's
cooler than I but I think what's really
interesting here is that XD ax wouldn't
have happened if we didn't get drunk in
the office and just start hacking with
gifts and this took Glenn on a trip
where he started giving conference talks
at cascadia jays in portland at JS comp
in melbourne at JS coffee in berlin and
his conference schedule continues to get
booked beyond today because of work like
xq so when it set you a challenge gib
city started as a one hour challenge and
it led to hours and hours of learning
and super amounts of fun so I want all
of you to go ahead and just do a dumb
thing whatever the dumbest thing is that
you can come up with that you think you
can do in an hour just try and do it
fact is if it's fun and you actually
achieve something in now you're probably
working it for the entire weekend that's
fine and another dumb project on Fridays
we have a thing that we
and our office called jelly jelly is
casual co-working we have a you know
reasonably sized office and we just like
to invite our friends to come in kind of
work and just be around as there for
lunch have drinks together again the day
one particular jelly day I didn't feel
like doing actual real work and I've
never used Bauer so of course I should
do something with Bauer right never used
it I'd also never ever written any
Python still have no idea what I'm doing
and I didn't even use sublime tix either
so of course what am I going to do in an
hour I'm going to write a sublime text
plugin in python that uses bowers so we
can install bauer packages because i
don't know that's the most sensible
thing that I could do in an hour I
pulled something together the kind of
worked by reading other people's source
code and over the weekend but fighting
it up and released it the last time I
checked this plugin have had over 10,000
foot installed and a lot of people
actually use it I don't use it so if
you've got some spare bandwidth and you
want to fix the issues have a look at
the issue tracker on there but what was
really interesting here is that after i
worked on the assigned about joining the
bower team which was a totally
unexpected result I didn't ever use
Bower before this point if like riding
this dumb thing python and I had no idea
what I was doing and using an editor
that i didn't use either which kind of
gets me to a point about open source how
many people write plus ones on issues
yeah your old jerks huh i think i really
hate this about open source i really
hate this leg hey please go and spend
all of your time and do this for me
because it really doesn't give anyone
anything and i want to let you in on a
little secret about open source you can
actually do open source without doing
anything this is my strategy watch
listen learn and just hope where you can
so the reason I say this was because of
a particular circumstance that kind of
came towards me there's the old saying
if you don't know what you don't know or
in my case I would say you don't know
what you don't know until it literally
falls out of your head for a little
while I was not a contributor not hadn't
ridden any code the match media polyfill
I was interested in the mass media
polyfill and I just started sort of
trolling around the issue tracker
following it and sort of looking at how
it worked it's really simple little
polyfill and I thought it's cool and
about two years ago an issue came in
that said that we should remove this
code there was a completely new PR that
rewrote all of this and it was a huge PR
basically rewrote the entire library and
I spent hours reviewing it remember I
was not a contributor to the to the open
source project and I just reviewed this
and the code was really good and so we
talked about a couple of little style
things that we wanted to fix before we
accepted it into the project but it got
in and months went on one day I was in
my team chat with one of my clients and
matt said we've got a production
performance issue on mobile does anyone
know what this crazy minified code that
says offset with triple equals 42 means
and I had no idea that I would know this
until he pasted it and as soon as he
pasted it I was like that's the match
media polyfill because I reviewed that
pull request you know months ago and
that's the only thing that I could
imagine that has code that's this
ridiculous and because of that I guess I
knew that there was actually a new
version of this polyfill which address
these performance problems and we
upgraded it the bower package and our
performance issue disappeared I know
that's a kind of a fun story doesn't
happen every time like that but
sometimes does
how many of you build things start
building something maybe working it for
a few hours and never show anyone got
everyone come on everyone does that
right I know you do you're lying we're
just late you're lazy or something then
almost forever particularly earlier in
my career I would think of an idea and
then ten minutes later I would be
writing code and my girlfriend would say
are you going to bed anytime soon or are
you going to continue to be hacking on
your laptop and i would say i'm working
on my laptop and i would stay there and
i would be working past two o'clock in
the morning on this dumb thing and then
i would wake up and I'd be bloodshot
going to work the next day and basically
hating my previous decisions of working
on this dumb thing um but for a long
time I didn't ship these things they
were half baked and like they weren't
really thought to the point of like can
i actually release this and I think dumb
experiments like that are useless
especially if you're not going to commit
to actually showing somebody or actually
sharing it even with just one friend
maybe if you're at your work or someone
on the internet that you talk to
regulate and for a little bit longer
after that I started bringing my friends
into my damn projects and I we also
found the situation where we'd start
arguing about the project before we'd
even launch it or showing anyone else
we're arguing about silly things that
didn't really matter because nobody else
knew this thing exists except for one or
two people so i'm going to set a
challenge for all of you here the next
time that you're going to build
something that you don't think you're
going to ship i'm killing kittens that
guy two guys should shoot so don't count
your days make your days count work on
projects that you think that you'll
share work on projects that are fun work
on projects that are dumb don't
necessarily do it for money celebrate
your wins when you do something cool
enjoy it may be launched something on
your birthday right so for me I don't
know about you
common birthday is you wake up and you
spend time with your partner or your
family and then they say I have to go to
work today and you say okay I'm not
working today and then the house goes
quiet and sit by yourself looking at
Twitter it's pretty boring isn't it so
instead I decided to launch on my
birthday this year for the past year
before I'd been working on an app called
caliber which is a quality and
performance telemetry suite for the web
it runs on chrome or uses chrome
devtools everything the chrome dev tools
can get caliber runs it runs against
your site every day or when you hit the
API and it gives you metrics about your
side like how quickly first paint was
what your CSS like quality is like what
your secret codes videos every time your
site loads so that you can compare them
and like look at screenshots of how long
it took something to render or maybe you
can blame a third party for their ads
being slow so I've been working on this
for a long time if you want to check it
out later it's caliber optical but I
launched it on my birthday and it was
the best birthday ever just for the next
like eight hours I just watched my phone
be like retweeting and people saying hey
congratulations you launch something
that's really cool so when you guys to
do that too this is one of my favorite
quotes by then period been period worked
on supply which later sold to eBay which
I think he was maybe not so proud of
after because they did nothing with it
they didn't ship it so I'm gonna kill a
kitten for that he said as a creative
person you've been given the ability to
build things by from nothing by the way
of hard work over long periods of time
creation is deeply personal and
rewarding and it means that your work
should be rewarding as well and if it's
not then something's wrong right we're
spending all these hours working on a
computer typing in staring at this
goddamn screen we should be enjoying
that our jobs are pretty great and as a
creative person you need to understand
yourself
I don't think you can underestimate
imports of understanding what motivates
you as a person and then working on that
and self analyzing and getting better at
understanding the way that your brain
works you got to figure out what makes
you tick you got to figure out how to
ship and as you do it you should repeat
and you should get better you should
make friends kind of hard sometimes and
depression isn't really talked about a
lot in our industry and like I said you
and yourself a loner the master of your
own mental state but you can help your
friends and you can help your colleagues
and not to mention minority groups as
well in short be better than you are
your career is long make it count make
it enjoyable and motor your career on
work that is not necessarily going to
make you famous or rich but just work on
stuff that makes you happy iterate on
that and when you succeed then worry
about money it will come because if you
don't it'll leave you hollow believe you
mum sometimes you need to quit there's
been many situations through my career
where I've worried about a situation
with a client or with you know when I
worked for companies where I hated every
day I regretted waking up I regret it
going to the office I regretted having
to work with that person that I didn't
like that didn't understand me because
I'm special and then you quit it all
disappears everything can be great be
ambitious if I had followed through my
career the old adage of if you're not
good at something don't ever give it
away for free I don't you start on
amazing opportunities to meet people
have to work on projects and you know
particularly becoming like sort of
friends with my heroes
I've always believed that sort of going
from the gut that I'm doing the thing
that is the right thing to do and there
are times are out straight away from
that path for a project or a particular
job sometimes your money working
blissfully is really important and while
there are times that you're going to
have to suck it up and just do your job
those should be exceptions so if I had
any advice for me comments to our
industry or any creative pursuit I'd say
figure out what's important to you and
strive to get there and don't be afraid
to do what people will tell you stupid
because if I had done that I would never
build all these ridiculous things that
have actually done more for my career
and more for me enjoying working with
people and learning from people then I
had ever done in my commercial career if
I had just done the commercial thing I
don't know where what I'd be doing I
probably would have quit by now
completely asleep so believe in yourself
and trust yourself and you'll build
incredible things do work that makes you
feel good start an event promote good
work make friends encouraged them have a
really good time thank