my name is jason chen and I'm from San
Francisco California in the United
States and I most
for developer I don't actually work out
any company right now I i started my own
company two and a half years ago sold
that or three and a half years ago so
bad and then worked at worked at the
acquiring company for two years which
was salesforce.com and after leaving
that I just went to work on open-source
full-time the company that i started i
was i was the founder and i was a
software engineer so I took a lot of the
product along with my co-founder and the
company basically it was a collaborative
text editor of a code editor and so
people used it to do remote interviews
or any sort of code collaboration
remotely and at some point we wanted to
transition that that into rich text
which is what got me started what got me
started going with quill GS which is the
thing that I was talking about today
yeah it started it started at the
company that I started which ciebie on
and we continue to work on it because he
all source wanted to build that into
their product and so we continue to work
on it at Salesforce although not as much
and then after i left i continue to work
on quill and so when we still sail
source open source it under bsd so it's
very permissive license and they're
they're very supportive even when we
were there of a bus working on it and so
but i decided i kind of wanted to do
that more and things ended with the
project that we were working on at co
source as well yeah so yeah so
javascript is the editor that i'm
working on quill j/s is completely and
in JavaScript or I guess technically
it's in CoffeeScript and it compiles to
JavaScript Oh
or of it on kind of other parts of it
are in JavaScript but yeah it's
completely front only JavaScript library
well so our company was sold to
Salesforce so it's not really mine
anymore and I don't have much control
over it um I'm not sure what their plans
are for it I've kind of not been a part
of that for a while so I guess I don't
know okay yeah I'd like to start another
company i think currently i love working
on open source I've met amazing people
on it while working on it and I think
it's it's definitely something that I
wanted to I did I wanted to do and
didn't have much time to do before with
what kind of a for-profit profession and
so I'm enjoying that now I do think that
a goal of any good open source project
is where for one it should have goals
and once those goals are met it's not
like a product that you keep adding on
to it has a kind of a defined purpose
and at some point it'll meet up that
purpose and all you really need to do
after that is kind of make it faster or
make it smaller or just the fixed bug so
I'm not sure I see a lot to do in close
future before it gets to that point but
eventually it'll get to that point and
eventually I'd like to start another
company um yeah so this first time I
I've been in Argentina in Buenos Aires
my second time in Latin America on so I
don't know that much about it I do know
you got
have really good food I like I'm almost
a carnivore and that I eat a lot of meat
and I don't like vegetables so I was one
of those kids I had one of the best
meals in my life yesterday last for
dinner we're just ate like four five
hours the red meat was non-stop and wine
and that was that was amazing so I would
love to see Argentina and Buenos Aires
continue that I think JavaScript I i
I've actually been I've been surprised
by what I've been able to learn at this
conference like you know I guess I like
as someone that is speaking here I guess
I kind of feel like on average two
speakers know a little more than the
attendees but even I was learning a lot
and I think it's very JavaScript
basically I mean it's kind of it has an
unavoidably important future because I
mean it's what everyone it's the one
language that you can use on the front
end so I be very I was very excited
about kind of the things in es6 that was
being talked about and I think that
actually raised a lot of questions were
a lot of stuff like coffee script that I
was using another typescript etc there's
more questions about those types of
things but I think JavaScript
undoubtedly has a very important part in
what