okay so yeah Nicole said I'm Ryan sin
and you can find me on twitter i have a
blog called the CSS ninja calm i also
work on moderniser and i work for a
company in Australia I called seek which
is like a job search website so monster
com I think you guys I feel yes I hail
all the way from Melbourne Australia was
a long flight here 25 hours all up if
there's a one cool thing you need to
know about Melbourne is it was founded
by Batman that's a fact whether or not
it's the actual Batman is beyond the
point so you're posting checkboxes a
pretty boring you know usually just
agree to our Terms and Conditions
they've just go away that's because
maybe you are incorrect because oh
because when we use the check
pseudo-class we can get some awesome
stuff happening and that's it so that's
a custom check pork using check and it's
just putting up at animated gif from the
background so it's all powered by CSS
only it so essentially allows you to
create interaction with our JavaScript
so it gives you state to CCA so it gives
you an on state gives you an off state
and allows you to react to a user's
quick without having to do event
listeners with JavaScript so the first
thing you might think of is you can do
custom checkboxes and radios this is a
cool example that I took from a
developer that Leah talked about who did
those are 11 buttons he did a really
cool example of doing radio buttons
where has a shiny dot looks like it
travels through and then the further way
you click the faster it looks like it
moves and that's incredibly simple so
all is is just in the mark-up this is an
input and a label and what we do is we
kind of throw away the input and we just
use that for their it's checked ability
so whether it's checked or unchecked and
what we do is we style the actual label
and we do that by using the direct
sibling Combinator selector which is the
plus so it allows me to say
want to target a label this directly
followed by an input and so all those
Styles pick up and then we've got the
checked class on the input so I can say
well when the inputs checked I want to
target the label change ourselves on
that and then the little neat trick here
to get all the other labels and inputs
to react to make it look like that dots
flowing through the whole the whole list
of radio buttons you can use the general
civilian Combinator which is will target
any any sibling not the direct not just
the direct one and then that shiny dot
is just just a background image using
radial gradients I've haven't included
all the prefixes because otherwise it'll
be huge use border radius which we will
learn about and then the tricky irony is
just transitioning the background
position and then using a our cubic
Bezier curve to give it the illusion
that of speeding up the longer way it is
lever has got a really cool website
called cubic Bezier com which allows you
to visualize all those all those
animations it's really handy so I wrote
an article about this technique of doing
custom radios and checkboxes couple
years ago now so you can check out my
blog these slides would be up and off
the talk so you can check it out another
example is the tree menu have you ever
used a file system in a new computer you
can expand folders I'm sure you've all
used up before and that's so that's
using check boxes believe enough so it's
just an ordered list and then so they
can go infinitely deep and you can have
infinite amount of check boxes in the
CSS is relatively simple to accomplish
that so you once again have an input in
the label and you style the label to
have the plus or minus since got like
the folder name and then below that
you've got like children ordered list to
denote that is like a subtree of that
folded list so I've simplified CSS
soybeans fit in here so just picked out
the important bits so use the general
similan Combinator again to target all
ordered
this that our insider checked input and
we can set the height auto soda will
just expand to show all that all its
children we push it in to give the
illusion like it's you know below that
folder and it means a few after and
before generated content to add the icon
so the plus and minus depending of is
checked or unchecked and just using a
sprite and then all we do here is that
initially all this Titans display none
and then when you put checked they're
all block so just like expanding the
folder really simple stuff I wrote an
article about a two so they're going to
take it up so you know that's okay to be
boring so I i wrote a young thing called
bootleg dot CSS affection called the
dodgy version of bootstrap because I
took a whole bunch of bootstrap plugins
and made them say so silent using
checkboxes the first one is the drop
down so this is all I've just removed
all the JavaScript and just kept the
bootstrap CSS file so you can see now
I've made this red just so for visually
you can see what's going on but
essentially these dropdowns here if you
can see them they're just labels and
when I click that I check see the
checkbox that then shows the menu below
it and this red background is actually
another label that expands to the full
width of the window this is an iframe so
that's why it's not expanding the full
width so then I can click anywhere in
dismiss it so used to clicking somewhere
and I'll just click over here I don't
want that menu up anymore just to give
that interactivity and basically this
label targets another input that just
make sure is everything is closed and
it's a common sort of technique I use
throughout some of these other plugins
so the mark-up is exactly the same as
the the bootstrap example as is Bruce
trapped too I'm not sure of receptor has
changed yeah so you can see here of the
label is that drop-down button and then
it's just got the unordered list which
shows the menu items and then I've got
that label down here which when this
one's checked it expands to the full
width of the window so you can click
anywhere to dismiss it quite easily and
then just down the bottom this is the
input that our targets to make sure
everything's hidden saying any false
negatives and then the CSS is real easy
so initially for the dismiss I have a
display none but I have a whole bunch of
style set up to say its position fix and
it expands to the full container of the
window and then all I have down here is
on the input I say when that inputs
checked or so the radios checked I
display the drop-down menu in dismissing
set the display block and then all the
blue stripe styles take care of how
everything else looks there's a collapse
or accordion once again I've got there
the red showing there so you can see
where not when I activate one of them it
actually displays the label of the top
psyche and then just dismiss it keep
showing it and this also has a so has
like a top level collapse all radio
button that is targeted to make sure if
I have none of them checked and they're
all collapsed and you know in the odd
styling I've got the input up here for
each specific item that needs to be open
and closed and then I've got the label
here and I just use the for attribute to
make sure I can target it the reason the
input is not inside this accordion
header is because the limitations of
using CSS I can't work my way out of a
container after work my way down using
the general civilian Combinator or the
direction coming out of the plus all the
tilde and then so the CC is here so I
use a trick so you may have noticed that
I'm like this one's a different height
to the other ones but it's still
experienced to just be the height of the
content so you can use a trick of using
Mac's light rather than height so
originally I think near Safari 6 and the
latest chrome can transition from height
0 to high order before you can do that
another browsers can't so you can use
the trick or max height so initially
when it's not checked it's got max 50
the height you set to auto we set up the
transition when it's checked
set the height to 500 so it may not be
500 a might be like 100 pixels and then
we'll just expand to its container then
you get some of your timing issues
because it's doing max Heights trying to
calculate it so when it's when it's
collapsing it will collapse over 200
milliseconds and then I adjust the
duration here to say it's over seven
hundred milliseconds so they sort of
look like they're happening at the same
time but you still get some odd behavior
we've got some tabs this is where you
start get to the ugly side of this this
hack and you have to have specific
marker placement and the CSS selectors
get really nasty so the mark up here we
have to have each top-level tab item has
to be input label can't be inside any
sort of ordered list or unordered list
because there'd selector restriction and
then each container is shown and so let
me get huge selectors like this because
of their constraints so I need to target
the first input and I do enth of type
and not into child because we've got
input label input label if i did a child
and it'll get the wrong item so you make
sure that it's an input and it's the
first one and if it's checked then we
find the tab content sibling and then we
look inside that and we find the first
deaf so everyone so when the first one's
checked we wanted to show you the first
content and vice versa when a son check
that's them displaying on modals that's
cool so you get the same same transition
you've got it fades in the background
pops down I've made a background red so
you can see see it fading a bit better I
can click there dismiss it I can click
the cross so like tan all behavior that
you used to with the bootstrap Murray so
yeah the that label is styled to look
like a button but really it's a label
we've got the input and then you've got
the modal container so these need to be
at sibling level so in order for me to
go when he puts check toggle that modal
and show it and do the animations and
then we use
the clothes modal input to do the
overlay so when the when you've launched
a mogul we use the red background I saw
was a just a label that's expanded to
the full width of the window and so
that's used to close it and and as the
transparent background that you get that
used to seeing with modal's and the CSS
is is really easy so you've got there
using the General Assembly Combinator
the target the mobile in cases any
elements in between the input and actual
motor container this is just an initial
Stiles to get it set up we use we
transition the transform over a period
of time when we do the opacity as well
and then to get it out of you initially
we just set its initial translate value
to be one hundred percent out of the
viewport so it's sitting up out of the
window you can't see it anywhere just
checked what we want to do to get that
same effect of the background fades in
and then then the thing slides downs we
just want to stick we just adjust the
transition delay to not not do that
transition for 400 milliseconds while
the other things fading in so you can
see on the on the modal close input with
in transition the opacity then and so
when it's checked the opacity is changed
you could always use a rgba as well you
don't have to use a pacity and then we
just make sure there's no delay I want
to check and I need to make sure that
it's not actually the clothes modal
because then you will get confusion
where when the clothes input is checked
then we'll get we'll try to target the
label below it and we'll get in a red
state so we just use not selector say
well if if the input is not closed modal
that's currently checked so we want to
make sure that when they launched the
modal we don't get any weird behavior
then then target the modal clothes label
and display it there's a image carousel
as well it's just nice and you may
notice some similarities between this
and the slide deck so it's like going on
this so I got to be carried away with
this talk I go call it in the meta
process
of a deep as always I get caught up in
the meta process of creating slides and
they ended up creating a check box
powered slide for my check box talk so
and I and I called it book I've
always liked that name so the carousel
and slide show Bob have very much and
very similar in how they work so we'll
jump to the editor so I just push this
to github the slideshow book but
basically it is it is just a bunch of
classes here and then I use SAS because
there's some some crazy selectors going
on there and be like you're just not my
brain trying to work out all the math
because it needs to know how many slides
you have to calculate where it's best to
transform the slide as you transition
between each slot so I've got this mix
in that loops over a variable so good a
variable slow count so you know demo one
there's 11 slides I'll then loop over
that and we'll work out all the
calculation and he seduces lots of um
working out well if it's this slide
number they need to divide it by 100 and
work out the percentage that needs to do
based on this light count and SAS made
it really easy let's go a nice build
process so I just run grunt and will
generate based on this load count the
CSS file so the output here you can see
first scroll down you can see it's
putting out all these crazy selectors to
work out when it needs to show the left
and right button when it needs to flip
it based on which cat you're on so like
initially you've got the second label
that sits on the right side and then
when I go to the second one then it
suddenly needs to position on the left
side and you need a third one there
there's a lot going on so SAS makes this
a lot easier and I don't have to worry
about working out or the the
calculations you can see like the
default decimal places percentage it
gets gets a little out of hand so sets
makes it it's usually much easier
process
so quirks and bug so it's not all some
sunshine lollipops in chat box world so
for a while there WebKit couldn't handle
checked and the general signaling
Combinator that's being fixed down and
Safari 5.1 and chrome 13 we're up to
like chrome 900 now I think so yeah
that's like a long-gone thing but if you
have to support older browsers
especialista fire which is I up to six
it wouldn't actually activate the style
so if you initially had the checked
attribute on input it would pick up
these styles but if you wants you as a
user you checked another tech box it
wouldn't actually pick it up so that was
a big issue so it would work with a
directive in Combinator but that
restricted you to the position of a
container that input should alter when
you check it any of the kenai people
there may have noticed I had a lot of on
click empty attributes on the labels
this is there because of an issue in iOS
5 where a label click click on a label
wouldn't actually check the checkbox and
I figured out somehow that I'm putting
an empty on click on there would
actually give it a kick up the ass and
tell to check the checkbox that was a
really known bug bears good to find a
solution to that but then you get there
because of a click event has a throwing
a millisecond delay you get that issue
where it can be a bit slow when it
checks on RS 5 it's been fixed and I or
six which is good downsides it is a huge
hack there's no denying that there's
accessibility issues so i talked to a
good friend jason kiss who's based in
new zealand is on very good
accessibility expert no just wanting to
review and confirm my beliefs that this
is horrible if you have screen reader
users and you confirmed that it was
horrible
because the problem is that a label
can't have a role attribute to make it
appear as like a button it's an invalid
thing so a label cannot ever be a button
so like the pad the modal with a label
styled like a button a screen reader
would see a label and black what the
hell's going on you've got no way of
switching switching so you put the Aria
attributes of like Aria hidden equals
true and then when you switch to display
some you can't programmatically change
attributes and CSS that's where you need
JavaScript so thorough downfalls there
sometimes requires specific places of
markup and by sometimes I mean all the
time so you need you've got that
restriction of that it's only siblings
the sibling combinator so they need to
be on the same level so like would i
share with tabs you get that sort of
ugly placement of markup and you get the
crazy CSS selectors to gso you get
overly complex electives using the plus
until the which son can hope your head
when you need to manually work them out
so browser support look at the browser
ponies here pretty cool so basically
basically means that they support
checked fancy is like Renault Sport
transitions and all the other nice stuff
to done makes it nicer to look at so now
least you there I 9 didn't support
transitions it was the first one to
support checked before that I didn't
support it I 10 introduced the
transitions animations so you can get
the nice effects going on here and
otherwise it's pretty safe to do a hack
around with it so the future maybe so
that is a spec roller who works with
google called tab Atkins who on his blog
blog wrote a proposal on there for being
able to toggle any element they
introduce these properties as four of
them and I've got to hear called toggle
dash star so toggle states toggle share
so going back to that modal example
on that modal I can say well this models
got two states it's other hidden or
displayed the idea is this is well you
can have more than two states so you can
just keep cycling through and have you
know as many states as you need and then
and then I can use that checked pseudo
class on any element so I doesn't have
to be an input and I can react to when
when the state changes and then using
the toggle share which is which works
the same way as a for attribute on a
label so I can associate toggling of
state with no element I can just say
well on this model Moodle button pass in
a simple CSS selector saying well you've
got it you can alter the toggle state of
that element and then you can avoid
those crazy selectors that you saw makes
it much easier but at the moment it's
just a blog post on his personal blog
then who knows if you actually get to
look at it and propose it and if people
who accept it but I think that would be
cool if we could have that rather than
using checkboxes and radios to hack it
that's it slides bootleg and slideshow
blogroll up and get up check it out from