123456 yeah okay right here me yeah yes
now sweet okay great for those of you
that are here to listen to the talk
encouraging move as close as you can to
the front i'm going to doing a lot of
coding examples and it's going to be
very different it may be very difficult
for you to see towards the back so it's
up to you as far as where you sit out so
welcome what I won't be covering today
is internationalization as well as a
localization because one without the
other kind of the purpose is defeated
and my name is Ben I'm a developer
advocate for IBM bluemix which is a
platform as a service similar to as your
Roku what have you but has some unique
offerings and services that kind of
separate it but it does have a lot of
the same runtimes containers virtual
machines etc that you're going to get
you know with most any platform as a
service so what are we talking about
today is internationalization which has
a short acronym I think may be 4i 18 and
excuse me so internationalization is the
process of developing products in such a
way that they can be localized for
languages and cultural cultures easily
for application developers which is most
likely everyone here in the room
internationalizing an application means
it's dragging all the strings and other
local specific bits such as date or
currency format out of the application
and so i'll just open up a browser here
head to amazon and to give you an
example what this would look like is
stay at amazon okay you'll see here that
as you check out the page and click on a
cyber monday deal and we'll check out
this really sweet racer so this is
delivered in English which is probably
the most common language but what if
someone in the Czech Republic was
looking at this and I wanted to see this
web page and
Jack what a application developer at
amazon would do is would go through let
me blow this up a little bit make a
little bit easier to see and they would
take all the text so such as this title
right here the currency here this
information that's right here and
everything all throughout as well as
numbers for quantity things like 2.5 if
you most a lot of language especially
European languages why have a comma
instead of a decimal point in that place
and so you'd abstract all of those
snippets of text strings and numbers and
then process them based upon the
language that was requested along with
the web page a bad thing to do and if
you want to get really really difficult
when it comes to application development
you want to embed text inside of images
and you want to be friendly to
international crowd or multiple
languages especially if for example if
you're developing applications from
Americans then you're pretty much set
you know English period you're done but
if you're developing for example in
Europe in which for example I was
talking to a developer from Belgium and
he was required develop language is
excuse me applications with Dutch French
and English and if you think about the
size of Belgium you know it's like
smaller than the size of Florida and so
and that doesn't include Spain for
spanish and italian and german and all
other languages that are within just a
couple hundred mile radius and so if
you're an application developer in
europe or something like that you really
have to keep this in mind and by
embedding text in an image that makes it
a poor user experience which we'll get
into a little bit later but
internationalisation would be grabbing
out these snippets right here that can
or should be translated so that way your
user can understand them in their native
language and culture so localization
which has an acronym of l10n is a
process of adapting applications and
text to enable their usability in a
particular cultural
linguistic market and localizing an
application means providing translations
and localized formats for those
abstracted bits so I'm going to give you
an example of what this looks like and
this is also using the library that I'm
going to do some examples in today so
format jas this was created and released
open source by yahoo and what this does
is let me see if i can blow this up
there's a very simple example in the
front that will kind of drive this
message home so let's say that you've
got a social media website and someone
shares that they've taken a thousand
photos on December fast 2015 well let's
say that somebody from let's go with
France visits that social media page and
that social media site of that
application wants to deliver that
content and a localized friendly version
for that user so if i switch to France
you see not only does the language
change but also for example the way that
the date right here is delivered in
English would be December fifth 2015
whereas in French the day is delivered
before the month and then a year and
then also you'll see here for 1,000
instead of having a comma and French
there's actually a space and let's look
at a different languages go of Japanese
I don't really know what to tell you
here but I imagine you into the
differences there if i look at
portuguese or Brazil you can see that
there can be quite a difference here
when it comes to the date and then for
the number right here in this case 1000
it's actually got a period so this can
become very complex if let's say you're
working on a product such as Google or
something like that and you want to be
friendly to as many languages as
possible because your product is can be
you know launched into multiple
different areas then this is really
important this can be also enormously
cumbersome if let's say you've got
hundreds or thousands of pages in order
to do this with doing custom strings
which is one way
doing this per page if i go to my amazon
if you can imagine doing a custom string
entry for each of these snippets right
here you'd go absolutely crazy and so
therefore having a tool that can help
you do this yahoo created this format
jsin and they open sourced it for our
benefit so that makes it a lot easier in
order for you to do that so in xmas
script internationalization was added to
spec in december of 2012 so built right
into the native JavaScript without using
any framework library what have you you
can by grabbing the language of the
browser so if you've got a computer open
if you just go to the web console see if
I can blew this up yeah I'll clear this
out if you type it's under the window
object so you can type window if you
want to but navigator dot language for
WebKit and what you get is in this case
English us because my browser is set up
for English us and so we can do with
JavaScript as you can grab that and then
whenever you want to format a date or a
number or what have you then ekman
script can grab your day to your number
what have you and then process it based
on this spec right here which is blown
up here let me see if I can find an
example here unfortunately xmas script
their spec just provides like a lot of
theory but it doesn't like ever really
have like a code example and I can make
it really difficult to I don't know if
there's any people on the committee here
but hint hint if you can kirkland if you
can throw us a bone somehow and so
instead of having to read through all of
this I forget where you can see the size
of this document is enormous but that
there are methods I'm sorry I can't find
them right here but what there are
methods in which you can translate a
like a date or a number what have you
very easily without using a third-party
library in order to do that but there is
an issue unfortunately with the
compatibility of this because well I
guess you can see if you're welcome let
me open the actual source page so on can
i use you can see in the
internationalization api that is from
2012 you can see some glaring holes here
in an explorer it depends on what you're
supporting but for anything explorer 8 9
and 10 it's not supported at all you can
see here looks like we've only got one
percent one percent one percent but this
is the big hole right here which is
safari in iOS safari so we've got here
not an enormous amount I OS Safari
number one's got five percent but
depending upon your market especially if
you're going to which developers a lot
of developers use Apple and so far it
might be a browser to use most
especially for iPhones that's enormous
mobile views I think crested already
fifty percent of web page views out
there and so depending upon the product
that you're creating the fewer creating
a web app that needs to be
internationalized and localized for the
people that are viewing it and you're
relying on that native support this is
missing from these browsers I have no
idea why a standard from three almost
four years ago has not has not been
implemented in these browsers chrome
though and Firefox as well as the latest
version being explored to support that
so you do have that caveat to work with
so the importance of
internationalization we've shown you a
little bit of an example here with
Amazon but partial or complete exclusion
internationalisation severely affects
your users experience with the product
and I'll give you an example right here
this is trenitalia which is a train
service in Italy I was there about a
month two ago and this is the train
service that goes all throughout Italy
and what you can see here is that you
see here that's a really nice feature
out if you saw that bar down I get to
that but
let's say that you've got someone from
Germany that wants to take a train in
Italy if this site did not offer
translations then options could be
incredibly limited now you can use
something like babelfish so if you go to
you know google translator babelfish and
insert the web page that way then you
can see the translation but as you
progress through the checkout as you
progress few pages then you start having
issues with cookies and other things
like that for session persistence and so
you can get all the way through to a
purchase page and then because of the
way that the web page is kind being
rendered inside of babelfish or google
translate or what have you it's just not
a situation to work unless you just have
a text page and also too I could pointed
out all of these images right here like
you can see up here I've got a drop down
here at italiano if i go to french the
image is let me go to english here the
images in this case this is a surprise
to me this wasn't working this wasn't
the case yesterday but in in this case
the image is with the text that is
flattened right into the image changes
if that is not the case then even though
you might have text that is translated
having an image with text and it isn't
translated can result in a lot of
bounces and people not being able to use
your product at all there is a option
here mate see if I can get to pop up
again the hopefully I can see this in
google chrome this is a great option
where you can translate a page
especially if you're visiting pages for
example government pages are terrible at
this like I was visiting a page for the
United Arab Emirates which is an Arabic
and they don't have a natural
translation so without this I would've
been really really up a creek and what
google chrome does is recognizes the
language that my browser uses which in
this case is english and then allows me
to translate right here within the page
all the text strings that it recognizes
and it will also properly translate
dates numbers things like that
currencies for me and it does that right
within the browser
this is an enormous tool this is not
something that's available in other
browsers but it's a great tool that is
available you shouldn't rely upon it but
this is something that will allow you to
do that exclusion of
internationalisation makes your product
inaccessible to non locale users this is
an Israeli news website and so you can
see right here notice something when it
comes to internationalization this is
important for CSS and page layout Hebrew
is a right-to-left text so is Arabic
Farsi etc whereas English German French
Italian etc is left to right and so when
you're developing your product getting
the user agents language should change
the CSS that you deliver the page format
to deliver and as well as the text as
well this topic is absolutely enormous
and I can't get it give an example of
every thing to consider but in this page
you can see there's no option anywhere
and someone can read Hebrew and pointed
out to me then please do but you can see
that there is no option to change
languages here and so if you're reading
a story for example last year in july i
was planning to travel to israel my trip
got canceled because of rocket fire and
as i'm trying to find out information
up-to-date information on the security
situation there these are the kind of
websites that i had to deal with and
thankfully with google chrome like gives
me an option here is the text of the
pages in hebrew no translated for me so
i can get the information that I need
but you also see from a user experience
standpoint this is a line right to left
and so this may not be an issue with you
know let's click on this page right here
this may not be an issue with just a
snippet of text and you can also to see
as I transition pages open there we go
great you can see here this creates a
readability if I'm reading this from an
english-language perspective having it
go from left from right to left is going
to create issues for me tracking line by
line as I go down and so there are
important things to keep in mind and
consider as you're trying to make your
website compile
for those users so what I'm going to
focus on for the remainder of this time
is implementing format jas I'm going to
try and say its framework and tool
agnostic as possible as I deliver this
information because that because you
depend upon your stack you might be
using ember Jas or angular what have you
for front-end templating might be using
dusty is on the back end for back end
templates or maybe you're super cool and
you're using ember on the front end and
the back end or you're using react with
having the front or back end but the
principles shouldn't matter the basic
steps when it comes to
internationalization is that first you
extract the text snippets that required
translation via some templating tool so
I created a very simple page looks like
this in which I have a date time number
percentage and currency these are common
things that are going to change based
upon someone's locale and the format
it's not just necessarily going to be a
translation of that text from like
December to dissent bruh you know for
French it's going to be also the change
in the way in which the date you know
the day is going to go before the month
format and I'm going to pull up my code
here and I hope everyone can see it in
my page here for internationalization
the first step is that I'm grabbing in
this case i'm using handlebars which is
like a very bare-bones basic very
similar mustache j/s templates and it
grabs the information here that I want
to translate and based upon the users
language it will translate it for me so
I've got all the fields right here which
will go back to the browser I've got my
fields right here and I'm going to
extract those out to some sort of
templating in order to make them
available for translation to use for
some service
the next step is to set up detection for
the script for the users language and so
down here you can see I'm doing this on
the front end to begin with and so this
is can be this is pretty simple to do
detector you don't have to worry about
like grabbing HTML headers what have you
the accept language parameter and I HTML
header will tell you what the language
is going to be and I'm going to detect
that and grab that into a variable so
that way as I'm processing through my
data down here I grab it for the correct
language and then when it comes to pull
my server file right here when it comes
to doing it on server side than that can
be grabbed in your request header so I'm
using Express here but to the request
the header and they makes the accept
language header that comes across will
tell you what languages are accepted by
or desire to be accepted by that website
and then for each request you want to
process and deliver the correct
localized strings based on the user's
language and so to walk through this
well first what I'll do is show you the
format JS website they did a really nice
job of putting this together it's always
nice when the website for a framer put
some aesthetically pleasing stuff
together but perform at jas there are
four integrations that they have done
automatically for you that makes it easy
if you use one of these languages to
pick it up dust Jas is from LinkedIn and
this would be all server-side rendering
to my knowledge it is talk here about
browser base and I have never used is
anyone here used us Jess in the browser
okay does it exist in a browser now or
has it always oh wow okay I'm sorry I
have always always used it on the server
side so there you go cool there's
handlebars which is most naturally
designed for in the browser but it can
also be rendered runtime and sir
ambridge is as well as react our
libraries that can run on server and
front end I would recommend front end it
can get to be kind of tricky depending
upon your implementation but if you are
doing server-side rendering every time
that you're going to change a language
you've got to resubmit the website to
the server have it process and return it
in pen upon somebody's connection
especially in developing areas for
example like India where the bandwidth
is severely choked by the factors of
billion people you're not a billion but
roughly about half a billion that are
trying to access the internet that can
take three four five seconds per page
you can also persist it if you're really
awesome of the cookie a token or
something like that that every time it
submits that it will recognize hey this
user wants french or something like that
but front end is going to be much
quicker in order for you just to change
the strings that are on there instead of
reprocessing the parcel processing page
on the back so with using handlebars how
many people have used handlebars in here
okay great so it's a very very very
simple format here would be right here
an example of that is using two curly
braces on each side and then having some
denotation of the variable in this case
it says price but there's also some
other parameters in here such as format
number which is going to tell our
library you can see it right here oops
now there we go right there to format a
number for us and then we want to add
currency to that so this is not just a
number but this is gonna be the price of
something and then the currency to put
that into and then we have our
information that handlebars is going to
use to render it so in this case I
locale is going to be us the context for
our template the price variable right
here is going to be one thousand dollars
and then this is going to be the
built-in handlebars method of template
and which it's going to accept a
parameter for a argument for our context
which is our data right here and then it
processes it with this international
plug-in which if you come
right here you see you will import
handlebars onto your page and then add
the internationalization special sauce
on top of that for you to render it and
then if you decide to do front end only
then you need to import the language in
this case French which I built my app
using English and French so you can
include you know five ten fifteen
what-have-you languages the great part
about doing this server side if you
decide to do that is as it says here in
nodejs the NPM package the data for all
150 plus languages is preloaded and does
not need to be loaded manually so that
can add a lot of overhead if you do in a
site like Google you know which is going
to have you know pretty much every
language available in it then front end
would likely not be the way to go on
that you could possibly include like the
top 10 languages and if that doesn't
work then you can do an AJAX call to
grab that script library from the server
and then bring it back depends on how
you want to do that so once I grab that
information here I'm a page and they
pull this up right here so I've got my
handlebars library my international
library and then I imported the French
library to show that to show the
different language support and then let
me on come on comment this there's a
polyfill called international Jas that
is necessary for Safari support so if
you're going to use this even if you're
using handlebars this library right here
you're going to need to include this for
Safari the north of that polyfill to
work there's anyone here that works for
apple or Safari then please a close that
hole for us and then I just included
jquery here this is not a requirement
but I just included for the sake of
making it easier to do Dom manipulation
as we're doing this so as my script run
so what I need to load all these scripts
ahead of time prior to execution of my
code I need to make sure that with
handlebars that I am registering this
international library so that way it
when it's processing those templates
it's
these things like formatted date
formatted time you can see here my
variable that I'm going to grab for my
JSON document is right here is a daytime
number percentage price etc that it what
needs to know to pick up what these
things are and then also these
parameters in passing like day month
year etc there's tons of different
apotheke can use to customize your page
to how you want it to look and so once I
registered that I threw in a document
ready function which waits for the whole
page to be loaded and then it grabs our
language which actually this is a
navigator is not on the top view it's
actually window got navigator but you
can just go with navigator works anyways
and then I've got to fall back here a
logic check that if my I'm only
supporting English and French in this
case and if it does not return navigator
language either returns undefined or
doesn't have English or French there I'm
going to deliver them English because
it's going to be most popular now here
what you can do all you can do also be a
smarter idea from user experiences have
a pop-up that says would you like to use
babelfish google translate or have some
other options that way your user isn't
stuck with that language and then a
firing off a function that I created
down here with the browser language that
was detected and so I'm going to grab my
handlebars content which if you're not
familiar with handlebars seems that most
people are handlebars execute in a
script tag that has this specific type
attached to a text /x / handlebars
/template and so if it's not within
there whenever this renders all of this
is going to be rendered as HTML and it's
not going to be able to be read by
handlebars after your commitment now a
lot of you probably used angular or eve
used whatever it's called ember and that
has automatic tag detection both
handlebars that is not the case and so
I'm going to grab that I'm a compiler
which which this does is this
this into the handlebar library and it
grabs the snippet tags that it needs in
this case my locality and from the
language imma grab is right from up here
and the Navigator language and then
here's my contacts on this page let's
say this was the information on a
product in a product catalog I've got
the price how many we've got in stock
maybe the percentage of you know sales
versus not something like that and then
the date and the time stamp to show the
difference when it comes to the
different language formats and then I'm
going to use the native method for our
handlebar as a template dropping that
data that I just showed you and I'm
going to replace it with the HTML this
is a well I'm gonna take the rendered
HTML that handlebars gave me and drop it
in this is definitely a no-no when it
comes to replacing nodes so like you
read in a node you you know edited and
you override it this can throw you all
sorts of issues but I'm just for the
sake of the simplicity in chianti that's
what it would look like so once I've got
all of that done I've also got two
buttons up here that allow me can seem
right here that I can manually change
the locale from US English and French if
I'd like to so once I load that up right
here so you can see this is probably
familiar to everyone here in the room
date time number percentage and currency
are all the way that we naturally would
think what am I click on the French
button what this will do is it will
nicely translate this not only in this
case will actually translate the name of
the month but will also translate the
format in which the date should be
you'll notice that the date here for
this number is actually day first not
month first like it would be in English
for the number this 47 thousands of
space now and their percentage is pretty
much the same the I think in English it
will be out of percentage be right there
in French I guess there's a space and
then for currency there's a space in
between right there and
I guess they add on the scent right
there with a comma and the US currency
which in the English language that
currency would go ahead of it right
there and so this is incredibly useful
if you're doing a shopping website or
something like that that's got thousands
of different products this will do that
for you and then also within here I'll
show you to the API here you can also do
more powerful things such as for example
yesterday today etc switches to French
and this will also translate common text
this does not include entire French
dictionary and it or you've got other
options here of like Japanese or
Portuguese for Brazil that includes
common phrases such as yesterday
December etc for you to use and then any
strings such as here my Amazon website
my product information about my
fisher-price Power Wheels Dune Racer
this would need to be text that you
manually insert or translate for you but
format Jas is a great job and I'll
scroll down here to give you an example
this allows a pluralization with text so
in this case we've got Annie took 1000
photos on December fifth and if I
translate this to French you'll see that
it will translate this string of text
for me and what it does is it correctly
puts because each language is going to
have you know sometimes noun before the
verb and set a verb before the noun or
they're going to have different ways on
how they affect nouns pronouns
descriptive adjectives and what this
will do is this will do this for you can
see you can kind of get this is the
language in which would look like so
this can get a bit tricky when it comes
to coding this in but this is a library
that can help you do some simple text
translations right there without having
to use any like third-party translation
at all I don't if you're on a government
website or health care or something that
the details are incredibly important and
I wouldn't rely on something like this
but if the details are not
you know depend upon something very
important than this is a service that
you can use and like here's another
example right here with more complex
trend transformation right here and it
does a very very good job of those
things the probably best way of using
this is a front and manipulation with
back-end rendering in the case of having
a site that's got multiple different
languages and needs to support so there
is a server-side version of this which
it's pretty simple in order to implement
this I've chosen to in this case you
musn't nodejs and we have our handlebars
library which this is the same front-end
library that you'd see on the browser
side page and this is the handlebars
international library and the code is
going to be pretty similar as well and
then I'm including the file system a
module in order to read in a file here
so whenever I launch up the server and
go to the root directory what I'm going
to do here this is important this is how
I'm going to detect the language because
I'm not this code is not running in
someone's browser and some I need to
grab that out of the header that is sent
to see what language and so if I i'm
just going to comment this out just to
show you OOP I'll just grab this right
here if you just see what this looks
like when it gets spit out
how is this 36 36 oh there we go okay
great I'm going to localhost and then
want to do that you probably can't see
very well all we can see right here
english-to-english us which is being
sent from my browser is sent and that
request header and then the more simple
version of that distinguish because
there's English Great Britain English us
etc that will have different ways of
pronouncing for example color see olor
in great britain english is co l oh you
are and so that can make some difference
in some cases and so once i grab that i
can then just run if you're basically
the same code that i did before so i'm
using a file system here to grab my
server file now this is also this is not
built with scalability in mind it's just
a simple example but what I'll do here
is grab the HTML from my server file
right here so here's my HTML file and I
pulled out all that JavaScript that I
was at the bottom if I pull up browser
at JS to see all this logic and from and
script tags are here I'm just pulling
all this out and doing its server side
and you see that's missing there and
then I'm able to just basically take the
same exact JavaScript and run it through
here and then just send that result so I
read in HTML and sent it back in a
response and then it will have the
updated information there I didn't have
time to add in an option to change the
language manually like I showed you on
that button if I pull that up right here
to go back and forth like this and
obviously this is not scalable you'd
have to write this for each individual
page but whenever that is run then it
will spit out the same information
without having any logic on the front
end so close that up we've got to like
three minutes left I encourage you to
check out if you got
your laptop open check out format jes
and kind of click around you can see the
integrations they did a really really
good job and this is a supported by
yahoo and so you've got a strong
professional development team behind
this and you also know that's been
tested is yahoo's in like 170 countries
and so you know that they've tested it
well and this can be a really quick way
for you to in this case creating some
rack components that will then spit out
in this case the currency back to you
you can implement this in probably 10 15
minutes for just a basic page and then
you can make your site very quickly
international affirming that can make an
enormous difference when it comes to
user experience and something i didn't
harp on too much when it comes to
accessibility is that we should be
designing for a web that's inclusive and
if you don't have internationalization
even the most basic support of it then
there are users that you are excluding
from using your product or service that
otherwise in this case can be done quite
easily depending upon the framework or
tool that you use so that's just about
it i'll be up here for the next session
starts in like five minutes i'll be
around here if you have any questions
anything thanks for coming hope you
learned a lot and have a great