Hello everyone
Why can't the slide show come out?
This is my first time in Singapore
Feel good
It would be better if you applaud now
I came to this meeting as soon as I got off the plane, so I did n’t have time to stroll
But I will stay a few more days later, I will look around
I brought my partner
I must say it was a huge mistake
Because she was really looking forward to the trip, especially the first few weeks
She ’s been saying that she has two weeks to go to Singapore, one week, five days
Could you please stop mentioning it
What I thought was that there were only five days to prepare my speech
This worst project manager has been mocking me for being poorly prepared
But one thing she is very good is that she can tolerate me
I am easily anxious. I will worry about it
I feel anxious about things that have nothing to do with me
Someone posted this on Twitter
He held the MacBook with two fingers
And it's on the concrete floor, I never fell asleep after watching this photo
This code also annoys me because there is no semicolon. Roar if you remember to always add a semicolon
Good, the rest are a bunch of monsters
But this is not the thing I worry about the most
But add something to the DOM and hide it, maybe wait until there is a click event and then show it
I would worry if the user would see something flash before the element was hidden
And I can't reproduce it so far
I have n’t met before, but it ’s hard to say under race conditions
So I usually reorder these codes, just to sleep
But in fact there is no race condition here
Because the code runs and renders
Their timing is tightly defined
And most of the cases are ok
This is thanks to the event loop, the next 30 minutes, if I do n’t mess up
You will know why the code works like this. I'm not sure if I can make it clear, I don't make a promise
There is something in the web page, usually we become the main thread
This is the main thread
The main thread is called because many things run on it, including JavaScript and rendering, and is where the DOM exists.
This means that most things on the webpage have a certain order
No code will execute at the same time, such as editing the same DOM at the same time
Then leads to terrible race conditions
But it also means that if the main thread has code running for a long time
200 milliseconds
Long time for user interaction
In this case, it is perceived because it blocks many other things, such as rendering or user interaction.
And I think it ’s hard to imagine this as a human
Because human
Very good at multi-threaded operation
For example, I can stand on one foot while waving
I'm talking, breathing, processing sound and visual information
Humans don't have a main thread and we are not blocked by irrelevant things
Except one thing
That is sneezing
Because other things stop when you sneeze. Such as not speaking when sneezing
Then the face becomes silly X
If you were driving, you would hope that no one would die as a result.
At least we become single-threaded when we sneeze
Loss of hearing, vision or thinking
Unless sneezing forces you to do so. You have actually lost control
Then the sneeze will end and the body will recover
You will know if there are fewer arms and legs
Are there missing passengers? Obviously we don't want to write the same code as sneezing
So although we have the main thread, we still want to start some other scenes
For network or codec
Or listen to the input device
But once these threads have done something the page cares about
They need to transfer information back to the main thread
The event loop is actually directing it all
For example, setTimeout, isn't this naming good? indeed. Is the order of the parameters wrong?
I think so. But have you ever wondered how it works
Okay, let's write a web standard for him, I'll do it these days
We start with setTimeout. When it is called, we need to perform these steps: wait for x ms and execute the callback.
But this doesn't work
Because it means that it will execute on the same thread as the method that called it
This is also JavaScript, so it will be executed in the main thread
For example, waiting for 5000ms, we wait on the main thread, which will block many other things
So this specification is not working yet
So change it. This way we perform these steps in parallel
That is to detach from the main thread and run at the same time as other things
This has new problems, because we are now executing callbacks from a non-main thread
Does not work at all
Finally, there may be a lot of JS code editing the same DOM at the same time
There will be many race conditions
So we put the task in the queue and then return to the main thread for execution
Now we are calling JS in the JS thread
This is how the browser works at its core
If you click the mouse, how is it handed over from the operating system to JS? It submits tasks in the queue
If it is a fetch request, how does it hand the response to JS?
It is still submitting a task. You send a message to the worker from the page and still submit a task
So regarding the event loop, I want to talk about the task queue first.
I find visual animation easier to understand than the specification
This is it, I hope I have made the problem clear
I really hope the question is clear, because my whole speech is based on this diagram
If there is nothing to do, the event loop will always idle in a CPU economical way,
This animation runs at 100% of real time
It ’s still too fast. To see clearly, let ’s slow down a bit.
After we submitted a task, the event loop went around in a circle. This is where the mission takes place
Here the browser says about the event loop
There is something for you
The event loop is great. Then add it to the to-do list. Will deal with it later
What if we submit two callbacks with setTimeout
We want to run in 1 second. According to the specification, we made clear that the two algorithms will be parallel
1000ms each wait
Then add tasks to the queue and return to the main thread
The browser said to the event loop, I have something here
But actually there are two things please, so each thing is added to the queue as a todo item.
The event loop indicates no problem, so it runs the first callback first
Then run the second
This is the task
If that's all simple
It becomes complicated if you add rendering.
The browser will use the rendering to update the screen content
The rendering step takes another circle, which contains style calculations. Which is to view all CSS
Calculate styles applied to all elements
It generates a render tree
Will calculate the position of the element
Then generate corresponding pixels
So at some point, the browser will tell the event loop
Need to update screen content. The event loop says I'll do it the next time I go to the event loop
I don't understand you but i
I consider myself an expert at writing bad code
I can make an endless loop with just a bit of code
Let's see what happens if that is the case
This page has a gif and text, a big button that runs an endless loop
If i click
Everything stopped, there was no way to select the text, and the entire tab was dead
The code is simple
How to visualize this process? After the user clicks the button
The browser tells the event loop that I have a task for you. Event loop says no problem, let me do it
But this task can never be completed
Always running JS
After a few milliseconds, the browser tells the event loop
We are going to update the gif
Remember to render the next time you are convenient. The event loop says: Uh ...
I'll talk about things when I'm busy
Then the user wants to select some text, it will contain click test
Look at the DOM and more. So the browser will say
I still have some to-do things for you
The event loop will say, do you know how long it takes to execute an infinite loop
Takes a long time as the name suggests
This is why the while loop blocks rendering and other interactions, but it is a good thing
Let's take a look at the previous concerns. I worry that something will pass by.
But it doesn't actually happen
Because this code is part of a task
So it must be fully executed before rendering
The event loop will ensure that the task is completed before rendering
However, I still have pressure, and I will still interact with each other when I see such code.
Well, while loops block rendering, what about this?
This is a loop, but every time we insert tasks into the queue through setTimeout
Let's see what happens
I clicked the button, as if the page was still working, as if nothing had changed, but behind the scenes, these things happened
Add tasks to the queue
Check the event loop
Extract the task, then submit another task, and repeat it forever
But we have seen before
Can only perform one task at a time
So when one task is completed, you must make a full circle to execute the next one.
So the browser can update the gif display at some point
This is why the setTimeout loop does not block rendering
But if the code you want to execute is related to rendering
Then it ’s not suitable for tasks, as far as the event loop is concerned
Task execution and rendering are not on the same side
We want to execute the code in the rendering step
The browser provides us with the requestAnimationFrame function to implement
I think this function name sucks too
RAF callbacks are executed as part of the rendering step and I will explain the benefits of doing so
I will make a box animation
I want to move the box one pixel at a time by using requestAnimationFrame
To create a loop
That's it if we replace requestAnimationFrame with setTimeout?
Looks like this
The box is moving faster now
About 3.5 times, which means that callbacks are executed more frequently. This is definitely not good
By no means good
Earlier we saw that rendering can be inserted between tasks and executed
But what can happen does not necessarily mean it will happen. We extract a task
Can it be rendered now, no? Can we make another round? Can we render now?
Still can't do many tasks can keep coming in
Until the browser can finally say
Next time I want to update the display
The browser can decide when to render, and its goal is to be as efficient as possible
Only render when necessary, if there is no interface change, it will not render
For example, when the tab is blocked and invisible, it will not be rendered because it is meaningless.
And most screens have a fixed refresh rate
Almost 60 refreshes per second
Fast or slow
But 60 Hz is the most common. If we change the style a thousand times a second
Will not render a thousand times per second
It will match the display refresh frequency and display performance.
Usually 60 times per second, faster rendering is meaningless and invisible to the user
But that's what setTimeout does
It moves faster because some movements are invisible to the user
Beyond display capabilities
Currently we have been using setTimeout as a shortcut to submit tasks
It's actually not convenient. Although we set the delay time to 0
Browsers usually use 4.7 as the default
By convention, browsers can use any value as the default
But we actually measured it is almost 4.7
There is no one special way to submit a task
We can use message channel to simulate me to test
If you can't stand the picture flashing all the time, I suggest you don't
At the same time, there are many tasks being performed. It seems that the position of the box is random.
Tasks come in every 200 milliseconds
Although rendering can occur between tasks, this interval can run thousands of tasks
Okay, finally stopped flashing
We imagine these to be presented to the user as frames
So rendering takes place at the beginning of each frame, including style calculations, layout and drawing
Not all of them are included every time, it depends on what needs to be updated
I like it very clean and tidy
And task
No bird at all these random event loops will guarantee
Execute in order of submission
But in a certain frame, there is no similar sequence.
We have seen this before in setTimeout
We got three to four tasks per frame
From a rendering perspective, three quarters of the effort is wasted. Some old animation libraries
Like to use milliseconds to simulate the callback execution frequency of about 60 times per second
They make a lot of assumptions about the screen
Assume a refresh rate of 60 Hz. Generally okay, and it does eliminate some duplication of effort
Unfortunately this is a serious hack, because setTimeout is not used for animation
Due to its inaccuracy, it will cause drift phenomenon
Causes nothing in one frame, but the next frame
But doing twice as much, the visual effect is poor for the user
In addition, if the task execution time is long, it is possible that the rendering steps will be shifted because they are all on one thread
This lovely rhythm was disrupted originally
If using requestAnimationFrame
Looks like this
Everything is clean and organized
Even this long mission
The performance trajectory I observed also pleased me
Of course, we cannot completely avoid the task
Such as click events, they will be submitted as tasks, and they need to respond as soon as possible
If you have something like timer or something from the network
I really recommend using requestAnimationFrame
To process tasks in batches, especially when you already have animations running, because it can save a lot of repetitive work
I treat tasks like people who drink sparkling water
I know their existence
But I try to minimize contact because I don't trust them
I think I have empathy, but I think that soda is disgusting
I never thought anyone would drink sparkling water
I have a list on Twitter full of people drinking sparkling water
Not weird behavior, I just need to know what they are doing
Just said, right, requestAnimationFrame
One more detail I want to mention
requestAnimationFrame is executed before processing CSS and drawing
So code like this looks expensive, but it's not
Because before rendering, JS will always be executed from beginning to end
So when you do this, the browser sits still and lets you play for yourself
CSS is not considered at all
Until the last render
It just looks at what changed in the end? Only this last line is useful
This also explains some of the issues that have bothered me before
I have an object and I want to make an animation
Location from 100
Up to 500
It's simple. So I have a listner, X is set to 1000
Then tell it to fade to 500
But the animation is from 0 to 500
Browser, this is not what I told you
I made it clear that the transition from 1000 to 500, I was wondering if it should be
Set all values ​​at once
I guess the reason is the same as before, the browser only considers the style at the end
It ignores the first deformation value
I want to put the second part in requestAnimationFrame
It ’s still from 0 to 500. What happened?
Let me tell you what happened. User clicks on button
A task is formed, so we come here, we set the initial value of the deformation here
We add an animation frame to the queue, and then make a circle, we set the target value here
But browsers didn't consider CSS until this point, just this purple part
Only here is CSS calculated
It completely ignores the initial value because the browser doesn't care about the style during the style change
Here's how to fix
You need to use two animation frames, now it will change from 1000 to 500
Here is a hack, you can use getComputedStyle and read one of the properties
It forces the browser to do style calculations a lot in advance
It will notice all values ​​set before this point
x-axis from 500 to 1000
But be careful this way, because you might make your browser do a lot of things you do n’t want to do.
It originally wanted to do it only once in a frame
In reality, the best way is
Use the animation API because you can specify animation parameters directly
But currently only Chrome supports it, so it's too early to talk about it
If requestAnimationFrame is new to you
That ’s not to blame you, maybe you are misled by some specific implementation
Edge and Safari are wrong, they put requestAnimationFrame here
The most obvious is that they are placed after drawing
This is annoying. Because it means that if the user clicked here
You want batch processing, so use requestAnimationFrame
Edge and Safari will render before calling your callback
So the user may not see the change until the next frame
This adds a lot of delay to what's on the screen
It ’s also difficult to batch jobs, I hope they fix it soon
This is what the web standard says, and Chrome and firefox have already done so
That's it for requestAnimationFrame, and I want to talk about microtasks
I dare say this should be the least known in the event loop
I will associate micro tasks with promises
This was not the case in the 1990s, when browsers wanted to provide developers with an interface to monitor DOM changes
w3c agreed and gave us some mutation events
When a node joins the body, I hope there is a way to know
Okay, so there is another series of events
There are many problems in reality. Looking at this code, I added 100 spans to the body
How many events do you think you will receive in this case? One?
wrong
100? One event per span, right
I will receive another 100
Because of this sentence
When the text is placed in the span, these events are passed up
This sentence will give you 200 events
Because of this simple DOM modification
Thousands of events are triggered. If you have very little logic in the callback
Will quickly become a burden. This will be a disaster in performance.
What we want is to listen to these jobs in batches
It's kind of like the browser behavior mentioned earlier, just sit back and watch
Then tell us together when convenient
Something to represent all changes
I only want to receive one notification instead of 200, so they create a new queue called a micro task
I have read a lot of documents about microtasks, and they all say that every event loop will process microtasks
After the task is processed, it is a micro task or something. It sounds like it is right.
In the event loop, there is only one place where microtasks can occur, but not where you usually encounter
And it happens every time JS execution is completed
When the execution stack is cleared
The micro task will run
So halfway through the mission
It is also possible to run microtasks, and it is also possible to run microtasks during rendering
Basically where you can run JS
So this means that JS will execute until completion
Add 100 spans, and we receive a callback after completion
Promise also takes advantage of this. We submit a microtask here and print yo
Then the execution is completed and a log is printed
We used micro-tasks, print hey
So this means that when the promise callback is executed, the browser will guarantee that no other JS will execute only halfway.
Promise callbacks will be at the bottom of the stack. This is why Promises use microtasks.
What if we write a loop with microtasks
The same demo as before
Click the button to block rendering and block tabs, just like before
Promise callbacks are asynchronous, yes. But what does asynchronous mean? It means
They will be executed after the synchronization code, all printed before Hey
But asynchronous doesn't mean that it will make way for rendering or any other event loop.
So far we have looked at three different queues
Task queue, animation callback queue, and micro task queue
Just to make your life less bitter
They handle it slightly differently
For example, the task queue only processes one at a time
If another event comes in, put it at the end of the line
The animation callback will be executed at once
Unless a new one is submitted in the process. They will be delayed until the next frame
The micro task will be executed to completion
Including inserted
So if your submission is as fast as processing, you will always be processing microtasks
If the queue is not empty, the event loop is blocked, which is why rendering is blocked
Sorry, I ’m excited when I talk about this, I hope you are the same
Thank you for being alone
I used to have a job
These are just my hobbies
Later, my hobby became a job, so I stopped.
I became bored
I do quizzes from time to time
This is one of my favorite questions. There is a button, an onclick event, and a promise is resolved
Then print some logs
But I have two event listeners on one element
If the user clicks the button
What happens and what is the order of log output
First the first listener is executed
Ok, it will enter the JS stack
Raise a micro task to the queue, reach the next line, print Listener1, this is the first answer
Most people agree with this, but what happens next, I started a poll on Twiter
I also talked to some people
Most people say that the next log should be Listener 2. 63% of people choose this
But this is not the correct answer.
Do n’t worry if you choose Listener2, many people are like you
The listener has finished executing, so the stack is cleared
So it's the micro task
This will run the promise and print Micortask 1
Then it ’s the second listener, so the order is Listener 1 Microtask 1 Listen 2 Microtask2
This is the case when the user clicks the button. What if we click the button by code? The situation is different
First our script will be on the stack and click
It dispatches events synchronously, so it starts executing the first listener
Submit the microtask, print listener 1, is the next step to execute the microtask? no
Can't complete a micro task
This is the difference. At this time, the stack has not been cleared, and the button's click method has not been executed
So execute Listener 2 and submit another microtask, now print Listener2
The listener has finished executing
The button click event is completed, the stack is cleared, and micro tasks can now be performed
They are executed in order, pay attention to this in actual coding
Pay attention when writing automation
Because automation may use code to perform clicks