mic check 12 hey everyone thanks for
being back here from lunch I want to say
thank you to jay s fest and CSS comp
Oakland the organizers Carolina and
Michael for giving me this opportunity
to talk about something that I think is
really fun and then I'm really
passionate about so let's see very good
so there's a lot of really fascinating
math behind the display of colors on the
web there's hue and saturation and
brightness and then variables of this
and that is a whole talk in itself but
what drew me to designing for the web
and the first place was that first of
all I could use really vibrant colors
and second of all that the web connects
you to information and stories and
people so I want to talk today about the
stories behind the hex values so for a
while I have loved these two things
separately I love riding CSS code and
making things look good on the web and I
love color I got really into namespace
colors when I saw this project it's
called music for the Memphis group and
it's just really cool basically visual
album almost it's imagining of what the
what this design group the Memphis group
what the type of music they would listen
to and the background is all these
different Memphis group patterns and I
like I started tweeting at the guy who
designed it and asking him how he did it
and he was telling me that the
background is actually rendered all with
SVG's and three different layers of
transparent SVG's and he was like I used
all CSS namespace colors for the colors
and this is something that I had heard
of but I never really made much use of
namespace colors like just by themselves
so I think everyone knows this but just
to make sure we're on the same page when
I'm talking about CSS namespace values I
mean when you're coding in CSS and
instead of typing in the hex value you
can reference a set list of key word
color keywords I think
about 147 of them and the browser and
everyone will know what you're talking
about so back to this project I was
talking to the creator of it and he was
showing me the color chart that he used
in order to make this design and I got
really inspired and wanted to make my
own but put it in rainbow order like you
do and when while i was doing this i
spent a lot of time with the names and i
got really intrigued about where they
came from a lot of them are kind of
quirky like some are really normal but
then some are really out there like I
think on this slide we see peach puff
and tomato and I wanted to know more
about how those names got chosen and who
got to pick them and I knew the story of
one recent color edition I think a lot
of you do that's Rebecca purple so most
of you know this but almost exactly six
months ago Eric Myers a big writer about
CSS and web standards his daughter six
years old Rebecca passed away after a
battle with pediatric brain cancer so in
her memory and in their honor a proposal
was submitted to name six six-thirty 399
after Rebecca and call it Rebecca purple
so this is this really incredibly human
moment touching story of naming of
colors and a great moment in the history
of the internet that really brings his
color to life and I was hungry for more
stories like this behind the naming of
the colors and I thought surely there
were more instances of why something was
called papayawhip or a mint cream or
gainsborough so I went hunting for more
anecdotes I'll tell you what I found the
reality is a lot more tedious and sort
of black and white and boring but
there's a lot that is revealed about the
history of the web and the possibilities
that lay ahead of us so the first thing
to clear up about CSS namespace values
is that they're not CSS original they
were there web standard colors and i
think i saw in Brenna's slides a lot
like she uses them an SVG they're there
they can be used across a lot of
different platforms which we'll get to
but they were originally descended from
the x windowing system which is a
windowing system for bit map displays
common on unix-like computer operating
systems so these were called the x11
colors and they were first shipped in
1986 so this type of windowing system
was one of the first graphic user
interfaces to render things in window
boxes and so having these standard
system colors were really important for
the differentiation of different areas
and sections and windows the original
late 80s list still had a lot of
variation between monitors so there was
kind of an agreed-upon set of names but
even within those the different vendors
would tweak the values for their
particular monitor so neither the names
nor the values were quite standardized
yet until nineteen eighty nine we see
the release of the fourth revision of X
11 and most of the colors that we know
today as web standard colors so here is
the beginning of that x11 color list
these colors were user tested and tuned
originally to an HP monitor and graphic
designer started to get used to them so
from there they were popularized by
Netscape and then they started being
widely used in HTML browsers and finally
in 2011 I think SVG officially
standardized them and then also in 2011
they were rolled into the css3 color
module so we took a while but the usage
in css3 is just the most recent tip of
the iceberg for these standard web
colors why did it take so long that begs
a question there's a big gap between
1986 and 2011 well as we have already
heard today it takes a while for web
standards to get rolled in and it's
normal for things to take I think tab
says like five years at the least
and also because apparently there are a
lot better ways to incorporate name
color values in CSS which maybe you guys
make use of you can sort of define your
own values and if you really like a
certain pink you can call it George pink
or project pink and then go from there
and so they're not necessarily needed
but I want to make an argument for using
them because I think they're really
great even though they're not CSS I
think there's a lot of good reasons why
to use them they are time and user
tested for accessibility I was really
nervous about this slide because I was
like I'm saying this but I don't know
how this yellow is going to look it
could really kill everyone's eyes but
it's going well so there you go because
they were put through the wringer before
at being added to the web standard list
we know that we can rely on them to be
good looking on the on the web and on
monitors so when you're writing code you
are obviously dealing with a lot of
syntax and numbers and I think it's so
refreshing that you can just use the
name and they're not case-sensitive
again they're recognized by all browsers
and they work across HTML and SVG and
they have really fun names so i will
highlight some of my favorite ones we
have honeydew papayawhip mint cream
Navajo white this was actually one of
the first ones that I was scrolling
through the list I was like what's
Navajo white and why is it orange
cornflower blue Dodger blue orchid
antique white gainsborough saddle brown
Peru ghost white these are just a few of
my favorite so while it wasn't exactly a
committee of people sitting around
deciding to name something gainsborough
or bone white i did find out where these
names came from so in 1980
9 for the fourth revision of X 11 this
is when a big bunch of the colors were
added and one of the one of the
contributors to this was Paul raveling
and he got a lot of colors from Sinclair
paint swatches and a lot of the ones
that a lot of the light and off white
colors were from Sinclair paint swatches
Sinclair paints was a california area
paint supplier and after these colors
were added they were actually bought up
by somebody in the bought out by
somebody else and they're like
completely devoured now but I went
digging on paint forums and somebody had
a swatch book from the late 80s and you
can sort of recognize some of these
names which is so cool I'll highlight
the ones that are like definitely in the
web standard colors but it makes sense
because thinking about like what the
goofy names are in these web standard
colors and when you're naming paint
swatches and you have to find six
different ways to say light orange you
get really creative so hence papayawhip
you may have noticed that a lot of these
colors which were using this and Claire
paint swatches there are a lot of beiges
and off rights so this is one of my
favorite sections but it does sort of
beg the question like why do we have so
many beiges I don't know about you guys
but I I maybe use a lot of Gray's a lot
of different like light or dark Gray's
but I don't really need that many bases
well this is because there's so many
options for different browser
backgrounds when these were standardized
in the late 80s and early 90s this was
so designers could find like the perfect
beige for their desktop browser
background so another big chunk of them
came from John see Thomas naming a lot
of the colors after Crayola 72 crayon
box that he had on hand in scrolling
through the list of the different names
of Crayola crayons you can recognize
some that are definitely rolled in I
think I counted 39 that are
definitely from this list and this also
makes sense because when you're looking
at naming a lot of colors it makes sense
to reference a commonly held standard
color nomenclature so these are ones
that are definitely from Crayola crayons
and then from there there's light and
dark variations so adding colors
actually seems to be a rare occurrence
for web standards considering we're
still working off the list released in
1989 besides Rebecca purple the names we
have today we're gathered from various
defaults and more or less are the same
even Rebecca purple which seems like an
obvious opportunity for doing something
nice and beautiful and human why not
name this color after the sweet little
girl but there was a big debate over
this over adding this and it was added
unusually quickly I think in less than I
think it was like three months but this
is because the creators of web standards
take their responsibilities very
seriously which is really good we want
that but it also means that colors never
get added to the standard list and I
just wonder why should we stop there are
we really cool with this or should we
question the standard list and make it a
part of web culture to expand this list
of colors I believe that color is one of
the ways that we can make the internet
more human and more fun I think that
default is boring and I think so many
websites seem to be generated from
defaults they have the same navies and
grays and black and default bootstrap
templates so I invite all color lovers
to think beyond the default but I also
challenge you to think about the color
of the web we have so many colors at our
disposal why aren't we using them we
have this great resource for trying
tested colors so there's kind of no
excuse to just pick some of these and
start experimenting I think that's a
theme of today is experiment and be
adventurous of course we have to keep in
mind accessibility especially when it
comes to rendering text the w3c states
that call
or should not be the only means for
conveying information or prompting in
action but still we should use more
color so I want to show you guys some
examples of sites that are using color
boldly and using it really well this is
a site for pollen Midwest and I think
that this website really struck me
because they use colors that I sort of
thought were off limits like this
magenta and bright yellow and they also
use a wider color palette than I
normally do I think typically as a
visual designer I pick one or two accent
colors and feel like I'm even pushing it
at that and then everything else I just
let be neutral and come stay in the
background but they've used all of these
really bright accent colors and because
of the mastering of design they pulled
it off and still made it look really
slick and professional but to me the
site is really memorable because of its
use of color and because of its color
palette so this is a portfolio for an
Australian designer and also a really
bold nice use of primary colors and a
bold color palette that I think makes
this portfolio website which we've all
seen a million of really stand out and
really be nice but you might be thinking
I have to work on serious things I have
to work on financial site and I have to
make websites that make people feel
secure about using it and doing business
on the Internet I hear you the biggest
projects I've done have have been these
types of projects for nonprofits dealing
with financials and working with
government websites too and the default
there is again to use like navy blue or
blue or blue and grey and black but my
trick is to kind of find like the little
instances where you can flip that out
and what I do a lot is use instead of
that navy blue is like a like a green
okay like a blue green and then use
illustrations as an opportunity to make
things really beautiful and you see an
even wider color palette because i think
if you nine times out of ten if you come
back with a beautiful design people are
going to be
one over by that so I say make it
beautiful and don't ask permission to
use pastels so there's one thing you
take away from this talk I hope it's
that but seriously we should have fun
with color we should use these CSS
namespace values and we should challenge
ourselves to think beyond default colors
and even push the standard list of
colors I want to make a shameless plug
for my own CSS color chart if you want
to experiment start here but there's a
lot of really great ones there's a guy
named Neil orange peel that has one that
is definitely better than mine but
different but you have this link so use
that one these are some some references
i used a big thank you to Chris Lilly he
was actually super helpful in answering
all my questions about CSS color specs
and web standards and thank you to
lexington ladies code club and lexington
kentucky to let me try this talk out and
to Code for America which is a great
place to work that lets you do such
creative things with color even when
working with governments and if you want
to talk to me about being a fellow
please do so thank you so much to CSS