hey guys my stock is going to be
involved a new way of making changes to
the source code but before I begin let
me ask you hi uncle kev have seen the
presentation by brad victor in lansing
calm principle okay so his I main idea
was about the immediate connection
between the source code and the result
let me explain you why is it so
important my usual workflow and probably
yours is simply the following I make
changes to the code I random browser
then I probably had to recreate the
state of application and then I look at
the results and compare to what expected
and then I repeat and I repeat even more
times because I cannot always for see
and understand what might changes will
result for instance if i want to say
change the loops or behavioral / button
on a web page i usually go to the answer
type in some changes then i save the
files which the browser refresh then i
have to scroll down to the place where
button is look at the bottom okay maybe
I have to change something more than I
go to the editor type in changing save
the file go to the browser refresh
scroll down look at and again and again
doing it all the day and maybe you're
doing the same and there is two problems
here actually the first is that I waste
time I keep them keep repeating and
repeating the same mechanical actions
all the day and I get tired and the
second is that as i do not have v8 in my
mind or sound dumb renderer in my mind i
often do not know what will be the
result and this makes my ability to to
create to play the staff to try things
to imagine quite limited so his idea was
that you make changes and you see the
result immediately at the same moment
you make this change and let's look how
it works in a real life now so here i
have my webstorm 5 running have anybody
heard about
that storm cool so this is an ID for web
development a lot of cool features nice
application and my project is a simple
static page that I have stolen stolen
from jetbrains website so there is a an
html5 can you see the code should I make
it bigger okay and there are some links
to the style sheets and so on and this
is how it looks like in the browser in
Chrome so this is nice page with some
books on shelves you know let me put it
to the right so since this page is mine
now let me change it so for instance
I wanted to change the title like at sab
curious bookshelf and you see that page
is updated instantly it is not refreshed
instead webstorm replaces the
corresponding Dom element while i am
typing to prove that let me do the same
with the tooltip you see this tool tip
if i scroll down and so I'd like to
something like URL with no page refresh
you know it's just the beginning if i go
to CSS and lets me for instance change
the color
or a wrong one sorry
you see the color changes the same way I
change it on the left
the same for backgrounds I can even use
a color picker to pick up any color on
the screen like this the same is for
four phones which phone would you like
more this one or this one or this one
haha okay next time if i want to say
give more space between the books
I can do it here this way or I can
basically use the slider
anybody likes it this man or I can make
the Dukes dance hey cool but this is a
another CSS conference not an HTML
conference is a JavaScript conference
right guess what will happen with
JavaScript let me add some more
animation to my to my web page lets me
draw a clock clock is going to be a
simple circle with with just a line for
the hand so let me create a canvas the
bottom
in some ways and height like this is
going to appear somewhere below the
books and let them create a new CSS file
like this so first let me register a
handler
which will initialize the time
like this and install a function that
will draw the clock yes sure like 10
times a second around place
so usual stuff like
okay so first I need to clear my context
like this then I need to draw a circle
so it's going to be context in path
stroke and in between I want to say
context arc
what's to remember
like this there is not nothing on the
screen and the problem is that this
unload handler has already been executed
so here I have to refresh my page okay
something is wrong this is probably the
center so i need to say cameras
cool if i want to say make this circle
nortek I the line width equals 25 oops
should be working let me try again
in just a moment guys we are all
developers you know
okay anyway it was supposed to be
working maybe i will try something else
let me try to draw these hands for the
clock
okay I give up don't want to waste your
time I'm sorry
oh thanks thanks guys you got a free
license for the next version yeah so I
can basically control the thickness of
the line instantly because Webster knows
how to replace that function that I
change so now now I can play with my
code like change their change any number
any parameter that I want you see this
line changes while I'm changing the
source code and this is the direct
change the source code not that
effective dome or sound with something
so they're both changes the source code
that code that you keep in your version
control and the code that the state of
the browser and so to wrap up I would
say that immediate connection exists
using webstorm you can have this
immediate connection to HTML to CSS
property beads color or margin or
whatever and JavaScript as well and you
can try this immediate connection right
now and I hope it will help you you just
can download a trial version of webstorm
for free and it's there if you have any
questions you can reach me by email or
ping me on Twitter thanks
does does anyone have any questions yeah
good in front
when you replace Dom nodes according to
the HTML you've changed do you exchange
everything or just the thing you've
changed oh no only the part that changed
and how do you figure out what is what
there are some code for that so
sometimes it's tricky Thanks so is that
support like trance piling from
coffeescript oh no not right now it's on
the plan okay right now we we can work
with static files like CSS and HTML and
CSS and less and all this all this
compelling are on the plum so so one of
the limitations from what you're showing
was the the window download thing um are
there other ones like that there is is
that like the only thing general
limitation is that if a function or
JavaScript code has been already
executed at the moment you change it is
gone on the next execution it's it's new
so we do not replay that the best
actions it does make much sense
actually have a question could you show
the refactoring support inside Webster
what kind of some kind of yeah for jobs
you introduce varietal is there not make
much sense right here extract method is
there or in line rename of course I
cannot remain turning this one but this
one will do named
there's actually many more cool okay one
more question
it's will work yes
the question was if I change a name in
one file with the other files be updated
after some cases where you don't know if
that function is used in the other
problem like if if ID is not sure about
whether is used or not it will suggest
you to review the occurrences that you
can manually include them or exclude
down for instance if you reference the
function by just a string literal its do
one of the cases when I d is not sure
what do you mean cool I think that's it