ah
why do you care about our x RX it's a
story rather the web is very
asynchronous look at this dictionary
suggest like when you type there's
events happening there's asynchronous
calls to the server and if you write a
lot of these things together your
program gets pretty complicated quickly
you have all these nested callbacks
continuation passing and our ex tries to
address that so if you look at for
instance at that sample it does suck you
up starts an async xmlhttprequest and
then it displays results in you could
write it like this and of course this is
a very basic sample that it's not very
smart I mean it does very well implement
it but this is like a good their first
attempt like you hook up to the input
key up in vent and then you start an
async HTTP request and once it comes
back you format the result at HTML well
turns out there is a couple more things
that you have to worry about first of
all you don't want to overload the
server so you try to tame the input on
the client you filter out the empty key
opps from your textbooks you filter out
duplicates and you want to tame the
input if the user is typing and you know
that he's going to type the second
character for its completion in 10
milliseconds it doesn't really make
sense to send an aging HTP request to
the server and put load on the server if
the user is never going to see that
value anyway and there's this thing
about ignoring old curious and we'll get
to that in a bit and you need to expect
failure web there's big pot holes in the
higher in the internet highway so you
need to expect failure everywhere so
let's look at that ignore old queries
thing so imagine that user types the
letter R in the dictionary suggest then
the server sends a response for
completions for letter R the user types
letter E and now one of the servers is
hit on your web form that is a bit
overloaded so it's going to take a bit
of time for this response to come back
meanwhile the user types next character
and
he happens to hit a server on your web
form that has plenty of time he had no
no load so he immediately sends back the
result and gives the completions for Rea
meantime the busy server decides to wake
up and send the response back for the
completions or of re and now the users
UI is updated with an old completion so
that's pretty bad and you don't want
that to happen so the code that takes
care of all the things that I just
mentioned can look something like this
and this might not be the optimal way to
do it but this is like a good first
attempt to write something like that so
we hook up to the key up event and we
check if there's no error occurred in
previous events then we check if there
is a difference between the current
value and previous value and we save to
the current value as for the next check
then we set a time out because you only
want to start sending the asynchronous
requests if the user hasn't typed
anything for 250 milliseconds so then
this can also have an error because the
timeout ap I could throw an error if you
have too many timeouts in the queue then
we continue after 250 milliseconds has
passed we need to have a request study
to keep track of all the requests that
happen so that we can only use the last
one that we are interested in to avoid
that a flapping problem that we saw
earlier then again because we now have
another async instruction me to check
again if there is no errors occurred in
this whole call and finally we get here
we can update the UI and we need to
check for errors in all these different
cases so all this taking care of errors
and all the different parts of your
asynchronous program can make your code
pretty bulky and harder to understand
it's not immediately clear what the the
issue was that you are trying to solve
here so if we now look at our ex and you
look at our homepage that it has like a
tag line like this our access to library
for composing a sickness and event based
programs using observable collections so
let's dissect that sentence a bit
asynchronous programming as I just
showed it's pretty hard right now so we
want to see if we can make that better
we're going to be able to compose events
you want to write a fluent api so you
want to just be able to say do this and
float by the next operation next
operation instead of having to wrap your
end program inside out which you have to
do with continuation passing right now
and then last mentions observable
collections well collections means that
we can do queries right neck database is
all about collections they're all flat
tables collections of data so maybe we
can do queries over these things as well
then so if you look at the RX basic we
have looked at like a lot of existing a
synchronous asynchronous patterns and
all of them they signal some kind of
completion when the thing that you asked
it to do is done most of them also give
you an error and there's various ways
that the different API suit is some they
take two different sets of continuations
some use the first argument of the
confirmation to signal error or not and
then most of them have a payload as well
and this can either be a single pale out
in the case of an asynchronous call or
it can be many payloads in the case of
event like mouse move so if you look at
our X we came up with the following
grammar there is zero or more messages
its payload or next followed by an
optional uncompleted message or a known
error message and I notice that these
this can only be one but this is pretty
mathematical and I promise no
mathematical stuff so we're over going
on the sliding pat down here so i won't
do more math stuff and so what's in the
package will dive in directly so RX
ships with a two prototypes observable
and observer and this is like the design
pattern from the gang of four from the
90s we have slightly modified it so the
subscribe just like in the design
pattern takes an observer that wants to
listen to that specific event stream or
a synchronous stream she do notice
there's no unsubscribe
so what we did is instead of having a
separate unsubscribe method we return
you a method of a function that when you
call it it will unsubscribe the whole
computation and the reason we do that is
because we want you to allow you to
compose all these events together and if
you have a whole chain of all these
different events you compose you want to
be able to unsubscribe them at a
moment's notice by just making one call
so the thing that we're returns you call
that and the whole subscription will be
torn down now if you look at observer we
split it into these three things that we
mentioned in our grammar all next on
error and uncompleted so if you want to
listen to these events you just
implement observer and implement these
three methods and what we do is by
default if you don't implement these two
methods on ever will fire out the it
will just read throw the exception and
on complete it will be seeing no up and
then for ease of use we also allow you
to just pass in a function instead of
having to create the observer object so
that's the basic part of the package of
course that doesn't have give that much
additional value yet the real value is
in in the lots of operators that we
provide so we have a lot of conversions
from existing JavaScript libraries we
have all the big ones jquery dojo
prototype mootools Yui 3 and then we
have a lot of manipulation operators so
we have projection time-based operators
buffers so that's really real value lies
the fact that you can combine multiple
streams and and modify the output so
let's look at some key concepts that you
need to know about observables before we
start diving into the code there's two
kinds of observables the first one is
rename call observables that means like
this one is like one of the most basic
operators it just creates an observable
that when you call subscribe on it it
will return you to value 42 so you
subscribe and your functional or
observer object will immediately be
called way to fail you 42
followed by a call to on completion I
don't complete it the reason we call
this code because it doesn't happen
until you actually ask it to do
something and that is in contrast with
hot observables so how observables are
things that will give events whether or
not you're subscribe to it so for
instance any of the mouse move events or
other events they just keep firing even
if you don't subscribe to it of course
we optimized where that we don't make
all the calls but it keeps firing in
theory so let's look at the most basic
way of using our X so as I said we
integrate with jquery so we just load
jquery followed by loading our x and
then the specific jquery bindings to our
x we just use the regular jQuery
selector to get a Dom element input
element in this case and we say we want
to subscribe to the key want to convert
the jQuery event p up to an observable
so this is an method that we added to
the jQuery prototype and now when you
ask ricky up event will hook up to the
jquery mechanism and give you a return
you and observable object and now you
can use subscribe to listen to it of
course this you could easily do without
RX but this is just the most basic
sample it actually shows how to start
with RX ok so let's do some javascript
hacking i figured that i ii didn't get
much time today so i'm going to do my
demonstrate IE even though it works in
all the browsers ok so after a simple
page just like let me close a couple of
these dialogues you give some more real
estate so I have a simple web page i
load RX jquery and jake RX jquery
binding i have let's show hold on i have
two elements and an input box and a diff
to show results um i'm going to write
the dictionary suggest sample using our
X so our first going to hook up to the
key up event from the input box
so I'm going to say input still to
observable off-key up and i'm going to
subscribe to that
and I'm going to pass the function what
it needs to do when a value comes
through and I'm just now going to put it
in the results so results innerhtml plus
equals value yeah let's see what that
does and of course I'm something wrong
refresh that demo effect okay let's
spare let me just change this to other
Lord see what I do wrong yeah it's just
something wrong with maybe a mistake oh
I know what I did wrong i was using
jquery object to use in NRH smell and I
should do in results the latest Mel fail
you there we go and still doesn't work
result selection series half dead
yes there you are okay so it gives me
object object and the reason for that is
because the event gives me the win the
event object back so I don't want to use
the whole event object i'm really only
interested in the value that's in the in
the textbook so i'm going to do a
projection here so i'm going to say
instead of having this event object in
here i wanna have developed and then I
pass in a function value return value
top source element don't fail you there
we go so now when i refresh this when i
type i get all the values of course now
when i do arrows so now when i copy and
paste the same thing in displace the
same value and when i do mt it also
shows that so i want to filter out those
events so first i'm going to filter out
the empty case
so if Lu is not the empty string I want
to fill send this through so now it
doesn't fire the empty case and if i
want to have two unique values there's
an operator that's called distinct until
changed it's like a distinct in a
database the only difference is that
because these observable streams can be
potentially infinite it doesn't keep a
cache of all the values that it's seen
previously it only keeps a cache of the
last value its salt so if you type a and
then a again it will not fire a but if
you type B afterwards and then a again
it will fire the eight again at a later
time there we go okay so that's working
now it's hard to see I guess so now we
have the the input that we want there's
only one thing that we still wanted to
add this we wanted to make sure that we
don't fire unless user hasn't typed for
a couple milliseconds so I'm going to
say let me throttle the user's input
here so throttle for 250 milliseconds
dot here okay so let's give this a try
so if i type AAA bc it shows up but i
didn't show the a and the B in a min
meantime okay so we have tamed our input
let's go make an asynchronous requests
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
say select for every value that comes in
making xmit requests and we have a
wrapper around the xhr as well so i'm
going to say our exit observable xml
HTTP request and download that from 16 8
4 2000
queer query is and i'm just going to
escape the value here and i believe if i
need to do one more see here ok let's
give that a try and i made an error yes
well that's right yep sorry oh yes
you're right type that weight and
there's still more errors of course I
need to return that value i'm not using
coffeescript
okay so now we get an object back which
is the xmlhttprequest so there was one
thing that we still needed to do because
now I just make an XML HTTP request for
every value that comes in then I just
said that that was bad because now you
can have this of flapping results
problem so let's go fix that so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to use the
switch operator and the switch operator
switches between all the new observables
as moment it comes in so it's going to
type switch and while reddit i'm going
to change this to change to use the
response text here there you go there
it's a 19-13 dictionary so it's a it's
not that fancy but it was the one I
could find it didn't have any license
issues okay so we have for addiction
it's just working so let's look a bit
more into what we just did with all
these operators so let's start with the
more basic operator so what we often do
is to explain all our operators is we
draw these things that we call marble
diagrams so this is the code for the
module diagram and then we show each of
the observables here where we usually
see all the inputs on top and the output
on the bottom and this shows time that
direction and then we project the values
how to go from the input to the output
stream so select will does it it gets
called for each value that comes through
its own next message and the user gets a
chance to transform each single value so
in this case we did the event source
elemental value so it goes from the
event object to the value of the data
and it does this as long as they're just
message come in until uncompleted
message comes in and the completed
message is just sent through directly
and doesn't carry any value of course
errors could happen and this could
happen in two places they can either be
errors that already existed in the
source observable or that could be
introduced by the user here in
in the in the selector function we try
to use aboard semantics or possible so
we sent these errors straight through
there's no manipulation on them distinct
until Chainz as I said it it starts
producing all the values through if it
has that value in its cache currently it
doesn't send it through so the second
value didn't get projected down then new
different value came in it gets in
through until a new value comes in and
complete it gets in through direct
directly and I think you can also pass
in a comparison if you want to do more
complex comparisons and just equality
comparison okay throttle throttle is a
bit more interesting operator because it
does time shifting so it the first time
the user types of character it starts a
timer and if the next message doesn't
come in by the time were times that will
fire it out so in this case diverse not
the second collapse before the second
value come in so it ignore the first
value and then after second no new
message came in so it projects the
second value the moment it gets
completed it actually sends it out the
moment that the last value has sent out
being sent out and that's important
because like if an error happens we're
trying to use a board semantics so even
though it's of value outstanding if an
error comes to we say up this thing has
to be aborted so we sent the arrow right
through and the one that was in flight
will never get sent out okay switch so
switch looks a lot more complicated it
just have to wrap your mind around it a
bit and then it will float automatically
how it should work so what we did in our
sample is that we selected from a value
to a new observable so what we actually
created was an observable which payload
it again our observable stem cells so
each value that comes through in that
original observable is itself an
observable so we can do is you can
right to these and project them out in a
flattened way so every time a new
observable comes in we start listening
it and all values get projected down
immediately the moment that on our outer
observe will a new message comes through
with the next observable we unsubscribed
from the first observable and then we
start listening to the second observable
and project each values through so the
even though this one had more values we
just ignore them if this one happens to
be completed before our outer produces a
new one if we just wait until the outer
want to give our new values and then we
complete when both the outer and the
last inner have both the completed
message so this is exactly solving that
issue with having xmit requests coming
out of order ok so our semantics get bit
more tricky because now there is much
more places where errors can happen so
errors can happen inside the interrupts
verbal or inside the outer observable in
both cases we just use aboard semantics
ok so our ex is a general-purpose
library it works not only on websites
and i want to show you that that's the
case so this virtual machine is actually
running node and what we did is I wrote
a couple wrappers around note to use
that create RX bindings observable
bindings for each of the asynchronous
operations so I'll quickly show you how
that looks like yeah
so instead of requiring sis and HTTP and
FS I require our axis in RX HTTP and
what we do stays we exported all the
original functions within with an RX
repper so I do it create HTTP server
just like a normal package but then what
I do is I want to get the parsed URL
instead of the the just a string URL so
i select in with a select the URL parse
version of it so that I can look at the
query and then as my dictionary only
works on alphanumeric sir alpha strings
I make sure the query is an alphabetic
character and so my observe will now
only contains URL request that that are
valid and then I do is select many so
select many is like bind in Haskell I
know for people who know that well does
it gives you an opportunity to replace
each value of a observable with a
function that's will show you the new
observable that's then flattened so in
this case I get the request in and then
I'm going to start an async read file
request so read that file and wonder
when that value comes through i select
the JSON and then in the end I just
subscribe to my event and we sent a
response out there
so as you can see it's not just for
website inference in any environment
that runs java script there's a lot more
operators in RX then i discovered in
this small talk there's a lot of time
based operators but for operators
there's aggregation operators there's
operators to convert from existing
events there's mechanism to create your
own observables so it's a it's a pretty
extensive package and the download the
the core of our exes 7kg zip and there's
a whole bunch of external libraries for
the integrations they are all separate
so you don't have to pay for the
download size like if you don't use
jojoba jquery you don't want to pay for
the download size of the dojo bindings
so what's next you can find RX on the
following URL and it's pretty crappy URL
so just type it in your fray for search
engine and it should show up we do a new
release about every two to five weeks we
have a web form that you can report bugs
features suggestions just help and how
to implement things we have a lot of
videos online think we have about 40
videos right now when we post new once
every couple of weeks and then there's
also two channels we wanted to use pound
there are hash RX but yeah there's a lot
of stuff there already that you don't
want to read so we're using our x GS and
RX net and you can also just look at at
my Twitter feeds and with that I'd like
to open up for questions
you had a question so that last example
that you show did you get note running
on windows no I didn't try I just sets a
vm yeah this is this is a Linux VM I
just I just did a app get and go going
so the licensing is a it's a custom
license but it's it's pretty much ses
license it's not officially supported
through product support right now but
you can use it in your applications as
you want it we had just switch this
thursday before we had to have like an
installer which is really painful if
you're not on the Windows platform and
the release that we did this Thursday
it's now in a zip file so it's very easy
to get on any platform in exactly a
question but the comments whereas that
does Marvel diagrams are actually pretty
cool I was just kind of searching around
actually top search hit for marble egg
diagram is the reactive framework does
curious there are other projects and
engine soul everyone uses a Microsoft
all the scenes but here's that are other
seems like that shouldn't be something
that other projects yeah it should be
something anything those asynchronous
can can benefit from this seems like
there's like um L would be like the
default place to go with these kind of
diagrams I you know this was like
inspired by some other is there another
um Elish vocabulary word I don't know we
came up with this when we like we need
it to draw these things and like how can
we explain people what to be a free of
these operators and just this came
naturally okay it's similar to like a
client-server diamond right we have the
two lines of time going on the sea make
requests McEvoy yep so which is
typically call the Stevens diagram even
the networking book okay this seems less
dogmatic and just useful yeah I still
want to invest so one of the things that
is still lacking is documentation like
we were small team we are three
developers plus one architect so as you
know documentation always lags behind so
one of the things like I have about 1500
test for RX and I want to generate these
two marble diagrams automatically so I
hope that that will help improve the
documentation any other questions I've
been doing quite a bit of similar a
project in a similar vein based off of
Tyler closest promises from hackers are
you aware exam is there a connection
distinction so there's a lot of reactive
programming going on and they're all
good packages the thing and we did is we
really looked at like the monads and
from functional programming and use that
that's our basis I have not seen how how
they base their programming but it is
interesting i took a very similar
approach the promise life as usual
it is addressing a similar it's less
about straining events and subscriptions
and more about the return results seems
like there might be some connection okay
I'll look into that I've not had a
chance looking it and all and I look
into this as well okay good well thank