hi everyone i'm lynn clark and I make
code cartoons and today I'm going to
walk you through the wilds of data
handling and react so how you handle
state any react application and I call
it the wilds because when you first look
at the landscape it can seem like it's
an untamed profusion of different
options for how to handle data it's
really hard to figure out when you're
looking at it what you might want to use
and why you might want to use it but
when you look closer you'll see that
there are three groupings of ways to do
this and they're actually easier to
understand than you might think so I
want to go for a whirlwind tour through
them so that you can have a better idea
when you approach your next appt why you
might want to use any one of these so
the first of these was flux and I'm
going to start with the colonel of the
idea that flux introduced that carries
through to redux and to relay and that's
it don't worry if you don't understand
it because this whole project started
because I couldn't understand it but
once you understand flux this diagram is
very clear before explaining the diagram
I should explain the problem that flux
solves so flux and react both come out
of Facebook and they were developed side
by side to address a certain set of
problems one really good example of this
set of problems was the notification bug
how many people remember this you know a
few years ago you go on facebook and
you'd be clicking around and all of a
sudden you see a notification for a new
message and you click the messages icon
and look at your messages and there's no
new message and so the notification goes
away and you start doing whatever you're
doing again and then all the sudden
comes back and just keep going back and
forth and back and forth and back in
this cycle this wasn't just a cycle for
you the user it was also a cycle for the
team at Facebook
you know they'd fix it it'd be resolved
for a few weeks and then all the sudden
would come back again so they wanted to
fix this once and for all and end this
cycle of unpredictability when they
looked at it more closely they realize
the source of the problems was the way
that they were handling data they had
these models and the models which held
the data would pass the data to the
views which would present the data to
the user would format it in HTML for the
user the views also provided a user
interface for the user to put data back
into the system so the views needed to
communicate back to the model they need
to update that data in the model but
sometimes when you may have changed to
one model another model would need to
update in response so you have this
communication between models too so this
starts to look kind of like an epic game
of pong it's really hard to figure out
where the ball is going to land throw in
the fact that these updates could be
triggered asynchronously you know you
could have a update that comes in and
kicks off two more that are happening
concurrently and that's kind of like
taking a bag of ping pong balls and
throwing it into your pong game like
everything is bouncing all over
everywhere as incredibly hard to figure
out where everything's go and so that
brings us back to this diagram that's
what you'll find if you see the flux
docks and this is the way that Facebook
solved that problem of the ping pong
balls just bouncing all over the place
it was with a unidirectional data flow
so you'll notice that this data flows
from one thing to the other my guess the
end it starts back at the beginning and
you should also notice that the first
thing there the first thing that starts
off this cycle is the action that's
going to become more important later but
if you don't understand what the parts
do I don't think this diagram even
though it shows you this unidirectional
data flow it doesn't give you a good
mental model of what exactly is going
on and it certainly didn't help me what
did help me was thinking about all the
different parts of flux as different
characters working together to take on a
certain task so I want to introduce you
to the characters that I have in my head
and hopefully that helps you understand
flux too so the first of these is the
action creator and I think of the action
creator as a telegraph operator
basically other characters come to the
action creator with a change that they
want to make and they have the action
creator format an action that represents
that change the action creators the one
that knows how the rest of the system
what language the rest of the system
speaks and it knows how to format these
actions in a way that the rest of the
system will understand them each change
that of you wants to make the action
creator turns into an object that
represents it the object has a type
something like message created message
read message delete and a payload which
tells it what message to do this to what
the text of that message is so you
define the list of those types like a
message create and have a full list of
all of the different possible actions in
your system so this is kind of nice
because it provides an API you know if a
new developer comes onto your projects
you just point them to this list of
different actions in your system and
they can know all the different things
that your system does so once the action
creator for mass this action creates
this object then it passes it off to the
dispatcher and I think of the dispatcher
is basically a switchboard operator it's
a big registry of callbacks it lists all
the stores has a list of all the stores
that need to be updated whenever in
action comes in and so it will send
those actions that come into it to all
the stores and I'll do it synchronously
it will actually not have different ping
pong balls going at the same time it'll
make sure that all of the action goes
through the stores before it triggers
the next one
now the flux dispatcher is different
from dispatchers in other systems and it
is different in that the action is
dispatched to every single store and
other systems a lot of times the
dispatcher will allow you to subscribe
to a certain set of actions so your
store might say I only want to hear
about message create actions and the
dispatcher will only send it that kind
of action flux sends all of the actions
to the store and it's the stores
responsibility to say hey I don't really
care about this one or I'm going to make
a change based on this type so now we
get to the store I think of the store as
an over controlling bureaucrat all state
and state logic live on the store and
there are no setters there's no way to
get in and change the data in the store
except for this action pipeline so I
think of it as you know the store is
basically saying no you're not going to
touch this data only I can touch this
data and if you want to make me to make
any changes to it you're going to have
to go through the official channels
you're gonna have to go through the
action pipeline once the store has
actually made its changes to the data we
get to the view and we have a controller
view and the view this underneath the
controller view so the view is basically
a presenter that just takes the data
that is given and turns that into the
something that the user can understand
turns it into HTML it renders the data
that it gets from the store the
controller view is a little bit more
aware of what's going on in the system
it basically acts as a middle manager
between the store and the presenter it
fetches data from the store and gives it
to the view underneath it to render so
those are the characters in flux now
let's take a look at how they all work
together to make an application happen
and before they start doing their actual
tasks they need to initialize they need
to do some set up to start talking to
each other so we're going to start with
a set up and then we'll look at how the
application works once it set up so to
set up the store will tell the
dispatcher what call back to you is
they'll say hey here's a call back as
soon as an action comes in just let me
know
and then the controller view will talk
to the store and we'll say hey can you
give me the state whatever initial state
you have and i'm going to send that down
to my views and so the store sends the
state which the control of you sends
down to the views below it to render the
this is the initial render of the app
and then the controller view goes back
up to the store and says and if any
updates come in just let me know and so
give us the store a call back to call so
everybody knows how to talk to each
other now and now we can start actually
performing having user interactions so
the user is going to update the middle
number set it to 10 and the view which
has received this user interaction is
going to go down to the action creator
and say hey here's some information can
you format in action for me and send it
off to the dispatcher so the action
Creator creates the action gives it the
action type and formats the payload and
then sends it off to the dispatcher and
then the dispatcher feeds it into the
store and of course this is where the
store says do I care about this how do i
change the data based on this action
type so then the store changes the the
data that it holds and it lets the
control of you know and then the
controller view says okay great and asks
the store to send down the new data and
then we'll pass it into the view below
it to rerender so that's flux you know
it ended the cycle of unpredictability
and all rejoiced and created a hundred
different implementations of it and now
we move on to redox redux is a lot like
flocks so it's just a couple of
different couple of differences between
Redux and flocks but if sup flux solved
the problem of this
you
but I think that this is a really good
use case for illustrating the changes
that he made so he was seeing debugging
techniques in other communities like hot
modular reloading and time travel
debugging and he wanted to introduce or
improve them and react but before I get
into that I should probably explain what
those two things are so let's start with
hot module reloading imagine that you're
developing a to-do application and this
is your to-do list object so you've
added a few to deuce you know eat sleep
and you want to change the way there
you're adding the to do's because you've
realized that as they are added to the
bottom of the list it's kind of hard to
tell that you're adding you to do is you
want to add them to the top of the list
so that people can see the new to do is
is coming in now as you're testing this
think about changing this ad to do
function so that it adds it to the front
instead of the back how would you
actually see that change happening once
you've made the change to the code how
would you actually check in your app
that it's working well you'd have to
reload this object but when you reload
the object you lose the state that's on
it you lose all of those two dues that
you would add in but you can avoid this
problem and the way that you do that is
by splitting up the object into two
different objects one that holds the
state and one that holds the
functionality that changes the state so
then you can reload the object that has
the functionality that changes the state
but you don't have to reload the object
that holds the state so this helps you
to bug faster because you don't have to
keep replicating the state every time
you change every time you fix a little
thing in your functionality time travel
debugging is kind of similar and what it
handles so with time travel debugging
let's start about thinking about how you
step through to debug a nap so you start
with initial state and then you perform
an action and that equals a new state
your application is in a different state
action and then you take another action
and another action what if your bug is
happening between step 2 and step 3 even
though we have this hot module reloading
which will keep the state you really
need to step backwards in time in order
to be able to test that between the
second and third action that you're
fixing whatever problems there what time
travel debugging does is lets you do
that it lets you step backwards in time
so that when you change your
functionality then you can perform that
action again and you don't have to do
the first or the second one again so
what do you need to do in order to make
time travel to volume work well you need
to get a snapshot of your state at each
of these points and how do you do that
well you can kind of see it already in
the way that I've drawn this you treat
this as an equation as a function your
initial state comes in and you add the
action but you don't change the initial
state you don't change that state object
you create a new state object and you
just keep an array of all these state
objects as they're going through this is
what people are talking about when they
talk about immutability it's the idea
that you don't change the things that
are coming into your function and you
don't change the object itself you just
take in some parameters and you output
you return you use your return value to
to give your caller or the value that it
means so Redux makes it possible to do
both of these things to do hot module
reloading on stateful objects and to do
time-travel debugging I'm not going to
dive too deep into a detailed
walkthrough of redox because it mostly
is like flocks and I've written this all
up if you want to go into a deep dive of
redux you can go check code cartoons com
to see that I do want to point out two
of the key differences though the first
is the way that the store works instead
of managing the logic the store just
holds on to the state it has like this
one state object the stink
single state tree it has all of the
state in the app which is holding on to
and then when an action comes in it
passes the state and the action off to
another object it passes that off to the
reducer and it's the reducer that figure
out how the state needs to change and
response to the action so you'll
remember this is what we needed for hot
module reloading you know we needed to
have an object that's holding on to the
state and an object that's actually
performing that changes on the state and
these reducers they do something else
too they make copies instead of changing
the state that's coming into them they
make copies of that state and then they
give that back to the store and so the
store just swaps out the state it's
holding on to for the new state there's
another difference between flux and
redox and that's the way that the state
is sent from the store to the view layer
so you know how in flux we had the view
layer letting the store know that it
existed and that needs to have these
callbacks called in redox there's
something called the view layer binding
and this will take care of a lot of that
plumbing for you so it reduces the
boilerplate a bit so that's redux and
now we move on to relay if you've been
following along closely up until this
point you might have a question that
you've been thinking about where's the
cloud where does the interaction with
the server happen in flux there's not
really a greed upon set place to do that
with the server even at Facebook
different teams would do this in
different places in redox there is one
place which is recommended middleware
but it still require some extra code to
wire it up really connects you to the
cloud and it wires it all up for you
without you having to put in too much
extra work at least on the client side
so let's look at how relay connects your
client up to the cloud but first we
should ask
what's in the cloud in the case of an
app like Facebook it's a huge graph of
data and when I talk about graphs here
i'm talking about graphs like graph
theory so a whole bunch of things and
relationships between those things and
these things they'll be things like
users and events and the relationships
will be things like friend are invited
to in graph a graph theory these are
often called nodes the things are nodes
and the relationships between them are
edges so you have this huge graph of
things and relationships between them
are nodes and edges but when you're
showing a page to an individual user you
don't care about this huge graph you
only care about a small section of this
graph and what really does is it makes
the connection between that small
section of the graph that you care about
in the cloud and your copy of it in your
local cache it knows how to manage this
for you because you declare in your
components which bit of the graph each
component cares about so it knows
exactly which bits of the graph to pull
down so let's go pair this with the way
the communication with the cloud usually
happens in a lot of other apps not all
other apps but a lot of other apps you'd
make a request your app would make your
request to the server and you have a
component tree you have this avatar bio
component you'll send up the request and
the server knows exactly what to deliver
because it delivers the same thing so it
will deliver the name location and
picture properties because it that's the
list of things that it knows it has to
deliver the problem is if you need to
add a new property to the avatar or the
bio component or if you rearrange things
if you remove the bio component the
server doesn't know about that you
actually have to make a change in the
server code at the same time as you're
changing the client code so this is
coupling what really does in contrast
is half the components say exactly what
it needs it says exactly the data that
it needs in order to render so the
avatar would say i need the picture the
bio says i need the name and location
and then the parent pulls those together
and sends that off as a query to the
server and the server prepares it on
demand for the for the application so it
gets pulled down and sent out to the
components when it gets put in a local
cache when you have this kind of
structure it enables some really cool
things having your components say
exactly what data it corresponds to in
the graph it makes it possible to
automatically do things like splitting
up your query so that you can have a
part that's delivered immediately and
gets rendered to the user immediately
that you know crease that more
responsive feeling and a part that's
deferred you send both those queries up
at the same time one will come down
first immediately and will render out
the component the other will come down
later will get merged into the data will
get merged into the little bit of the
graph that you have in your local cache
and then it will be sent out to its
component and that will render it also
makes it possible for you to reduce the
size of queries that you're sending up
so let's say you have your day than this
local cache now and you've gotten to
another page and you need to get a
little bit more data in order to render
this page but you already have most of
the state than your local cache so you
don't really need to download it again
so we'll just take out really we'll just
take out the bits of data that you have
in your local cache push it up push up
the query and then when that comes down
I'll merge it into the graph send it out
to the component and it doesn't just do
this for data that you have in your
local cache it keeps track of pending
queries and what parts of the graph
those are pulling down so you know
queries that have gone off to the server
but haven't come back yet and it will
remove those from the outgoing queries
to
it also makes it really easy to sync any
changes that you're making to the data
in the browser up back up to the server
it will even handle optimistic changes
to the UI so you know assuming that
you're going to be able to write this
data to the cloud and updating the UI as
if you were able to do it so you send up
this let's say that you accepted an
invite to an event you send that up to
the server it makes the change in your
local cache and actually displays it to
the user and then when the response
comes back down you know might be an
error it might not be it'll handle that
whatever comes down now I don't have
enough time to go deeply into how relay
does this house you'll see there are a
ton of characters involved here and
that's because relays doing so much more
for you it's actually a framework as
opposed to flux and redux their patterns
for handling data but relay is a
framework I do want to point out the
thread that ties it to the other two
though and that is that state is changed
using objects that represent that change
in flux and redux you have the actions
and relay you have mutations that get
passed around to make these changes so
that's relay if you want to dig deeper
into it I'm going to be publishing a
series of posts that explained
everything about relay starting next
week so you can follow code cartoons or
sign up for the mailing list to get
notification of that so let's review
these three starting with flux so flux
addressed the unpredictability of data
flowing through Facebook's apps and the
way it did it was with a unidirectional
data flow you know views asking action
you know creating action having the
action creator Creed actions sending it
off to this patcher which sends it off
to the stores which changed the state
and then let the view know that the sea
has been changed and then the view
requests the state and sends it down to
the views Redux built on this and just
modified a few things by
breaking out the state into its own the
state storage into its own object and
the functionality that changes that
states into a different object and also
collecting snapshots of the state and
then relay built on some of the same
ideas as flux but made it possible for
you to connect the section of the graph
and the cloud that you care about to the
local cache in the browser thanks very
much for listening I hope that was
helpful and if you want to learn more
about any of the stuff check out code