thank you yeah I'm just glad to be here
all right it's getting towards the end
of the day so I thought I'd start my
presentation with some questions also to
help me do some research as I formulate
the rest of the presentation in my head
so who here is a JavaScript developer is
your hands alright great so I'm in the
right place okay who here works as a
developer on a team with more than five
developers on it all right now keep your
hands up if you work on a team between
five and thirty developers awesome just
give me a moment I you are all the
people that I want to talk to you after
this because my talk is actually about
engineers as makers and this is
something that comes out of my current
role which is VP of engineering at
social tables or DC based event planning
software company and we have five
developers now just about to be six and
so something that I'm thinking about a
lot as a first-time engineering manager
is how to how to best use these talented
people on my team and to continue to
grow and build that so a little bit
about me I'm a self-taught programmer I
put that in quotes because so many
people have helped me along the way as
mentors as as peers learning alongside
with me but that's what people say about
themselves is that they're self-taught
so I just put that there and a little
bit of color for this presentation
I was actually a former business analyst
for client services firm so while right
now I'm working on a product company
that does you know b2b sales I have set
in client offices before doing project
plans and project management and and
scoping so about this talk well it's
actually really simple it's about
getting from point A to point B and in
this particular case I'm going to define
point a is just having people people are
your raw human resources the talent that
will get you places so point B here is
product and we're all JavaScript
developers since you all raise your
hands and so products really here is
like software applications that people
use and I'll just throw in a little bit
of a refinement on that so products that
other people actually want it's kind of
a key piece especially if you're trying
to make money so very simply I just try
to break down products into the simplest
things that I know about them when I'm
trying to get to a point from point A to
point B and that's a design and code and
what that really means is that we've got
designers and engineers and I'd like to
keep those separate I know there are
people out there that you can do both
engineering and designing I'm thinking
that's like less than ten percent less
than five percent of people really do
both those things so I person we go
ahead and assume that those are two
separate people in those places and then
flushing out the other side you know
products that other people want well
then we're talking about customers and
keep that in mind because customers is
really important later on so you know
these are some typical engineering
responsibilities I mean I pulled these
words off of like you know job pages you
see them all the time on you know
typically front-end back-end I most of
the time you know you're hired for one
or two of those there's also testing QA
DevOps all sorts of specialties and then
you know in some companies you've got
one person doing all these other places
you've got a lot more specialization and
since when our JavaScript conference you
know we use node.js which i think is
amazing because automatically you can
have people do back in in front end
pretty easily I know there's caveat set
but really it's not that much of a
difference to take someone who just
knows client-side JavaScript well and
have them do server-side code so you
know for social tables it's really about
doing all these things and everyone
doing all these things well that seems
like a lot right but what if we added
all these other things that I've
highlighted in green project management
feature prioritization UI UX and new
product development well you think at
most places these are these are job
functions that other people do at social
tables and other startups that I I think
might adopt this role there's a lot of
blending that happens and I think this
is kind of a philosophy that I've
adopted as I've been thinking more and
more about this that I really want to
preserve engineers as makers I really
want engineers to be thinking about the
problems that their customers are having
I really want to take engineers to think
very deeply about how to solve those
problems and owning it owning the whole
pipeline from kind of concept to
finished product of course there's a lot
of teamwork involved in that but that
leaves the question how so I think this
is the point where things get kind of
unclear well I believe it comes down
mostly to this a direct line to
customers so link between engineers and
customers has to be strong it has to be
the engineer kind of understanding that
the problems of main of the customer and
kind of understanding where they're
coming from and again i'm coming i'm
talking about b2b sales but I hopefully
this applies that anyone who's working
at a services company or working at a
consumer product because your customer
is usually not you I'm sure the engineer
and so here's an example of what we've
done and we like to do is uh we actually
this is a picture of Romney here who's
actually in the audience one of my
teammates so we actually go to industry
events
said we're an event planning company so
we got to go to lots of events where you
see our customers all the time and we
demo our product in front of them we use
our product with them and so here's a
picture of robbing a couple of our other
teammates just add an event mingling and
here's another one of my favorites it's
it's taking turns on customer support so
I know there's some people from ol arc
around here yeah I love a lark it's it's
always a it's either really funny but
it's well it's really funny to interact
with customers sometimes so I'm just
going to read this out so there's a
customer they just made a diagram and
social tables they open the PDF and
close it out on accident where did it go
she he or she asks and then Jake on my
team says hi there the PDF is probably
still on your computer some sort of
downloads folder I see using google
chrome on windows could you hit ctrl J
for me and then the user says oh my god
it's there what a you know what an
eye-opening experience to see that oh
these people you know aren't actually
that savvy with computers letta love
your products so you need to make sure
that you keep that in mind when you're
building something so thank you a lot
for providing that like day to day
laughter and also making that line 22
customers so I'm sensing like a lot of
kind of like silence here i'm not sure
if it's me or if it's we content but i
really think this is kind of a cool
place to stop for a second and just say
like and hopefully ask if anyone else
out there has any ideas about how
engineers have interacted with the
customers has anyone had like an example
of something they've seen before no one
just strike that on Twitter oh yeah
definitely yeah if they if they tweet at
you and they have a problem or anything
like that definitely
so YouTube videos and then they interact
oh really wow so video response oh
that's great all right yeah so I think
there's there's plenty of things you can
do out there this is just a few but like
going to meet your customers in person
and training them on your product
reading industry blogs in books it's
it's a great way to kind of understand
where your customers are coming from
visiting them and ultimately it's really
just about building relationships with
them so I have a couple customers that
I've just talked to over the last couple
of years and continue to so whenever I
have an idea I just shoot them an email
and ask what do you think about this is
something that you actually have a
problem with and you know I talked about
some of the other things that that I
hope engineers will take some ownership
of and one of those I think that's
really important is project management
so here's an example of a simple project
plan that someone on my team put
together for you know we do this every
once in a while for like bigger projects
it's like you know anything that's going
to take more than a few weeks and so
we've got you know things like yeah
stakeholders here so we've got our head
is just like talking to the customers
again directly I'm figuring out what
their needs are the reason why I think
project project management and having a
project plan done by an engineer is kind
of cool is because you can start
actually going directly into user
stories and proposed architecture going
into sort of design considerations even
from like the front end point of view so
you know what what templating engine are
you going to use or what database tables
do you need these are things that the
engineer really knows best so why not
have them jump in and do that from from
the very beginning of the project I
talked before about engineers and
designers and and I think this is where
like when you talk about user interface
and user experience which is kind of the
next thing that I think engineers can be
good at
I found that design needs visual design
needs tend to be very spiky over time so
when you are releasing a product you
have a lot of design needs you need to
have a lot of thought put it exactly how
it's going to look sort of get a good
baseline of aesthetic out there also
figure out some basic interactions like
drag and drop vs point click or keyboard
based interaction these are things where
designer really needs to spend a ton of
time and your design needs to spend a
ton of time between these major major
iterations and redesigns I think
engineers can go and come in and
actually come up with new features on
their own probably with conjunction of
the designer but this is something that
engineer's can pretty good at if they
pay attention to what they're doing very
closely so they can actually code the UI
of you know if it's just another
functionality another another button
that already has styling they can come
in and figure that out without much help
so I did say that I was going to talk
about some pitfalls and I think there
are really three ones that I can think
of number one how does it scale so i
said i'm part of an engineering team of
five people or startup is not that old
it's about 23 years old and has like 35
employees now that's not that big so how
are you going to take this model and
scale it out number two engineers are
ultimately responsible for executing and
building code so isn't this a lot to ask
for on top of that and number three what
if engineers just don't want to think
about these things so I'll try to answer
them and I actually this is something
that I'm going to say is a work in
progress and I'm learning as I go so
really would love to hear other people's
thoughts afterwards but number one how
does it scale well it comes down to also
great communication I think
communication is one of the things that
I always look for for people that I'm
thinking about hiring on for the team
because when you don't get to have that
much direct interaction with the
customer I think that's going to
naturally happen over time it's going to
get harder your best line of defense
against that is having great
relationships with the other departments
in your company so sales marketing
customer support are the ways are you
know and inside of our company are the
ones that always have a direct line to
the customer in the industry so having
great relationships with those
departments is going to give you the
ability to scale out that that direct
line and another thing that I think this
is actually kind of more standard to be
honest is is dividing my product lines
or customer segments I chose this too I
think there's other ways you can divide
but the point is that you need to divide
and having and have small teams and it's
something we're trying out now where we
have product lines and we have lead
engineer taking on one of the big
project projects and products coming out
and I think that's a good way to scale
as well and then as far as isn't this a
lot to ask for well yeah it is that's
really my answer to that is that yes it
is and that kind of just leads into
number three really so you know
engineers wanted to think about these
things because they have to want to do
it myself included it comes down to
culture comes down to what you stand for
as an engineering team and if you stand
for people who want to make things who
want to start projects from beginning to
end who want to conceptualize and build
those are the people that will do well
in this kind of environment it's not
just taking orders from you know having
a completely mocked up PSD and every
little step along the way spelled out
for you so you know our culture is about
taking chances our culture is about
failing fast and and stretching their
abilities and wanting to talk wanted to
expand I guess what you'd call
your typical day to day engineering role
so just quickly touching on what this
framework means for other functions I
really believe that product managers
designers dedicated QA in this
environment actually have an even
greater potential to to be really high
leverage added added teammates because
you know when you have engineers that
can kind of help out think of help think
of product needs when you have engineers
that can help with UI UX you have
engineers that can test their own code
in each other's code it makes their jobs
more about adding value and business
value and so you can probably have one
designer scale out to to you know work
on multiple product lines for example
and then I just have a flannel talk
because I've been talking basically
about engineers being really cross
functional and I see this kind of
happening down the road even now where
where people can have room to be
cross-functional I think this is
something that I will continue to be a
trend I hope it's a trend and
specifically with people who are not in
engineering roles learning to do basic
engineering like well like
responsibilities I guess so some
examples of this are sales people making
like lead scoring algorithms you can do
this in Salesforce you can figure out
who you need to contact first that takes
a basically I wouldn't really I don't
know if its coding per se but it's it's
thinking in that way mark inators
building pages and unbound this is saved
my team so much time like whenever you
need a new page like it's just going to
look just like last page except it needs
new content so now we have all that
marketing stuff in unbound switch you
just smell it's just you swap it in and
you can change it however you want you
can a be test we don't have to touch it
and it looks good designers can leverage
rapid
typing tools we've been doing this for
our latest mobile app where you can
actually see it work it's not you know
coated and I an objective-c it's not
coded in html5 it's just you clicked a
button and then the next screen unfolds
and you really get a sense of how it's
going to work and then you know even
customer support these days on our team
in our company has the ability to to
send out automated surveys to be able to
code there HTML emails with surveys
built into them which i think is really
great because you know it's them not
needing to rely on us once again so
that's really it for me I wanted to give
this talk as more of a discussion
starter so I would love to talk more
especially those people who kept their
hands up so thank you thank you for
bearing with me and you know it's
getting late I probably some of you
probably got stuck in a rain as well and
got in at 4am so I appreciate the