I work at kins in com I'm in charge of
the development team there we do photo
sharing for private groups and from
there print products we use a lot of
JavaScript but that's not what I'm here
to talk about and this is one of only
two slides I have so we'll get back to
the second one at the end what I would
like to talk about is pervasive computer
literacy so how many people here have
not heard of Alan Kay I don't know who
he is right so Alan Kay he he worked on
the alto which became the inspiration
for the Macintosh he worked on small
talk which beget self which begat
javascript and one of his more famous
quotes perhaps was that the computer
revolution hasn't happened yet I think
during the the dot-com bubble people got
too busy making money to actually make
computers better and we're just getting
back to to where they left off so one of
his uh his inventions that never
actually saw the light of day it was
never a physical invention it was more
of a conceptual one was the dynabook
which was a computer small enough to
carry around that a child could program
and so we're halfway there we've got the
computer that you can you can carry
around easily now how many people have
seen the blog posts and people
complaining that kids these days you
know when I was a kid basic was on every
computer and we learned with peaks and
pokes and we liked it now they they tend
to ignore the fact that there is
programming tools freely available for
every computer that only a download away
at most but more importantly every web
browser is a programming environment
it's just not as easy to bootstrap into
it to sit and write your JavaScript and
have people able to see it and test it
so I wouldn't want to give everyone
basic today I would rather give them
HyperCard or logo or something that
gives them a visual feedback because
kids standards today are more than
seeing hello world on the screen they
want to see moving pictures so I think
we need to get take promote jay s plus
plus and look for a javascript
revolution in teaching and I think tools
like the ACE editor that we saw earlier
tools like jsfiddle that let you test
javascript or easily eloquent j/s which
is a book that includes a console for
testing I think all of these are useful
and important steps but ultimately
programming is hard and expecting people
to program their own systems is
achievable but it's not going to be easy
and the the important thing is to
remember what are the irrelevant details
that we can take out of their way so I
don't talk to you about something that
isn't JavaScript for a moment which is
called scratch scratch is a project from
mi T's lifelong kindergarten program and
it lets you drag and drop and snap
blocks together to write your program
like snapping legos together I have two
children and both of them learn to
program with scratch after trying other
visual programming languages there are
there are several star logo there's a
alice 3d so scratch is easy enough i set
myself a challenge to make a game in an
hour and for that i had to think of what
kind of game you could frighten an hour
and I came up with solo pong so it's
pong in a circle one player and you can
see it's not perfect
so very very simple it also scratch it's
implemented in squeak small talk it has
a Java Runtime so you can upload applets
for your game and there's a whole social
network that's involved with it so I put
my little game up there and people
commented and gave their high scores and
suggestions for improvement and how to
fix the little thing with the ball
getting stuck so unfortunately I can't
run scratch on on my my iPad they
they're rewriting scratch now and
they're rewriting it in flash which
doesn't help me any so what scratch
gives you is readable code so not only
can you snap together building blocks
but my son who learned to program
scratch when he was 6 could download
other people's programs by the time he
was eight but he didn't understand how
they've done and read their code and
make modifications and then upload his
changes so I don't know if you've ever
tried to maintain the code if someone
you've never met but being able to read
someone else's code is huge the other
thing it gives you is you know we've
solved two of the major problems with
programming so we most languages include
array bounds checking to avoid overflow
errors most programming languages that
come out now have garbage collection to
avoid memory leaks well in scratch you
cannot get a syntax error because you
can't assemble the program so that the
syntax is wrong it also has built-in
graphics editor and it's easy to to
create animations and games it supports
sprites supports turtle graphics but it
has very strong limits you can't talk to
the network you can't talk to you can't
have anything persistent and it's made
for children so my son already bumped
into the the limits of this and went on
to a program called gamesalad which lets
you create apps for the iPhone and iPad
and also in the past month he started
programming in JavaScript with Raphael
so now I want to talk to you about what
water bear actually is
so water bear Takes the idea of blocks
and brings them to the web so you can
create a program with the same kind of
snapping and dragging
as in scratch but you can do it no any
web browser right now right now it's
mainly tested in Safari and in well it's
Safari mobile but it will it will work
anywhere I'm not trying to build scratch
with this I'm trying to build a reusable
toolkit for building any language with a
visual component so you can use this to
wrap Python or Ruby or JavaScript and
get the results so one thing that you
can't do with scratches see well how
it's implemented underneath and here
once you have your blocks you can
actually see what code it's going to
generate for those this has a huge
benefit for teaching programming it's
very easy to teach me teach kids how to
drag blocks together and snap them as
again like I mentioned huge build a
benefit for readability for maintaining
existing programs and learning from
programs as a form of literature to read
learn by reading and it's got a bridge
to text based code the other thing is
that you can actually write code now on
your tablet so if you've ever wanted to
just drag and drop code and test things
out with a computer that fits in a bag
easily besides one with the keyboard you
have an option now one of my goals with
water bears to keep it really really
minimal and to work with the web not
against it and i had was tempted several
times to try and make it more and more
like scratch and backed off when I
thought of easier ways to do it that
work with the web the the workspace
which has evolved with the language
because for a visual language you have
to have an ID that's 650 lines of code
Emily including the HTML CSS and
JavaScript the implementation of the
blocks themselves including the drag and
drop which getting networking across the
devices was was one of the harder
problems that's about eight hundred
lines of code HTML CSS and JavaScript
and then the definition of the language
that I have here which is based on on
Rafael library that's another 650 lines
so there are limits to this this system
because it's strongly typed and the
typing is built into the blocks
themselves so you can't drop the wrong
type into a into a block so this is this
block takes two numbers and adds them
together returns the value so you can
you can drop another number Block in
there but you can't drop a boolean block
in it won't let you so there are limits
in the types of programs you can express
with that because we use loosely typed
languages so round-tripping JavaScript
code isn't isn't available in this yet
although I do have some some ideas for
that
another limit is that as scripts grow
they become kind of unwieldy in size
just in the physical real estate of the
screen to see what's going on so one of
the approaches for that is that i'm
going to add blocks that encapsulate
other blocks you make just like defining
a function you'd be able to define a new
block within the scope of the system and
the other the other limitation right now
is that as each block has a fixed number
of arguments so if you water beer right
now is available on github and it has a
website water bear lang com it's not
actually a language it's a tool for
making languages but water bear blocks
for making languages was too long to
register as a URL so the website right
now just drops you straight into this
IDE for for dragging and building
applications I'm going to be adding more
information about how to define a
language how to how to wrap it and how
to extend what's there already and i
thought i'd show you how an actual block
is made so this is the definition of all
the blocks into in water bear right now
and the majority of them are just a
label and a script and each of these are
templates so when it it sees this number
that has a default value and a type it's
going to put an input that only accepts
that value and then the script is also a
template it says whatever block blocks
follow this will be here and the value
from this input will go here and then
just writes that out so it's very easy
to to wrap libraries and to make new
to make new blocks
so uh does anyone here know what a water
bear is yeah crippled so water bear it's
also called a tardy grad or tardigrade
it's a microscopic creature they are the
hardiest creatures on earth no they can
survive vacuum high levels of radiation
heat extremes of heat and cold they're
extremely robust which is where I got
the name for this is that I want this to
be a robust system that can survive
different languages so the future of
water bear includes automatic code
layout so that you can import existing
code and have it shown as blocks I want
you to be able to create new blocks
within the IDE being able to do things
again that you can't do in the
inspiration for this in scratch you
cannot persist things so I'm persistence
right now is is a user generated it will
save your script as you run and it'll
save so it has basic persistence using
the local storage but being able to to
save your own data for your programs for
high scores and things and there are
many types of objects that still need to
be added variables arrays objects
themselves actors and sprites ultimately
i'd like to see this become part of a
form of active content or books can be
written about programming and they can
include bits of of water bear as a
workspace to work through the problems
and being able to have embeddable
scripts that people can reuse
there's a book by cold mindstorms by
Seymour Papert and which he describes a
how children learn and they learn best
by being immersed in an environment and
the only thing that we actually teach
that way is language because we are all
immersed in language all the time what
he envisioned and why he created the
logo programming language was being able
to create worlds that immerse children
in different topics so you could learn
physics by being immersed in a physics
world where you can play with the laws
of physics and see what happens being
immersed in a mathematics world where
you can see why the rules of math are
what they are and what would happen if
they would change being able to create
these worlds and expose them both the
children of up to children of all ages
could be a huge benefit to to learning
and to for a pervasive computer literacy
if you've seen the Khan Academy he's
doing this for for some subjects the
Khan Academy has videos on all sorts of
different subjects and now you can
participate in quizzes within the the
website there so you can learn you know
it's self learning self-directed
learning I just noticed this morning
that John Resig left Mozilla to join the
Khan Academy which is was interesting
and beyond teaching I'm hoping that this
can be a small part of making the world
safe for casual programmers so I
mentioned my son and he's very very
involved in computers he really enjoys
programming he thinks of himself as a
programmer he's ten years old my 14 year
old daughter on the other hand is an
artist she she's working on a novel she
draws she plays guitar she learned
scratch but she's not interested
particularly in programming on the other
hand when she wants to embed a animation
or quiz or something on her on her blog
she turns to scratch codes it up puts it
up there and he's done with it for
another six months so that kind of
casual programming and making that
accessible to people i think is a huge
step forward and I'm hoping that that
water bear can be a small part of of
that that journey
now I've gone through my prepared speech
now was if there are any questions or I
can I can show how the anatomy of the
blocks fit together yes it will yeah
yeah that's that's a hard problem with
JavaScript makes me appreciate the
simplicity of Lisp sometimes but as far
as the structure yes
whatever
I think that yeah we need a mix of
metaphors and tools I don't think that
this is one solution for everything I
think it's approachable for adults there
are other metaphors that that work in
other contexts a lot of image processing
and sound processing tools also have
visual components like pure data or
quartz composer where you you drag lines
to connect inputs to outputs those are
also valuable and they show the flow of
data through a system better than the
blocks on the other hand I think you
know the snapping of blocks together is
one that people just get very
intuitively so yeah I think we need more
than more than one metaphor for sure and
also I think we need to to provide
bridges between them which is why I
added the the text view it's showing you
what the code that gets generated is one
of my one of my earliest experiments
with this was to create a turtle
graphics system where you could drag the
turtle around and it would write the
code out for you and then you could edit
the code to see what it would do so you
could learn by doing directly a direct
manipulation but I think bridging the
textual code representation gives them a
strong learning path are there any other
questions
on the website you can also get to
things like the anatomy of the block
that show how they are generated what
the what goes into each of those blocks
which is helpful if you want to extend
it show you one larger example
so this was I don't yet have this is the
one with where the ball moves so this
was a port of my scratch project I don't
yet have collision detection implemented
so it doesn't actually play yet but it's
a just an example of a larger group of
blocks showing different event captures
so we have when the program starts
create the art position it and then when
when the left and right keys are pressed
to just move it so pretty simple stuff
the other people who who could find this
useful are people who really aren't
attracted to programming for the sake of
programming but like processing you is
designed as programming for artists but
it uses Java syntax which seems to me to
be a little contradictory so wrapping
processing j/s with this we could be a
next step
so now I'll get to slide 2 there aren't
any more questions thanks to chris and
laura for the opportunity thanks to
brian larue for promoting us the scratch
team for building a system worth
imitating and seymour papert now on k
provision and Burt builder saw this on
the the Jays comp website and he's
already building a language using it so
for for bravery and foolhardy pneus my
first early adopter there and if you're
interested in following and finding out
more about water bear water bear lang on
twitter that's where i'll announce
changes and updates Thank You rose take
me home to the place I belong hold the