so all the most of our previous
communication of react we talked about
big ideas like the virtual Dom we
rendering the entire application on
every single date or don't use template
use JavaScript and in this talk I'm not
going to cover those but I'm going to
talk about all the small details about
the API of react that makes it scale to
Facebook engineering so right now we
have more than we have many subs ins we
are component inside of Facebook and
we're really committed to it and this
requires some things you know to make it
scale and so the best way to make the
project the developers more productive
using react has been to minimize the
time to find the root cause of a bug so
ideally we would like to reduce the
number of bugs in our system and so we
can do that one by not making any more
bugs but this is really hard to do and
the second one is to make fixing bugs a
lot easier so this is what we've been
trying to do with react and the way to
do that is first you need to understand
how a bag is being fixed so for example
in this case we have a 2d MVC with one
element but it says two items left so as
obviously a bug
so as a developer you're first going to
try to reproduce the bug and put your
application in that state and then
you're going to want to find the code
that was being used to generate this
number two and so as a web engineer
you're going to right click inspect
element and they're going to see that
and so now at this point they're going
to find some things that's unique for
example the string to do count and
you're going to wrap on your entire code
base and you're going to look for to the
count and you're going to find all the
matches and try to guess which one is
used to generate it and so it usually
works pretty well but it's a bit of a
eaten miss process and sometimes like
you're going to use a component that's
being used like all over the place and
you're going to have to dig more and you
need an intimate understanding of the
code base that you're looking at in
order to debug so in order to make this
part easier we introduced the reactive
tools so if you install this little
Chrome extension then you can click on
the react app and it's going to give you
the react virtual Dom node that was
being used to generate this element and
so in this case they're going to see to
do footer and the interesting thing with
this is at Facebook we uniquely named
all our react components and so you can
look for the file to do footer digest to
find where the code is being executed
and we've got some nice things as well
which is props and state of your
components available on the right and
they'll live editable so you can change
the count completed count and it's going
to level dates so now we found the file
that was being used and this variable
count is the one that value is two and
we want it to be one and so now when I
ask people how do you debug this like oh
what's of your process they're going to
say oh I'm going to use a debugger and I
often look at them look over the
shoulder and I'm like yeah you're not
doing it right like you're lost and it's
not working and there are two
fundamental issues because with that so
the first one is the debugger is forward
in time so you set a breakpoint
somewhere and you go next was as a
developer what you want to do is to find
the places where this variable has been
updated in the past and so you want to
go backward and the second one is the
debugger you're going to execute like
every single line so you can you have
some control you can skip over function
but like it's really limited and if
somehow you screw up and you press run
one more time like you have to repeat
the process like from the start and very
hammering whereas at the developer you
would like to be able to go back only
where this count variable has been
updated and then and if it has been
updated multiple time you're going to go
back and back and back and you can put a
controller plug and we run and see if
this variable as a right value and once
you see yeah once you isolate where the
Prabhavati curl is then you can do your
things and fix the bug and so now that
we understand the process we need to be
able to actually make it faster so the
first type of variable the account can
be is local variable and local variable
are easy to debug because they are
scoped to a function and most of the
time functions are really small like
less one than one and red lines and so
you can just follow up as a developer
and you're going to see why it's not
working and why the assignment is not
good so at the extreme opposite is the
state of your application and if you
don't do anything on your code base to
structure it correctly
the variable can be updated like form
anywhere like your state can be updated
from anywhere and any file in your
system and this makes it very very hard
to go back one step
so with react what we've done is we
scoped the state to a component a react
component this means that if a state
variable of the react component doesn't
have the right value you only have to
look inside of this component to see why
it was broken so but one file is still
quite big and we with react we added
another constraint which is that the
only ways to modify the states is yet
two functions get initial state and
third state and because we added those
constraints you can just control F under
file and look for set state and you're
going to find all the places where the
state has been updated and this in a
couple of seconds so we reduced the
search space from the entire code base
to a couple of lines in your file and
the second type of variable in a reactor
application is props so props are values
that are being passed from your parents
and one of the great property of props
is that they're immutable so you should
never update your props this means that
if the value of your prop is not correct
you just have to look for your parents
for the call site that was being used
but still the call sites if your
component is only being used one or
twice and it's going to be easy but if
it's a core component then you're going
to have a lot of Co sites and one of the
trade
of passing things program it declare
like of passing things and specifying it
is that it's quite viable for example if
you want to pass an element from a
grandparent or a grandparent to a child
then you need all the elements in the
between to know about it and we look
around and there's actually a solution
that for this which is for example in
angular the scope all the values are in
a rigid from your parent and a
grandparent and you're going one parent
so this has a good effect of reducing
the number of code that you have to
write but it also has a very bad effect
which is that if a perhaps is doesn't
have the right value so now you not only
have to check all the co sites but now
all of their code sites and all of their
whole site and all of the echo sites and
at this point you basically lost you
have to search like a large part of your
code base and it's really hard to track
bugs and as a corollary it's also hard
for someone to change evaluate at a very
root level because you've got no idea
was children and grandchildren and want
grandchildren are going to be affected
so in order to write your you in order
to test if you didn't break anything
like you're going to have to check a lot
of files and usually you're not going to
and you're going to introduce bugs so we
decided not to introduce this feature
and instead having a lot being a bit
more boilerplate and again if you're in
a developer tools you can just press up
and you're going to see which parent
components has been called so if you
ended in this setup you can know
instantly the local sites so it's again
shortening the step
so this is for profs and States and we
also introduced something that's very
unique among JavaScript libraries which
is that you can type your probes and for
example in this case the count value is
a number and is if required and active
to the world is a string and we're doing
at runtime to check those types and in
order to understand why it's useful I'm
going to step back and look at languages
in general so we've got basically like
two main families static languages and
dynamic languages and if you see the
evolution of static languages they're
trying to make you write less types for
example in C++ they recently introduced
the Otaki world which lets the compiler
infer the type of the variable for you
so you have to write it and now if you
look at dynamic languages for example
JavaScript and PHP since you don't write
any type by default we want to write
more types and for example JavaScript
introduced typescript and PHP introduced
AK in order to that and the combine the
and they both converge into what I call
a sweet spot which is that you want
types and function arguments and you
want all everything else being n typed
being inferred by the compiler or by
whatever and there are two reasons for
that
sorry and the interesting thing is that
you could you can compare a function to
a component so if you think about a
react component it's like a function
that takes properties and that returns
of your children and so in that in this
case that makes sense to type component
props like languages type function
argument
and their two main reasons to that the
first one is all about documentation
because the interface of your component
is typed this means that you can as a
developer just look at this file and
you're going to see all the type all the
attribute that it that are required and
you can call this component whistles and
the second one is that it prevents the
propagation of errors so for example if
you have a bad variable in one component
and you pass it to another component and
that passes it to another component and
modify a little bit in JavaScript it's
really going to throw and so this bad
value can like propagate very far and at
one point is going to throw and it's
going to be really hard because it's
going to take a lot of ups you know to
go back to the initial issue and so if
you have exit and so if you have
prototypes then you're going to stop the
propagation of those exceptions exactly
when the parent calls a child so you
know directly whenever is going to be
whenever the problem is happening and
you don't have to do those ops and so
all of those like it's it's really
intuitive to if we have you if your goal
is to reduce the time it takes to trace
back where the variables get set
it's very intuitive to do the step that
we've done but someone on Twitter asked
me I don't like JSX and I don't like the
way the react the is constructed and I
want to use jQuery instead and we've had
great success from from the CoffeeScript
community and the closure scope
committee in coming up with new DSL to
write them elements so it's not so
why not using jQuery but in this case as
a fundamental issue with this is that
you never know when a components using
the jQuery way of doing it is completed
and so at any point in time someone can
add an attribute to that component and
what this means it's someone can for
example in this case override the IG
element and at any point in time and
it's very bad for when you're developing
code because now anytime you have a
function call in your code that passes
the element now you have no idea if the
function call is going or not to mutate
the element and so if you want to know
whether it's mutated or not then you've
got to inspect that function and all the
function trees that is using this
element and we've get we've add in the
past a lot of bugs because of this
because someone deep in the call stack
like this modifies the element and it's
really hard to understand why but at the
same time once an element is form it's
very useful in occasions to be able to
modify it and we need to find a way to
do it in a safer way and for this we
introduced the API clone with props and
clone with props takes an element and it
takes new props like new attributes as
going instead of modifying the element
it's going to create a new element with
all the modified properties and you're
going to assign it to a variable and the
very interesting fact with this is that
now you any call sites that wants to
modify this element is going to return
the modified element and so you only
have to look at this specific call side
pattern if you want to see if an element
has been modified or not and
since this pattern is usually the
exception like you trim down a lot of
potential source of bugs in your
application and one of the one other ID
about this is for props and with this
we're using immutable objects and you
might think that immutable object you
can only get benefits from them using a
scale or Lisp but in fact you can also
use the benefits in JavaScript if you
impose that you can modify object and
they have really really good properties
you know also debug elements so in order
to conclude at Facebook we have a motto
which is move move fast and break things
and what it really means is it's okay to
break things but once you discover that
something is broken you want to fix it
as fast as possible and especially you
want to fix it before it goes to prod
and in order to that we want
I was application we want to be able to
fix bugs in a very fast way but we don't
know how to do it fast so what we want
to do is to be predictable and when
fixing a bug there are two main sources
of in predictability so the first one is
finding the root cause so you got a
repro case and how do you find what was
an issue and so with all the steps I
described we can make this a lot faster
and the second one is and so once you
know the root cause then you want to be
able to find a fix and this part is not
usually the hardest part like all the
interviews and all the school like
you're an engineer too so you can get a
problem and your form to find a solution
so we are pretty good at doing this but
then the second inflexibility is what if
your
fix is going to introduce a mess or bug
and so this is a really bad moment for
example if something is severely broken
in production and you want to like
fixing a fix it as soon as possible and
then you come like you learn to fix and
then you trigger something else another
bug and then it triggers another bug and
then you've got to like figure out
another solution and it turns out that
by making finding the root cause faster
and easier you're also making your
application easier to read and also so
if you're doing a modification to
variable it's really easy for you to
trace back how this variable is being
used and therefore it's also harder to
introduce bugs by modifying this
variable without you knowing about it so
this is what I have I hope it was useful