[Music]
so hello everyone I am Mariana as you
can see these are a few versions of my
name where people love typing them the
first one is the correct in case you are
doubting and today I'm gonna share my
story from upper labs hackerspace so
upper laps is actually a physical
community not just an online community
it's a hackerspace if you if you are
familiar with the term you probably know
what I'm going to be talking about it is
a community where we care mostly about
open source projects these are the main
pillars what we send and try to promote
which is open source technologists open
data open technologists under its
alternative licenses for creative works
like music and images and designs and
all of this kind of stuff but how I got
there all started back in 2016 when I
was on my second year on my University
my bachelor set is at that time in March
a friend of mine called me and told me
that in two months in May at the time a
conference is going to happen a
conference which is called Oscar open
source conference Sylvania and they are
looking for volunteers most of the
volunteers usually our students and then
asked her why should I go there why
should I spend my weekend helping you
know a conference I had never been to
one that's true so I followed her advice
I attended the conference I stay there
for two days I met a lot of people from
different countries who knew a lot of
stuff different kind of stuff and I
realized that tech is so diverse on its
own not only the people that
says it but also of trying to find what
she liked the most for some of our
people that are coding other that like
system and administration design and
even people who are like more into them
this marketing part there are more
people's person I am NOT I hate public
speaking as you can see that is a
picture of that day I am somewhere in
the middle three years now back to 2019
and I have learned a lot from this
community because later on of course I
joined them and I kept organizing
smaller events rather than just an
annual conference I have met amazing
people I've had the chance to attend
larger events like this one and made
people like you the most important to me
part is that I have become a little bit
more confident for myself not that I
became more smarter than this than then
I'm the same person but just that the
boost you get from these people and
their kind words make you feel more
comfortable about you and also we share
what you know for sharing your story
like these sessions are you sharing your
knowledge and your experience is what
will make people like me at that time be
in a stage like this
a few years later and you can do that
but many many ways a way that I chose to
reshare what I knew was in January when
I found out about this conferences and
before I apply I shared it with my
community we have an online forum that
is course for him and I said that hey
guys like I saw on Twitter that this
conferences are happening they have some
scholarships a good forum I am a scholar
this year I shared the links
unfortunately the CFP was closed at that
time so I just carried for people who
just wanted to come as guests and attend
the conferences
so not only meals and other girls
applied for the conference and that was
my right way of saying thank you to
these people for everything that I have
done for me and probably give back
something to them that is all for me
thank you