you
so I'm Richard this is Daniel and the
wig we took out the circuit breaker
pattern in JavaScript and it's the same
before we probably could have done a
better job of titling this because
unless you know what a circuit breaker
pattern is you it might not be obvious
but it's essentially a way to isolate
communication between web services in a
distributed system so go back a little
way
Yama's started as a pretty standard
rails app but as we start to scale our
project and add features we found that
we hit skating problems pretty soon so
he needs to rethink parts of our
architecture we started by extracting
messaging service called fede which we
built on the JVM so one of the first
game cross we hit was with our how he's
storing messages we actually got to over
a billion rows in Postgres in our
message table so we clearly need to
rethink how we did this and we
implemented fede but to represent a
scalable representation of conversations
using just the message IDs and then the
actual content of the messages was
stored in rails still so whilst that
didn't change things that much moving
this stuff out into a separate service
and a separate data store allow us to
dramatically reduce the load on our
rails app and also reduce the amount of
stuff we need to store in our Postgres
database so fitti worked really well and
as we have continued to scale our system
and add new features we've essentially
fought that same approach so we now have
over 20 services say things like farvel
which is our upload service mug shot
which resizes images paddy which is a
like collaborative editor thing and this
is provide us with quite a few benefits
so the most obvious one probably is
being able to horizontally scale each
service independently so we need to add
capacity for fede we can do that really
easily without increasing capacity over
the whole system it's also nice to
separate concerns so understanding what
each service does is much easier as it's
a separate code base then it would be if
it was part of the like one massive
repository and it's also much easier to
deploy these things so if we make a
change to mug shot we can
deploy that one service without having
to take the risk of deploying the entire
system and finally it also improves the
full torrents of Yama so if one service
goes down ideally at least it shouldn't
bring other things down with it it
should be separated whereas if you have
a single app then that's a single point
of failure and if that goes down then
there's not very much you can do by
separating things out into different
services it's allowed us to degrade
gracefully when things go wrong so this
is a little out of date actually but it
gives you a rough idea of what our
architecture looks like and it also show
you some of the problems with this so
whilst building things in a
service-oriented ways give us a lot
benefits it does it does definitely
increase the complexity of the system as
a whole
so each service is easier to understand
but that largely just pushes stuff out
into complications with how things
communicate with each other and how
those services are coordinated
maintaining API contracts is also much
more difficult because you might make a
change in one part of the system and it
will have very big profound problems in
other parts system that you weren't
aware would would be affected and this
also relates to debugging so when you
get a bug reports tracing those symptoms
back to the actual root cause is far
more difficult because instead of it
being due to a nicely isolated part of
the system is usually a result of lots
of things interacting together and
causing a problem and then finally
handling failing dependencies really
needs to be thought of upfront so the
fault tolerance I mentioned on the
previous slide doesn't really come for
free you've got to think about how to
handle the dependencies of each service
when they go down because if you don't
that will also bring your own service
down and they'll potentially cascade to
the rest of the system so to look at
this in a bit more detail we're going to
take a look at our completely service
which is our web service for providing
autocomplete results so if you pass the
name Bob it would turn all of the Bob's
in your network but on a large network
that could be hundreds of names and we
don't want a force I use
to search through that list so we use
another service called pranky which rec
which ranks things in relation to you so
completely uses this to sort its list
based on how likely you are to want to
come to that person and then passes back
the most ten or like ten or twenty most
relevant users but with this pattern if
Frankie goes down then if we don't think
about this at all and that's also going
to bring down completing if it fails
quickly with a 500 error we can at least
handle the error normally and continue
on
but if prank is just unavailable then
the request is lighters timeout which
means we'll have to wait for that to
complete before we can pass any
information back to the user and we also
need to do this every time so every time
complete it makes a request to Frankie
even if we know that's likely to timeout
we still need to make that call and wait
for it to fail before we can actually
continue and worse than that if anything
actually relies on completely then this
latency could cause failures which then
start to cascade through the rest of the
system so one way of dealing with this
is the circuit breaker pattern circuit
breaker pattern monsters requests being
made between services and records any
errors that are thrown and if enough
errors a throne to go over a specified
error threshold then the circuit breaker
is broken at that point or requests a
short-circuit didn't don't actually get
passed on to the service we then allow
periodic retries to test the current
health of the system so we don't want to
permanently disable a feature for
example so in our example the circuit
breaker was sit between completing and
pranking and as long as these requests
are successful they'll just get passed
through you as normal but if Frankie
goes down then it will let a few more
requests through but it will record
those as errors and once enough errors
have come through it will go over the
error threshold and it will open the
circuit breaker so at that point it will
short-circuit the requests and they
won't actually get passed on to Frankie
this allows completed to fail fast and
not wait for timeouts to occur and you
can actually then specify fallback which
will happen in that case
so in completely sense it will
just return the unsorted list of results
which obviously isn't as good as
returning more relevant results but at
least means that our application can
continue to function in some way when
there's a failure in part of our system
it'll just have some other benefits they
burst and they were handling in that you
can report when a circuit breaker is
opened and then logs out somewhere so
you can get idea of when your system is
facing problems and it also prevents you
from hammering the same service when
it's already down which will make it far
more difficult to recover when there is
a problem so we use hysterics on our
back-end services which is a Java
library built by Netflix there's a few
really good blog post about how its work
and the documentation is really great so
it's free easy to see what it's doing it
also has a sister project which provides
the real-time dashboards so this will
log when any circuit breakers are opened
and you can see that here and monitor
any problems you might have with your
application but we like client side
calls in our application in our example
sorry the completed services in yet ever
called from the browser and if
completely goes down then we're going to
face the same kind of problems that you
would did when Frankie went down we'll
have timeouts delaying user interaction
and we won't actually know that
completey has gone down potentially if
it's in a recoverable State so we really
need something to sit between browser
requests and completing to monitor
request going through recalls any errors
that happen and then deal with that case
when it does so we've essentially
implemented hysterics in the browser or
at least a simplified version of it and
release that github so Daniels going to
talk a bit more about the specifics of
that right so our implementation is
pretty similar to what hystrix is doing
in the Java side of things what we do is
we keep track of the results of every
command that gets executed through the
circuit breaker so we know the number of
successes failures timeouts and short
circuits which are commands that failed
because the circuit was open and we only
keep track of these results for a
certain amount of time which we call the
window which in our example is 10
seconds we divided the window into
buckets in this case into ten buckets so
we have each bucket containing one
second of command executions what
happens is that every second an old
bucket rolls off the window and the new
bucket rolls in so we're only keeping
track of the last 10 seconds of
executions the values in these buckets
determine if the circuit breaker is open
or closed so what we do is after every
command we calculate the percentage of
failed requests so we sum up the
failures and timeouts and divide it by
the total number of executions and that
gives us the error percentage if the
error percentage is under a certain
threshold which may be 50% so if the
error percentage is under 50% then we
let the circuit breaker closed and
commands execute normally but if the
error percentage is over the threshold
then the circuit breaker will open and
any commands that come after this one
will fail instantly but the service may
recover at some point so every once in a
while we have to check the status of the
service somehow what we do is after the
circuit breaker has opened we let we
wait for one full window so in our
example that was 10 seconds so we wait
for 10 seconds and then we let a single
command execute if the service is still
down and the command fails then the
circuit breaker will remain open but if
the service has recovered and the
command executed successfully then the
circuit breaker will become closed and
any commands that come after this one
will execute normally the API is really
straightforward
so you just instantiate a new circuit
breaker for your service here we have
completely breaker and we pass the
necessary configuration so here we're
saying that the length of the window is
10 seconds we're dividing that window
into 10 buckets we're also saying that
the timeout duration is 3
seconds which I'll explain in the next
slide we're also setting the error
threshold to 50% so when we calculate
the error percentage for a window if
it's over this threshold then the
circuit breaker will open and we're also
setting a volume threshold which is the
minimum number of commands that have to
execute before we start calculating
stats and why is this even necessary
well imagine if you instantiate a new
circuit breaker and the first command
that you execute happens to fail then
you would have a one hundred percent
error rate and the circuit breaker would
open immediately so you want to avoid
that situation and that's why we have
the volume threshold we wait for in this
example five commands to execute and
then we start calculating the stats so
now we have our circuit breaker and we
want to run commands through it a
command is just a function which
receives a success and a failure
callback and you can do whatever you
need to do inside that function and then
you just need to notify the circuit
breaker of the result so here we're
calling completely results which is
probably making an ajax request
if the request is successful we call the
success callback if it fails we call the
failure callback and this is where the
timeout comes into play if neither the
success nor the failure callbacks are
called after three seconds then we flag
this command as a timeout so we have our
command to run it through the circuit
breaker we just call breaker that run
and we pass the command we can also pass
an optional second parameter which is
the fallback which only gets executed if
the circuit breaker is open so if the
circuit has broken it keeps the command
execution and invokes the fallback
directly in the fallback you can call
some other service or maybe let the user
know that the system is in a Down State
and after the command has run we update
the statistics and set the state of the
circuit breaker to be open or closed and
that's it really it's pretty simple
all right so in summary circuit breakers
allow you to fail fast when there's a
problem and degrade gracefully to other
solutions they can prevent failures
cascading through your the rest of your
system so you isolate points of
communication to prevent problems going
through to other services and they let
you discover any problems early and
allow you to more easily recover when
they do happen and that's it so yeah
give any questions or that trip pretty
cool
sitting beside Brian here and he had a
question can you go back to that diagram
of services that you have on your slides
is nothing connected to Wario because
he's a jerk
what is why are you I think it's only
accessed by the browser right let's say
it doesn't appear never fails yeah
already exists in the browser sounds
about right
any other questions oh we're five
minutes late really no no we're breaking
until four I think so we got a shitload
of time I'm basically just eating time
right now cool all right thanks guys
we'll be back at 4:00