good afternoon okay we start now because
we have somebody waiting for the first
session so good afternoon as a very
short introduction to the work and a
torque today I would like to introduce
you to two later a number that are as a
root of our visit in Berlin today which
are for the body is making since a very
long time software programming software
in client server and desktop environment
with a consistent philosophy which is
developing simple pragmatic predictive
tools to develop and deploy business
application so body is a small large
software company we are based in Paris
but represented all over the world and
we address small medium sized businesses
of course we we have since many years
many web in web tools integrated in our
suite but one year ago we started
thinking but our knowledge our way of
work could bring an added value in the
pure web development area so we started
a new laboratory project which name is
Wakanda so what kinda I would have loved
to present you a new superhero because
we will have all of us super arrow but
in actually work and either is an
existing term in the Marvel Universe but
I'm very sorry it's it's a pure
coincidence and actually Wakanda we
chose this name because in the shoe
language it means in a magic and it's a
property it's a qualification for beings
things and butter
having internal magic power and we
thought it was a good a good
correspondence fitting with our goal and
the way we consider the the programming
activity so we started to build we built
a narrow ND team led by Lori Bhatia with
the funder of 4G actually and it's a
dedicated team which has been working in
the latest number of months on the
project is still continuing and today
it's a very first time we present the
project as it is today and so we are
very honored and excited about that to
get your feedback so i will let
introduce you to Alex on moco that will
show you some cool feature about what
kinda thank you hi I'm Alexandra ago I
was very excited when for they contacted
me to say we want to make a new web
application maker ok we want in our
magic oh nice very good and how can we
do that so I was very happy to see also
that we share the impression that
javascript is a powerful language it
it's very good for and very flexible and
it started being more and more powerful
the engines just show us that the
growing up and they don't have to be
jealous to other languages so this is a
short map of all we we imagined web
applications development of web
applications what do we need so we will
present to the server side where all we
worked on the server we will present you
although I will
the communication or we wanted to
enhance the communication level and oh
it can be binded to existing objects
frameworks and always the the way we see
all this widget could be improved upon
query seems like that we I will also be
able to show you or give you a small
picture of some web tools we all need
some web tools we never used for your
bag or things like that and I'm sorry
but the wacondah studio I will just
expose what is being implementing inside
but I can show it to you so what do you
did we imagine for the back on the
studio we think about when you are
building an application the first thing
its conception you have to make the
construction of your business model so
how do you design it with different
administration and conception tools
after there is another layer which is an
improvement with code with things like
that and after the with deployment so up
to optimize you optimize your your
application with caching mini feeling
she sings a good so another point when
you build for web application you have a
server you need to administrate it and
it's not the same well yeah it's not the
same capacity we are asking to an
administrator or to a developer or to
business model maker so we wanted it to
me to be very simple with the basic
things anybody could require you can go
to throw the settings and fix advantage
see advantage settings if you need but
you have directly quick dashboard and a
Miss
oops then another thing we always about
it's about testing we must test our
application if we want it to if we don't
want to have performance issue or
security issue and if you we don't want
our we all fear the bed so you need
testing we used about it for JavaScript
for when developing functions we say
okay tdd test drive and development it's
good but sometimes we were a bit we are
some programs because we didn't detect
it where it came from or between server
client communication so we wanted to
provide an easy way to make
communication testing so this tool allow
you to allow you to create a test case
on the HTTP layer once you build your
task a to generate a JavaScript code you
can just customize with what you require
what you want to get what you n turn to
what you expect to receive and then you
have a test fit they begin so the scary
part you we find some debugging tool in
web development it sees your own server
side on client side we have Firebug okay
and between it's not an easy way to to
see welcome weather back come from this
was we make communication layer testing
tools so in the same spirit we made
debugging tools remotely so you can ask
and make a step-by-step execution on
server side form the client and the
other side should be available to we
looked about existing protocols we just
we started to make our own
protocol but after we looked for those
it's working it's not very end it very
very good looking but it's working so it
will be implementing in the studio and
we want to implement it also in the
Firebug console then web services web
services most people think immediately
to soap it's good because now we start
to add about West web services which is
I think very more powerful and more
adapted for also HTTP but sometimes it's
easy to think just I call the function
so an easy way and the simple
communication layer it's json-rpc it's a
bit like a similar pc but with a json
lightweight and the protocol is really
simple but how to make it simple for
generate these functions and to use
these functions so we just want to say I
created simple function with access to
the database or to anything and I want
it to be used correctly by the client
and easily to the clay so I can provide
different kind of a firm and formations
like GS doc and also i can give more
complicated information with json schema
it works too so this information will be
used by the server to control the
parameters it received before executing
the function and on the client side
first we will say ok I want functions
which ones where will I put my functions
we all know that it's not good to have
it in the global area
so I can specify some native space this
is just one way to say we are one
functions and which functions i want you
can specify it in a JSON configuration
file and you can specify directly in
jazz in Java scripts out but we found
that an easy way when you are developing
to say okay I would just test it and
when you are in for a prediction mod
also you can add and they read some
things like that and make some other
configurations like okay the beginning
God yes no and this is flick HTML
compliant then we just said I want it in
the custom admin named face and which
method i want i can use it directly it's
working no program i can use it
synchronously I synchronously specifying
understand I'm sure you you know how it
works hello dr. Donna tree and a this is
only form well the the methods I asked
before but what if in a specific case I
want to use the method I didn't declare
you can just call some on-the-fly method
on your own server on on other servers
squirrelfish yes we had to choose a
JavaScript engine and we really believe
this is one of the fastest if not the
fastest we just so we just look too
different possibilities why no wasn't
the more performance so I think this is
a good choice and we will be able to go
very far with that come on Jess yes if
we want to use server side JavaScript
and to make it really big matic we have
to to have a common interface with
different and giants and we
difference of assigned and presentations
so 40 is really following it very near
and we will make what we can do with the
time we have because we are a small team
to to make it the more adapted the more
conformant and to provide some knowledge
so one of my specificities it's the HTTP
so I made a big screen a big spreadsheet
comparing the different HTTP interfaces
on the different application of
server-side JavaScript so I hope this
will help to other the good way the best
way to endure the HTTP web prices and
something I very care about its HTTP as
a lot of thing to offer to us and most
of them are not really exploited so I
observe with a good Antipas we can be
better things so after one of the good
the the best capacities of the 40
company it's the database it's working
with the database since a long time it's
an improved data bus it's working in a I
think thousand applications so it's yes
64 violin even a Unicode audio would
attend from that and what about it this
is relational database you can be used
to make SQL request but if you are in
javascript javascript interpreter is on
the same level than the SQL interpreter
this is a very important part you don't
have to generate and we don't generate
SQL queries the javascript is
interpreted directly on the database
layer
so you can ask for tables cause the
employee regards you can get it but this
is just for administration if you want
to make the cut for your application you
will ask for the entity level on TT
model level so i don't know if you are
aware about auntie T models it's a bit a
business abstraction so you can have
direct access to automatically generated
and GT models on the existing tables
it's very undie to start and you can
extend it and make it more hierarchical
and more more business view yeah more
usable you don't have to care about
relations and XE things like that you
are on the business layer so or do we
use it the JavaScript as access to an
object logit logic excuse me so you can
call employees but this is not the same
this one I call an employee entity model
so this is really i attribute i am
working on native object so I as i said
we directly by need to the database we
don't have to care about requests we we
are directly working on the data so this
is just an example so i can specify some
filters i can drop the item i received i
can ask Oh get work location about this
employee object this employee as a
company attribute that you don't have to
make much work i could have written
directly that i don't have to make
functions for that but if you want so i
will have an address object with its
attributes it can be recursive that it's
not a problem wanting to
to understand its attributes are objects
like you are used in JavaScript so it
can be strings it can be integrals but
it can be author on TT models it's quite
the same for the for the engine so the
REST API as we said JavaScript interface
is on the same level than the SQL one
sits it's the same thing for the HTTP
level but we didn't bind HTTP directly
to the world a chevelle model well it
was not we didn't find it very
interesting so a good point about the
MTT model it's it makes it very easy to
consider your data as resources as we
need it for West service so you can get
it you can delete it we are working on
resources and it's your fleet sorry for
I have difficulties to say this well
yeah Hika so you can you could have done
it on a employee name and and go on so I
will try it I will try to show you
two-bit in life so this is a JSON view
of what returns the server so if i go on
my browser i just will refresh it to eat
live ok it this is the catalog so I see
all the available quantity models you
can see some avid little Dora before
this is automatically generated on TT
models on the existing tables the other
ones as the extended entity models you
can just go through i'm using json view
extension for Firebug you can use it
very good I can check just the
description of the on TT model which
attribute it up what kind of type I have
some are more complicated than others
well I will take another example fight
employee yeah you can specify some
constraints because it's a business
logic and on the same way you have the
data you why so I will go to describe an
example this is combs it's some
companies I have an entity set of
companies I just deployed one a good
luck if I Doser ok and you have a
location attribute which is in reality
they failed I its by need to cities and
cities is another entity model I could
have asked it to 12 it directly in the
response and I didn't done it forum for
location but I did it for staff as you
can see the you were avail I said expand
staff ok expand staff all the stuff is
in my response I don't have to generate
another request this is kind of what you
need if you do you need to have very
precise information or do you need to
have all in one request when we are
talking about optimization we know that
sometime request at the cost so you just
have to look what anti fast you are
building and what information you will
need do benchmark then another example
ok just to say we provide this
information in JSON but some clients are
best will use it with very easily just
in XML but not very easily with JSON so
you can access the same informations or
you can access it or you will be able to
access it in an interactive HTML view
so this is an example I will just make a
refresh so you can see what's going on
okay refresh so you see the client is
asking for the catalog which will
describe the model of the UN the entity
will will work on after is looking for
the top 41 the 41st ones so I see the
just 12 okay but I cannot for and what's
going on there is new request then can
be generated and you can see I'm working
on a million of entities so this is easy
to navigate you don't like to say okay
next next act this is kind of
administration view because you you
didn't say okay you want that here I
want that no this is a direct view
interactive view of your data you call
you should you should limit access you
pull your administrator okay then if I
want some information I said this is
yucky ah sorry father damn it I said you
can access to all these tributes and
this is recursive so I just I for the
information
okay I would just a very touch screen so
we will drop that okay and so if I
require for the information it's loading
the staff who are spending even if there
is a lot of entities the the data
provider is filtering it say okay i will
send you in next pages if you need you
just have to ask me when you need it so
we wanted to give an abstraction about
the technical specificities the next
next next okay you don't have to care
you shouldn't have to care about that
you should have an exception layer so we
we put it on the data provider and the
data source is taking advantage about
that so that our solos also have context
so these two widgets because this is
widgets yeah that share the same data
source so you don't have to say I want
to bind this widget to this other widget
no they are binding to one data source
which has the same context that's all
the communication works then
so yes you can do SQL request if you
want we just say it's not a good idea
but if you have an administration hood
for an expert data does on the
relational layer you can give it give
him this access adapters because we want
a platform to be open we want to
interact with other project and we we
don't want to make works that could be a
could have been done better about other
people okay so we will try to provide
your own widget if we sinks if we think
that we didn't find it all the way so we
have to communicate with a lot of people
so adapters must be easy to do so we
made it sums for extra GS jquery we made
some proof of concept for binding or
data provider with a jquery data grid
with a live scoring or salad and we're
working on an adapter for the Yui 3 dot
o the last version we also in talk with
will benefit ejects org and from the
cooks do guys so they run they are
interested in this project so we hope
that you could also be interpreted in it
and if you have some to some products as
I could communicate not only on the
client side ball also with server-side
we we are very open for it so this was
we try to make a quick picture of a lot
of functionalities a lot of things we
are working on so i hope the principal
was understood and you audit the the
specific disease of work under its the
fact we choose a very powerful
script service items I we wanted young I
talked about we noted before we wanted
to focus the development on the business
layer this is very important as I saw
the project working on this focus too
and one of the important thing is no SQL
generation you you shouldn't have to go
through SQL to get the data no this is a
way it can be a good way for for some
administration think so but for the
business view you should be able to
access on on the business layer directly
with the JavaScript Antipas and the same
for on the HTTP level so what do you
have to say more I think we are on the
end and we will have to ask your
feedbacks so unimportant things it's
still a project and there will be a
Developer Preview available at the
beginning of next year so just go and
check if you are interested we also on
Twitter and I hope this was interesting
I've used some questions yes
of oh do it
concurrency
so well the president which is a very
good developer and image that arise so
it was very easy to to bind the
JavaScript engine on the data bus so and
I is the one who made all those on TT
model layer I don't know if I understood
watch the question yes
women's accessing NASA
right we will really cared about this
abstraction of the technical way so
normally on the JavaScript side you
don't have to care about it
good question yes this is a proprietary
server the we have on HTTP server but we
looking for interaction with other
servers to so about also a database
servers about also HTTP servers but
because this is really optimized we will
be we should be able yes to communicate
with others but you won't have this
optimization so we will try to make it
the best we can but it will be difficult
to as the same direction because of the
SQL or things like
yes
so I'm styria if you want I can make one
to one de Mo's or things like that and
answer to other Christians you have a
jean michel we can also answer to
questions about the marketing questions
about even what you could think about
thank you thank you