[applause]
Hello there!
First of all
I just want to pay tribute to the organizer of this conference
I think it ’s been a great experience from beginning to end.
and so...
[applause]
Awesome
Hello everyone! My name is Anjana Vakil
I became an English teacher and became a computational linguist
Before turning into a software developer
As I mentioned just now
About six months ago, I knew nothing about functional programming
Just a little knowledge of little Xu
Want to do today
Take you over and see what i have learned
About functional programming with JavaScript
I am not an expert in this area
So this will be my journey of learning with you
Nothing more
In the end, I will try to spare some time to answer some questions
See how you wait
So why am I standing here
Share with you about JavaScript functional programming?
About six months ago, in the fall of 2015
I went to a programming group in New York
Called The Recurse Centre
Its quick promotion
It should be one of the best programming group experiences I have participated in
Is a programming retreat
You can go there to study
Things that are interesting to you in computer science
So i got there
Many people are talking about functional programming
Functional programming, Haskell, Clojure, all these great things
Many people who are using JavaScript are starting to enter nodes
These are some very interesting topics
So I started talking to the people there
Want to know what these things are
So what is functional programming?
This question can be answered in several different ways
First, this is a programming paradigm
Other examples include imperative programming
Like always saying do this and then do that
Object-oriented programming
Maybe many of you have written object-oriented JavaScript
You have objects and they have ways
Then you change them and so on
Functional programming is also a paradigm
Function is king
We will discuss later what this means
This is also a coding style
Organization code
Write code
Project-like style
Not only that, it ’s an accessible mentality
A way of thinking
A way to approach the task
This is also a very interesting trend
There are many popular words
Talking to someone at a pre-meeting or other occasion will make you super popular
I'm just kidding
But this caused a lot of attention
So I think this is very important
To find out why everyone is so excited about it
Why use JavaScript exclusively for functional programming?
I don't know if you have similar experience
Maybe for more experienced JavaScript developers
But when I started learning JavaScript
Some object-oriented programming experience in Java, C-Sharp
Those things
I find object-oriented JavaScript very confusing
How does prototype inheritance work?
A few of you, raise your hands to see
Who has encountered an error, problem or accident
Do something ...
Yeah, right?
I found it really tricky and confusing
So I thought, well, I know I want to learn more about JavaScript
But let me let go of the object
Try to think functionally
May be simpler in some ways
And avoid some of them
Caused an error by binding this to the wrong thing
So at least functional JavaScript is more secure for me
Not so tricky
Easier to debug
But easier to maintain when building projects
We will look at some features later
Will become easy
Moreover, there is already a large developer community
They write JavaScript in a functional style
Many libraries outside
Help you write functional JavaScript
Many people are experts
For example, there is a talk about Ramda in the next room
Someone here can talk to you too
And they probably know more about functional JavaScript than I do
But the point is that there is already a group
So this doesn't necessarily need to be done by yourself
Fighting JavaScript
There are others who support you
And I found it really helpful
Ok
Hope by now i have convinced you
Functional programming is at least fun
And we can use JavaScript to compile
What shall we do?
What does it mean?
This is the question i am asking myself
Most important
Maybe it sounds tautological or obvious
In functional programming
You will want to do everything with functions
So we use functions to express everything in the program
Of course, the function is just a
Something that accepts input and gives output
So what we have to think about is
Types of data flow for program input and output
Rather than thinking about objects and their interactions
And how they work
Or compare the imperative steps to the steps on the recipe
Here we are thinking about how to express it all
In terms of functions
Accept input, provide output
for example
This would be a non-functional way to get the text
"Hi, I'm Anjana" appears on the screen
I can assign a variable I call "name"
And store the text "Anjana"
I can say hello, such as "Hi, I am" or "Hello, I am", or something
Then log it to the console
It's an imperative style
Do this first, then do that, then do this other
No function here
We are not expressing this in terms of how inputs are converted to outputs
Maybe a more practical way to do the same
This is a very simple example
Is to define a function called greet
With parameter name
And return a string with "Hi, I am"
To the beginning of the name
For example, if I enter greet
String Anjana
As input
Then I get the output "Hi, I'm Anjana"
This is a way to express this function from a function
OK, so ...
Maybe the main question about functional programming
Is to avoid side effects
Instead, use pure functions
What does that mean?
Side effects are anything a function might do
Not using your input to calculate its output
And return that output
E.g
Printing something on the console is not returning output
It is doing other things
Something on the side of a function
Or if your function uses some globally defined variables
To calculate its output
It doesn't just depend on the input of the function
So that ’s not pure
It gets something from outside the function
And somehow include it in the function's function
That's just a quick explanation of what a pure function is
Can avoid side effects
For more information
There are many articles on Wikipedia about such things
But basically
You want your function to do nothing
Except accepting input, use only that input to
Calculation output
Then return
That is pure
For example, this function
We have a globally defined variable name
Will be used in the function
What you see in this last line
It is used so there is no input
We do not have a name as a parameter to this function
It just reads some information from the global state
That is not pure
The reason it is impure is because
And the return value of this function is not what we care about
We care about doing something
Change the world in some way
Except return value
In this case, print to the console
This is not a pure function
A pure function might look like this
it's here
The only thing that matters for this output
Is its input
The arguments we pass to it
The only thing it has to do is return its output
I seem to say a lot of pure functions
Because at least for me this is really a key thing
A key part of my functional programming
Is to think in the purest way
Another key point is the use of higher-order functions
Therefore, this refers to some functions that can accept other functions as input
A function that can return a function as an output
Basically treat the function itself as an object
They can be passed to other functions
You can have layers of functions in functions
This is the so-called higher-order function
Often appears in functional programming
This is a random example
Suppose we have this function here
makeAdjectifier
We give it an adjective
It actually gives back a function
It doesn't give back strings, numbers or similar
It gives us a function
This will add adjectives to the string you provide
For example, I can use the makeAdjectifier function
Enter "cool"
And get a function that becomes a coolifier
When I pass the string to coolifier
"Cool" will be added to the string
If I write "conference", I get "cool conference"
The concept is that we have a higher-order function
Give back a function
Probably digest this concept
At least for me
One of the keys to being able to write code in a functional style
Because we will see later
We need these higher order functions
To avoid some tricks
We are used to using from other examples
What to learn if you want to integrate functional thinking
For me it's about getting familiar with the concept
it is good
One of the things we want to avoid is
What we are used to doing is iterating
Use something like "for" or "while"
We are used to iterating through a list and performing operations on all items in it
Functional style
We may use higher-order functions, such as Map or Reduce or Filter
Usually as input
Not just a list of ways to do something
But also the function to be applied
For the sake of time, I won't go into details
Map, Reduce and Filter functions
But because of my colleague Khalid, I found
A cool graph, properly interpreting Map and Reduce
Maybe you have seen it before
Everyone, MapReduce sandwich!
The idea here is, suppose you have a list
In this case a bunch of vegetables
Uncut, whole vegetables
There is bread here too
We want to transform the data somehow
For example, we slice the data
We have a "slice" or "cut" or "chop" function
Apply it to every item in the list
I usually make "vegetables for sandwiches"
Complete these
This is chopped
But we will use Map in a functional style
After giving it the list of materials, give the function "chop"
And I will get a new list with all materials already chopped up
Then we have a Reduce function
Basically group all the items in the list together
In this case, layering
To make a delicious sandwich
And Filter
Maybe you hate cucumber
You can have a Filter function
make sure
Only non-cucumber vegetables can pass the filter
This is the way we use these higher order functions
To become familiar with iterations of the type "for" or "while"
What you are used to doing in functional programming
We provide functions to higher-order functions
Such as Map, Reduce and Filter
Get the sandwich we want
To reiterate, this is not a completely clear way of explaining
To explain the operation of Map, Reduce and Filter
But a lot of information on the Internet
We want to use these instead of "for"
Another thing we have to do is
We need to avoid mutation data, avoid mutation
Mutation refers to the placement of a change object
When we have something immutable
I believe many people are familiar with the term
This cannot be changed by data placement
Once set, it will always exist
It will never change
Let's see an example
Because for me
This is another thing that requires a little harder understanding
This is an example of a non-functional mutation
We have a room variable to store the list
"H1", "H2" and "H3"
Because we think the room is like that
At least that's where I thought the room was
It was later discovered that it was not actually "H3" but "H4"
So let's replace the content at index [2] in the room with "H4"
So our room has actually changed
We start with ["H1", "H2", "H3"]
Replaced by ["H1", "H2", "H4"]
It is still stored in the variable "room"
But actually we have changed some placement
And this is avoided by functional programming
Because this can cause a lot of problems
This is one of the reasons why we pay special attention to this
And through such object-oriented methods
Sometimes you can change things in unexpected ways
You thought you were dealing with
If I thought the room meant ["H1", "H2", "H3"]
And I don't know anywhere else in my code
I have replaced something in the array of rooms
I may be in trouble
I may end up introducing errors in the code
And it ’s hard to track them
Because the room here is right
The room there is wrong
what! What happened? What went wrong?
My goodness!
Crying in front of the computer
No, that's just me
So a better way
Is to treat all data as constant and never change
E.g
Even if nothing changes, we still have the wrong room
["H1", "H2", "H3"]
But instead of changing its position
I want to sort out a new room array
Use this map function
Is what we mentioned just now
Where I want to map
I'm adding functions to the map
It will look at each room in the list
If it is "H3"
Ugh! I am missing an = sign
This is the temporary slideshow ...
If the room is "H3", return "H4" instead of "H3"
Otherwise the room prototype is returned
OK, it ’s not important to understand this example
But the point is, once I assign this new room variable
New rooms have correct values ​​should be "H1", "H2" and "H4"
But the room is the same as before
No change at all
This is the same as the room
We will not change it
This is very important for functional programming
As i said
It can help you avoid a lot of trouble and many mistakes
How much time do I have?
it is good
We have some time to talk about persistent data structures
The problem with invariance is
When you treat arrays and things like this as invariant
What you end up doing is making everything
If I want to change a room in this list
I have to make a whole new array
When you deal with small things like this
Maybe it's not a big deal
But as objects grow larger and more complex
This brings efficiency issues
Because if you want to copy everything
Things that haven't even changed
Every time you make a small adjustment
You want to have a new copy
Will cost you a lot of time
Must read everything in the list carefully to copy it
Will eventually take up a lot of space
Maybe once objects start to grow
It will be a problem
One thing that is very popular in the functional world
One way to address these efficiency issues
Is to use persistent data structures
This is what Phil Bagwell introduced theoretically
He wrote a paper called The Ideal Hash Tree
After that I can put a link in the slide
Rich Hickey, Clojure
Data structure implemented using Bagwell's idea
Make Clojure more efficient for these immutable data structures
And these functional operations
it is good
Persistent data structure operation
If you indulge me
I will use this blackboard
We go retro type yes that's happening
it is good
If we have an array with H1, H2, H3
Usually what I do in a variable world is get rid of this
And use H4 instead
But as we said, we want to avoid this
If I copy it into a new array
I copy H1
I copy H2
Then I replaced, instead of copying H3, I put in H4
Great!
But now I have to store two arrays
Took a lot of time
See how long it took me to do all this
Isn't it?
I know you are as unhappy about it as I am
Your expression tells me
Conversely, if we represent this array as a tree
Every leaf node of this tree
Is one of the things I want to save
Maybe one of two or three or even 32 things
If I want to change something
I don't need to replace the entire array
I just need to create a new node, like this H4
I can make a new tree
Repeat H1 and H2 instead
I can use the same thing and just build new nodes
Connect them to this new element
So now I have a data structure containing H1, H2 and H4
But there is no need to rebuild
I only need to change a small part
And reuse the old structure of lists
This concept or theme is called structural sharing
Because we can share some parts with the old and new versions
Allows us to add more efficiently
Change or move things from a vector or array
This can also be used for things like maps, hash maps, etc.
Basically expands the functional programming world
So we do n’t need to waste time
And expensive space
To keep updating our constant data
So, to do this in JavaScript
There are several very popular libraries
I especially like Mori
Show you the link later
It actually uses ClojureScript
Has this kind of data structure
After porting them to JavaScript
Use them directly from JavaScript
it's great
It also has many general-purpose functional programming helpers
Such as Map and Reduce and many other things
There is another popular library called Immutable.js
It was launched by Facebook
Is complete JavaScript
I have no experience myself
But I know many people like it too
Yes so these are
You can try to use immutable data structures
If you feel impatient
I understand
I can feel your excitement yes, great
Ok we continue
If you are ready to try
As I said, we have Mori and Immutable.js
Links to these libraries
There are also many utility libraries
Don't pay too much attention to this persistent data structure
Instead give you a lot of help functions such as Map, Reduce, etc.
For example Underscore, Lodash
Today I discovered that Ramda is one thing
Because a few days ago there was a talk about Ramda
there are more
In fact, Javascript has some built-in functions
For example, arrays have built-in Map, Reduce functions
A few slides ago we saw this room.map
This is because the array prototype has these functions Map, Reduce, etc.
You can even do some functional programming with pure JavaScript
No need to use any libraries
it is good
If you sit there and think
what? I don't understand immutability
Side effects, what about pure functions now
If you want to learn more about all these popular words
Like I said, all these catchy buzzwords
It's the word I've been throwing at you for the past twenty minutes
I highly recommend a good introductory article called
"Introduction to Functional Programming"
Written by Mary Rose Cook
A former promoter at The Recurse Center
Is what I keep mentioning
Link there
But basically this is a very good introduction
Some more depth
Some "commandments" for functional programming
I also mentioned today
If you are a little curious
But it ’s not clear what I mentioned
I highly recommend you take a look
I guess that ’s all for my speech
We should have a few minutes to answer the question
About eight minutes
But first I really want to thank you
My name is Anjana Vakil
Anjana Vakil on Twitter
There is a link to my GitHub
Would love to stay in touch
If anyone is learning
Functional Javascript, newbie like me
Welcome to contact me
Can support each other
I want to thank in particular
JSUnconf Organizer
Especially these diverse sponsors
I was also sponsored
It should not come without a great agenda
And all the sponsors who sponsored these tickets
Special thanks to The Recurse Center
And alumni who helped me learn so much
Including the latter, Khalid
There is another alumni Sal Becker
Think i explained a lot about this
After a lot of conversation at The Recurse Center
If you are interested in spending time
Self-directed educational programming seminar in New York
Be sure to check out recurse.com
Is an amazing group
Ok, that's it, thank you
[applause]
Thank you very much
Yes,_____
Does anyone have any questions about functional programming?
I don't know if I can answer it, but I can try
Yes
Actually, my professors
Always say object-oriented programming
Better than functional programming
I was thinking that would be better
Or do you think we should use
Functional programming on JavaScript only
Or other programming language such as C _____
I think this is a good question
Kind of entered
I think this is a programming paradigm
When I was learning functional programming
I even started to wonder what a programming paradigm was
Why do people argue about them
Why people hate functional programming
We have to do it functionally
Why do n’t people think that functional programming sucks
We need object oriented
I came to the conclusion
No one is better or worse than the others
They just have different advantages and disadvantages
And different situations
They will be the best tools
To solve that problem
For example, if you want to write scripts quickly
I did it quickly on your computer
You may only do it in an imperative way
Do this, then do that, then do another thing
If you don't need to maintain it
Just need it to happen there
Imperative programming is a perfectly legal paradigm
If you want to model real objects
And how they interact
How they work and what you can do
It ’s like modeling, I do n’t know ...
Library book
Or teacher and students
And how they are related to each other
Maybe it makes most sense to consider it in an object-oriented way
Because that's the problem you want to solve
Object is being modeled
Is the origin of this paradigm
But if you want to avoid some of them
That's what i said
When you may have something
Does not involve real objects
It ’s because of what needs to be used
And this brings all kinds of side effects and weird errors
It's hard to track
Then maybe you have to think again
Functions on data
Passing things through multiple functions
And went through various transformations
Not that the data is changing
However based on old input
We are getting new output
Then functional programming might be the way
And it has a lot of points for example
You can break things into small functions that only do one thing
If you want to change something
You don't have to change the structure of the entire class
Just change a small function
That function is responsible for doing what you want to change
I think this has its advantages and disadvantages
Nor would it say that it is better than object-oriented in all cases
But I wouldn't say it is better to target in all cases
It really depends on your situation
It also introduced the programming principles very well.
I used to be a philosophy major, maybe it ’s why
Do you have any other questions?
You mentioned the Map function
And the Map function does not work properly
Then do you mix ...
Previously, I was more familiar with object-oriented programming style
Instead of over-functional
That's pretty cool
Teaching knowledge to test our function
Can also avoid concurrency
Map functions may introduce features
Non-blocking, concurrency and commitment
I do n’t think I am qualified to talk here
I want to leave this question to the audience
Does anyone have a response?
_____
Fight, fight, fight
Just kidding
Kidding i'm just kidding
It will break the rules
_____
I guess it might be a hindrance to the conversation here
But we can discuss outside or in a small room later
[laughter]
Thank you for your opening question
That is a good question
I also want to know the answer
Looking forward to having more communication with you
I guess...
That's it for our speech today
thank you all
thanks again