there are many things in life that I
really enjoy more than good healthy
broken code I mean it's kind of
something that we experience in our day
to day lives all the time there's
nothing that we're ever gonna do to
write 100 percent perfect code it's
inevitable that we're gonna be shipping
things that are broken it's no it's
inevitable that we're gonna have to
debug these things we're gonna be bugs
in my production we're gonna have to you
know do whatever it is that we do to to
fix these things so who am i that light
just got really bright my name is Matt
Roman all I am the lead operations
engineer at discus so first of all does
anybody know what discusses a few people
cool I would like to note that I do not
write JavaScript before discus I am an
operations engineer I got roped into
doing this with a project called sentry
sentry is an error aggregation and an
error logging service it's an open
source project that originally came out
of Python and it has since evolved into
us being able to aggregate exceptions
from Ruby Python Erlang go and
JavaScript so I came onto this thinking
that the JavaScript client at the time
was really really poor and I figured
well this can't actually be that hard I
might as well just go at it and try to
fix all the problems little did I know
that browsers are really really really
terrible at doing these types of things
so kind of before I go into things I
kinda want to kick it off by this little
funny excerpt that I thought of and I
thought of a if exception happens in
production and nobody saw the chrome
debug console did actually happen
this is kind of something that happens
all the time you know we we ship
production code all of our tests pass
things were fine until users start
complaining and we have no idea why this
actually happened we've held this
post-mortem debugging so it for people
that aren't familiar post-mortem
debugging is the concept of an exception
has happened we don't have the
information at the time but we need some
way to figure out what happened and
debug it after after the fact so to go
with post-war debugging ideally we would
like to know that these things happen
before users start complaining to us
that's not a great user experience
people are reporting things are broken
and whatnot we would like to go to stay
on top of these things and know that
these things happen before they have to
tell us the ideal world these things
would be covered by tests right we would
write our tests we would cover every
test case with a TDD the out of
everything and everything would be
perfect and fine
in reality humans are actually really
hard at writing tests and this is due to
a factor a large number of things with
those being we don't know all that we
don't know all the test cases we can't
anticipate that our users are going to
do something really really really stupid
that we didn't think about users gonna
click a button eight million times
thinking that it's not working we didn't
anticipate that that's gonna happen
they're gonna have some crazy
combination of browser extensions and
all this other stuff that who knows what
they're doing a lot of times we actually
don't get tests at all so that's that's
the other side of things we can be as
meticulous as we want and write all
these tests in reality most things
actually don't even have tests so it's
that doesn't help us at all
also QA processes are faulty for
basically the same reason why writing
tests are pretty faulty so there's all
the combinations of browsers QA teams
are expensive you know there's a lot of
different cases you have to test at the
end of the day you're still not going to
do everything that every single user is
going to test users are your best QA
team they're the ones that are gonna
figure out what's broken they're gonna
do they're gonna touch everything that
you didn't even think was possible and a
matter what you do bugs are still going
to get into production
there's just nothing you're gonna
nothing you're gonna be able to do about
it we should just have better tooling to
get around this and deal with these
issues so if you guys work on a product
that users are using if you're fortunate
enough to have customer support or
someone just emails you and says
something's broken typically you get
something like this you get someone
that's angry and irate just says it
doesn't work for me well what do you
want me to do about it so we look at it
and if we're fortunate enough and we
have an actual text savvy user we can
maybe get a screenshot of their chrome
console we can somehow coerce them into
opening this up reproducing the bug and
we can maybe get a screenshot of
something like this this is probably the
best case that we can get out of
post-mortem debugging without doing
anything fancy so it ends up turning
into actually a lot of this it works for
me I'm not gonna fix this because I
don't know how to debug your problem and
your users usually can't give us enough
information to help us fix this how do
we begin to be more proactive about this
I guess at the beginning we want to be
able to say on top of this if we want to
be able to know these things before our
users are actually telling us we don't
want to rely on them doing faulty screen
shots and and all this stuff to tell us
here's what happened we don't want these
reproductions steps we want to actually
see what happened in real time we want
to see what the stack Trace is and all
the information in the context so we
should start capturing arrears and we
start logging as much information
automatically so that we can debug we
can get notified of these errors we can
track these on graphs we can do all this
up this information in real time on
behalf of our users before they start
complaining and telling us that you know
something's broken something start with
the most obvious way of doing this this
is what is my absolute favorite so I'm
sure we're all aware of this window dot
on everything if you're not the TLDR is
the window down earlier is a global
callback that is effectively a try-catch
over your entire application I also like
to call it window dot on nope it's
literally the worst way to capture an
exception that you can imagine
the signature of the callback looks
something like this so it takes three
arguments the first one being a message
the URL of the file that caused the
exception and then the line number in
reality usually end up getting this
cryptic script error message if any of
you have seen that before trying to
debug things I will explain who that is
more detail in a second so kind of the
problem with all of this is that out of
these three arguments that we saw none
of these are an actual error object
they're just a message URL and a line
number so in practice these three
arguments end up looking something like
this
we have some type error we cannot reap
repartee foo of undefined we have the
URL that it happened we have the line
number and a glance this actually looks
really useful we can we can drill under
our code we can see what is line 10 oh
this line you know something was
probably faulty here and we've we may
have solved we may be able to solve the
problem with this but your code is
actually probably minified line 1 is
your entire application you have a
million characters on this one really
really long line also your JavaScript is
likely being hosts on another domain so
we're talking a CDN or some extra sub
domain or a cookie list domain or
something like that the problem with
that is that these these window deny are
subject to cores so for the cross origin
request scripting and what that means is
when it gets the window down or you get
is then shaking is that it's something
like that it's cross-origin something
researcher whatever we're in the end
what this actually means for you as you
get script there so if you have your
JavaScript on a subdomain or a CDN or
something that is it doesn't have the
proper course headers and all this stuff
to go with that when it all right error
does not actually tell you anything it
tells you script there line 0 and an
empty URL you literally no idea what
happened just that something happened
though in newer versions of browsers
specifically gecko 31 in Firefox and
Chrome 28
introducing a more expanded version of
window Don on air and what this looks
like is they've given you two new
argument or two new arguments that are
passed through there's a column number
and then an error object that's passed
through now we have our error object
I've been talking about these error
objects well why are why are they so
important why is this better to work
with an actual the string message why is
this better than that generic type error
well first of all we get a stack trace
from this or we can try to and for those
aren't aware as that curious is just a
record of the function calls up until
this point within the current call stack
so it's a sequence of function calls
you've called a a calls be a calls or B
call C and whatnot down through what
they call as a call stack basically when
you're debugging something if you don't
have a stack curious it makes things
really really difficult it's probably a
little bit more difficult to dig into
the air because you see you can maybe
see that this exception happened at this
line but you don't know how you actually
got to that line you don't know what
function called that function you don't
know the order of events that preceded
that so to explore this we're gonna open
up our favorite executable node and
we're just going to simply throw a new
error the the message wall I'm sure
everybody has seen something like this
this is what comes back when you just
when you just arbitrarily throw and do
not catch an exception so I'm gonna
break down what what these individual
pieces are so the beginning we have the
name so in this case we just threw a
generic error this would also be a type
error or reference error or something
like that
and then we had the message so this
would be that long something is
undefined or whatever earn this case we
just pass the hole and then below that
we have the actual stack trace so we can
break down the stack carries in two
frames so each line of this that curious
gives us a very useful information so we
have a caller this is the function that
was this is the function of that frame
this is the source that that
function was called in so this case was
a venti is the line number of this came
from so line 95 and the column number so
for fun we have we don't have this
property off of the error prototype dot
stack for fun does anybody know what
this the actual type of error dot stack
actually is it is a string probably the
most useless thing that you can get back
from this so the way if you want to
start breaking this apart and you want
to extract the pieces out of it you need
to use a regular expression something
like this and this is also note this is
very specific for a v8 stacktrace so
this is kind of what's this begin to
look like in practice so here I've
written some really bad code we can see
that we have a function show thing this
show thing takes an arbitrary index as
an argument we expect this index to
exist in this arbitrary things array and
we're calling the Foo property on it as
we could probably do you know if we call
it the show thing 1 the result of things
index is going to be undefined and
undefined does not have a property foo
so fire up note again and we want to
actually execute this we will see it
does in fact throw a type error and to
go with that we can see this it's very
useful stack grace so we see that type
error cannot read property blah blah but
then we see right below that we can see
that it was within the show thing
function so within that show thing
function it also tells us exactly what
line number it happened and actually
exactly what column number raised the
exception and then if we keep traversing
down the stack we see line 12 which was
exactly where show thing was called it
had it's an anonymous function so it
doesn't have a name in the call stack we
also note Firefox does something very
drastically different it's the same
concept you still have the stack
property but since it's a string these
things are formatted completely
different so there is no standard around
how these stack traces are formatted so
if we were to write something that
extracted all of these different
components and all of these things for
different browsers
also note this changes per version of
browser so this is not even just all of
firefox this is you know firefox 14
versus firefox 25 versus whatever same
for chrome same for safari all these
things are different formats so if we
were to write something we have to write
a bunch of crazy regular expressions to
capture all of these different cases and
we have to also sort of feature detect
to determine which ones are going to
give us this type of factors now if we
go into minifying our code if we minify
that exact code we could end up with
something like this it should be
relatively possible it's pretty small
but we can see that there minification
we've we've removed all the white space
and we've also shortened our symbol
names so in this case if we look closely
there is a function end this signifies
what show thing was previously so if you
run this again we indeed get the exact
same exception except now we get line 1
call them 125 this now gets a little bit
more complicated to debug and figure out
what's going on right in this case it's
probably still kind of deductible but we
only have basically one function in play
if this was our application this might
actually be column 20,000 we also see in
the stack it happened at function n what
is N there can be multiple ends now
through minification we have no idea
what's what's actually happening here
we're very close at this point this is
how things are shipped in production
usually so something was invented source
maps I'm not sure the exact purpose that
these were been for probably with
CoffeeScript and all this other stuff
but the fact of the matter is we now
have these source maps and these source
maps are it's a map of minified tokens
to portions in the original source so
kind of what this actually means is if
we look at our source map for our window
guess we get our line 1 column 1 25 what
the solace map will tell us that you're
actually looking at line 9 column 30 of
the unknown if I drew on the script and
it will also translate that symbol end
to show thing so now we're kind of
making some progress we could we can
apply
sourcemap - are minified source we see
this exception random exception we're
able to actually get back what we would
have if we weren't running minified
source but the caveat is that source
maps require three three things to
actually be useful one is the file name
obviously the script that is coming from
the line number in the column number
without all three of these pieces of
information a source map is literally
useless there's nothing you could do if
you just have a line number you cannot
you have line one what are you gonna do
with line one and unfortunately call
numbers are actually pretty rare to get
it's getting better
through modern Chrome and Firefox oddly
gives you the column number of the top
frame none of the other frames it only
gives you the top frame don't know why
but that's the way it works
Internet Explorer just good luck no I do
you get terrible things from that window
Nair also has only a line number as we
originally pointed up so if you look at
this line in Firefox so we have one of
our frames we can see that we get
everything except that nice little
column number that we we would like I'm
never gonna explain Internet Explorer
but if you want to have some fun and
torture yourself please feel free to
explore this stuff Internet Explorer
because it's it's it's a it's right also
this this air duh prototype got stack
being a string really really sucks we
need to keep track of all these
different regular expressions we need to
keep track of the evolution of all these
browsers and the bottom line is there is
no standard around this so we can't just
come up with one regular expression that
solves the problem for everybody we have
all this feature detection we have to
determine what version of Firefox to
parse the you know that specific
exception out we just have a mess so v8
came out with something a while ago that
is really really interesting I don't
know if this is necessarily the best
option out there but it's probably by
far the most useful today unfortunately
it's only v8 but they've introduced
what they call is this call site API and
this is similar this is access to these
raw frames so if anyone that has worked
with Python and debugged
actual stack traces in Python in Python
you're able to literally traverse the
frames programmatically we're able to
walk up the tree and within that tree
you're able to access all the local
variables in each of the frames so I can
say what was the previous call which
would be analogous to arguments dot
caller you could walk up this tree and
you could say what functions were in
this scope you can walk up the next tree
or the next frame and you could say what
functions are in this scope and this is
extremely useful so we can see that when
we got into this show thing function we
may see that something was undefined but
we don't know why it was undefined
because we don't have the variable that
was actually passed through we don't
have access to these local variables um
so this call site API is is starting to
head that direction I don't know if the
ability is there to actually do all the
local variables but it's it's getting us
so that we can avoid parsing these stack
traces so what it introduces kind of as
the basics is this error duck prepare
stack trace and this air duck prepare
stack trace is a global call back which
for what it's worth is probably a pretty
terrible idea as well because people
conflict with this what you do with this
is prepare stack curious is you're able
to tell the engine how do you actually
want to parse the stack trace so the
default callback to airdrop prepare
stack trace is what we would see in v8
it's the string representation of what
our frames were but since has been
exposed we can actually use this to our
advantage
we can tell v-8 how to transform these
raw call sight objects into what we want
as the error dot prototype todd stack
property or we can actually not parse
them at all which is actually what we
want to do so this case of a callback
that we passed to air to prepare stack
trees we get two arguments are passed
through the actual error object and then
the frames if we just simply return the
frames from this we have access to the
raw call sight objects error dot stack
is no longer a string
so if we if we want to loop over all of
these frames we have access to these
getter functions like get function name
get line number and get call number and
now we don't with the parse regular
expressions this is a very good step in
the right direction basically this is
probably the only the most useful
information you can get out of it
there's a bunch of other functions you
can get out of it but I think this is at
least heading in the right direction the
problem that we have with the error nut
prepare stack trace is again like I said
because it's a global so if one thing is
trying to do something different with
the tired of prepare stack trace and
you're trying to do something different
you have conflicts so you need to do
this roundabout logic of setting it to
some variable overriding what it is and
inside your callback call this function
to get the functionality but again
because we're accessing this dot stack
off of these errors we get into a lot of
funky race conditions so in practice
this is ends up not being too useful if
you do anything in node and you work
with CoffeeScript coffee syrup is a
really good example they override this
area to prepare stack trace to give you
a better dot stack representation so you
can utilize that one here when you're
debugging what happens is if you try to
inject this you are now conflict in what
they're doing so either you're gonna
break what they're doing or they're
gonna break what you're doing so your
objects are actually are pretty cool so
we have a much better use of these as
opposed to these string stack traces now
how do we actually collect these
differently with this lovely try catch
so very simple we have something like
this we have we have our function we're
calling do stuff and we want to catch
the error and then in our ideal world we
want to log this error and then we want
to rethread the error the reason why
we're wreath rowing the air is because
to us this is an uncaught exception we
don't know how to handle this our
program should not continue executing
after an exception has happens we want
to rethread it until we fix a bug so the
fun part right here is this log error so
once we're able to catch the exception
we're actually able to extract all this
information and do something very very
useful with this with this error object
the track catch is not very very
scalable you it involves you having to
predict where your code is gonna break
you're gonna wrap every function in a
try-catch and hope that you know you
you've actually wrapped the right thing
and if you don't it's gonna bubble back
up to wind it on iron and you're back to
where you were you started with so what
we need to do is we need to wrap
everything so we need to wrap something
in ice what we call in Python is a
decorator but some just have a function
that calls your other function so you
just call this wrap function and pass
the argument of the function you're
actually calling and this would do the
magic for you in a very generic way so
this looks is the only thing we had to
change is this first line we just wrap
our entire outer function with a wrap
there's gonna be some caveats with that
because it obviously is within the
current stack so anything that you call
as an async callback is not going to be
within this stack so you to wrap all of
the your AC callbacks as well in this
wrap so that sounds pretty cumbersome as
well so and the last thing that once a
turn real quick is a century so as I
talked about that I'm a core contributor
century and we have this library to go
along with century called Raven gas so
raven genesis job is to do all these
terrible things for you we do this
through means of monkey patching we
patch libraries we patch into libraries
exception handlers so for example
angular has this global callback which
is effectively their windowed on iron we
inject into all these things and we try
to capture all these things for you and
then we send that along to a server so
we monkey patch we also monkey patch the
native objects so we monkey patch a set
timeout set interval like it gets pretty
obtrusive but it does this job the raven
parses the error reports the information
to the central central server the Sentry
will fetch your source maps and give you
a nice clean view of your error so if
you publish your stuff and you have your
source maps as well we will see the
exception and we say hey here's the
source map let's actually make this
pretty and if your exception has the
line number and the column number we can
actually give you a view that looks
something like this
so this would be a few inside century
and we can see that we had some
exception we can actually see the nice
full stack that you should get if you
were trying to debug this yourself but
the nice thing is that you didn't
actually do this yourself this was
something that a user did this user
invoke this error somehow we get alerted
and we saw this in in century so I'm
kind of calling out that I would like to
help make this stuff better and by this
I mean exception handling in browsers I
would like to see if there's some way to
get standards going on or trying to make
this call site API or something that
makes makes this process better
exception handling should be pretty
simple Python is by far probably the
best example of this in my opinion I
want to help with this process I want to
be involved in Mozilla tickets I want to
help Firefox give to par with how these
things work and I want to understand why
maybe some of these decisions were being
made so the kind of summarize I have a
few references of of these projects I've
talked about so obviously century Raven
Jazz then there was this browser Stax
project that we put together which was
really interesting and what this does is
it uses sauce labs to call to capture a
call stack across every single browser
they support so if you want some laughs
check that out we have iPhones Internet
Explorer every single browser they all
literally do something completely
different
there's also a really nice library
called stacktrace jeaious that helps do
some parsing and do some logic that I've
talked about
zone jeaious is really interesting so
das kind of does a lot of what Raven
Geist does but zone just takes that to
an extreme
it literally monkey patches everything
and gives you these crazy contexts for
so everything so nothing really gets the
window down on it every execution has
its own context that is captured and
then also there's documentation for that
new JavaScript factories API at the call
site API that's it so apparently I was
told that we don't have we don't do
questions any more so someone will
please pull me aside later and I can
talk about this stuff for a really