on a small software firm called
balderdash we do nodejs consulting and
so forth I'm on github on Twitter etc
you can find me if you want to follow
what I'm doing but right now I'm going
to talk about use myself almost as a
case study for like the just totally
ridiculous and crazy career path that
I've had ever since I started
contributing seriously to open sores and
I'm trying to draw some lessons from
that generalize some things and figure
out what I've learned in this process
might be of interest to other people
alright so general outline a program
time going to talk about talk about
myself because I'm up here and I know
most about myself talk about the open
source economy how open source can flow
into an actual profitable lucrative
career and how contributing to that and
injecting yourself into that world can
be a really bad experience I know a lot
of us here contribute open source anyway
but it's it's a good reminder I think in
a good sort of helpful way to inspire
people to contribute more if I can also
convince you they're gonna you're going
to make money doing it three I have some
this this layout right here's is
misleading but 3 i'm actually I have
some questions that I think
introspective type questions that I
think are good to ask yourself as your
sort of sorting out where you want to go
with your career what types of things
are valuable spends of your time and
which things maybe aren't and for how to
actually utilize all of this to make
money or if your profit could be
anything right if you're if you if your
goal is to solve some problem that's
never been so altered or just build some
applicant for your own purposes building
it in a cave by yourself
even if you're going to be the primary
user is not the best way to do it it's
going to be way more fun to go out in
the world and find other people who care
about the same stuff you do so okay this
is the part where I talk about myself I
live in Norfolk Virginia that's
balderdash whoo all right yes that's my
my team back there obligatory clapping
for me we've got an office where real
place we do real things we have a lot of
fun so this is my resume I i bought a
really big book from books-a-million
before I had any money my mom bought it
for me and I convinced because I
convinced her and I had this vague idea
that like C++ was like a thing that the
people were doing in the real world so
I'm like yeah I should just get this
real big book and just like read it and
learn C++ bad idea um I you know I have
a brain probably wasn't able to collect
most of the concepts but I was able to
write little programs that did useless
stuff but it was a fun exercise I went
to college got a CS degree started a
bunch of failed businesses in college
and so then I just left college with an
even more urgent need to make money I'm
really bad a really bad employee um I've
I've learned this myself the hard way uh
and I think I'm like a lot of people
though because I've worked with other
people who were terrible employees for
some reason and because i think we're
developers so we're all hired anyway
right if we don't have a code and your
if any sort of engineering background or
if you learn stuff yourself you can get
a job writing code even if you're
terrible so I think I'm in that category
actually I feel like I'm pretty decent
at writing code but i'm bad at being an
employee about it like being productive
in that environment and I could
contribute open source so I have some
testimonials from some some people I
know
Ryan Quinn fortunately isn't here but um
what like the second month I hired him
he gave me this feedback which if you
want to call it feedback then that's
fine uh but it's it was really
interesting actually because he's like
he literally said this he said you're
actually really terrible at your job
like what are you doing and in n he said
can we hire like a real project manager
who actually knows how to manage
projects because I'd never been he's
right I'd never been a project manager
before and now I'm in position where I'm
managing a business and we have a ton of
different projects so I'm actually
managing multiple things and this was
earlier this year when we were just
getting started and was not very good at
it also my mom every time I tell her
that I quit or get some new job she
she's very supportive I mean she
ultimately doesn't care she just she
doesn't care like oh you're working on
some new thing I'm as long as you like
what you're doing that's that's good
enough for me so these are some things
that people say about me talk about open
source because that's really what this
whole kind of my whole thesis kind of
orbits around open source so first
consulting the this is these are some of
the differences between working for a
traditional kind of software company or
another company where you're at
department in them if you're a
consultant or if your team of
consultants you don't you don't get paid
for showing up you get paid for doing
things you have lots of customers your
customers are your bosses and because
you have lots of them if you don't like
one you can you can get rid of them and
not have to find a new job you just make
less money temporarily that's it's a
nice it's a nice distinction and the
bottom one is important if you start out
a loan which depending on how you if you
if you want to start a business if your
entrepreneurial if you
start some open source project you can
either start alone you can find a group
of people in real life and go that route
but as you become more busy instead of
just working more and trying to be like
the superhero in your company you can
just work the same amount but hire other
people to work with you this is really
cool when you find a project or business
that other people care about it in the
same way you do a good way to to meet
other people that way open source
economy there's some parallels here so
you build up your reputation your
networking your kind of stature your
clout on an open-source land by doing
things that's the same bullet point as
the first one in the consultant one and
when I say consultant I really just mean
like someone who's unemployed but still
makes money I feel like I fall in that
category open source is based on results
you've got to do stuff you commit code
you build some new project you're good
at reviewing other people's
contributions you're good at moderating
discussions in the in the issues things
like that and once you're there enough
and people kind of get used to you and
you meet other people online and then
you can go to conferences like this and
put faces to like github handles and
Twitter handles and so forth that's when
you actually begin to trust people this
isn't really the case when you're trying
to get hired at a company every company
like the interview process at most
companies is just complete voodoo-like
they you know studies show that they
decide whether they want to hire you in
the first 19 seconds or something and
it's just it's terrible so you end up
working with a bunch of people who were
hired in the first 20 seconds of them
seeing you and so like you look like the
person interviewing you right then you
like they're going to mediately like you
more because we're flawed human beings I
already covered the other two things
although the bottom thing is important I
think open source before if you look at
it kind of academically at a really
macro level it looks like this magical
communist
stick sort of symbiotic magic land where
everyone's just doing everything for
free and let's just all build things for
the good of the community and and all
this stuff but if you actually zoom in
and been witness the mechanics of how
everything's working everyone is super
selfish they want to do what they want
to do or they're trying to use it as a
means to some end to make money or to
become famous like if you you know build
some build some open source project with
a gazillion github stars right and
that's like that's like a strange form
of currency in our in our niche of the
world and it's it's pretty cool I mean
everyone is competing there are tons of
competing projects there's no there's
never any there's nowhere on github or
an open-source land nope one project
that rules them all except for maybe
maybe Linux that's sort of the like the
granddaddy of everything three this is
this is like these are some of these are
like banal platitudes just kind of
pointless cliche advice but these guys
are going to flow into some other things
i'm talking about also if you're bad at
stuff you can do it if you want but my
general feeling is that to use another
cliche like catching a falling knife is
painful if if you're going to if you're
going to be swimming upstream or
anything else like that where the odds
are against you don't do them unless you
like really care about them unless
you've gone your whole life like i
really want to do this one thing that
I've never done I've never experienced
and I want to learn it cool go do that
and become not bad at it right if you're
bad at stuff and you're never going to
get a good at it don't waste your time
right focus on things you care about and
things that you love and hopefully the
overlap of things you're good at and
things that you like doing that will
grow over time
I talked about earlier its rich strong
Lee incentivized inside of companies to
try to save the day when other people
won't or can't every business has
problems especially in software where
look nobody really knows what they're
doing it's it's really it's really
enticing to say you know what I'm gonna
I'm going to bite the bullet I'm gonna
stay up on I I'm gonna make our delivery
happen on Monday or whatever i'm going
to stay up over the weekend like guess
what all deadlines are anyway
it at some level of every company
depending you all you have to do is go
up high enough you never reach a point
where the deadline is actually something
important it's just it you just go all
the way and it's everybody making
updates all the whole way there's never
any well we have this delivery has to
happen when these planets align or the
world's going to explode that's never
going to happen deadlines are always
crap so if you're going to stay up all
night to try to help your boss look good
to their boss so that they look it's
it's it's it's all crap all the way down
don't do it because you're doing
yourself a disservice because guess what
you just you just stayed up all night
you made some delivery happen you did
the work of four people in two days and
because you didn't get any sleep first
of all you probably wrote a bunch of
crappy code you're gonna have to
maintain forever and now you've inflated
the expectations of yourself to everyone
around you forever you're screwed you
can never you have to do this all the
time it's it's a it's a bad place to be
it's another kind of vortex right the
imposter vortex something I think I
think we talk about a lot of this
conference which is good I have a
slightly different way of looking at it
though I think that a lot of the popular
lore around imposter syndrome is robots
around you know you you can you can
you're actually really good at what you
do deep down inside you just use don't
realize it and looking at everyone
around you look at them do stuff
you're you're seeing that is a well
they're so successful but I don't feel
that way so I you know I don't know how
to get there to me imposter syndrome is
actually the way I sort of avoid this
whole process is that I decided several
years ago that nobody actually has any
clue what's going on we're all just sort
of stumbling and bumping around in the
world in this like this really thin air
soup that we're all in together it's
keeping us alive and we're just trying
to figure it out right I happen to have
a degree from somewhere and the piece of
paper says like great like you learned a
bunch of stuff good for you but what
that what employers see is oh this
person knows the stuff we need them to
know no nobody knows anything our job is
to figure stuff out it's not to know
what we're doing looking at it that way
I don't feel like an imposter being up
here talking to you about this about all
this stuff because I'm trying to say
that I don't know what I'm doing right
that's that's my goal here and if i can
get up in and make a powerpoint
presentation something called powerpoint
so it's something else about this next
time you you're feeling apprehensive or
blocked by something that's that's
abstract like an emotion or a certain
disposition toward feeling like you
shouldn't start something because why
bother that's this is it's fun just just
do stuff because it's fun and in the
open source world you'll find other
people who want to do the same thing and
care about the same stuff it turns out
that job titles are actually marketing
terms job titles don't confer or convey
expertise or knowledge they're designed
to make people good and not bit like in
do hard work at their jobs right my
first job out of college was working for
a Wall Street firm and have this
interesting interesting take
on how to get productivity out of people
and it wasn't good the mindset is or was
or this isn't general but we heard
people talk about this a lot if you if
you get somebody to work 80 hours a week
for a year then in and get burned out
that's like that sucks right because
then you lose some some valuable person
that knowledge that's been built up over
that year is now going somewhere else
you lose this continuity but to a lot of
managers that's that's fine because for
that year you got two people for one and
they're burnt out there going to leave
something leave and go somewhere else
because what you can find somebody else
who's willing to do that there's this
endless line of people you can always
hire to be superheroes and try to get
that next next job title that next
promotion for like a four percent raise
or whatever probably whatever company
you work for like they have so much
money there's so much money this is this
is America it turns out that that money
is like everywhere except for where it
needs to be like there's tons of it
everywhere except it's not being up like
it's not applied to the right things
it's sitting in you know corporate bank
accounts and all these companies are
just buying Treasuries because they
don't have anywhere to put their money
they're paying it out as dividends and
so forth which is great like if you
should build up your career and buy
socks and 401k and all that but um you
know that'll be good for you but while
you're working there they're
incentivized to pay you as little as
possible while keeping you happy and
feeling important I think the open
source world back to this this
meritocratic mindset of produce results
hang out with people network it's a much
it's much more direct path toward doing
what you're supposed to be doing instead
of playing you know playing some
corporate corporate game this is sort of
how we get there right if we want to do
it we want to do
you could start moonlighting right if
you work somewhere now if you're
unemployed then that's great right you
have you have so much time and freedom
to like peer above all the crap and like
sir billi evaluate these sorts of things
on your own you like look for a job
right so you can you can like pay your
bills and stuff but it's good to stake a
step back and think about what's out
there and realize that open source is
actually a very viable path toward the
type of career I think that a lot of us
want but we're not quite willing to make
the leap right the whole the boats
leaving the dock sort of thing and like
you've got one foot over here and you're
trying to make sure that the boat
doesn't leave but in like and then you
fall in atwater striking that balances
is important commit everything this is
just how how you exist as much as
possible right you want to inflict your
ideas on the world and that sounds like
a violent thing but by putting yourself
out there and by doing logging
everything you do in software if you're
at software developer don't don't hold
back just just commit everything push
everything I wrote some stupid little
thing I wrote some idea paid like list
of ideas that I have well if someone has
the similar ideas you they're going to
google it and find your project and then
start asking you about hey were your
thoughts here can I do this or this like
I think I can do this better can I like
submit a pull request yeah great right
then you find a team sort of naturally
through through the open source
community process who all care about the
same thing that's really cool finding
people who care about the same thing as
you not just having a bunch of people
hired and planted on this team like
coincident to you like geo proximal to
your person it's it's much more magical
maybe I don't know what the word is it's
it's not forced
there's something having having things
naturally arise from like they're like
the great initial conditions as it's
it's it's cool in and of itself having
thing's for sure you can learn to get
along and build rapport with your team
but doing this naturally in open source
finding people who care about the thing
you care about before they're forced to
do it is is really neat so right i
already already mentioned this the point
is important and this goes back to some
of the things i was talking about near
the beginning is don't try to be good at
everything right if you think you're
good at everything you're probably wrong
i'm going to create a huge mess for
everyone around you so just stop dude
stop that right don't try to be a hero
try to be good at things you care about
and by caring about them and by wanting
to improve that's all that matters
you'll get there right if you care about
stuff you don't need to know everything
up front again none of us in this room
or in this building or in this industry
none of us are paid to know stuff before
we're doing it we're paid to figure it
out as we go because nobody nobody knows
how to do this its software it were
engineers engineering stuff we're
building new things if you were already
done we be it wouldn't it wouldn't be
the same right we it wouldn't matter
that we could figure stuff out we being
we'd be some other field this is this is
a kind of a grand izing statement a
little bit don't don't go flip the table
if you do make sure no one's out no one
else is around but video it and put on
YouTube maybe
in the meantime contributing to open
source is fun not everyone has a ton of
time after work to just continue to sit
at your computer and write code but I
think one of the things that we get
sucked into is again I bet very few of
us in here work only 40 hours a week and
most of us don't get paid for those
extra hours you're just giving your
company money by doing that they already
have they have plenty of money that
they're not giving to you so don't
there's any reason for you to feel loyal
in that way unless you really like what
you're doing you know what if you don't
care how much you're getting paid and
you really love it keep going that you
know that's that's what we're focusing
on here is doing what you want to do you
can look for other jobs in the meantime
if you just want to get paid more while
you're doing stuff even if you like what
you're doing go find another job offer
and negotiate it's a it's a great way to
unlock value that's there already but
that you can't quite honored because
you're in some sort of pay band or
whatever your company or if you know
they don't want to give you a raise you
can just leave and go get more money
somewhere else right you'll you'll make
the same sorts of friends that you you
currently have in your current company I
know a lot of us are nervous about
contributing there's this there's this
on Twitter there's this thing called
your first PR your foot pull request
this is how to start getting into github
it looks for pull requests or issues in
github that are accommodating to a
first-time github user or a first time a
new developer or maybe you're not
developing anything oh maybe improving
documentation or something like that
this is a good way to to get started I
recommend if if you're if you're not out
on github
or some other open source community
website take a look at this it's pretty
neat I actually went back and there's
another website is it's like what was
your first pull request ever and I went
in that it was like really nostalgia
standest alg akit was like something
with google web toolkit that I I don't
know I don't know I remember what I did
but man i wish i was over there holy
crap its Twitter exploding they may
announce some other amazing thing this
is my goal right we can all do stuff we
don't know how to do because we lose
track the fact that we do this every day
anyway we're all doing stuff we don't
know how to do I didn't know any of the
words I was going to say up here until
I'm up here right that's that can be
extended to anything right I don't know
what all the code is going to look like
for something I'm gonna build I might
not even know what I'm going to build
but I'm going to work through it both in
my head on paper and then in the
community get that feedback loop started
and just just do stuff right it doesn't
matter if it maybe build something and
nobody uses it right that's that's fine
nothing is a waste of time if you get
practice and you're able to hone your
skills in the meantime that's it is if
you have fun awesome right having fun is
is its own has its own value this is my
last slide by the way I think that if
you're interested in it actually is my
last slide okay making sure I'm gonna go
back to the front if you have questions
about anything i'm on twitter or github
I feel free to contribute to any of my
projects right because again open source
I'm selfish right I want people to
contribute to my stuff and you never
know once you build up this reputation
on github you can start looking at you
you get known right I can
I can look around github and around the
community and around here and take oh
yeah that's you know that's that person
from github and you once you are that
vertex in this social connection that
people are making as they go through out
you know their lives in the career you
become more valuable right opportunities
actually do come from other people it it
matters how hard you work and who you
know so I think in our industry open
source is the best way to leverage that
sort of networking process you don't
want to toil in obscurity and it's good
to get out there and do things that you
know maybe you're not comfortable with
but you'll you'll get there that's it
you can be the CEO of anything you want
especially if you're unqualified makes