so rather than this being a presentation
which you've had a lot of over the
weekend we are the penultimate talk so
we thought we'd do something a little
bit different we're not exactly famous
for any open source libraries or 3d
graphics inflammations and JavaScript
whatever but we have put on a conference
I don't even write code anymore but we
thought we'd do it sort of podcast style
and maybe just be a conversation so at
any stage we have slides and we put
together and we would like to to go
through the slides and that's just to
keep us on track if we get completely
derail but do feel free to derail us
because it's just kind of it's a
conversation so yeah we're gonna kick
anyone's gonna kick us off though so as
Paul said this isn't a technical talk
this is more of a talk about a journey
well that's very personal to Paul and I
sometimes we shared that journey
together and sometimes we kind of went
our separate ways but always kind of
found a road back to each other and on
the journey we met many people around
the world in various communities phrase
open source communities developer
communities some of them are in this
room but all of them in some way kind of
guided us helped us along I helped us to
kind of really travel this personal
journey that we've come through the last
couple years ourselves I helped us to
understand it um so what does i have to
do you guys well we're all really on one
journey of some sort or another and you
know for example we're all here at JS
conf is a journey that you guys are
sharing over the course of the weekend
on his a journey that started back
sometime in 2008 I think in the US and
in a dive bar in arlington virginia
Chris told me earlier on today and and
is a journey that started with an idea
and like like a great piece of open
source code that idea would have been a
iterated on and contributed to by
multiple people over time so if Amon
appears boring to anybody feel free to
Gong him so that we move on to the next
slide you're a prick Heyman is the vice
president of engineering at Engine Yard
his company orchestra was a PHP
Ben platform cloud it was acquired last
year so basically he's better than
everybody here when I met him first he
was developing PHP and I'm pretty sure
he was one of those guys who thought
that javascript and jquery were the same
thing or started with different things
but he did try to make up for his crappy
coding with his personality but i think
his coding was better so sorry so last
week he got awarded the the irish
internet association from that visionary
award and i remember i remember when i
used to like consider the people who won
that award with all but seriously has
inspired me to be a better person for
the last kind of 56 years that I've
known him I set up a co-working space in
Dublin then I am and he was the one that
dived in with complete passion and like
his passion and his ambition is
completely infectious and I really has
driven me over the last few years I just
definitely feel like a stronger person
when I'm around him and I it's been
awesome and he's really picking up when
she was pursued was down and and kind of
brought me down when I was too cocky or
whatever so Heyman is another he's a
great catalyst for ideas and social
change and he's just he's not actually
that bad of a developer i thinks
preciate it well you know i didn't know
this is going to turn into a roast and
so all i have to say is Paul Campbell is
a scholar and a gentleman and I'm proud
to call my friend so take that yeah
people have called fun come from the
pasta being like and stick it in
your pipe being like our wedding so this
this podcast does it worry is called
shocked and shocked is the Irish word
for 47 and why would we choose the
number seven well traditionally
culturally seven has had a significance
around the world you can think
yourselves are various
apples but you know we have lucky number
seven and today indeed is the seventh of
October when key dink I think not we
have seven musical notes and just like
seven musical notes java jazz comp has
its own various associations with seven
so yesterday morning there were seven
songs even though he didn't realize it
Jed had actually prepared a perfect
number of songs coinkydink I think not
indeed there are seven wonders of the
world as there are seven wonders of jazz
calm so we've got a bubble isn't the
bubble amazing we have bacon last year
yeah we had the Russian by the exhibit
eyes it was a if you weren't there you
weren't there so I'm not go into it so
we have we have was his classes that's
the class keyword of course note was
launched at JS conference 2009 if you
weren't there you weren't there and we
have a quadrocopter lead they're pretty
amazing said certainly wonderful and a
magnificent I might live with some beard
hold on
so this I have to say the first time I
met max Ogden I I nearly got down on one
knee and kissed his hand this is a
magnificent example of how to live your
life had to be a man we salute you
worried max speaking of magnificent
there's also the Magnificent Seven of
jas cough yeah malta vulgar Tiffany and
of course the family Williams seriously
that the the j s comfy you hashtag is
just something to behold I mean we are
it's amazing so of course Snow White in
the seven dwarf Sun intern j/s comp has
its own snow white and the seven dwarfs
or show white and there's also gimpy
blankie boozy our brine labu Z Brian
LaRussa Brian the boozy uh Baldy where's
Baldy Yolo uh hi frame and my horse how
could we forget Bob
alright so there's also the seven deadly
sins and shocked is the Irish word for
seven so if you think of this talk as in
a shock béchamel DePaul August amo we
are dressed in our traditional Irish
costumes that we program in every day
top of the barn until yet this podcast
is called the seven sins of Paul and
email so the timeline is six years yeah
we didn't really dig this one true so
just imagine this is next year and yeah
there you go right come on still just
six we start with chapter one pride
pride takes us back to Dublin from maybe
2008 2009 and we was a tech community in
Dublin were quite backward as everything
is in Ireland what the and we
travel there was a group of us traveled
to San Francisco and after we came back
we were inspired to well I wasn't
inspired i was just kind of mainly sore
um so one amongst the number a guy
called anton Mannering he put on a
meet-up called tech Lud am it was a
terrible name I mean but he managed to
attract tens and was either with more
than 100 people at these made up but it
was really great it was it was it was
the first time that we felt that there
was actually something happening in the
community and Ireland and it was so much
it was so bad like that there'd be
people putting out open sore her even
success stories and you'd read about
them in the newspaper and they lived
like an hour away but there was no there
was no way to go meet them is no action
that was the first time that I had ever
done it but what was really interesting
about it was that one of the kind of
entrenched guys who had been running a
different set of meetups he was like all
know these things are damaging I they're
gonna these meetups are gonna be
terrible for our and it's gonna be was
really just protecting his own patch you
know and it turned out that tax code was
amazing and didn't matter that I just
name it didn't matter that it was
in
crouching on this other our alma mater
vs free booze it's pretty much what
Kenny I wasn't very funny so anyway the
lesson that I learned any way from back
then was that Anton did not need
permission to go out and put on this
this meetup he just went and did it he
went booked a bar and he invited some
people and loads of people showed up and
I went but for the first time I met I
thought meet up just a bunch of Irish
people who were putting these things out
there and they just it was really good
and they just turned out to be ordinary
Irish guys you could sit and have a chat
except instead of chatting about
football or whatever you were able to
talk about whether he used imagemagick
to do browser based image compare that
it was just it was brilliant the other
thing I learned to us on nobody really
owns a community and you know the were
people telling him that he couldn't do
it because they owned the community you
know that's just so so
bright-eyed bushy-tailed Paul an emo
very valuable lesson Jesus that's a
great one and to some of the first
chapter a quote from Jeremy asking us
from last year so chapter two and yeah
so um we had a from our point of view we
were we were looking at that the
activity that was happening over in
Silicon Valley and other parts of the
world a lot of activity around startups
around developers in startups round open
source a lot of real world communities
coming together that may have met online
in some way and we didn't we didn't
really experience much of that in Dublin
until this this point and and we were
envious about what else was going on in
another part of the world and so we
wanted to create a bit of that on our
own you gotta understand about Ireland
is that it's it's you know it's four and
a half million people it's it's it's an
island and there's a mentality that
comes with that and wherever you guys
are from maybe you've experienced a
degree that but you know when you're
live in a small population it's it's
very easy for to be told you can't do
stuffins very easy to think that and
well why would we bother going abroad or
to other countries when we have
everything we need here which is you
know it's it's totally at all so what
what what communities international
communities or better water for open
source community service and your neck
sir and yeah so our perspective was
local versus global and we want it to be
among the best or what we thought was
the best and our perspective was limited
to the people we interacted with on on
Twitter and so I guess what I'm saying
is that we had a motivation to go beyond
Ireland and that was actually half the
battle arena and then during this time
we in our notes for preparing we refer
to this period as the trough of despair
because we were putting all this effort
and money and time into trying to build
little companies and things and stuff
didn't really work out that well oh we
were trying to figure it out but in a
trial and error but we we just kept that
he always had time for points are we
were still bright eyed and bushy guess
and to some of this chapter was the
whole package old Irish proverb it's
sure to be grand Paul has a different
perspective on this and I do yeah so the
interesting thing about this phrase is
that everywhere else in the world the
world grand means doing things on a big
scale with massive production values in
Ireland sure grand means Asher just just
run it without test their every grant
you know with me good good good enough
is good enough yeah yeah so we just
wanted we wanted to sort of take it to
the locals and say that we wanted to
compete on an international scale yeah
which takes us to chapter 3 gluttony it
takes back to this fine city from four
years ago known almost I'm we came to
Jay a scarf for the first time I think
was the first conference that we had
traveled to together and it was it was a
life-changing experience and yeah that
sounds really douchey to say but
actually was seriously though I mean I
hope that some of you if you've come
here for the first time and would agree
that it's hard to distill just why it is
I mean maybe it's the talks and maybe
it's the talks that you don't understand
but you know you hope that you'll
understand next year maybe it's the
parties but it really comes down to one
thing I think I understood it most after
the talks when I kind of assimilated
everything and I put out a tweet saying
hey I'm organizing a dinner I think I
said I was organizing on Ruby dinner
because but a few people came and I just
learned this thing that all of these
people these heroes the people that I
revere
as celebrities they watched breaking bad
too and you know what i mean is like it
was just it was just i felt like i was i
was part of a family and where i was
able to talk to talk to these people let
Allah or let alone be in the same room
with them and it really was just those
are really important lesson oh my god
because it's it's so hard when you're
removed and you're from various
communities and you're watching from
afar and you hear enough people being
spoken about on twitter or mentioned
done conferences or whatever it's very
easy for the thing that they're they're
big shots when really it or not they you
know yeah they ship the same color you
do so at that conference i really need
to think about things before saturday at
that conference um Yan said to us of the
on the last night that there was a few
people getting coming to tan from github
and that Yan had just spent five days on
his feet he needed to go to bed but he
needed people to entertain the gate up
guys because he wanted to impress them
so we turned to a bunch of nobody Irish
mocha whatever I'm hilarious I don't
remember it like that so anyway so we
ended up I with the gate up guys and
which was amazing here's a shot of from
7am hover after having not finished um
here's proof that we were actually there
um and
and one of the the phrases that came out
last night as we were learning that
these guys were just people and that we
could actually talk to them and interact
with them was this this lovely request
that Scott from github said to me and it
was just I'd love to come to a fun
conference in Ireland so that night that
night something changed and the seeds
were sown so the next chapter then that
moves go straight into the next chapter
which is lost and it basically started
in a room that following january i guess
and where you going with this well this
is the inception of different so
it was an aim was office and we were
talking we were talking and trying to
figure out what we didn't we scheduled
flunk out for april yeah yeah
twenty-fourth of a pro 2010 24 okay and
so it takes us right up so we said we'd
do it we planned it we put tweet satan
and people bought tickets actually and
yeah and it this is you this is me
alright Jay my name is Ray hey so yeah I
mean we'd never organized a conference
before the only real good example of a
conference we'd ever seen was Jay's conf
I was blown away by the fact that I
turned up to Jay's campana on a Friday
and went home on a on a Sunday and I
didn't have to put my hand on my pocket
for the whole weekend and thought
everything I needed was here and I've
been to a few conferences for but I
don't blew me away and the gen genuine
nature of people just willing to connect
and we be friends you know to form new
friendships I'd never experienced at
conferences before the fact that this
circle table seating arrangement that
you're sitting out right now it was
there at the very first one has been a
consistent team through the whole way
through and it's communal I mean you're
you may be facing this way but your son
at the same table you're not kind of
shoulder to shoulder with somebody or
looking at the back of somebody okay
you're looking at the back of somebody's
head but and the point is that it's is
this is a scenario that's more open to
having a genuine conversation and maybe
making friends and when you make friends
in the industry you never know we're not
go
so we were driving down to the idea was
to put fun kind of on a boss and that we
do a tour of ireland while listening to
people tell stories dokas ages to get on
that idea we were gonna do the
traditional kind of venue and just Paul
was being whining about it and he said
we can't do that and I'm glad he was
pushing banish yeah we do something
different yeah so anyways Tuesday in the
conference is starting on friday we're
like really excited because it's gonna
be it's gotta be funk off like it's
gonna be a good time so next thing we're
we're which I'm then on the radio it's
like a up here you told the icelandic
volcano has erupted where there there
may be interference with flights where
there may be means every single flight
in the entire sky over Europe has been
created and nobody can fly to Ireland I
my response was I sure it'll be
grand so hey Rose says he's like I
wouldn't it be funny if people couldn't
fly to get in the front of one cough and
I'm said I had to be terrible yeah so
that night we decided to postpone the
event like three days before and we
didn't know what to do and the one thing
we didn't do was we didn't panic like we
didn't go oh my god this is gonna be the
worst thing ever it's a complete failure
we've just this thing is just we're
doomed we a few people emailed us and
said they were gonna come anyway we were
like whoa she better do something this
is why i think what i said earlier on a
bed we have different perspectives on
our phrase shirt pocket it'll be grand
as done he gave his perspective but
another way of looking at it is if you
know remain positive and and don't worry
too much sometimes she just worked
itself out so just like Anton had done
in January we we booked a room yeah we
put a bit of our budget to put on the
bar and some of the speakers they flew
in and they came and gave these ad hoc
talks and I think there was about 70
people just showed up and had a good
time we completely put the cold
conference back six months we didn't
have to issue i think we issued one
refund because the disc edgell didn't
work all of the speakers bar one were
able to reschedule and it was just not
it was like I mean this is what we were
faced with
who does that happen to and this is what
we got we got it wasn't a conference it
was doesn't I know it looks like seven
people there but there was actually more
people behind the photographer and that
is a cage that we're standing on so it
definitely was a true case of like it
could have been a complete and utter
disaster but unfun cough kind of put us
on the rail and said okay even though it
wasn't what we had planned that this was
really good we wish let's go ahead and
do it in September yeah and that takes
us to chapter five slow so we didn't
actually do any more organization just
to all the organization trike I tell ya
that the t-shirts were already printed
the venues were all booked they just to
change the bookings the deposits were
paid I was kind of a relaxing couple of
months while we just waited for
September to come up to after April and
it was it was just it was crazy so it
takes us to September from from two
years ago and then this was the first
fun cough and it was a conference on a
bus but the really interesting thing for
me about fun conf was that a lot of what
we did was on waiting we just kind of
wanted to play with the idea of a
conference and we put people all
together for breakfast in a restaurant
and then we put them all on buses
together for speakers and attendees all
together in the buses in the morning we
had an after party which was a very
enclosed self-contained area and it sort
of it it gave this sat up where there
was no fractioning or there was no
distribution everybody was kind of all
together at the same time and and it
created an interest in scenario where
people will be sitting on the bus beside
the CTO of Amazon not realized who he is
and then he you know gets up and gives a
talk and it's like well then then later
they'd be like that guy knew a lot about
AWS for it for an old dude it just it
was just so I mean it was fun like to do
that to kind of from master by with
people and and so the idea was I called
it the trap it was we were trapping
people in this limousine party bus to
them actually and so even though people
were trapped it was quite good fun it
was yeah it was kind of flashing lights
to his music there was a microphone
people
and we put did a great thing that it was
there was no presentation so no actual
screen rant and so people had to rethink
how they actually conveyed ideas so
didn't have the benefit of a big screen
and laptops so we we encourage people to
think about it more like telling a story
rather than giving a presentation and so
not only added to the informal
atmosphere so we put on good food that
was important trap people with drinks on
the buses there's people kind of
enjoying themselves this was the bar
that I described this was the lunch I'm
and that was us I'm doing the first one
as you can probably tell i mean we it
still does have an air of like you'd
notice was our first conference because
we were really there was a degree of
flying by the seat of my pants but the
idea of kind of just shaking up and
not doing things ordinarily like that
was really really infectious and this is
a lovely quote that that happened
afterwards and well this was the
following you but it all came down to
that it all came just put give people
something to talk about and maybe we
could make it work so flying into the
next chapter greed um yeah so just
brings us to sep tember 2011 and phone
come to we've taken some of the lessons
that we learned and we'd picked up a
couple of other things along the way and
we really wanted to kind of one of the
things that I taught phone cam phone
went went pretty well one person came up
to me at the end of the night and said I
was great what are you going to do next
year and I'd already in my head saying
we could just do the same thing every
year and you know people love it but
because you know there was an
expectation in that we need to do
something bigger and better it was like
well what do we do that's bigger and
better I remember the I was in the the
pre-party I think for again Jay a scarf
and I think we had just done fun cuff
yeah and it was the free party and I was
kind of high on being in Berlin and
meeting all the people that we've met
before the previous year and having
since done something I was saying if you
all wouldn't have amazing to put it in a
castle and peaceful the look I would get
would just be yes
it was great it was like as they parse
the idea of being in a castle in the
sides of Ireland and then the
realization that maybe it would happen
like if we can do it in a bus we could
do an apostle and we did and we went on
didn't Castle show photos in a second
and what we really learned is one it can
be done um and there is I did not know
you could rent a castle frantic so I
went and organized the castle while
amons company got acquired and he got
married and I'm oh yeah thanks for
covering my back their paltry Shannon am
and so we put it on and but the thing is
the week before the conference Eamon
came to me with this idea yeah I I don't
know I just subconsciously I thought it
would be great to have juxtaposition of
a DeLorean and a castle with a clan and
a donkey and I wanted a stuffed badger
and no lady smoking a pipe in a deck
chair but I couldn't get one of those
but the guy who got the donkey from me
rang me and he said hey do you want a
llama as well I said what really
you got a llama yeah totally for the
same price yeah if you think they do it
if you've ever seen a bunch of
JavaScript does that developers chasing
a llama down an Avenue so that it
doesn't escape into the dilemma right
away it was nearly blood on the streets
it was it was wasn't being cooperative
the donkey was a stubborn ass uh-huh the
question the back of my rational mind is
why why not and then the excitement was
that is going to happen next week
annotated it was great was good fun and
the idea about pro meaning production
and we see it here all arenas like the
production values here are incredible is
it fun comp is not a professional
conference by any means it includes a
lot of very professional people and
profession PA but what we learned by
kind of asking the right people and as
it happened the people in the castle
works like they were they were royalty
level professional and so the production
value there was amazing the food was
incredible the setting was on the screen
actually took a lot of burden office you
know there's a lot of different scenes
people were come when we realized that
you could put a gig in a dining hall in
a castle and have the most amazing sand
and the moat it was like okay this is we
can actually achieve this and that's Oh
next one look sorry yeah okay
I'm one that's the castle it was just
like wow cool I'm and then leaving this
chapter funk off to a quote from one of
my favorite people in the world so it
was the idea that it didn't have to be
just reinforced and again bring
people to this great venue and just do
make it really comes into the
motivation and this is a big difference
between community organized events and
say professionally designed and curate
events by you know official event
companies is the motivation behind it is
is completely different and I guess
greed is there in both cases so the last
chapter was greed and we wanted we were
greedy because we wanted to bring people
together and build a conference for
ourselves right who do we want to see
talk who do you want to hang out with
right so there's a self interest in
there where is professional event and
conference organizing companies are in
it for the money and so really those
those two motivations are different than
it really shows in the outcome and this
is I doing the reasons why I've always
thought Jay his comp was that and really
a top of its game when it comes to
conferences that the motivation behind
this is one thing and one thing only
community people and that's why it's
awesome okay go next route the final
chapter tiger ha so it's takes us back
to the last month or yes two months ago
night funk alpha 3 and we had said a few
times well there was a few things that
had been said but one of them was we
should keep it to three um why no real
reason it just kind of felt right and
but the other reason was that people had
said the first time how do you top a
boss I was like well easy a castle they
had your dava castle and I said well
people didn't leave but I had been
pitching this idea that maybe we could
have a bunch of people just like this
having lunch round tables and as they
were sitting there they would see
helicopters descending yeah and then
they would say well cool helicopters and
then they would say now you can get into
the helicopters were going on a journey
together I didn't think it was possible
I did not know you could hire a fleet
Ali grabbed one just last day
well it turns out that you can actually
hire helicopters and again why not so
for fun count of three we we wanted to
go all out we wanted to go out with a
band we wanted to go absolutely nuts and
I wanted to do the helicopter idea so
damn bad and the Helena call the
helicopter call was in fact there was a
point where there was a point where we
reckon that if if it would just cost too
much to do it but we we stayed true to
it and like it would not be the same
whatever the hell you got short-selling
update the thinking the thinking of
anybody coming along so fun craft would
be 999 euros yeah am I thinking was I
want to do helicopters I don't care what
it costs out you don't want it if
people want to trust me to do this then
yeah well I'm not that Sean true in the
end the website no funny you guys saw
the website was just a picture of an
island with the question do you trust us
yes or no there was no schedule or
speakers or you know anythin that was it
and when you hit yes you got asked to
pay des neuro and well we we were
successful in selling it and creating a
big enough budget where we could afford
helicopters and then just another quick
thing to say is that we didn't actually
make any money we don't we paid for our
own plenty of tickets yeah and they
weren't cheap so the last thing that we
learned from doing that is that like we
did want to go out with a bang um and
here's a few highlights from funk of
three these were the this was the name
badge like that the we double as a
drinks holder we also kind of decided a
few months beforehand up we're going to
grow at our beers actually Paul decide
about two months ahead of me didn't tell
me suita head start so his beard is way
more impressive than mine still not as
awesome as yours don't like we did the
helicopter thing but the phone call was
funny it was how's it going there I see
you have a helicopter company and would
you be able to bring a hundred nerds to
an island next September and you're mine
was like yeah no problem I didn't know
it did that ease into her later
helicopters and the stage setup we was
with lots of balloons and things with
the great thing about a couple of people
brought their kids you can see and
there's lets jaxon younger those photos
yeah young ridley there is being handed
to his dad Sean
from the helicopter and then that's Tom
presser Warner from github he gave his
talk with his baby strapped it to his
chest baby didn't wake up at all amazing
the cool kid and then just like why not
have a conference in a castle why not
have a conference and have loads of
clips yeah we didn't get the really we
didn't really get the winner that day
but I was like cool um and the idea was
as well at making it the last conference
making it the last one it kind of made
it that bit more special all right i was
a bit sentimental in it lots of people
have said all they'll read don't want to
go next year and I'm like no you won't
it's sorry you missed that chance the
ship or the train has passed or whatever
a helicopter has helicopter has landed
yeah um and it was it was just really
really special to to sit and know that
we didn't have to do it again and that
this was the last one we really put our
absolute awe like it literally if we
could have translated our personalities
into a conference it would have been fun
come through he couldn't have done any
more like there was there was no
resources available to us I've no
regrets i'm happy absolutely and this
was this was all singing i think yeah to
the lads at about it was great um
so this is the philosophy we prefer to
be back to the future din star wars um
go go in how are we on time don't great
two minutes ok cool so to sum up the the
final chapter is this amazing quote and
I'll read it it's what we think or what
we know or what we believe is in the end
of little consequence the only
consequence is what we do so to sum up
we didn't need permission to do anything
is we didn't ask from issuing like we
just said let's go do this and we wanted
to be amongst the best in the world and
we fought too and like we didn't have
any right to be but we just went did it
I'm we weren't netten discovered that if
you ask people things and they usually
respond and it was nice oh it wasn't
that if we asked people it was just they
did respond to me I couldn't believe
like yeah um we didn't panic I should be
granted we just put people in a box and
hope that by bringing good people
together that it would work and it turns
out that it did work really well for us
what so you lock the exits so no one can
leave that's a that's a great one and
pro means production I think another
thing about that is that you don't have
to be in any way professional to have
high production values I think that's
the key there I'd professional has
become used and abused sure but like we
didn't have to be in any way a
professional to do and it was great ah
so are happy to finish so that's pretty
much the end but there's one more thing
so no I started a tradition i think that
the pride of it i started this yessir
i'm the first funcom I we were at a bar
and I went to the bar man he was an old
german dude and I said can still taking
this to the next in labor or the next
day I wanted to get to the next level
and he he again it was that look of
parsing no no no it was the old guy it
was I said it to the old guy he was very
old and again it was his famous it's
amazing away booze you know just
transforms your memories face his face
went quiet as he was parsing what the
next level might be and then he went ok
and he leaned under the day at the table
they pulled out this box and the box was
kumily come rolling is some Canadian
show of hands anybody ever had come
reeling before alright so crumbling is
this weird cross of Jagermeister and sis
custom cough syrup and discos acid
assess Coulson so I led the charge for
the first one there was a local guy
there and said that you cannot buy one
crumbling he was actually the dude who
was asleep in that photograph earlier on
in the presentation you think I we had
his head down here so he says you know I
have one without yet completing the coma
link circle so yeah so 2009 we manage I
came to these we managed to do 50 and
there was barely about 10 was there 2010
you know difficult second album really
was you know we didn't maintain that
record and there was less was there as
well I just want to say I thought that
was enough I don't condone the
continuation of this tradition I think
that has already jumped the shark so I
want to I want to talk about projected
growth this year it's clear data you
know phone come visit the only
partnership that has been abundant
between the two of us he's he's laid his
cards on the table he doesn't want to be
part
tradition anymore I had a to the
things last year really yeah Wow right
too um so anyway look if that's he's
just it's just one more thing so that's
Sam that's pretty much it and this was
in no way photo shopped at all so to sum
up that was just that we've done um
we've learned a fair bit about it but it
doesn't have to mean anything to you or
reflect anything to you it it's just
stuff that we did and we did as a
personal experience yeah we're just
literally buddies having ideas want to
do cool stuff for people right I mean
everything that we've done we did not
fun crafts did not make a single penny
of profit that's that's taking a
positive spin on it but any man those
heading up I wouldn't regret it
for a second I think it was just
definitely the thing I'm most proud of
anything I've done so far I am and it
was great so I run at another conference
this is my other conference it's an
apple compazine Tony yes guy so I've
decided to treat funk off as the
shedding of my puppy fat I do plan on
doing other conferences and it'll is
that little bit less off the wall but
I've taken stuff that I've learned and i
plan to kind of a apply that i think my
favorite lesson is that the pro doesn't
have to be professional it can mean
production values and you don't have to
be snotty to have high productive and
that's what I'm going to take with me
yeah in the future so so my plans for
the future and as Paul mentioned I my
company got acquired by engineered so
I'm VP of engineering there where I lead
a team of 40 very smart people around
the world and my plan is to continue
decide to do that and bring them to a to
new level as far as other conferences
Ivan I'm a very community or orientated
person on I'm definitely going to
continue to visit conferences organized
meetups and try to kick ass as much as
possible and then the final thing that
we definitely agreed that we would we
would say is that if anybody found
anything that we had to say interesting
and once any help or comments or
or advisor literally anything and please
do we're very easy to find just Google
us got good SEO well I'm in competition
with a dead priest I mean in competition
with a a guy who drives a truck and I'm
in competition with a doctor there you
go and finally it's been such a
privilege to be here thank you so much
for your attention when I totally run
over yeah and haul blog or haul group
Malta everybody thank you so much for
having it's like you're listening to us
and it was amazing to be here thanks for