Thank You Alan he's been killing it all
day at the bad jokes it's actually a
really hard art form because these jokes
have to be good enough that we realize
our jokes but bad enough that they're
not better than mine and that's hard to
do
alright so I'm super excited to be here
and to be speaking this time I've been
to one other Cascadia j/s and I wasn't
attendee and it was one of the best
conferences I've ever been to hands down
but first some housekeeping we're not in
Portland we're in Seattle there we go
all right fix that so hello I'm Michael
Ling I'm terrible at talking with myself
so I made this cheesy collage to do that
instead I try to get outdoors and stay
active when I'm not at a computer but
for the most part I fail at that and I'm
just at a computer so this stage here
isn't really my natural habitat
by day I work at this company called
hashey Corp I'm a UI engineer I build
the UI the Nomad UI we have all sorts of
open-source products there but I'm also
a volunteer so on white sand weekends I
volunteer for this organization called
civic and here we have this mission to
make public information public knowledge
basically we think that there's this gap
between information being public and
that information synthesizing has
knowledge available to the people what I
registered 503 C we have two people on
payroll and our process goes something
like this
for six to nine months out of the year
we take about a hundred more volunteers
we work on five different projects
ultimately creating an open API and a
web experience for each one of these so
for this 2018 project season we created
a housing affordability project a
neighborhood development project a
transportation systems project a
disaster resilience project and a local
elections project showing them as an
ordered list like this is kind of
misrepresenting it isn't some sort of
priority queue so really an unordered
list is better but even this kind of
gives this serial idea and we didn't
work on a one after another they were
all done at the same time so this is the
best way to represent this information
okay you may be wondering like how in
the world did we manage to do this and
I'm so glad you asked that
welcome to my talk so I have about seven
lessons that I want to talk about both
successful ones and failures and the
first one is to have an org chart you
have to stay organized to your
contributors need to be organized
at a bargain we have over 100
repositories and over 200 people in our
github board working on over 30
different teams and it gets kind of
chaotic I don't think we do a very good
job but there are lots of examples of
people who have done this honestly
better than we have one example is amber
Jas I think that they've been very
thoughtful in their open governance and
their organization so they have a core
team steering committee and then
additional core teams for these sort of
satellite projects such as ember CLI and
amber data but the key insight here is
that your organization is in network and
networks are graphs and when you're
looking at graphs graph complexity is
measured by the number of edges this is
the part where even though it's a soft
steel stock I have to talk about
computer science so once you get to 50
nodes you actually have a thousand 225
edges if everyone's talking to each
other so instead you reduce that
complexity by eliminating edges by
creating an org chart you do exactly
that but when you're doing this work you
really need to be cognizant of Conway's
law the gist of Conway's law is that
anything you make will show signs of how
that you're organized here's the whole
boy if you want to read it but I like
looking at code instead skip the
documentation and it kind of reads out
something like this first thing you want
to do is create an organization the
system is going to be something that
organization produces and then when that
system has issues you you try to change
things with it but that system still has
issues because the organization is what
you got to change you can also think of
it as this the system is a function of
your organization so to change the
system you need to change the input the
organization being really heavy-handed
here but this is like the
bidirectionality here is a key insight
so in 2016 or we're gonna work chart
looks up like this we had a founder and
we had five projects all reporting to
the founder I had great results
everybody loved what we built teams
worked really efficiently but each
project looked entirely different like
you could you wouldn't realize that it
was the same organization behind every
single one and I put an extremely heavy
burden on this person in charge
so when 2017 would change things look
like this again a founder again five
project teams but now an additional
platform team in an Operations
Coordinator who facilitated
conversations between the platform team
and those product teams that ops
coordinator is actually the room right
now hi Megan
and in 2017 we have more uniform results
which is exactly why we made the org
chart change so that was good we had a
good distribution of responsibilities
but it was inefficient we had the
blocking request going through the
founder and through the ops coordinator
and it sort of incentivized heroes on
the platform team and they became single
points of failure so again in 2018 we
looked at it again and we ended up with
this so now there's the founder side of
the house working with the project teams
and each of these five product teams
also have the mini org chart within it
it's some sort of leadership structure
and the technical platform side of the
house you have the CTO yours truly and
three other three teams underneath me
for DevOps for front-end and for design
again each with their own team lead we
had uniform results which is good we
didn't backslide we still had a good
distribution of responsibilities and it
was more efficient because blocking
requests were now being load-balanced
with these team leads but there was a
lot of management overhead and it
repeated work being done on project
teams so I'm sure again in 2019 we're
gonna change some stuff but you may be
wondering how in the world didn't even
get that many volunteers I mean like
it's really easy for my product make an
org chart it's just me like that's it so
that leads us right into lesson two if
you build it they won't come so we're
surrounded by popular products like this
that have over a hundred thousand stars
and a trillion billion people liking it
and like we call like these engineers
and rockstars and like Kent Dodds has
been on 17 slides today I didn't
actually count but that might actually
be an underestimate so products don't
start out like this they just don't I
had to dig this old react web page out
of the wayback machine because this is
what it looked like when I was first
looking into react it first off the idea
that the react site even needs a page
called why react anymore it's kind of
amusing but this give it five minutes
section is even better just reads react
challenges a lot of conventional wisdom
and at first glance
some of the ideas may seem crazy and
it's just hilarious like not too long
ago they thought their ideas were crazy
and now it seems more crazy to not use
reacts ideas so things can change pretty
quickly just look at this guy
so even the richest man in the world
first had to prove that he could sell
books before he could prove that he
could sell the promise of jobs to the
New York government for billions of
dollars so we all get caught up in
what's called this high insight bias
where we see success and we assume
that's just how it was ever going to be
it's inevitable success happens because
that's a good project and was always
gonna be we forget to see all the hard
work that went in the beginning and that
the risk you take on and the potential
for failure we also get caught up and
this sort of stars phenomenon it's
important to note that that doesn't mean
success our front end probably gets
Civic we have more contributors and
stars which is kind of crazy but it
turns out you can get people interested
in your project without it going viral I
used to think something like this
regrettably the products inevitably
became successful but it's just not true
I mean a bad product is likely not going
to be saved by good marketing but you
just can't rely on word-of-mouth to get
your product out and when it comes to
getting volunteers it takes a special
form of marketing that forum marketing
actually has its own name it's called
recruiting so I want to talk briefly
about some of the tactics sivak does or
has for getting volunteers first we
build a network we have an email signup
pretty bread-and-butter typical
marketing technique to get sort of leads
we also want to leverage existing
networks just by being on Meetup means
that our meetup is going to be
recommended to people in similar ways
and this is a great way to expand a
network we have a lead gen form for
gauging interest in skill levels and
then finally we interview and pitch
these people to get them on teams and I
want to put emphasis on pitching because
often we think of recruiting or
interviewing as a way to challenge a
candidate but when we're challenging
candidates candidates are also
challenging us we want to work places
that are good so we're also judging the
people interviewing us and if you can't
get people behind your mission I'm not
going to join me please fast lesson
three here you need to ask what your
community offers members Dan pink has
this book called Drive where he really
dug into what is motivation and he came
up with these three pillars autonomy
mastery and purpose
I suspect that Dan paint must be pretty
well off because uh money's nowhere on
this slide and it's been my personal
experience at least
that people will put up with a lot
they're being compensated well or even
if they're not being compensated well
but the alternative is no money at all
and the problems that come with that
so vault earrings in this fascinating
place where there's no money component
and we're a company gets some sort of
degree of forgiveness when it comes to
autonomy mastery and purpose
volunteering doesn't people will just
leave let's look at the 2018 org chart
one more time and let's drill into the
front end team we made a dedicated
funding team for the first time in 2018
and as mentioned this is because we
wanted a unified web experience for all
the projects and it makes perfect sense
for the organization and it honestly
came out great but it suffers when it
comes to ball to your motivation do
these people get mastery if you're an
apprentice engineer sure you're writing
code for the first time in a safe
environment with no real consequences
because yeah gonna be fired right for
autonomy
I bet this sort of depends on how well
we were at the tickets but I like to
think that our our individual or our
volunteers can surprise us and kind of
go off the beaten path and for purpose
only indirectly you're working on react
components which are far removed from
fixing Portland Civic problems which is
probably what God she went to Civic in
the first place so things start kind of
looking like work and once you realize
that it looks like work but you're not
getting paid makes a lot harder to go
every night at 6:00 to 9:00 p.m. to
volunteer for this thing um I don't
really have an answer for this one it's
just sort of something we ran into so a
lot of iteration underfunded team and
other platform teams also as it turns
out so this is just something I have to
think about maybe something you want to
keep in mind super sad but uh here's my
cat's well Hudson five product
management is for everyone much like
marketing early in my career I kind of
thought that product management was
unnecessary that engineering was really
work and product management was just
pretending to be an engineer so when you
think like that you kind of think
product management must be optional very
very wrong by the way product management
itself is an expansive and difficult and
complex complex career path and when you
ignore it you're gonna run into one of
two walls but first wall is that things
are being added to your project sort of
haphazardly and this may be great for a
sense of involvement in the community
everyone's crushing it getting their PRS
merged but your personal vision kind of
gets lost and you start to feel like
you're losing control
was once your baby while number two's
the opposite you never let go of control
your voice is final your rationale
devolves into things like well it just
feels right to do this or what you're
suggesting is just not good for this
project
he's Kanaly any contributors just
remember that even a benevolent dictator
is still a dictator
I went crashing right into wall number
two this year just head-on I went in a
room factored our entire funder in
architecture it's work that needed to be
done and there was a plan in my head and
I just sort of acted on it I didn't do a
good job sharing this plan with others
though so some people offered to help
but I rejected them I was just saying
like you can help but you'll need to let
me finish this initial refactor first
and ultimately the refactor was
well-received and we were able to
collaborate after the fact but it would
be wrong to call that a flat a success I
happened at 20,000 line PR with ninety
commits and there was no documented
issue with the problem beforehand like
that's red flag City and I had a lot to
say in the pr2 about my choices and
ultimately I think that people were
happy with the changes but while I was
working on this I just left contributors
in the dark and I just covered it away
in a dark corner and that's no good for
those contributors so when discussing
product management we talked about
things like road maps or things like
North Stars there's lots of wayfinding
metaphors pretty much all of them I
prefer the metaphor of a vanishing point
so objects that are closed should be
very clear detailed and understood and
this is what requires a media attention
as focus and focus but there's obviously
a farther away they kind of become
blurry ER there's a rough idea of what's
ahead and that idea is shared amongst
teams for release it needs to be but
it's also understood that a lot can
happen between here and there and what
you see may actually be a mirage so to
embrace product management he needed
spend time thinking about what you're
building and ask yourself these kinds of
questions what's right for your project
what's wrong for your project where your
priorities the timing right and how do
you even know if any of these things are
true why do you feel the way you do if
you do this work you'll tear down wall
number one because now you have a plan
you'll tear down number two well number
two because you're able to articulate
the reasons you're rejecting work
communication makes all the difference
here being able to articulate your
thoughts and motivations is key no talk
simply without a pop culture reference
so here's a scene from Bojack horseman
if you aren't familiar with the show
first you should become familiar with
the show and second Bojack is a horse
man naturally he's also a depressing
alcoholic / washed-up TV star the show
focuses on and Todd here in red is the
unlikely friend who is here finally
venting his frustrations and it's a
super intense scene and if you've seen
the show I'm sure you remember this
scene I'm particularly drawn to this
line you need to be better struck a
chord with him mostly because it came
from a friend like Todd could walk out
but instead he's confronting Bojack and
saying look man you need to be better
and that's enough I can't say it's okay
you're gonna do better next time
flat out you need to be better and our
friends are our fans they want us to be
better and our contributors are too they
want you and your project succeed so
saying no isn't automatically a letdown
but letting a project spiral or fizzle
out absolutely is
so on that low note in Lesson number 5
lower your expectations this sounds
awful but I assure you it's not here's a
ridiculous graph ideas come faster than
implementations and you're never gonna
be able to get to all of your ideas the
optimist will say yes do all of thanks
we can do this
meanwhile the past mints will say
something like doesn't ever be able to
do any of this I don't like either these
outlooks I think they're both pretty
unproductive the optimist is ultimately
going to be disappointed and the past
mess will achieve less than they could
have if they believe in themselves and
meanwhile they're going to bring down
everyone around them instead I like to
sort of exist between these two spaces
or the realist may say something like we
have a longer backlog thing we can work
through or the idealist may say
something like let's track all of our
ideas I bet we can surprise ourselves
with our output here's an unscientific
chart that basically just says I'm right
and realizing my idealism is a little
more effective it's great go ahead and
take pictures
but we need to stay tethered to the
reality of volunteering so I personally
want to be 100 at volunteering I want to
be the best that ever was like no one
ever was there we go detective Pikachu
coming in May so I also want to be 100
at my day job and I want to be 100 at my
friendships and my family in my
relationship and life upkeep but I can't
I like everyone else is bound by a 24
hour day and this is just simply too
much stuff what if I lower my
expectations I can fit everything in and
it's also when I'm kind of bored or like
I'm upset with myself I need to remember
that when I over book myself it impacts
the lives of people around me there's a
blast radius to everything that you do
and it's going to impact the people you
love so even though I've lowered my
expectations and I encourage all our
volunteers to sort of do the same and
take days off over 20 18 we were still
able to ship this customized exploratory
map where we correlated poverty rates
with access to food we were able to
share insights from public attract
campaign financing and we were able to
open up and visualize Harvard's state of
the nation's housing report and we
analyzed TriMet ridership data year over
year to tell them these ridership
changing how our neighborhoods looked
these years and we created personalized
Maps using the Department of geology and
mineral industries Cascadia subduction
zone research to see how different
neighborhoods would fare once the big
9.0 earthquake hits so Captain Obvious
reporting in here slow and steady is so
much faster than not moving at all
alright there are ways to work smarter
and not harder though so even if you're
doing less work you can sort of create
an acceleration effect by doing things
like lesson six writing the docs so we
build on top of open source and one of
the great features of that as we get a
head start because our projects like
react and redux already have awesome
documentation and shout out to ducks
learn did a great job reacting Redux
both have amazing documentation but
you're never going to get something like
this civic questions are never going to
be answered in redux Docs so there are
benefits to writing your own one is that
you don't have to repeat your
explanations and now volunteers don't
have to rely on you to answer all their
questions
in person explanations end up being
blocking requests well doctor
asynchronous and as much as I'd love to
scale myself out horizontally that's
called getting fat but when it's a web
server it means you now have more uptime
so what does this kind of product
specific documentation look like for us
it was as simple as committing markdown
files to our repos I think as engineers
we're really easily distracted by the
machinery of Docs and we quickly end up
in rabbit holes where we start talking
about different static site generators
and templating options and how my static
dad can beat up your static dad and
different deployment pipelines and we we
sort of forget that the most important
part of the docs are the words and that
writing good Docs is already a hard task
and it doesn't really need further
complication on day one but keep in mind
our writing Docs doesn't have to solve
you of all of your responsibilities as a
mentor maybe your Doc's aren't reading
well or maybe they assume more expertise
than a volunteer has I mean after all if
books were all that was needed to teach
stuff I mean wouldn't need teachers and
hopefully I don't need to explain to
anyone that we need teachers all right
final lesson here this one isn't really
my area of expertise smarter people have
said much more on this topic and they're
way more qualified than I am but I
really do believe that the times up for
white guys who assume this is someone
else's problem so I'm gonna try to go
through some of my thinking on this the
very first question is why why should we
even care about diversity inclusion I
hear a couple common excuses over and
over the first one is sort of the
meritocracy fall people are truly
created equal then every individual
individual must be hot-swappable
or I might be a white sis hat man but I
read about these issues and I can be an
ally for people with different
backgrounds so first to clear the air
here people aren't identical no one's
saying that we're all individuals with
unique experiences and perspectives
equal here means equal treatment in
equal opportunities as for that second
Hajin of the problem you may be a
fantastic ally it's absolutely possible
but everyone suffers from unknown
unknowns and we're always learning and
even though we try our hardest stand up
for people from different backgrounds
it's just not the same as representation
and it's never going to be this chart
here is completely unscientific there's
no
way to quantify the things that you
don't know you don't know but there's
plenty of evidence of this problem so
let's go back in time here and look at
how a photo labs were calibrated and
they just didn't have dark skin tone as
a mind they use this picture of a white
woman with black gloves and it meant
that even to this day people with darker
complexion have a harder time showing up
on cameras in this kind of problem it
just keeps happening
here's another problem with dark skin
tone calibration where soap dispensers
don't work and it happens again heart
rate sensors have a problem with dark
skin like at this point how in the world
right this is not an acceptable problem
to have and maybe your startup product
isn't like hand dryers you're probably
not working on that although I bet
there's some disruption there so you're
thinking this isn't my problem because
this is the niche target audience that I
can actually represent maybe I
personally work with civic tech and
civic tech needs to work for everyone so
I can't avoid this but keep in mind that
this isn't only an issue for whites this
hetman we happen to be the dominant
demographic which means that we carry
the most power and therefore
responsibility for driving social change
so even movements like me too doesn't
keep Kavanagh out of the Supreme Court
and that's because of white guys just
own that but individually no one is
diverse a group of white woman is going
to be biased towards woman needs in a
woman at wedding excuse me in white
history likewise a group of black men is
going to have similar problems this is
because diversity is a group phenomenon
only groups can be diverse this is going
to change over time as your group grows
or the composition of your group changes
it also means that rejection on the
grounds of diversity shouldn't be taken
personally it just means the problem
lies with what you either do or don't
add to a community but on the flip side
if you're the person who's choosing a
candidate or a volunteer to be to join
your team keep in mind that diversity
isn't always visible there are lots of
things that make us diverse that we
can't actually see with our eyes with
all this in mind how can we expect DNI
to solve itself
someone needs be paying attention to the
composition of your community and it's
not enough to react once a community
gets a modulus is the issue
to compound consider shellings
segregation model it's very simple model
meant to see if segregation in the u.s.
is potentially the result of just a
slight preference rather than an intense
deep-seated racism I mean it ignores
mounds of historical evidence in caveats
so it's not like the most accurate
explanation of American neighborhoods
but the emergent behavior is still
interesting because it turns out over
time agents do segregate based on just
this slight preference what's most
fascinating to me is that there's
nothing in this model that is explicitly
about race and sometimes people have
reasons for their preferences I've
worked with plenty of women in tech who
look for companies that already have a
good number of women there that's
because they're sick of being the token
woman who suffers from token woman
problems like these are big things like
stunted career growth or an increased
risk of sexual assault but also small
things like just being cold all the time
or expecting to conform to the one of
the guys attitudes or just being the
de-facto dishwasher I think this is a
valid preference and there are many like
it but the grand effect is that if you
already have a decently sized son
Lajeunesse culture you have an uphill
battle to fight for diversity and this
is why it's so important to take DNI
seriously on day one you need to be
proactive in recruiting individuals and
to do this well you need to have
internalized the real reason why we even
bother
it's not about hiring women so we have
women it's about eliminating blind spots
by having more representation and if you
can do this if you can nail recruiting
and that fixes half the pipeline problem
but pipes have two ends we also have a
DNI retention issue in tech so employee
attrition is normal there's nothing
inherently wrong with that people leave
jobs but in tech retention rates are
lower among underrepresented groups this
means that even if you do an outstanding
job recruiting a diverse group of
volunteers you may end up with the
mosely homogenous group over time by way
of attrition but you can be proactive
about ski boot engine rates as well
whole talks can be given on this subject
we here's a starter kit first be open
about your values culture ad will
usually mean something at a company but
if you can't articulate what that means
then you're creating a space for bias to
creep in likewise you should write
rubrics for all of your assessments
beforehand this can be candid assessment
it could be code review it could be
promotion assessments but if we don't
have a framework for
your judgments then once again bias is
going to creep in third you should have
these one-on-one meetings with people
and really listen the easiest way to get
caught off guard is by not paying
attention and I personally like I said
like to sit in front of a computer away
from humans so I like to avoid
uncomfortable situations like everyone
else
so it's really easy to not have these
meetings because that's the path of
least resistance it's a bad thing to do
I assure you the fourth is that this is
ongoing work taking an unconscious bias
training is great but it doesn't mean
you're now impervious to any potential
misstep it's about putting in place
processes and best practices to reduce
as much risk of missteps as possible so
the last point I want to make about this
though is mostly for my fellow white
guys in the room I've talked to many
white guys who feel like they're now
walking on eggshells kind of consoling
on the edge and fearful of ladies social
justice coming down and just smiting
them into oblivion and like I'm gonna
get that there's a lot to be mindful of
these days or really always but suddenly
we're not aware of it so there's so many
ways to screw up but I personally find
solace in knowing that no one is asking
you to be perfect a microaggression here
and there isn't going to melt your
coworker turns out under represented
people in tech like seriously tough and
they deal with this crap every day and
it's really easy to tell the difference
between an honest mistake and
disinterest or adversarial protest now
this isn't to say that you should do
whatever you want without thinking first
because there's so much you can learn
about others by just spinning a few
hours on the Internet
like it's senseless to expect
underrepresented people to correct you
on things that you could have just
looked up on your own but when you mess
up and you're going to mess up here's my
three step guide to recovery first
apologize for your mistakes second
reflect on why your mistakes were taken
the way they were and third use this new
knowledge to be better in the future
and although like calling out white guys
here this is good advice for everyone we
all have baggage and it's often
invisible and we'd all benefit from
taking the time to understand each other
so to wrap things up here growing and
managing a community is just incredibly
hard work it really is and it's so easy
to be blindsided by the responsibilities
required when you started out as an
engineer and gives kind of wanted to
code and be helpful but I assure you if
you can commit to these responsibilities
you will ultimately build something that
is much more helpful than it ever would