so let's talk about p oj s first of all
thank you all for coming here I know
that I'm competing this fall down stairs
so I'm amazed as many people came here I
would be in vaults talk right now but I
have to get the talk right now so my
name is on us Carl I've work this was a
lot and this work i'm presenting today
was made by by now something like 15
contributors that are not all on a slide
one person is gonna slide is julian
actually made the slides for me he's
also half a PDF of GS offers so Julian
raise your hand hi Julian yeah p Please
time Julian you don't have look at
montes kind of slides I usually make
that's a big plus so I'm going to talk
to the what PR rendering and about
structure PDF and how we do this in PDF
OGS about images and fonts but also I
would have spent quite a bit of time on
the problems he encounters encountered
and also actual performance problems
around here and I want to show you what
kind of things are really important to
optimize if you are looking at system
like this and then we conclude is a to
do and the to do list or PM tjs and
double gatorade MO so the goal of the
PDF ojs project was to produce a
faithful high quality fast efficient PDF
renderer and by the time we started this
project really the motivation for us was
to find out what is possible to use the
HTML Javascript platform to build a PDF
member at that point they were a couple
connect to a PDF renderers for tiny
subset or maybe can not draw figures PDF
like render commands but collection PDF
renderer and all browsers at that point
you're using native code to do PDF
rendering so chrome for example embeds
is like commercial foxit PDF renderer
and we were just wondering why it's not
being done in javascript in order to
find out and personally I'm not reading
a web authoring a platform engineer I'm
a browser platform so I was curious
whether there are things in a platform
that some are prohibitive maybe it's a
slow features on the same so there's one
experiment in browser technology with
event PDF entering and really the the
main goal from this perspective being a
browser implementer is you want to avoid
having native code no platform
of former vp engineering of mozilla
affectionately called Acrobat Reader or
popular native code execution format
there's every time you put native code
into a browser there's always a risk if
getting it exploited and PDF readers
have been exploiting a pass intensively
so the last major iPhone exploit wall
space on the PDF reader in the iPhone
itself so using the web to build these
pieces gives us a secure platform where
you can run PDF documents display that
may don't with your risk of being taking
about shop so that's at the PDF format
PDF is kind of pretty standard document
format it looks very similar to unlock
my formats like your documents there's a
header that tell us a little bit about a
PDF version and this an actual body wrap
contains streamed objects that are
identified by a position into the file
and this building an object or after
concepts of the different pages that are
linked together to a document and
individual pages of rendering commands
and images and so on and then at the end
of documents there's a table the xref
table and this provides click mapping of
object ids to index us into the file so
this is what you use to achieve fine
individual objects in this large file
and this fights going to be large that's
a megabyte so it's really important to
have a central point where you can find
them and then the trailer at the very
end of the file kind of tells you how
you can find to the root of this object
tree and when this PDF format was
specified many many years ago it's kind
of predated really exchanging data or
the wire so I just for my country not
very suitable to actually be transferred
because you have too busy fetch the
entire file all the way the last bite
before you can display any single page
so by now there are couple additional
extensions to this format but it can
only just fetch some parts of it and
stuff like that so there's like
complications on top of this but this is
the basic structure the video processing
this is for currently loading the entire
file with six HR into an array but we
can also support very easily this idea
of having range requests only get parts
of the files you can quickly window
these things and you basically you
create a PDF document object around that
and you can fetch pages from that the
document and these two stages to
rendering first we start rendering by
providing a graphics
context and the page and this is going
to go and read all the objects
associated with that page which contains
of rendering objects and images and it's
going to process all of them to identify
resources we have to load before we can
actually display the page and then once
those resources have been loaded in
particular fonts and images then we can
actually execute is the sequence of
commands that we have just reported for
the page this is important because in a
general HTML page when you apply some
custom font by CSS then the CSS rule
takes a moment to load they can just go
ahead and render the page miss of their
own font and the browser automatically
is going to we render the page assume
the actual CSS rule and the font is
available for canvas unfortunate is not
being done so if you set a new font on
canvas and don't wait for the browser to
load it and start drawing you just get
the bad font in there in its it so to
avoid that be basically that's what we
record these pdfs home as first and then
load the font the months of font is
loaded then they actually display the
page so here's an example of a PDF file
and an object on this kind of PDF file
so object number three is a page in this
this PDF document and have read two
important parts when it's the resource
part where funds and graphic objects are
in and then contents is the actual
command screen that renders a PDF
document so initially we attach numbered
option number three if you say get page
and then if you start rendering we have
to fetch the resources and actual
content and parcels further and this is
what the extra content stream of this
page he looks like it's a sequence of
commands here streams can Adobe's way of
saying array so it's just an array of
commands that executes in sequence in
this very different commands here the
first one sets a graphic state this is
the second one is the s0 there that's a
fun command it says select 10 and then
you can see actually text go on commands
the middle part of it and if you were to
look at a PDF document in a text editor
and it's not encrypted and it's not
compressed you would actually literally
see this text here so it's a text-based
format however to achieve better achieve
small documents frequently is actually
compressed with zip so basically the
stream part isn't taken and compare
it's a simple deflate algorithm so in
this first step that we collect all the
resources we walk the extra catalog and
find all these different funds and
anything else you need and apparently
build an intermediate presentation that
contains all the rendering commands that
we encounter and again we cannot execute
them yet because we have not loaded all
the resources associated with it so you
can see here that we set the graphic
stage and then we nor this dependency
this actually goes off and files off a
custom CSS rule that attaches to the
document to load the font and the
satphone command here cannot be executed
yet we are destroying this in an array
as soon the actual font loading is
complete then you can execute this
sequence and the rest of the IR looks
pretty much like a canvas interface so
canvas is currently the back end we are
using and it's roughly the same commands
that are also in canvas though one minor
difference is that we actually keep
track of the state of a per serve and
texas output it so not everything in PDF
is absolute position actual text you
have to measure how long the virtus and
then position refers to the air since
there might be more text showing up
without an extra positioning so once
then all the phones are loaded then we
can't you go ahead and execute the
sequence of commands and all the funds
will be available and all the images we
are payable and we can draw them to a
canvas and that's it images so PDF
documents can contain a bunch of
different image formats this is like
eight or nine different ones pretty
common one is jpg and then we first
started this we did a little experiment
of implementing jtag just in JavaScript
they turned out to be really really slow
something like 10 to 100 x slower
depending on what exactly the JPEG file
look like so what we ended up doing
instead is since the format stalls
natively supported by the browser we
just take the content of the file and
basically for encode it and then stick
it back into a Dom element that does the
actual decoding work for us and if it's
not a JPEG stream then we have to do the
manual the corn by hand there's a bunch
of different formats if it is at four so
PNG for example can appear NPS
unfortunately the pd a-- the PNG format
that we use is not exactly the Veda PNG
standard looks like there's a couple of
different things in there I'm not sure
it'll become available so I think by the
time that it is they avoid the sound of
an entire past yet so I do
like snapchat original fit and that
ended up not being what's being a
standard so PNG we have to do by hand
it's a pretty efficient file format so
it's not very difficult to do that
there's also this just bitmap
compression formats and so on but you do
they're basically just read the data we
convert it to a color space and then use
canvas and just blit the pixel data and
there so most of this tends to be three
efficient fonts so PDF documents can
contain a bunch of different font
formats as type 1 fonts type two phones
type 3 fonts and the casual observer
might think that these are like super
sized right like type 2 is a superset of
type 1 and then type 3 super sub type 2
and there's this farthest thing from the
truth so type 1 and type 2 are super
sets and subsets of each other and you
cannot cannot convert trivially either
one into the other but you can do some
tricks so type 1 fonts actually not
support on the web type 2 fonts are it
since you can convert it to open type so
what you end up doing is we take type 1
fonts and kind of reinterpret them the
interpret the sequence of commands that
draws the autumn out of the phone and
amid the equivalent have two
instructions for that and convert all
the hinting data and they get a type too
fond out of that and a type two font we
can wrap into an open type font
container and then that the browser can
load and I'll use a custom CSS rule let
me inject in the document to actually
load the font as we are parsing through
the document unfortunately some funds
cannot be converted this way so type 3
fonts they even go a step further and
it's typed refund every glyph is a PDF
document so in theory for every glue if
you can have a video playing in there
and I will flash running and everything
else creativeness you can do in PDF so
attack free fonts you cannot convert
this easily basic whether you're
planning to do there this is simply use
the rendering pipeline you already have
to draw a to individual good it's going
to horace loeb fantastically type free
phones almost never use so it's not be a
practical problem alright so this is
kind of nice part so far everything's
weird everything is great everything is
fast let's talk about the promise
furniture and live a quite a few so
there's plenty in a browser no way to
detect it on it's loaded I explained
this before on canvas that if you just
specify a new font and start drawing
with it you can have the wrong form
under the fundage
loads so there's no way to get notified
right now that's of course kind of like
BRB so the ended up doing is you can
detect it and I by by indirection so you
can set yourself a timeout that's going
to call you back all the time you're
waiting for the phone to load it can
take the little one pixel canvas and put
the font in there and then measure its
bids and if the font loads eventually
it's going to change then and then you
know the phone has been loaded of course
this is not a particularly efficient way
of doing these things so that's that's a
nice thing when you're working for a
company it makes the browser so you can
talk to the guys so do these things and
we already proposed in addition the
html5 to the lord have an event in
actual font loading is complete on the
canvas now that kind of random problem
ran into was actual phone measurements
so I explained before that in PDF not
every command is absolute positioned in
case of text you're supposed to measure
the width of the text and I continued
after that and this over that sometimes
absolute positioning as well so it's
very important to be very precise on
measurements and it turns out if you
measure with canvas fonts on many
different browsers including ours you
get kind of like results a little bit
off by a couple pic pixels but that's
enough like your fonts kind of blew into
each other looks really crappy and we
realize that this is a rounding error
that happens in many font
implementations so many browsers didn't
use the same font engines and they have
certain rounding errors they're getting
used by PDF and you're not doing a very
gross hack to other come back though at
the end of the talk I can show you what
it looks like took it everywhere all
these kind of things subject response
look very different than in Europe
platforms it looks different for paying
the person operating system different
from like version of the OS to be
depending on canvas drawers so on more
modern platforms like mac OS and the
recent version of windows looks pretty
good but if you go back to Windows XP
you cannot on your own text selection
doesn't be repairable for us right now
these in cameras to the back end so you
exploring other options they are using
SVG for example a text search little bit
easier to do that on canvas printing is
the same using right now fixed size
canvas if you print that we leave a
little black crap because we are
pixelating at a much lower resolution
this mostly again an API problem there
is no turbid good API right now on the
web to print so I'm be filed a bug and
it's something they want to fix so it
should be much more efficient way how
you can communicate
print commands for example you could
have a print canvas they can say okay I
want to like to print Lima canvas I will
do print commands on it and the browser
can figure out how to translate that to
your local printer and a performance of
course is a problem i'm going to talk
about that a little bit more in a second
been doing this project II this has been
my first video our JavaScript project
I'm not a drastic web author I do
browsers for a living so then they
started doing this is very important for
us to have very nice maintainable code
because we're not very good javascript
hackers so want to make sure everything
is really extensible people to
understand it they start a project
straight on github phone and make sure
people can help us and how about just
committee contributors so we really try
to write very nice stylized modular code
that's great however in some cases it
also has to be really fast so if you are
sitting somewhere deep and an image
decoder we have to make you t-shirt it's
very fast and efficient otherwise be
doesn't seem enough competitive for some
native code PDF reader and their must
view the goal we wanted to see that you
can use javascript to be as efficient as
the native code implementations so just
a couple of things that's going to run
into an optimizing observations more or
less then we've this piece of code here
is the actual deflate algorithm that we
also had and decompresses the PDF
command screen that comes with another
text file and first for tonight's
modular version was way too slow to be
used and I use the profiler then we're
going to go ahead and find out where the
problems are one of the first things i
optimize is that this little compunction
their insurer buffer but it does every
time you're decoding more data from the
compressed file you have to make sure
you can write your output buffer and
it's ensure buffer make sure but it is
enough room to ride another character
and I used to call this straight
directly from the code and it turns out
this function part is way too expensive
there are too many characters these
files a large amounts of megabytes and
make Bay 20 function calls really slow
so instead but you're not doing is
either kind pulled if condition out of
there and we only conditionally call it
if the buffer needs to be extended and
that mean that was a base substantial
speed up at the same time it's important
you don't go overboard so kind of this
kind of inlining makes sense
we perform is critical and it's a very
thin function you don't want to go
overboard completely stop using
functions because your coat looks
totally unreadable so just get code here
that's actually a very substantial
amount of code I use several times in
its function if I take that apart
everywhere then the code needs to be
long and readable and there the function
call overhead is much less in comparison
to what happens in the function so that
one we didn't touch and then similarly
vettel like helper functions are on this
like code one shift right at sixteen you
can't afford in this kind of performance
critical code according to helper
functions it's also important the wavy
represent data here so this length the
code is an array contains data and it
contains we two different things length
and a code initially we used to have an
array in there is two indexes index zero
index one for data and length and it's
additional area look up was also pretty
expensive so just kind of munch those
two numbers together and shifted them
together and that God where's another
like fifty percent or so speed
improvement so it's very important that
when you have critical code after you
have written in a nice way you can go
ahead and optimize it and you will only
do that for the critical parts of your
code something else that I was talking
about earlier is if you're using the
internal jpeg dakota in the browser and
it's really important abroad jpg is a
very complex format it's a lot of
complex math going on to decode it you
do not want to rather than JavaScript
unfortunately we are into the same
problem here as this PNG that Adobe's
implementation of JPEGs subtly different
differs on the way sentiment on the web
in particular there's something wrong
with color space conversion so actually
hear the vet is wrong on the web the
Jeep actor displayed is the very
Photoshop generates done not the way the
standards say and you can't we change
that because so many images are made by
Photoshop and in PDF the format is
correctly the way the spec wants it to
be used and unfortunately incompatible
so if you try to render the document at
the PDF JPEG you get completely wrong
color space so the end up doing we can
manage the JPEG fiber redid the insert a
little header the browser knows about
and choose a different color space and
then we load that you leave rewritten
jpg file into the browser that made that
work
that's or at least I'm going to talk a
lil bit about the way we journeyed all
these data streams so we have frequently
but we do in PDF to jsu read data and
invite out data into a file again or a
buffer and then loaded into browser and
the first naive implementation that
someone from the team did look like this
here you get the screen data as a bunch
of bytes and then you've a lot of right
function that you give an array of data
and it goes through that it's a for in
loop and pushes into a new font array
we're also new phone data is collected
and then down there is kind of roughly
about the font loop well look look like
there's some data by pull out of there
and be right two bytes for example with
a file and this was horribly slow and
for like many different reasons and just
animate a couple of minutes or four in a
race if you do a for in loop or an array
and the indexes have to be string defied
in the for in loop so I in this array
learn in this loop over this array it's
always a string by the specification so
you have to take this numeric index is 0
and 1 and string defy them all the time
and that definitely substantial cost so
you want to avoid for in loops or a race
the next thing is the actual push on an
array to store data it's not a
particularly good idea that's really
expensive you have to call this native
push method you have to extend their
array every time so that turned out
pretty expensive down here to write out
the data and he created a new array
around it every time and modern GCS can
take care of the trash for generating
here in this loop but just making that
object is pretty expensive so you're
kind of using Apple of like cash space
there and the hardware it is to make all
the solar rays and that's what at least
also call in this function here it
almost does nothing it's a pretty big
overhead so after optimizing all these
things the font loading code would
substantially faster and I was after
optimizing either but pretty curious
what is actually really the fastest way
in a browser to ride into a variable
size buffer and 20 prize that you eat
strings and that's the sweetie weird
because strings are not even eight byte
array is every 16 bit arrays so
basically what I ended up doing a
current code base now is that we have
started string out empty and then
concatenate characters in there using
from charcoal and give a constants we
have to write in there because you
this hex string notation to write it in
and the best explanation I can give you
for that why strings are so efficient in
browsers is that they are highly
optimized for benchmarks so kind of pre
sunspider it's like very popular a
terrible terrible JavaScript benchmark
people used to avoid string
concatenation because it was terribly
slow in ie6 now in a post Suns by the
world and suffered a lot of string
concatenation so today everything
everybody deeply optimized for computing
strengths some knowledge reaching
operation so if you want a bit something
really fast what you do we have to make
a benchmark and then everyone's been
optimized for it all right that's what
at least typed arrays to not to be also
a really important performance feature
for us so we switched all over they used
to type the race the best we can and
that gives you a nice speed up and even
for literal is just like tables of data
it's actually very efficient to do that
it's often also more compact so this is
for example a 32-bit array of 32-bit
integers and it's much more compact
represented to the typed array because a
regular arranged larger data entities
that store the type and the value and
type the race everything is the same
time unfortunately for type 2 race you
can't form easily the literals or on
them so what you did because we make a
regular array that you can initialize
the literal and then this rather typed
array all around it and for a brief
moment you have the full array in memory
but then it gets replaced this it happed
array of course and then some some
browsers you don't have time to raise a
new slides Opera Safari mobile 99 don't
heaven yet as far as I can tell in that
case you just emulated type area so
using traditional erase and their their
API is roughly compatible so basic on
these browsers works is a little
emulation layer in between it's just
much lower believe what I was going to
encourage this a couple of slides views
to hear is I encourage you to use
profilers the really fundamentally
useful in our code base you go ahead and
you write the code as nicely as you can
and you grab a profiler and you kind of
knock off the top like five or six
performance photos you can find that
visit has already taken care of the
majority of the performance you can
squeeze out of the program so you can
have it kind of boat you can have a very
nice modular code the same time it can
also be very efficient and some of the
stuff is really subtle it's very hard to
tell so I started
fi I was founded type of syntax really
confusing so I like to avoid it like the
plague and I wrote myself a little
helper functions like is now it's going
to tell me that that value as a number
and the users very consistent is the
code base and one of the things their
profile are highlighted as I was going
through the cool base is that in this
little loop here where data is being
processed and rewritten I used to I used
Islam to check whether that the value
was getting back as invalid a bite or
actually I have reached the end of the
file in which case i think i define it's
coming back and this function call to
islam was the majority of the cost of
this loop here and like ninety percent
of the time was being spent calling the
islam function not even inside it as
much is calling it so a profiler can
very easily kind of highlight these
things and there's various different
ones other the Firebug is available
Firefox and then Kate based process of a
profiler built in so we can very nicely
identified that's a problem you can just
take the guts of the function in line it
and you have a limited overhead for the
call there and that video get this goes
a long way so you sacrifice a little bit
of beauty there you fix a couple places
up and they're not as nice as you would
prefer to write them but you get me a
dramatic performance improvements um the
last but not least don't pause we all
have run into quite a few problems just
this dumb cause being slow and the
reason for that is that javascript has a
different representation for objects and
most implementations of browsers which
are usually in C++ so even JavaScript if
a Jobs get string a draft object and C++
it is like see strings and see the space
objects so whenever you call the Dom it
take those jobs objects return to see
those fast objects and then it dont does
some processing on it and then it
returns the data which we have to again
convert back and we the only way to make
that fast is to not do that do not on
the damage with it all can avoid it so
in this case here is rattled cash around
measure text so whenever even measured
text for the same form or the same tags
and the same size then we just don't hit
the dorm again put in a little cash on a
JavaScript side and everything is much
much faster and this particular useful
for rear ndering so when I showed em own
a second you will see that the second
time you go across the pages is very
fast instant because nothing has to be
really measured anymore
and something else it's this one is live
here is a little ugly hacker was talking
about so I mentioned to you then many
browsers don't measure fonts right in
canvas so if you end up doing we just
take the text and we pick a much much
larger font size so it's like 50 times
larger and then you measure the text is
a larger XL size and then we divide it
by the P modification factor this is not
exactly the size because hinting can
cause different text measurement but
it's it's closer to the truth then if
you just use the direct methods all
right a couple things of the f to still
do there's more fun than printing work
to be done they're not implementing
entire backyard vendor some more back
ends in particular at fuji in HTML maybe
advanced PDF features like forms and
stuff like that and automated testing
zalto pretty important it's very easy in
the code size of the size of the code
base we have nice pretty easy to break
stuff if you don't have decent tests all
right demo that's what people want to
see anyway so I was not raised enough to
give the entire presentation this on
this video for GS but you can see that
we can render the entire content as well
you see a couple of entering artifacts
here and there many of those actually
are in keynote so keynote exported a bad
PDF it's not even prev you can actually
read what we roughly looks the same and
then be able to like slide out here that
shows your preview and it's actually
using the same renderer so if I cool
down really quickly you can see this is
all these your Android so if you only
display a couple of these things and
lazily render them and the rear ndering
is fast enough to kind of keep up this
actual scrolling and then hopefully the
network is going to work because when I
contribu this here so this is a little
demo that someone from Azad put together
this students from this university so
this is a 3d that GL canvas that uses
PDF to jas to render the content of this
very first document that we end up is
PHAs and put in a few then you can
rotate this around and zoom into it and
what not and this going to show us a
power wheel you of using proper web
technology so
it will be much much harder to do sounds
like this is a native cool plugin
because you have to get the content
somehow into the web stack and if you
use that technology to render these
things that's already automatically
there all right that's for my talk any
questions
so there's a pdx back the spec tells you
about pdfs were supposed to look like
and then there's reality which is part
of a different on that gear to
reverse-engineer so there's many PDF
termination to literally hundreds of
them and you have to come back guess a
little bit and look at different
documents we find out what the reality
looks like but the basic spec is
available and it's an iso spec we
started we pick candles as the first
thing we will do HTML and SVG next
there's no particular reason we know
that campus is very fast for the same
reason as string operations fast this
time competed in marketing / canos
performance so everyone men's and make
the candles really fast so we knew we
would be very fast as canvas we have not
investigated other ones yet it will
probably be fast as well oh yeah
absolutely so SVG is for text selection
and printing very interesting yeah
you
sure I'm not too familiar sports i know
there's roughly based on a PDF rendering
pipeline so it should be possible yeah
yeah oh ok so he was asking that it's
possible to render he related specs like
the ports you I rendering pipeline to
PDF to GS and I swim yes specifications
but I assume you you dropped a lot of
stuff because the PDF reader does a lot
of fancy things let you decide what to
throw ok so the question box with the V
implement entire speckle we have dropped
parts of it because the PDF readers is
so extensive that's what we true so the
octopod reader is like a 50 megabyte
download something that there's a ton of
crap in there there's like various two
jobs with engines and I think a flash
engine or two flash engines various
stuff that you don't need that's just
for the business modulus every year they
put up a new version of a reader some
more crap in it and in reality most pdx
an event don't reuse that so if you look
at popular readers like the monitors in
chrome or the preview one that's a mac
OS that thing really to supports PDF 1.3
plus a few little things so that's
roughly what we are shooting for we are
shooting for compatibility vyas
ninety-nine point nine percent of the
PDF you will find on to that and that's
a much much smaller subset about the
actual spec is so we kind of knew what
the important stuff is and from the arm
is iterating we pick a new document that
we find somewhere the PDF education so
it's all for example it's going to see
what features are needed and add those
the impression that would be very useful
in other professions as well very good
um so the disease of stuff for example
we were considering that it's still a
quite a bit slower actually so by the
way some incident code it's up on github
the zeod stuff in particular is going
too slow in a browser and Java scripts
like 10x lower so than native that's
something we were considering there's
also we we found also this holds in the
camera specification you cannot draw a
dashed line in canvas you can emulate
that it's just really hard math so
that's something we propose that's
already in this back actually similarly
there's compositing things together in
canvas and merging images is kind of
difficult so they will use this project
to kind of drive what kind of features
are missing absolutely in the questions
are back maybe all right
yeah so I used to work a JavaScript boob
unless there's a talking on JavaScript
performance and also couch catches
performance so there's an ongoing battle
to like nature's get fast that's going
to take some time javascript is language
is actually much harder to optimize than
a traditional i typed statically
compiled language as a simple thing as a
function call with this is really hard
to tell where it's going there might be
a getter than just fired you can be
seated in a code easily that somewhat
change the binding of that function on
this somewhere else or you might want
the Dom the dumb cause an event handler
that changes it somehow so it's very
hard to determine you can do you can do
optimistic population you can kind of in
line and guard against not failing these
things are being done so the next
version of our compiler will do that to
degree but right now if you wanna make
it fast and current browsers if you do a
little bit of poo finding a little bit
of August occation a couple lines of
code you get massive performance gains
so I think it is worth it
absolutely so the goal for this quarter
is if you want to put out an extension
that you can download and install and
ultimately we would like to see this in
Firefox about our main focuses Firefox
that's we know best it runs committee
contributors have poured it to Eddie
browser out there it runs very well in
Safari Chrome and Firefox it runs
somewhat in ie9 as well I just really
slow because I don't have typed arrays
yes well so when we set out to do this
project really one motivation was very
marginal platform side like we don't
like plugins plugins crash their crappy
their security problem so if we pick
kind of one popular plugin or native
code piece PDF but flash is kind of the
obvious elephant in a room as well so
they has already been project we do
flash it's it's very partial that's very
small and we are very hopeful that that
project will be extended rather poor
just like it will eventually your place
flash conceptually PDF and flush every
the same thing you have commands in the
stream that summer renders stuff to the
screen and I think you proved that you
can look very effectively using the web
pipeline can I PS like canvas a very
high level very efficient api's to this
kind of pixel pushing so really all you
do is kind of map the high level flash
format to a high level a canvas format
there's not all that much heavy lifting
and computation to be done in javascript
so you can do it very efficiently all