my name is Kevin markman and I come to
you from New York to talk a little bit
about taking web apps offline and what
it takes to do that and how you can do
that because realistically your app
isn't there for your users unless it's
available to them all the time so first
I want to tell you a little bit about me
and my my background I come from a
history of C++ desktop applications and
they had the exact opposite problem so
the issue they face is that they didn't
get any of the advantages that the cloud
brings to to us to us javascript HTML
CSS people and that is the update update
cycles for years a product that i worked
on three years ago still isn't launched
I've launched more and the in the last
month then I've launched from my
previous job which is which is kind of
crazy so at the same time there are
things that desktop apps do well that
web apps suffer with and one of those
things is offline and Doc's offline was
a huge effort and it really pushed the
boundaries of what's possible and by
taking this step forward I think what
we're really showing the community at
large is that it can be done it can be
done for you so first what stocks who
here has used google documents by a show
of hands that is fantastic that's pretty
much all of you so i should be able to
skip through this quick sesh I through
this quickly but i do want to give a
high-level overview so what Google Docs
used to be a couple of years ago is
content editable which is basically a
text area into which you type it
transferred it puts it all into HTML it
would send it up to the server the
server would store it as HTML and that
was bad that was bad because the model
the view the controller they're they're
all the same thing basically you can't
have your model and your and your view
both be HTML so what documents is now is
it's a full fledge word processor what
you see on the screen was placed there
explicitly you can have tab stops for
example in HTML we placed that text
explicitly the cursor for example is
just a 1 pixel wide div which blinks on
a timeout
timer right so when you click back when
you click into the document it
explicitly positions that div in that
location everything is done in
JavaScript so that's really cool and
that really enables offline web apps the
number one thing that you need is you
need everything to be done on the client
if your app depends on constant server
communication to get all of its
information then you're you're gonna
you're going to suffer so we start off
in the right place but there were still
a number of things that we didn't do so
what we do what used to happen two years
ago Doc's would connect to a server and
pull down a huge chunk of content and
that includes the model the application
itself meaning the the JavaScript the
CSS etc and along with all the
configuration options and that
completely breaks MVC we're bundling it
all together so why do we do it for
performance but obviously or as you'll
see will we will have suffered because
of this but what's really nice is that
after this one chunk there's only little
things being sent back and forth to the
server the client really does the heavy
the heavy lifting here so that means
that if you have a really laggy
connection it doesn't matter you can
continue typing away and after that
connection is restored it will all get
sensitive server the server's really
just the persistence mechanism and the
client is the client is there for
everything that you do that really
enabled us to to take off line to next
step in the sense that we already had
this infrastructure from our real-time
collaboration built into our app so what
is Doc's like now as you see i make no
there's no separation between server and
storage to us server and storage are
sort of the same thing when we pull the
document from from storage or server it
doesn't matter so let's walk you through
at a high level what happens so first we
have this happy user and he types in
Doc's like google com he types in a
specific a
cific document ID either by bookmark or
using using the drive launcher and from
here chrome triggers the fallback
application because we don't have a
network connection let's assume we're
offline now the online flow is largely
unaffected the fallback application
takes them to a place which determines
which binary to run and we'll jump into
this in a second determines which binary
to run which java and c says to pull in
determines of the dock is available and
then sends the user to the docks
themselves to an offline specific binary
that offline binary then reads the
doctrine user data from the database and
uses that info to load the offline
document we use we then use browser we
then use browser history AP is to
rewrite the URL to make it look like you
were the online binary so why is that
important we don't want to surface to
the user that anything is different
everything should look identical
including the URL as a matter of fact if
you hit refresh it uses the current URL
in the URL bar so it will actually go
through this entire flow of hitting the
fallback application figuring out which
binary to use ensuring that the document
is available offline etc if if you don't
have a connection so as the user
interacts with their document as they're
typing stuff in it gets saved it gets
saved both locally as you see in uh in
the first part and then down to the
server what we store locally is pretty
much identical to what we sent to the
server and that's done so that as we
read it back it's exactly what the
server is sending to us so this works
really well except this only talks about
one document so what can we do to really
push this out because we have lots of
documents that are offline we have
what's known as a shared worker this is
actually a JavaScript shared worker
which which we synchronize all documents
with in the background so there's a
locking mechanism which I won't go into
in this talk it's an entire talk in
itself to ensure that nothing gets
written to storage by multiple by
multiple tabs at the same time but every
single docs tab that you have open has a
pointer to the shared worker so the way
javascript shared workers work as soon
as you close all tabs that points them
the shared worker dies so we also do one
last bit of magic which is a background
page this background page is a
permission that's granted to us through
a chrome app which is why we insured or
we force you to to install the drive
chrome app before before you can use
offline and it's really there for that
permission because if you're typing
offline and you close your tab and you
have chrome open or you have your
computer on and a couple of days later
you still haven't gone to Doc's you
really want that content available it'd
be crazy if it weren't there so let's
drill down a little bit I want to talk
about two things which were which were I
think the really novel parts about Doc's
offline so the first one is how we
manage loading so I talked about
choosing binaries the fallback
application what does that mean and the
second part is matching static data and
these two things really came up as we
were developing we didn't we didn't
envision them beforehand especially the
matching static data and now that's a
really really interesting one so I'm
really curious too I'm gonna ask you
guys a couple questions there as well so
first we're going to talk about managing
offline loading I first want to talk
about the application cache who here has
used an app cache in their in their
applications awesome great so I'm going
to go over this really quickly basically
an app cache allows you to store static
data on disk you reference it through
and through the HTML tag you say you say
the man the app cache manifest points to
this file it's just a blob that looks
like this it has an explicit section
Network section and fall back section
explicit section says if I hit this URL
always use what I have available locally
network says if I hit this URL always go
to the network and the fallback says if
I don't have
a connection available then fall back to
this so so what was the difficulty with
Doc's one of the things that is unique
about Doc's is we don't have just one
binary we have several binaries so for
example we have apps for domain and
people can choose to enable or disable
experimental features that leads to
different binaries but we can't
determine that from the document URL so
as the user types in the URL hit center
they're offline we have to pick the
binary based off that app cache does not
provide us a way to do that there's no
code that that can run there's not even
regular Express regular expression
matching in the explicit explicit cache
entry so instead M excuse me instead
what we have to do is we have a fallback
application so this syntax right at the
bottom says that if the user goes to
anywhere on docstoc google com so doc
cycle combat blah it goes to the
fallback location instead which is also
an explicit cache entry so let's
actually step through an example of this
so the user put some puts in the URL and
or clicks a link to it whichever way
they get it the application at chrome
decides that there is no network
available or the server responds with a
400 whatever forces it and it says hey
look there's a fallback location for
this so from there it forwards to the
fallback location the fallback location
takes a look at the URL which is in the
URL bar and it tries to interpret a few
things what does this point to is the
point to a document yes it's pointing to
a document does the user have
permissions for it uh what kind of
binary do we need for it etc it's the
one that actually does all the
processing by looking at the URL and and
making decisions from there and that's
the way that we can actually intercept
intercept it if those aren't available
if they answer those are no you don't
have the binary or the user doesn't have
permissions it blows up if you do then
we pick the binary and we forward the
user there but there's a catch you can't
there's no way to really communicate
with the binary so if you have an
application cache and you have an
explicit you have an explicit cash there
everything including query params have
to match exactly to hit it except
hashtags so hashes allow you to add
information after a URL it will still
hit the correct app cache manifest if
it's there before the hashtag and
everything afterward is ignored so we
encode a bunch of stuff after that
hashtag to relay that information from
the fallback application to to the
editor itself so that way we can we can
encode the things that are on the
landing page of the editor which weren't
there which are there on the online flow
but we can't get at immediately so
another thing that we noticed for
example is that it's slow to read we use
index DB its load to read index DB while
things are loading because the async
callbacks come back asynchronously at a
time and what you can't determine so if
a large JavaScript binary came in in
between it takes forever to cut to get
the call back and you can't have that
you really want to snap you load so from
there we parse the URL we extract out
the doc idea and whatever other things
are in the hashtag and then we rewrite
it using the browser html5 history API
and that's basically our initial load
flow so that worked really well except
we bumped into this issue and we really
we really only came up on it
infrequently but it was affecting more
and more users and we couldn't really
figure out what was going on so CSS and
JS bundles have to match the landing
page landing page here is just the HTML
page that's served so how does this come
up in practice same buddy have have an
idea of when the the JavaScript in the
HTML page wouldn't match so
this comes up so first let me let me
tell you why they have to match so our
HTML landing page actually points to a
javascript binary that has a hash tag
attached to it so for example we have
the HTML page refer to my javascript
binary 1 2 3 and that ensures that the
api's that are used between them are
identical so why is this a problem so
let's actually step through this and try
to see when this happens so there's a
level of indirection that's added by the
app cache so the user requests the app
cache manifest from a given machine from
machine a and that app cache manifest
says ok so your HDL page is / page for
example or / edit for documents and here
is your JavaScript binary etc that's
fine the users happy everything's good
and then the user goes to actually fetch
that so first they go to fetch the the
hash static content so they go and fetch
my JavaScript binary one two three
perfect not a problem and then they go
to fetch they go to fetch the HTML
landing page and now they hit a
different machine that machine could be
on a different a different schedule so
for example as we're rolling out new
versions of docs this probably won't
come as a surprise to you guys but we
have more than one machine running
Google Docs so as we roll as we roll out
new versions not all machines are on the
same version and that's exactly what's
happening here when we hit when we hit
machine be to actually retrieve the HTML
page it points to my JavaScript binary
456 the worst part about this is that
there's no mechanism to stop this the
the server will order have to return to
hundreds for all of this which from its
point of view it started everything
correctly the browser will see
everything returned properly so it says
my app cache is up-to-date it won't
retrieve a new app cache until there's a
new push so that could be you know a
week so that user won't be able to use
their offline application for that week
because
as soon as they get to the landing page
it will point to a JavaScript binary
which doesn't exist offline because
they're pointing to one two three and
they only have four five six offline so
they explode and exploding is a problem
so there are actually a few solutions
that are possible here does anybody have
any ideas send really bumped into this
before but I hear a yes out there so
what what was your solution or if you're
if you're willing to share it okay okay
that's that's a that's a related problem
so his solution was to make sure that
that that didn't change the the URLs
didn't change that's definitely one
solution and that's something that we
wanted to do but we decided against it
and the reason is you get a lot more
cash hits if you uh if you hit if the
binary is always the same name so for
example if you have my JavaScript binary
1 2 3 you can you can say this expires a
you know a dozen years from now so that
the client never has to refresh the
binary and we weren't willing to undo
some optimizations that having a hash in
our in our JavaScript would an hour
JavaScript binary name would do somebody
else have any ideas all right well I'll
throw some out there so you could
download multiple binaries you could say
I'm going to download java script binary
one two three and four five six the
issue is that we have to know beforehand
when we're going to updates four five
six so before a push we would have to
tell all existing machines hey the next
JavaScript binary is going to be four
five six so download both of them and
that's sort of crappy plus the user is
going to have to download a lot more a
lot more JavaScript binaries and it's
just not the cleanest approach so you
could put the binary and slamming page
instead of having an external javascript
binary just in line it the difficulty
there is really performance
it's really what it boils down to it
also deviates from the online case and
we really wanted to keep the online and
offline flows similar so performance the
problem because we we dynamically
execute our scripts to ensure that only
when we need something does it get
pulled in so the user is able to edit a
document before all of the javascript is
even downloaded so we could put binary
into a comment and then evaluate that
comment so this is actually what what
other people do this is this is a fairly
common pattern and this is one that we
were really considering the problem is
it will deviate from online and offline
and the online case we don't want the
user to have to download two megabytes
of an HTML page before evaluating a
comment and we really did want that that
hard barrier there so you could version
landing pages the other thing you could
do is instead of having / / page or /
edit you could have / edit one / edit to
and / edit one will map to my JavaScript
binary one two three my you know edit
two will map to four five six the issue
is then all applications then have to
know oh I have to hit / edit to instead
of / edit three or instead of / out of
four and getting that coordination right
between all the different editors or
between all the between the fallback
application which actually loads it and
the end the push is kind of complicated
which leads us to intercept entries
which is what we ended up going with so
who here is familiar with the chrome
specific for as far as I know comes to
the concept of intercept entries in the
app cache awesome i'm going to teach you
something new so so chrome specific app
cache entries allow you allow you to
intercept urls using a prefix match
before they hit the network so how do we
use it we can say URL returns URL to so
in this case what we can do is we can
append that version so we can append
that version but have / edit reader
subversion in other words we can have in
the in the explicit entry section we can
have / page given that version we either
through a query parameter or however you
want to append it's that URL then we can
have that intercept entry say / page
always forwards to always forwards to /
page with that version attached so how
does this work why does this work so
what ends up happening is the browser
will actually try to download / page
with the given version if it hits
machine be if we go back to our diagram
and it hits machine be it's going to say
I don't know what that version is and
it's going to send back a 404 the
browser just going to get that 404 and
it's going to say well this app cache
this app cache update was a failure so
let's throw this away and then it does
it again so if the if the machine that
you hit is on a different version if the
machine that you hit when retrieving the
app cache manifest is on a different
version than the machine that you hit
when you actually retrieve the landing
page it just won't update the app cache
will not update so this is guaranteed to
work which is pretty neat and it
requires no difference between the
online in the offline flow we can still
use / page 1 online we don't have to
append a version number to it so why
this talk so I have just a few minutes
left and I really want people to think
about offline it's best for you and it's
best for your users if the stuff that
you if the stuff that you work on is
available for your users all the time
they will be much happier than if it's
available to them only when they have a
connection I'm sure people here despite
how how connected we seem to constantly
be have experienced network outages been
on a plane etc so web apps and
traditional apps are fairly similar
except now web apps can take advantage
of all the benefits of the cloud plus go
offline and I think that we've really
demonstrated it with with Doc's offline
I also wanted to point out some of the
things that made it hard for us like
matching static content through the
landing page that's something which
earlier earlier offline things like
there I mentioned it gears actually did
right and an app in the app cache world
that's that's been difficult for us to
do and it can be done so think offline
whenever you construct something make
sure that whenever it goes to server
just send its local store as well then
read it back from local store so I have
a few minutes left so I wanted to thank
you all for for coming and sitting
through my talk I didn't know if anybody
had any questions about any of the
things that I've discussed and i'll also
be available at the at the google booth
after this so feel free to visit us
we're in the and the lunchroom yes hey
so with the intercept rules was that
something that you put into chrome
because docks required it or is it
something that chrome put in then docs
discovered it like as it is that is eid
back loop or that is an excellent
question so the answer the answer is we
discovered it so if you take a look at
if you take a look at the history of it
intercept entries were added sometime
last November in the newest version of
Chrome nightlies at the time and and we
took advantage of it at some point in
June something like that so that was
that was innocent of us other questions
kind of a follow-up to this one are you
pushing that to standard bodies to get
because that sounds really useful but
then it only works on Chrome it is
incredibly useful so that's something
that we leave up to so there was a talk
earlier today in this room about pushing
stuff to standards bodies and it takes a
lot of time so that's something that we
have been pushing for there are a couple
of things that are better slowing that
down but this is something that we're
pushing for we think that it's an
excellent improvement to every browser
if it's one of its one of the things
along with getting permissions from the
chrome apps and background pages etc
that are preventing us from doing docs
offline cross-browser right now it's
chrome only so
pushing this to through standards will
make docs offline work everywhere that's
the better for us so that's definitely
something that we're pushing for other
questions I think that's it I think
that's it for now if you have any more
questions Kevin will be at the Google
booth inside but thank you very much