hello all right thanks everybody for
coming out the title of my talk is
atomic components managing dynamic react
components using atomic design so just
quick show of hands who here is hurt
atomic atomic design previously great
awesome um who's heard of react okay all
right you're sort of redox and data
management flux okay okay great all
right so um this is going to assume some
prior knowledge of how data is managed
outside of just specific react
parent-child type stuff um going to
assume a little bit of prepare knowledge
about redox or flux just data cross
component communication via some sort of
you know third party however atomic
design you know will be will be getting
into um so my name is Joey I'm a
front-end developer at balderdash we are
no Jas consultants and maintain errs of
sales um that's that's my website find
me on the interwebs at yeah Jody doe
it's just my name mixed up all right
atomic design so what is atomic design
it is a methodology for creating design
systems and the way this works is that
it's broken up into five discrete levels
you have atoms molecules organisms
templates and pages um this was designed
by Brad frost and dave olson they um
have a little library to help you
organize your project in atomic design
called pattern lab pattern labs at i/o
and atomic design it lends a context
interfaces it's very client-facing it
helps I take some sort of
static mock up on these components are
these are these small pieces and allows
you to put an additional layer on top of
it which might sound like bloat but um
it it provides a sort of focus that
allows you to with these descriptions
communicate more easily across across a
team or explain to your client exactly
how this is going to work in a greater
flow of things why do we need it so
anytime we come across some sort of some
abstraction or conceptual blue we we
have to ask ourselves is the return
worth the investment right so long in
our case I know as developers we like to
maybe sometimes over design our
structures and our systems um just
because we feel like that's thorough but
when we already have something that's
you know on a pretty flat simple level
adding this canned a lot of times
bringing a focus to it an organization
that doesn't quite um exist well it
doesn't exist without it right so um the
atomic design in this case helps chunk
with these five components helps create
this artificial hierarchy of the
components in a mental way so how does
it do this well it breaks it down into
five atomic levels so on the Left we
have a small atom arm which I'm get
composed into molecules which then into
organisms int and then into templates
and then into actual pages so with atoms
and molecules and organisms what is an
atom right well an atom in our domain is
something like an input element or
button element just small very low level
HTML elements molecules would be a group
of these together let's say a search bar
right we have an input field and we have
a button that works with that input
field those together form some sort of
you I togetherness a concept in the UI
that is on we wouldn't think of them
separately so we can think of those as
an organ as a molecule then we take it a
step further and we say well that on
that search that search bar has a
further contacts usually in UI patterns
some and some sort of maybe a header
element or something like that it can be
anywhere I can um you know be in a
anywhere on the page but it still is
usually grouped into something that has
a greater context and that's where our
organisms come in at least an atomic
design so these are repeatable elements
or groups of molecules that tell a story
in the UI and so here's an example of
them right so at the top we obviously
have an atom underneath that we have
molecules we just have some sort of some
sort of text along with an input and the
button together those three atoms form a
molecule might be over explaining this I
think is pretty pretty intuitive
underneath that we have an organism we
have a logo we have some some navigation
links and then we have the search bar
together and that's in traditional
atomic design what's what's considered
an organism so outside of that Brad
frost recommends that we break our
chemistry analogy and we just completely
pivot into templates um because it quote
makes more sense to our clients in a lot
of way um these are the templates are
just groups of organisms that are
dedicated to a page level abstraction
and can moved around wireframe style the
the pages would be the actual instances
of those templates that are designed to
be deliverables so yeah okay that's
fantastic um it's great for documents
great for print but you know we don't
deal with that stuff anymore we're in a
post document arrow um we as react are
building user interfaces not necessarily
pages and style sheets and you know we
have one HTML document we're serving not
pages that match up one to one with the
styles or just views tied to specific
models we have things that we have
small components and groups of them that
need to have their own information it's
a very very pre spy idea so react does
have these very specific concerns as I
mentioned we we have these living
breathing life cycle driven components
with these contextual stores that model
are you I state anymore it's not like
we're just pulling anything out of a
database anymore the organism relates
only to other organisms in the atomic
metaphor and that they coexist in visual
space right along when along one one
another on the template or page this
says nothing about how they're going to
talk to each other it simply means a
visual organization and grouping and we
have concerns about how we can actually
make these things talk to one another
when when it comes to implementation we
lack that atomic principle so can we
solve that doesn't AMA caprent.com we as
react developers use the same metaphors
because they seem very useful right I
mean we start with you I we start with a
mock-up and then we chop it up and break
it down and organize them try to find
something cool with our directory and
good way to good way to put them
together so we can get this like actual
tangible feel with it so this is great
for that how can we use it arm luckily
pattern on pattern lab is designed a
very and very you know Foss manner it's
very flexible with naming a structure
it's brand new right a lot of stuff
we're seeing in the space is new and
open to change there's no one right way
to do it and we think that's just fine
main things as you please and we'll
leave the hair splitting out of things
fantastic all right so let's let's
rethink this how are we going to do this
well so what I've done is on we're gonna
we're going to not break after organisms
we're not going to pivot the templates
in pages we're instead going to extend
keep keep with this economic this
ecological metaphor and add to new
levels the ecosystem and the environment
so we'll go from atoms to molecules
organisms ecosystems and then into a
sort of larger environment
and what these do so we're also going to
slightly modify the organism arm there's
a problem with the organism I feel where
the organism is a top level minute
pivots anatomic design they say okay
yeah an organism can be either you know
the header the footer these groups of
molecules I get that we group these
molecules or let's say we have a product
grid we are right we have these
repeating products something it's a
repeatable container that's also an
organism and it's like okay so we we
have something that I understand the
grouping inside the header but we're
also just going to leverage this
organism because we want to pivot to
templates to describe product grids also
which are fundamentally different as
repeatable containers are not a big fan
so I say let's let's keep the organism
is repeatable container that's fine um
but now that we have these these new
concepts to leverage the ecosystem and
environment let's figure out if we can
we can take the context of what would
encompass some sort of header or footer
and maybe you know abstract it out so
you see where we can go with that so
we're atomic design pivots towards
client understanding with pages and
templates we need a pivot towards
implementation while still retaining the
usefulness of the visual metaphors so
with the ecosystems we're going to see
an example so this is our fake social
app fantastic it's great um it's just a
mock-up that i put together we see we
have some sort of hey what's up you know
it's going to tell someone my status
some notifications or messages chat
people on the right or buddies you can
see who's online talk to them if we won
I have some other stuff in there some
post some comments on there a lot of
people like my stuff at school have a
lot of friends gotta get nice gallery in
there showing some awesome pictures from
Jas calm my profile image let everyone
know who I am and how I see myself
alright so what we're
to do instead is that this is the
environment we're encapsulating the
whole thing environments are going to be
a little bit flexible because in a lot
of times when we're not just building
this you know like great little isolated
you I that is super cool on dribble and
moves inside and things change inside
this little card container and stuff
like that we actually still are building
product that might need to move from
page to page we need full pages so this
environment is going to represent this
pay the still same page level or if you
don't need that if everything is just
moving pieces inside of the static you I
just one page level your environment is
the application itself be your app
component it's also important to have
the so it's good to have supper shell
not even for like flocks of redox or
anything because a lot of times if you
have siblings like us siblings like the
nav bar or the content container um you
still need a way to get that information
from an outboard to that so you just
pass it up and that's down and so you're
good there the environment still lends
itself to there so it is flexible in
that way but still very useful outside
of that I want you ought to take a
minute just to think so we know the arm
we have this environment we also have
these ecosystems that are going to
obviously be sub junks of this we're
going to break them up into contact with
rule components like I'd mentioned
before on the the nav bar or something
like a some sort of header or footer so
if you were to do this given this you
guys have just heard this just now um
take a moment to think about what you
would imagine would be the ecosystems of
of this right I'm going to show you in
just a second of how I interpreted this
because a lot of these are just design
decisions so this is how I think
ecosystem the ecosystems would be we
have one on the right for the chat we
have one for the main profile and then
we have one that would maybe be a header
or footer so they they should represent
the major core container components and
ideas the interface is trying to
communicate
um also provides a nice isolated context
for when you're trying to style the the
three major ecosystems here chat header
orientation and profile if you're using
Redux for your data management this is
where I have to assume the prior
knowledge there's a thing called smart
components which if you don't know redux
um the smart components are the
container components that are going to
not only hold dumb components to which
you pass pass your state and prompts but
also communicate with your reducers and
get the information you need to pass it
down they're kind of like the managers
in the application and this also lends
itself really well to these this
ecosystem metaphor this is where um that
manipulation is going to happen helps um
not so we can still leverage these
things right because you know a ver mob
came up with this smart and dumb the
dumb czar your will be your organisms
and your molecules and atoms and you
just pass them down through it and it's
nice that this level of abstraction you
know there's this conceptual bloat still
is able to map pretty well two things
that are already out there so we don't
need to add another thing it just it
just kind of plugs right in because
we're all thinking along the same path
sort of thing with on breaking these you
eyes up into up into new ways so yeah
they're both are responsible for both
handling the data and delegating the NIP
you laid state so notice that we still
have one ecosystem that is significantly
complex versus the other two um the main
profile ecosystem that could probably be
broken down even further because I don't
think we're ready to go to the organism
level yet um so ecosystems as a nature
can be nested so we we break it up with
visually and it allows us to have some
sort of isolation for when we want to
pass things around and that way we could
be like hey you know go go wrong with
this this profile part of the ecosystem
and you go run with this and then we'll
just worry about connecting later maybe
maybe even make it a dumb AP system they
don't have to be smart right consider
that one a dumb component then have the
parent ecosystem the larger one the
profile section
the one that's going to handle all that
so you know you work on that you work on
that and what we'll figure it out later
so after that we're going to break it
down into organisms right repeatable
containers chat instances each of which
have a molecule that is you know your
name your profile picture um the
repeatable posts inside of which could
be a number of different things right i
mean they're just like cards they have
this one has a text this one is
information about who's following me um
two down there's one there's about the
some sub information about what I added
with my new gallery you know just
repeatable elements I think that's
pretty straightforward so how do we
organize these right um this is great
it's it's very useful to UM to start
thinking of these components in this
this just slightly abstracted way to
kind of lend to you know give them some
sort of orthogonal contacts if you will
arm but can we also use this to help us
actually literally organize their
components in our project and the answer
is yeah so just a just a brief tour of
how things used to be organized right
and react in the beginning everybody
just we had a components folder and we
put them all in it was cool it was it
was very poor because we were like oh
these components are cool this new idea
you know we weren't really organizing
our directives like that until and then
John Papa came along and was like hey
let's let's add add an additional layer
of context let's say hey you know what
if all these directives are going to be
inside of a footer or header let's um
let's make a footer component let's make
a footer folder or something and put all
the directives that are associated with
that in there same thing we so we
started doing that with our react
components we said okay you know what so
I've got a header part I'm some header
components is getting kind of big got a
profile I'm going to put on my profile
components in there and a footer and put
on my components and that's fine that's
kind of how we do it today the most
common way to organize our your
components
but you know this arm you still have to
refer to is it still requires some sort
of over design I guess in a lot of ways
I mean you'd have to a lot of thinking
about naming and name spacing and where
you going to put things and we're going
to call things and might not be too bad
of an issue but um when you when you can
instead go back to what we had which is
this an idea of okay look these are all
components yeah they fall into these
trick these these are these ideas but
these ideas don't relate to with a
specific type of implementation for
application that we're going to use they
might you know we might want to reuse
them in other things and they're now
scope to this you know profile idea
let's instead you know let's go with
something flat let's this is going to be
a molecule no matter where it is it's
pretty clear this is going to be an atom
it's pretty clear so we can take what we
had just that components folder and then
make our five atomic folders and just
start you know throwing our components
in there as they as they receive the as
they as they match up with these atomic
principles so what's what's nice about
that is that it hopes when you're trying
to refactor you want to change things a
lot of times if you want to consider an
organism something on an organism level
smart and that makes you want to change
it to an ecosystem instead of going up
and then finding exactly where that was
in the project previously and finding
the name and finding the path for it you
just go up one level because
everything's flat and you change the
name and you just say alright this
molecule there and or ok that's the
ecosystem now so that's that's a brief
idea of what atomic components um can
can help you with we've used didn't few
of our projects to really great success
um communicating with design especially
designed knows these things you'd be
surprised how quickly even non technical
managers can pick up on this type of
they will they kind of go off on the
road and you you know II first start
doing this feel like you might have to
handhold or something a little but then
the you'd be surprised it's actually
really intuitive I'm hoping that you
know when I when we did a little
experiment with you know okay you create
your own ecosystem sort of thing we all
probably kind of broke it up into at
least those few sections right might not
have been exactly that might have been
more might have been a little less but I
think we all understand is you know
front-end developers exactly how these
you eyes lend themselves so to get
started um I put a little boilerplate
atomic components app up on github this
is the app right here these little peace
signs it's an environment holding two
ecosystems inside of which are for
organisms inside of which are molecules
with two atoms so it uses you know
webpack and SES s modules and you know
redox and all the cool fun stuff so you
can just clone it and get started and
play around with it and hopefully find
as much use in it as we have I