so it's very nice you to come here and
after the bubble accident so all the
rain will stay in the clouds from just a
little longer I'm going to talk about
Mona Lisa I've 30 minutes if you've any
questions just try to interrupt me I
hope to address them during the talk
unless I'm running out of time so I'm
told not to wander this up on this side
so probably going to stand here so this
is what I'm going to present the agenda
and presenting now a family Guatemala
loose Lisa who knows the painting well
that's nice see a lot of hands I'm going
to tell you what mona lisa has to do
with the Traveling Salesman problem if
you don't know already what relation
with the P versus NP problem is and
welcome to the TSP art which is actually
the main subject of this talk so the
Mona Lisa she's very well known I guess
everybody raised his or her hand but
she's a mysterious woman as you know
family known because of the enigmatic
smile and just chillin at the bottom
here and there's a lot of talk why she
smells like this there's even a
Wikipedia page with a lot of conspiracy
theories why she's smiling but I think I
know why she's smiling and let's do was
another detail of the painting namely
this road and why is this important well
if two little bit more about Mona Lisa
so who knows the details about the
person behind the portrait again this is
good because then I can tell you the
next slide the portraits of Lisa
Gherardini she lived the in the
Renaissance period in Italy and Florence
vini was a very famous family although
at the age of of Lisa ash the the family
ran out of money so she married
Francisco del Giocondo which was a very
rich mostly rich silk merchant and when
I discovered when I was
looking up Mona Lisa I was very nice to
see that she married out of love so that
appeals to my more romantic side but
what do you do if you are modestly
wealthy you have to look at the
expenditures you have so that's a that's
why the following problem comes in this
is Venice not Florence and let's say
that lisa has to go and talk to a lot of
merchants and salesmen and have to
travel through vanish through all these
places somewhere are interested buyers
some are sellers of silk and the
question is if you have to visit all
these points what is the most efficient
route to to do this does anybody have a
clue nah me neither because that's
basically the main point of my article
of my my talk the task of finding for a
fine a number of points the best route
through the points at the shortest route
and that's actually they're called the
Traveling Salesman problem and this
problem is well known it's actually not
invented by monnalisa you can imagine
that it's used and at that time already
but it's firmly stated by a
mathematician an Alton and so this is a
little bit about my background on math
admission mathematician Lee train so the
question is how would you solve this and
I please raise your hand again like you
did when you was asked you know the
model exam how would you solve the
problem
yeah so that's it's a very good
suggestion trial combinations record the
shortest that's actually my answer as
well and interesting enough we as
developers we use mathematicians we as a
species don't know another better
solution in a particular sense of the
word so although this is a it's a good
algorithm to solve this problem or it is
an algorithm let's say let's say the
least of that it's not very nice to do
that and why not well let's imagine a
one-point city the problem will become
trivial there's only one possibility to
check and let's say that we can do that
in one second as the number of points we
have to visit gross it's in the
left-hand column the possibilities grows
which is extended like very fast and the
duration I've made the second line
average yawn I hope not i'm going to
join your to death with this go but it's
amazingly how long how fast the problem
gets out of hand so for example with 33
cities in the tour if you have six
possibilities you can jaan at a time
average lee but if you take 15 towns i
can't even pronounce the number in
english but it's roughly three centuries
before you finished checking all the
possibilities so this this is an
inherent difficulty the problem with the
possibilities because we has the GS com
sure whether on nobody well there's a
there's a Rubik's Cube on on the front
and the Rubik's Cube has a roughly the
same amount of possibilities as 15
points of the Traveling Salesman problem
but some people can solve it in 20
seconds so there's a really different
different problem than the Traveling
Salesman problem and that's a very
interesting property would you like to
talk now so word of the P equals NP
problem who knows what it means
okay well that's interesting but that's
precisely what I want to talk about so
there's a famous unsolved problem in
computer science famous for a lot of
reasons just recently there was a movie
about travelling salesman problem which
had the subject this problem so that's
why it's famous and there are popular
reference to it but what does it mean
actually well if you explain the two
different peas in there so what does P
mean so let's let's assume we have a
function edition everybody knows how to
do that and we're going to profile this
method on the following data set so the
profile method is not shown but it will
run a few times of this function with
the data two three and two so it will
actually answer with five I guess so
this is actually very interesting
because what I was expecting and this is
also nicely when you're preparing a talk
is that the amount of time to perform
these runs would grow it's actually not
the case so we have to talk to somebody
who knows the vm a lot better than me
why this is but you can imagine if
you're doing this calculation your hand
shift for example let's take 31 and 27
you have to first add 127 to form 8 and
then 3 to 2 245 so that's the answer and
if you do this for longer and longer
numbers you have to take longer and
longer time but it grows nicely and so
the P stands here for polynomial so who
knows what a polynomial is okay so
polynomial informally means efficient
it's not entirely the case but as the
input grows so if you have larger and
larger number let's say we have a two
two more two more digits then the then
the run time of the algorithm doesn't
grow very much actually so let's the
numbers grow twice as large the rent on
will grow twice as large for this case
so that's polynomial and generally this
means a computer can solve this
efficiently and it's obvious occasional
addition but there are other exam
balls so I just told you what P means so
does anybody want to guess what NP means
and so the obvious answer will be not
polynomial and that's not the case
unfortunately so we go to the next slide
what does NP me it means actually
non-data Mason deterministically
polynomial so at the end doesn't have a
relation to not p and i'm going to try
to explain what that means again we're
going to profile a function this time
there is a verification of factorization
so let's say somebody knows their
numbers very well and can call out the
factorization in prime factors of six so
does anybody know the factorization of
six yeah two times three to six so
you're going to be my Oracle which
whispers the answers in my ear because
when I'm verifying the result I don't
have to I don't have to do the hard work
i can do the easy work so it's somebody
asks what are the factors of 27 my
Oracle would answer three times three
times three and I can check in my head
three times three is nine times three
threes 27 yeah my oracle is very good so
this is this is the case with MP there
is a question what is the product of a
what's the factorization of certain
number and somebody can give me the
answer and only want to do is can I can
I check it is this clear until now
somebody's not in that's good okay so
informally NP means there's a problem
and I can check the answer in a
polynomial time so i can efficiently
check the answer so the famous question
is about is as follows now there's a
slide there is every problem that can be
verified efficiently like factorization
if you have an oracle you can check the
result is itself efficiently solvable
well who knows the answer to this
question
really there is no answer well that's
that's that's more probably the best
answer today because nobody knows for
sure so this is actually an open problem
which is formed in the in the 60s when
computer science read took off and
nobody knows for sure it's actually one
of the most famous millennium prize
problems designing me know the Cray
Institute the clay Institute is a
mathematic institute founded by a
billionaire which is money to spare and
he wants to sell seven problems the N
equals NP problem is one of them and if
you can solve it you will win a million
dollars so that's why it's interesting
to work on this problem and actually
it's very interesting because the
Traveling Salesman problem is an example
that is known to be easily verifiable
because if someone gives you a route and
you can check what the length is but
it's not easy to do this actually not
sure what's happening now so if you are
at work and you need to blow up your
mind and you can work on the on for
example minesweeper because mine
sweepers also is a problem which is
known to be np-complete and if you can
solve it efficiently you can win a
million dollar so cue balls walks in and
sees you solving minesweeper you can say
no no I'm doing research so that would
be an interesting problem to this day
the reason why another reason why it's
famous is because XKCD did a comic con
it so brute force solution the big o
notation says drin time something I
would rather run time so and faculty
that's a long time you can do it a
little bit better but still it's a long
time so nobody knows an efficient
algorithm to solve this problem so if
you're walking out this bowl you have to
remember one thing if you know something
that falls in the class of NP complete
then you can do something interesting
because there is no known efficient
algorithm yet so you have to do other
things
so what does have to do with TSP arc
well a traveling salesman tour has an
interesting property so let's assume
that there's a route this is a small
part of the route through a lot of
cities so for example the route shrubs
along the bubble enter there through the
left leg crosses over to the other
sitting down over the ground and up
again so this wouldn't be an optimal
solution because there's a shocker short
con does anybody sees it already well
there's some points oh sorry I have to
click this I guess so you can take a
shortcut so if you're entering from the
upper left instead of going down the
other side you can go straight down and
this is actually shorter because you
don't have to travel this lag and this
lag so this is it shorter there and it's
shorter so you have a smaller route so
this is an interesting problem in any
rendition of a traveling salesman
problem you will never find crosses and
this is a nice aesthetic property that
you actually can fill out a form it
never touches the self you can trace it
with one pen without lifting your hand
so this is a very arty and aspect of the
of a root this is a traveling that
solves the Traveling Salesman instance
so how can we use it to render the Mona
Lisa well first if to stipple it's
actually a technical term I guess the
Mona Lisa and unfortunately I try this
out with my browser and because I wanted
to do this presentation my browser and
it is a hard problem to stipple a an
image so i could only use a thousand
points and then that this is a an
example which you didn't use which isn't
formed in the browser and then you can
all see the dis isn't an optimal tour
because there are crosses here so it's a
bit of a shame then this is an
indication that the Traveling Salesman
problem is a hard problem to solve but
if you take this offline and invest more
time because I tried it with 10,000
points and it
just freezes my browser so i took this
offline and this is actually an example
of rendition of the Mona Lisa solved as
a traveling salesman problem and painted
the tour and I think this is a very nice
example of how fundamental research in
mathematics and computer science
combined with art can form beautiful
pictures so is this clear what I'm
talking about great there's a question
or okay the question was what points are
you visiting the picture so first of all
you take an image and you make a
black-and-white version of it and then
probably you just the brightness of it
and you throw a lot of points at the
image and you form the image by the
darker regions the the image will clump
to get of the dots will clump together
and then the writer in regions the image
are or sparser so actually these this
this makes a rendition of the image just
like that the last slide the previous
slide so this you can see the Mona Lisa
in here and if if you have more points
the more points will grow together to
form darker regions so these points
actually are used to solve the Traveling
Salesman problem this is the answer your
question great this one
so the so the mansion is this isn't an
optimal solution this probably isn't the
optimal one that's correct because this
is actually up on a website to try out
your heart problems and it's solved
because there's no crossings you can see
that but a problem so you don't know
your goes it so hard to do correctly
answer the question is this the optimal
tour it probably isn't this one that's
correct it's not optimal other questions
because it's time for questions now so
will be nice so if you don't have
questions I have a question for you so
this is a look probably not going to see
the result of this but um I had a small
daughter she's a year and a half and
she's great and although I don't want to
push her into a technical job it would
be great if she wanted to pursue that
and if you're a female technical person
I will ask you to go to this website and
give a write a letter to Sophie which is
a year and a half with some advice
because I think it's very hard for women
in this society with a lot of men in the
technical side to become a technical
person and work on that so this this
repository would be my present for 12
birthday that if she wants to be a
technical leader in this field that she
has some advice from for female role
models so if you take the time if you
know a female role model so that's
basically it are there any more
questions for done don't go all right