hello hi welcome to my talk it's very
loud there we go better still pretty
loud so my talk is called untitled thank
you all for coming here no just kidding
it's called breaking the rules mitering
your node application and my name is ron
i am from company called upbeat and we
do monitoring and this talk sort of came
out of some of the recent work we've
been doing with node and specifically
monitoring in node so it's gonna talk
about how you can do monitoring in node
in sort of a general way hopefully is
going to be interesting and hopefully
we're going to be breaking some some of
the rules a bit m so the goal here is
and i want to show you how you can get
out of the box monitoring for your web
application in node and so our box
monitoring for me means that i can see
how long my endpoints are taking to
respond but I can also see how long time
I'm spending in each endpoint talking to
Mongo Mongo DB for example how long time
I'm taking it how long time it takes to
talk to Redis how long time I'm spending
rendering templates etc and I want this
/ end point but further than that I
wanted to be out of the box so that I
don't have to go and change my
application very much to get this
monitoring so I wanted to work in a way
that I can just request a module and
that basically gives me out of the box
monitoring so how do you do that so
first i will introduce a bunch of a
small little things primitives and so
this is a trace bookkeeper it's very
very simple you can call call start and
end on a trace bookkeeper and basically
it will create a new trees if it doesn't
already have one with this name that you
gave it then call start on it and then
you can in the tree
ace em with a specific name so that's
pretty simple and I want to keep one of
these trace bookkeepers around for each
request to my application trace looks
like this and so when you do monitoring
a lot of stuff goes on at the same time
how do you measure time spent in an
application it's that can be kind of
tricky so let's say you have two Mongol
crew is going on at the same time you
doesn't really make sense to sort of add
the time up that each each one of them
spent so the the semantics around how
you actually how you actually measure
time when stuff happens concurrently
it's kind of interesting and what this
trace thing we'll do is that let's say
you have to Mongo queries that start
approximate at the same time but one
ends a way later than the other one then
with this trace a primitive here we're
going to count the time from the first
one started to the last one ended hey
what it also does is it can sort of
measure consecutive traces so if you
start a mockery and then end it it'll
take that time and summit with the next
Mongol crew you're doing so if so if you
have mon crews are not overlapping it
will some the time for each mockery
together okay so there was some
low-level all of the stuff and sorry
that was some primitives I think one
more thing to notice here is that I'm
using the high resolution timer and if
you're doing timing a sort of monitoring
like this you should be using the high
resolution high resolution timer because
it's much more a low-level then then
breaking out dates and started starting
to compare them and yeah okay so let's
not bring some rules first we want to
hook into HTTP server ed listener that's
part of the reason why we do that is
part of the idea that it should be
something that works out of the box and
so what I'm actually going to do is I'm
gonna monkey patch a the ed listener a
method on HTTP server and there's a lot
of stuff going on here but what you
actually need to sort of
is that we will call on request instead
of the original call back and we'll
we'll start a new trace bookkeeper for
this particular request will set it on
the request and once the request is
finished we extract the route name from
the request and we call this mythical
request finished so this obviously
requires that you're building an Express
application but you can do the same
thing for most of the other frameworks
out there yes okay now this was sort of
our hook into the request response cycle
now let's actually start measuring some
code so this is an example of how you
could be calling Redis talking to radis
this could happen anywhere in your
application and it's pretty standard so
you try to get a key from ritas and when
you when you get it you can log it out
to the console so how would we measure
the time it actually took to get this
key from ritas this is one way to do it
you can see that i'm using something
called trace code here and i gave trace
code is the name that i'm passing in
this time it's just ready to get sort of
indicates what I'm what I'm currently
trying to measure and you see that the
trace code will return a function that
then wraps the original call back so
when I call trace code it'll start the
timer and then when the callback is
called I'll stop the timer and then call
the original call back you could monkey
patch the register library if you wanted
to get this out of the box I'm going to
leave that as an exercise but it's quite
simple to do and you can see what trace
code looks like here so it's also quite
simple M will call stop on the current
on the book key before the current
request and when the when trace cold is
called and then we return this function
and that will wrap the original call
back and call end on the on the
bookkeeper for this for this name so you
might think this actually doesn't work
because there's something missing here
and then you will be right the request
is missing so what's going on here
is we have a request that comes in
through our HTTP server and we want to
measure some code that happens somewhere
else in my application and connect it to
this request because I'm not per request
oh poor endpoint measurements so how do
you do that that's pretty difficult
because a lot of stuff can go on in
between the request to the web server
and you actually measure measuring some
code somewhere in your application so
connecting measurements to a request is
not that simple um you have event loop
chicks and you have a lot of requests
going on at the same time so there was
this wonderful API called create a sink
listener and the quote there's from the
documentation and what this does is it
basically gives us a hook into the event
loop so that means we get a call back
just before anything is put on the event
loop and we get a call back just after
something is about to start that was on
the event you and just before we put
something on your win loop we get the
option to store some data that will then
be restored when that thing that we're
about to put on the event loop actually
runs and do we use using this you can
actually pass down the request from the
from where the request from where we
hook into the HP server all the way down
to where we want to trace our code so
it's like a primitive to actually allow
us to pass a context between a sinking
ticks in node that's wonderful that's
exactly what we need unfortunately it
only live in node for very very short
period of time that's really unfortunate
so how do we solve this we do some
monkey patching so basically what you
can do is you can monkey patch every
single time or in every single scenario
that something gets put on the event
loop and obtain the same functionality
and that's pretty complicated some
libraries out there they've tried to do
it and so the most popular one is the
esig listener there's also some stuff
going on in anglo
world with zone j/s and there's
something called a shrink wrap and as a
working group that is working with this
which is the most promising of the sort
of native primitives right now and it's
not the not in yet but hopefully it'll
be that soon so we don't have to monkey
patch so badly ah but so for right now
you have to you actually have to monkey
patch so there's this library called
Essex state that Thomas wrote some of
this right here and it's based on a
solicitor so it takes this pretty
convoluted interface that's called a
create a sink listener and basically
allows you to save some state anywhere
in your code and all the stuff that you
put on the event loop will then have a
this state available for you and so it's
a much more intuitive interface and it
looks like this so you require a sixth
eighth you basically set something on
the Essex state and then it gets sort of
frozen so when I put something on the
event loop it's going to take whatever
is in my currently well whatever is
currently in my state in Essex state and
make that available when the when the
thing runs that I've that I've put on
the event loop so this will print foo
and then bar which is a little bit
counterintuitive if you look at the
execution order here um but that's sort
of a simplified or a much easier
interface for us to use to pass data
between execution context so let's go
back to our beautifully wrapped HTTP
server so the new thing here is that
when I have a new request I actually put
the request in my asking state which
means that all the stuff all the things
that I put on the event loop now will
have access to the quest and which is
great that we like what we need that
means that in my trace code helper I can
just pull out the request and start
doing my measurements on the request but
that's quite useful
and all we need to do now is actually to
when our request is finished we need to
take all the measurements that we made
for this request and sort of put it in a
in a global somewhere that we can access
and so that's what fit request finish
does this is what that looks like and
it's very simple just to sort of take
the stuff that is in bookkeeper and put
it in request stats and I can spend too
much time with that and then finally we
can expose it as an end point in my
Express application so that's what this
thing does you see at the bottom here I
have / stats and calling that I will get
a nice JSON that actually shows what the
time has been spent on and so what i'm
doing here is i go over all the stuff
that i have in my request stats and
average average things out so i can see
on average how much time is being spent
in Redis how much time is being spent in
on go etc and so it looks like this
basically exposed to the endpoint you
can see how many requests are being made
to each endpoint and you can see em how
many red is gets how much time i'll
never spend on ready skate how much time
I spend on L range and how much time I
spend rendering the index view and etc
yeah so that was sort of a whirlwind of
how you can patch up your your node
application to get performance out of
the box and there's a lot of
complications involved here and so add
up at upbeat we've been working on this
and if you don't want to spend all that
time doing it yourself you can can check
out of it it looks like this and that's
pretty much it actually that was 12
minutes