so chat for a second about Bespin just a
couple of slides but then i created this
missile labs and quickly grew a nice
community of i'm sure stuff over here
like Julianne Moore turn like a ton of
people there's like twenty committers at
this point I think and we wanted to
build this editor of our dreams that was
totally accessible from anywhere
included any device in any location we
kind of played around a little bit about
what would it be like if I'm on the
beach my boss calls me I want to fix a
bit of code and I could quickly on my
iPhone or pre login have a little weird
you do I it they're going to fix that
better code hit upon it and then keep
going on our way that was kind of like
one of the visions also going to a
friend's house and being able to get
your entire environment we wanted it to
be really simple like text may and not
be this like really bulky ide and it was
all about this performance that I talked
about this morning was like can we make
this thing scale correctly and then we
wanted collaboration to be a key feature
if you're on the web we want it to be
very very social and so what does that
mean what would it mean for us to
actually be able to write code together
and do fun things so we played around
with even bringing kind of gaming
functionality so like the team leader
kind of joins builds a bunch of unit
tests you have to go off and like score
points by implementing unit tests and
stuff like that and then making the
command line kind of integrated I just
like I loved c'mon Lions I love
Quicksilver Eunice Kamala's I wanted it
kind of baked in to the system and we
had a Mozilla ubiquity I really wanted
to kind of baked those together to add
till I just make it very easy to add
functionality and then to have this
thing fully self hosted so just like I
used to be the Emacs user who like read
my email through
emacs and all that crazy crap and i want
i want that when we have to sell post it
i'm a web guy i want the thing to be the
web for me to be able to trick it out
because you know i'm acting in this you
know eight hours a day so i want to be
able to make exactly how I wanted so you
know here's a little mocker some of the
stuff that we had you know Leon with the
find files aboard and doing all this
crazy stuff with canvas Julian actually
implemented the first find files that
was out there and then collaboration
being able to go through here and have
you know this is simulating one person
at it in a file versus the other one and
we ended up using something called mob
right which was done by a Google I and
it's a platform neutral solution for
doing this collaboration stuff and we've
also we've got people working like in
the eclipse foundation to build support
for it over there and there's even
someone doing a VI implementation so we
hope in the future you'll be able to
collaborate someone could be on Bespin
someone can be under clip someone
communal VI or what have you and just
make it so you can just share code and
see everything that's going on including
things like selection and we had like
autosave building right from the
beginning so in a very first prototype
you could like start writing some code
go home open it up and replay all of the
things that you're done so you always
know you're in exactly the right place
and that's gone and
we'd be coming back again and then we
want to want it to have a place like
goof around and play with new things so
this thing that looks like a defrag
would it be like if we could visualize
our project in different ways so see
who's working on one what's happening in
real time and being able to like really
kind of get an understanding for the
holistic project as a whole we had to
search code across the entire project
across the whole company's projects
across open source we just kind of felt
like they have been that much innovation
in the IDE editor space and we wanted to
really have somewhere to kind of play
around with this stuff yes
just kind of playing around to see what
kind of visualizations can we do to kind
of show what's going on in a project
right yep exactly and other people you
know picked it up right away over the
first weekend this guy Boris from the
Eclipse Foundation took Eclipse stripped
off its head ran it as a server and put
best been in front of it and so that an
enabled Java compilation and get errors
back in and stuff like that because we
have you know best burn is like actually
a whole bunch of stuff there's just the
editor component itself that you could
use for anything there's the server
which has an epi and then there's kind
of the full basement experience or
whatever that has the command line and
everything else within it and of course
everything's you know Mozilla fully open
source and we want people to start you
know doing fun things with it and that's
already happened x wiki build it in
right away so you can just edit using
bass burn you saw the Atlas guys how
they're a palm two days ago we just kind
of showed off a little bit tool called
areas which is a full WYSIWYG designer
tool for aimed you know kind of at the
mobile web but it could be used relief
or anything where you can just kind of
take your UI build it a long wire it
together using Bespin and so that should
be coming up pretty soon it's pretty fun
and then what we really want to do in
the future is also kind of do a lot more
on the server side and so what would it
be like if we had server-side plugins
and this is where the commonjs stuff can
come into that enables to do really
really powerful things on the server and
like you know be running only your
JavaScript code so you know exactly what
methods are available because we can
expect it at runtime and take some of
the small talk stuff
and build it in so that that's some of
the stuff that we kind of you know in
dream world really want to get to and
kind of play with but at this point
that's just kind of oh you've got your
thing back let's have Julian kind of
give you a walkthrough and his world so
the current state of things are we've
got this best friend boo-boo happening
we'd like to change the library that we
use every few months so we started off
ironically we had a new tools version a
prototype version the dojo version and
then we have sprung core going on now
now it's going to be in product dies
okay so what i will show you is the
actual version that you can also run on
Bespin doc mozilla.org and it's not yet
its local version here because the Wi-Fi
is not that speedy
okay good we got it okay um so this is
the version where we were before we
start the reboot broke progress and the
three board fail progress we got the
basic editor running you can do some
scrolling but there's no real ide so I'm
not showing you this and our aim is to
get to this one that is that you can see
here now within the end of year maybe
something beyond that so the first thing
that show you the editors editor itself
I mean this year's transcript file your
the cursor just can i function and got
basic highlighting yeah so
a world
basically it turns out if you want to
implement that on html5 it's really
simple because you can use cameras for
this it's just nothing then well okay
you've got to you have a syntax ladder
there to say okay you want function to
be blue and some are text screen or
whatever but if you have that you just
say well print that formed with well
that cherishes at that point and then
Meg translation in x and y for scrolling
that's all the hard part is to get
keyboard handling mouse handling copy
paste undoing all that stuff in there
just see this file here is one of the
basic files this here's just keyboard
handling and this somehow set up a
continues and continues and continues
this one cursor focus management and the
real pain so now we end the pain
function so something that's four break
points and that's somewhere where magic
a min so real and them feel right
somewhere yeah here is that formed and
then you read say Phil text and
everything else that's just for
adjusting colors in whatever but I mean
II de is something more than just text
editor so most time we spend on working
is doing other things for example in
best friend you also got the command
line building it's really powerful you
got code completion for somebody can
types set and chose you settings that
you already had so you can set font size
and I want this to go to eight and see
your font has changed there are also
some nice stuff like and well I want to
follow someone that's when you go to
collaboration and then okay you got
share help you got nice way to use this
command CD command and have back and
feedback from it but just command line
it's not man enough you also need
something like to access files so
therefore this quick album please don't
ask me why does this what crash at
around should be transparent but it's
not and with this um quick search you
can research out over your entire
project for example and let's see we go
something history chairs so this is the
history got any we can change file ribs
class this one here I mean what do you
think what language is used to implement
eight this just HTML
and what do you think this one here is
implemented of so in fact it's also
canvas so you got here components that's
one of our underground and underlying
canvas two kids that we use or we step
away from that you got this one to
select files but then you got a-you
powerful one or just
yes and while it's not a whole idea but
parts of it so this one is canvas cool
this one is canvas but for some this is
HTML me to bar around here Reynold with
canvas but inside its HTML and it turns
out you can do recreate things if it
comes to if you use canvas for example
can do slides and then if you think oh
well I make this a little bit more you
can add columns in there too sir kay it
doesn't fit but I make it some way fit
in there yeah it's written so this will
spence work I guess most pace and it's
called found ahead and wrote this is
pretty cool library in the swing
community
down
so he came over here
the problem is is like the level of
complexity
some of the other folks someone who
implemented the border code took the
vials CSS
it was just a fun experiment relatively
canvas within it could have but now with
backing away from using scrapple
yes
so here I mean you got simple file
access thing you can change bro checks
open files focus say okay open the HTML
file so you got this one here then
there's a preview button can hit it and
opens you to page you worked on this is
for example so canvas something about
handling how to get focused working in
canvas it's not that easy okay so this
is something about navigation so but
well I mean now you can add files you
have command line to run commands you
can open files but there's also an
interesting question how do you get
files in and out again of cloud because
otherwise or in normal cases you sit in
front of your computer every file is
just there you can just use it but if
it's in the cloud you've got to access
that file and best on the three ways at
the moment one is you can download your
files again which is well possible but
not at nice and there's a deploy
function which means it takes your
project and sense oh I am vtp and tune
server and have it there or you can use
CVS so at the moment we support svn and
mercurial and github our kit is on the
to-do list for a reboot progress okay
and then we got a great collaboration
feature but you won't show you that
already okay so it's just a little bit
talk about canvas and our best in
general and where you use canvas for and
you get questions about more technical
things so true how much to dive in there
or
I
results
with this version there's no real
embedded version supported I mean this
one but it never get too much attention
and after reboot progress there should
be the best man that runs on the server
and there should be a embedded version
of bascom and read something like oh I
want to have this plugin in there and
this plugin this plugin builds you just
one chance file you've got to plug it
into your website and yoga so that's
what it should end
yes
Oh
so the entrance under actually
I
this is
issue
and should be possible after we will
progress process that you just provide
you syntax highlighter as a blog in and
then you just edit some how to best poem
then it works so it should be really
easy to extend best min data right
oh it's if you use collaboration you
first say okay I want to share this
project and then someone else says okay
I want to follow this one who share the
project and then you see it in your file
browser because I was you should just
shared to the person but that person
might not be interested in it you say
well I'm really interested in what this
person is doing you see all the shares
that he offers to you
yes there's
so
this
so it's also plan to at future like time
machine to bespin that's something well
your plan not sure of it ends like this
that you reconsider k I stepped away
from pc and who did some change
afterwards on that file and maybe leave
some comments you can see me well that
may be okay so take though but I want to
get back to my stay before because just
grab otherwise and so it's something
like a VCS but its reach that saves
every state you can step forward and
backward and add comments on that that
would be really social together then
yeah
the
it's just
so
also
yes
this
there's
Oh
love