hey everyone so I'm Alex I'm from the
kendo UI team and i'm here to present to
you the kendo UI framework I certainly
think that you want to get things done
because the other session is about
Arduino and QR drones in it's totally
awesome and I think that this would be
more like getting things done stuff so
about can do you I well here's a summary
of what I'll talk about so why do we
build the kendo UI framework what's
currently present in the framework then
we'll do a quick demo of the of some of
the features then we'll talk about the
future and after that you'll be allowed
to ask questions so why can do you I
it's a framework and there's plenty of
them around and you might have noticed
that there's one for everything so
here's a quick list of some of randomly
chosen very popular frameworks it
there's everything like there's a
taxonomy of framework of features like
there's frameworks about templating in
there's quite a lot of them and there
are also components like jQuery UI which
doesn't have a grid and charts and there
are different volumes that are providing
such functionality and if you do watch
project and you want all this like
template in Cannes UI widgets and
charting and grids what do you have to
do you have to pull all different
versions of these frameworks and there
might be incompatibilities they marked
different licensing models there there's
quite so
few things that might go wrong and that
could really burden your work so we have
a non unified framework so there's a
framework for all of these features but
they are not in the same place we most
of these frameworks are written by
really smart and talented individuals
but they don't really have a roadmap
that they fall and now some of them do
but most of them don't and of course
there's the support part of it so if you
want support you have to purchase it
most no most commonly from a different
company that for example for jQuery UI
you have to purchase it the support from
my pen tool which is a great company but
it's still different a different persons
who are not writing called codes in the
jQuery why so if you have a professional
project you usually don't want to risk
anything and you don't want to waste
your time fixing other people's books in
the components so we had a talk about
one hour go with the guy he told me
we're using that that tree view from a
tree view plugin but we had to fix other
people's code in order to get our
application going so that's a problem
and our intense with Jake with kendo UI
is go from this to this so one framework
one unified that contains all the
functionality needs about for your next
vacation with support and with
predictable schedule and let me tell him
these things so we haven't missed a
release in the last three
earth at all so we say it's one release
four months that's it we ship another
thing to notice telerik the company I
work for is worth lira noun for its
support so you get support from
developers of the frameworks that you
use you publish about you submit a bug
gets fixed and that's 24 hours for so
you get it in on the next day most so
let's delve in some technical stuff so
what is scandal you I can do I is a
framework built on top of jQuery and
well we use a lot of html5 features but
black attacks but also new JavaScript
API is that have come with html5
movement and it's also quite a lot of
css3 features so we'll keep the buzzword
bingo let's say and with after all the
targets the create a unified framework
that contains all this stuff so what are
the components of this framework so
firstly we have UI widgets there is
currently 13 UI widgets and we point out
plenty more most notably we have a fully
functional grids and a chart right now
we're improving the child support pie
chart with our next release which will
be next week we also have a data source
which abstracts away all the data
operations so we have this source that
pulls data from XML or remote services
or perhaps in the future from down I
think and it strikes the sorting the
filtering the grouping of this data for
all other parts of the compound
of the framework this is single point of
failure if you have a problem with your
data you know is the date source we also
have templates which we spent quite a
lot for which we spent quite a lot of
time and just for making them really
really fast so let me show that so this
is a
that's not visible on the screen it
okay they're fast so next what are the
benefits of this framework after all we
want to hear for unified framework that
has less blue code so each component of
the framework knows about the other
components and this means that the grid
will know about the data source and you
simply attach data source to the great
you won't have to write any code that
merges the two and also the grid can
fully understand templates and tempting
language it's built for speed which you
didn't see but i'll be sure to show you
to you at the booth downstairs if you
come and visit us it's familiar to
jquery dance because our IP eyes are
really close to the jquery development
model with chaining and their each
widget is simply a plug-in a jquery
plugin that can extend your HTML we've
gotten aggressive roadmaps already set
and they're supported so let's do them
the source of the demo is available at
give her and that's a short year of that
and here it is so that's basic page that
uses the candle component so we have a
html5 doctype etc we've got to style
sheets one that handles all the
positioning and layout that's the kind
of common CSS and one that handles the
teaming of the library so right now we
have three different teams but with farm
on improving that situation
after that we've got the only dependency
of jQuery and all the components of the
framework bundled together in one file
and that's it with that you can start
writing can do code instead of watching
me do that oh wow all the code is tacked
I'm on github so let's get the next
stage it that's the boiler plates that
you all right so so we need data source
we do a binding to Twitter to the Search
API of Twitter so here we have the data
source as you can see we instantiate the
data source on line 15 it's in the
candidate namespace and it has three not
all components unit so we have the
transport which is held data travels
between the server and the client
secondly the schema which interprets the
results when the data comes from the
server and the last one is change event
which is all fact everywhere every time
that the datasources filtered or sorted
or when new data rise to the transport
is sports also crud operations but in
this case we need only the query Twitter
the twitter api so here's the twitter
api and we search for the Jays conf you
tack scrubs it's working the browser its
I
this nothing actually but the the data
is walk to the console because that's
what we do in the change event this view
is actually the method of the Dead
source that represents update that has
come from server so the next step would
be to instantiate the grid that is bound
to this dark dead source let's skip that
step it's tagged grid and here we have
it so we just create the elements and
end it to the body and called the jig
the candle grids jquery-ui rj jquery
poem as you can see it's knows about
dead source and the big source is
encapsulated so it's totally detached
from the grid and this will enable us to
do one more thing in a few moments but
let's keep the grid right now so we have
also the common definition we just takes
the fields from the date source and
shows them in a mind grid so how does
this look like oh it's like that fine oh
great
oh you can see also the temple thing
yeah we're fastest yeah so we have a
grid and oh it's not much
so the next step would be to use
templates in this example so let's get
them from git git checkout templates so
as you can see now we have a template
specified for this cone which takes the
content of the user templates stack and
place it in the grid the user template
tag is actually unknown execute scripts
which contains the following and as you
can see the templates are deeply
integrated in the grid so you have a
tight integration between all components
of the framework you don't have to write
any code that makes this for you and
that would look like this so we have the
afters and links the users in the grid
using the template back to our
presentation what's next so right now we
have four major points that we want to
implement but currently the framework is
in beta and our official releases in
November mid-november hope for the
official release these features will be
finalized and we also have a better for
new mobile framework Oh can do you I'm
mobile what this framework will what our
idea of this framework is is that you
can get you'll be able to get a native
looking Qi for each device so when
you're you called your application once
and when your users go to the website
you've coded if they're using an iphone
they'll get an iphone you
why and today use android phone or
windows home they'll get the respective
styling and look and feel like the
system they're using another thing to
notice is I don't have side for that are
the models of the dates or so you'll be
able to define your business objects in
your eating the scheme of the base
source which will automatically create
the objects you need from the dates or
so you query a arbitrary service and you
redefine what the results are in the
dates or so they'll be transformed to
the results you want another thing to
notice is team builder which will enable
you to create different teams for the
widgets and our idea is to make it like
bookmarklet that can be enabled embedded
in your page while you're developing it
so that you can pass the colors and all
the shiny stuff and get CSS of what your
team will be so that's it for me
download your better today I urge you to
the soul you can share your feedback on
user voice and will be there to listen
if you have any questions feel free to
ask them right now on twitter or at the
booth which is downstairs
so any questions yes let's see that I'm
not really sure actually
was it whole or a mmm oh yeah so can do
all right now is 250 q bites yeah and
that's all the framework so that's the
chart etc we plan on creating a way to
specify which components you need and
bundle it up but much like most
frameworks out there yes
take the source wouldn't one thing I was
missing was something like
so the question is models are we going
to use models and also want some kind of
mapping never make sure that the same
but funny sorry
regis data
the same i see i see so so did conflicts
like resolution so yeah and falling well
i'm not the one who works on that so i'm
not really sure about that but i know
that two of our team members are
constantly working on some resolution of
such conflicts when you for example when
you edit data that the data is
consistent between surround one so but
it's pretty magical for me so yeah have
no idea how oh yes
so the question is what at what time we
want to release the mobile version so
our schedule is usually some in
mid-november there will be a beta
version of the mobile yes with the final
version of kendo UI there will be a beta
version of the kendo UI mobile and
usually four months after that worship
official version it could be faster it
but it depends on and we could ship it
earlier so at most it's four months from
November that's much so mid-march other
questions yes
yeah so the candy aisle is open source
it's dou Y sins under GPL three and if
you purchase the commercial license
that's soft so you can do whatever you
want with the commercial license so you
can download the source code from the
link that isn't there ah yeah is there
no it's not yeah the from candy i dot
com so what can do you I dot-com you
click download better and you get the
source code and the examples yes
I
I'm sorry could you start again yes yes
we we have on this and we're currently
not have not started yet but I think
this is really close so we'll definitely
do that yeah what the defense well right
now you have a list of dependencies that
it's just in the documentation which
components are depend on which parts of
the point in the framework but we'll do
that automatically so that you can
bundle it and modify it yes
it's not yet announced so I counter it
I'm not the one who inside that and it
will be definitely published with the
official version of the okay yeah myth
number from the official can say other
questions yes
like
so the question is whether it is easy to
substitute the templating engine all
right now it's not I guess but we could
think something of that so yeah
shouldn't we wanted to do that because
the templates are really fast
Oh
aha well especially for that for the
simplified whoops and special syntax up
oops we're thinking about that too so
web I think mustache has on each
construct that its rights over items yet
we're thinking about that oh yeah I you
definitely can use mustache but our
other tempting lounges but I'm not sure
right now how easy it is oh yeah but
we're thinking about other questions