hi everyone but we've got at least six
alive people which is a good thing and
all right so I was very I was very
surprised when I got accepted to Jas
cars because I don't write JavaScript
that much in fact I don't write any
JavaScript sometimes I played with
node.js because I like to look around
but what I got accepted the reason is
because I wrote something I wrote an
experiment because I like breaking stuff
I like playing with technologies I like
seeing what's out there so what I did is
a real dis experiment that will see
later on which is essentially mixing PHP
and nodejs together it's nothing from
production it's just for fun really but
over the course of the past few months
I've evolved I've changed a lot and
initially this stock was supposed to be
bitching about node.js and PHP but
instead I decided to just call it mixing
technologies instead of breaking them
this this came from last week actually I
was a i was at phone conf and i saw one
of the speaker from this afternoon which
is mark Chris Williams which you should
go see a stock by the way and he
reminded me that I can't tell too much
because I don't want to give away what
he's going to be talking about but he
reminded me that we were more than a
language so hopefully that's that's what
I'm going to be telling you today I'm
going to tell you about my experiences
and i'm going to show you the experiment
at the end
alright so here's a story of myself I'm
a perpetual learner that's all I do all
I want to know is more stuff my brain is
like a fractal the more you deeper you
go in the more I want to learn stuff and
there's one thing I've been there is one
thing I really hated in terms of it when
it comes to engineering and its its
constraints I really really hate
constraints to some extent constraints
make sense but to some other extent it
limits your imagination it's not only
engineering anymore it's arts that
that's that's what we do and what we
have to really focus on is thinking
outside the box and when I say thinking
outside the box it's not only when
you're coding something and when you're
developing something let me give you an
example all right there's there's this
guy and I'm gonna try to do it as he did
it yeah so hey it's a teeny Tina and I
am from Naples Italy and oops sorry
there i am from Naples Italy and the
Queen Margherita is visiting yeah so
it's like this and he says my name is
Rafael Esposito what could I do what
could I do he says oh ho I can take the
bread yeah and the slap-a- soma cheese
and then the slap-a- summer tomato sauce
and then the guy thought outside the box
that's what he did and he created one of
the most popular dish in the world which
is pizza that the modern pizza with
tomato sauce which is pretty cool and
you know that there are various examples
like this for instance someone had the
idea I have a Charlie and had a suitcase
what can I do with this and then he
created a suitcase with wheels and
there's another example that's really
really that I fell in love really when i
got here at JS conf it's it's the guys
downstairs they thought outside the box
they said hey hold on if i have foosball
have an arduino have cloud computing
have html5 nav CouchDB what can I do
with this there you go you end up with a
digital foosball table which is pretty
slick in my opinion well yeah there
there there there
so I the gooks table talk yesterday but
I would have included them in there but
I didn't other examples of thinking
outside the box was mixing pearl and see
about 12 years ago I created PHP and
then created CPP in v8 and some awesome
sauce and he ended up with nodejs which
was pretty groundbreaking in my opinion
in our industry but more importantly its
intrinsic to us engineers and developers
and it's it's something that's inherent
to our use of technology because
everything we use is a mix everything we
use is a mash-up of previous
technologies pretty much and there's one
thing that I really can't stand and I'm
a victim but I'm also one of the
perpetrators of this issue is we all
have God complexes you write JavaScript
you think you can write everything in
JavaScript you write PHP you want to try
to solve every single problem in PHP you
write early and you say oh it's so much
better at least there's one no actually
I love our long as well but I'm not
gonna bitch about it about this whole
thing and there's one important thing to
remember when you mix technologies or
when you write your language you're
merely the owner of your own realm you
need to get out there you need to to see
what other technologies are doing
because remember one thing your users
are worth more than technology they are
who is going to pay your bills or who
are going to pay your bills they are the
ones who are affected but all those wars
when we fight between javascript PHP or
ruby and PHP or pearl and what else but
there's there's a great man that once
said al words deception and I'm a big
fan of Sunzu and and I think this
applies very well to reading hacker news
and seeing this this new technology is
so much better than everything else
because all words deception in our world
it doesn't affect us ourselves engineers
too much however it affects our users a
lot our users are confused they come to
you they say
I want to television that's going to
play html5 and that runs on Ruby and
that can write C they don't know what
they're seeing they are being deceived
by ourselves we need to get better than
we need to get better we need to sort
ourselves out and start interacting
together because every single technology
has a different use case pretty much and
they can be useful so um I'm gonna give
you a little example that I actually had
that was something that happened to me
on the way here from the airport and
dublin and i'm going to start this by
saying polyglot isn't this just I write
a lot of languages all right see I write
PHP I write Python i right airline I
love languages so on the way to the
airport I also speak it a few languages
as well because I love languages and
they're easy to learn so this taxi
driver that's going to be an example of
mixing technologies and mixing languages
this taxi driver says what are you going
to do in Berlin I said well I'm going to
a technology conference speaking about
technologies he says oh really and then
at this point when the taxi driver said
really can you tell me more I knew this
was not going to end well so I said yeah
it's talking about languages and you
know he wanted to know more so I started
explaining its its its JavaScript
conference and I'm going to talk about a
different language and he's like huh so
he stayed stoic there for about five
minutes driving and then he says how
many languages do you speak at this
point I had the perfect example for my
talk today and I couldn't stop I
couldn't just tell him no look it's not
linguistics it's actual engineering and
this example came to me and I said when
I say use the good technology for you
it's the same thing in languages i don't
speak German but there's a German word i
really like with his shot and hood and
when that taxi was talking about
technology mixed with linguistics but he
was very confused I couldn't help myself
but think about this word because it's
exactly what it was I enjoyed this
because schadenfreude is basically the
pleasure derived from a misfortune of
others and I could see his bad luck
trying to get into technology and trying
to get trying to understand more it was
it was interesting but in this
particular use case I couldn't use that
word with him I couldn't explain this to
him because we're not robots when we use
technology you know we have to use what
makes sense in what use case makes sense
so what I'm gonna do is now is a rapid
rant hopefully I'm gonna try to the
mitten I'll make this work in 30 minutes
so it might be really hard so let's talk
about no chance for a little bit who
uses no Jas here Wow who uses Python PHP
yeah don't be shy don't be shy yeah I
know look all right no jess is trying to
be the next PHP am I wrong saying that
isn't that what Ryan said a few times
through emails and sure the mailing
lists let's start relaxing all
right because PHP is trying to be the
next PHP we don't even know where we are
yet no jezik is probably the most
interesting project I've seen in years
because it redefined the status quo it
it completely taught outside the box i
said well it got popular obviously but
it's an want to do something i want to
solve in your use case i want to i want
to try something new and I don't think
no jess has to be the next PHP or the
next anything else I mean why why would
you want to do this you have a great
vibrant community you have a great
package manager you have great people
you
great core developers and companies to
back you up whereas on the other hand
ourselves PHP myself I'm a time to time
core contributor at the PHP I don't even
have time anymore to argue because PHP
is in a different league than nodejs I'm
not saying it's a better League I'm just
saying it's a different league it's
different issues there is no other
project out there apart maybe from Java
but Java is very different there's no
other project apart from PHP that has
the same issues that the same growth
that has the same use on the web and you
know what when when I see people trying
to be the next PHP I think that's wrong
PHP is there it's doing its thing no
Jess it's doing its other thing and it's
sweet and it works so there's
this book that's pretty much changed my
life I think or my way of thinking about
businesses and products and it's called
the innovators dilemma to do like a too
long didn't read resume of this it
basically means for me is the incumbent
PHP the one that was the leader in the
web we pretty much sat on her holes for
a few years because we were at the top
of this we were used by everyone whereas
when node.js came it forced us to rid of
redefine ourselves redefine our
processes see how other technologies are
doing things see how new platforms are
growing and and this is great PHP has
been stuck in a loop for many years then
it started growing again once we saw how
no jess was bringing new things but now
what's happening no Jess people are
trying to make PHP and PHP stranded of
features of no Jess it's it's a bit of a
mix-up that I don't agree with but
either way I think it's very interesting
to see how how the two worlds can
collide together anyways I'm rambling
know how much younger about 15 minutes
just about here 15 all right so what I'm
going to present you now is an
experiment that I did um it yeah I don't
even know how to just define it I'm an
engineer I like when things are pure but
i also like learning new things and i
like to redefine what I'm doing
I like to improve myself an open source
is my life so obviously when something
comes out I need to train however I'm
very very lazy and I have a lot of work
to do and I don't have time to start
rewriting on my code to pour it into a
new language or port my old thing to a
new it's a new platform or to something
crazy I mean I love html5 I love PHP I
love JavaScript I love web sockets I
love Python I love our line for fuck's
sake I love technology and as I said I
had a lot of code I wrote a lot of code
in my life in at least 15 languages and
i still use whatever language works but
one night it was a Friday night and I
was pretty drunk sitting in my office
working and sipping on some wine what
had this idea what if I could run PHP
from nodejs because the funny thing is
PHP has been very boring for many years
but since the arrival of PHP 5.3 we have
some pretty cool things that i'm going
to show you even though I they're
completely overkill for the code
examples i'm going to show you we have
namespaces we have closures more
importantly we have a much better fast
CTI processor now called fpm and I
figured hold on no Jess could replace my
engine X and I could use web sockets
directly from this so I started hacking
away and that that's what happened it
turns out that it worked so what we're
going to do now is I'm actually going to
show you off what you know what this
experimented and hopefully there's Wi-Fi
hold on you see terminal there alright
so I'm going to start by showing you a
very simple yeah yeah don't say anything
all right I know and I shouldn't pseudo
alright so if people want to go to this
address that I'm gonna get someone to
chat with me sorry camera I have to step
out of the lights let's get someone to
chat with me all right
they're trying to chat with me do you I
want to go in there if you have a
computer feel free hold on this one's
gonna be very short don't worry because
it's kind of boring so let's say a
speaker that's me oh hi so ah stupid
thing hold on oh I got a litter Thank
You xss people alright so that's a very
boring example of nodejs and web sockets
I think we all heard everything that's
that's there to be sad about node.js no
no that's why I said thank you very
successful very nice hold on that's not
sockets in PHP n so the thing is I don't
want to give a talk about nodejs because
everyone knows everything about nodejs
already so let me just open the terminal
here what we're gonna do is just so
you're the server is very simple is that
too small to big in the back does that
work alright so let's do this very
simply I just include socket i/o because
I'm i said i'm very lazy i'm not gonna
write my own implementation of web
sockets obviously so i use socket i/o
and then you know the usual you said
your I use Express as well because it
manages my relative out this stuff then
that's the app the app receives a
connection receives next nicknames and
then it disconnects it's very very basic
it's the default example from socket i/o
so I figured what if you have a business
you need some real time web chat or some
real time access some real time
interaction but you also have a lot of
business logic developed to compute your
financials or any imaginable kind of
piece of code that would run on PHP that
everyone already has somewhere post to a
vanilla bulletin board something well
what we're gonna do now yeah
alright sorry it went back to the PHP
initially the example I wanted to do was
a very very cool anyone knows humming
bird which is like live and analytics of
your website in traffic and it's super
super slick and I wanted to mix this up
with because I'm a bad citizen and I for
the example here I wanted to snip the
network so what I wanted to do is send
everyone to a network at to the
hummingbird page find their address
compute that through my PHP script via
nodejs and get the information back and
display something else but it was kind
of boring it was over complicated and I
think one of the main themes that I
remember or Die that i can think of when
i when i think about know j/s conf it's
pirates we all love pirates so I decided
to write something funnier um so for now
I'm gonna show you the code first I'll
show you a server that's the actual
interesting bit all right we start a
server remove this yadda yadda that's
the main road that displays the index
just like the other one but not that's
where the funny bit comes in yeah back
on that you process true notice to
express it identifies the route and what
it does by a surf PHP it doesn't it
doesn't do a request to apache or two
engine X what it does is I wrote this
think of node PHP which allows you to
interact with fast CGI directly true no
it's Halle invented it's all very fun so
that's what you do you just have a route
and what we're going to do is show you
how that actually works so let's just
switch back to our yeah yeah there you
go
alright start that server
of course of course what I didn't get it
today
alright
oh sorry there you go
alright if you guys want to refresh use
the ipod to refresh or use your
computers to refresh go to the same
address Oh a penis connected this is a
very kinky night so all right start
start saying you know normal chat room
conversation say how are you and how's
it going and yada yada yada bigger penis
oh my god what the alright here's
what I'm gonna do now i'm gonna click on
this here now if people could start
chatting with me yeah sorry that's the
default so you said hey say say how are
you are where's the party tonight i
don't know if that's gonna work yeah see
what's actually happening here is Oh
someone clever someone very clever see
what it does is it grabs your you're the
string you're sending when it receives
it translates it using a translator it
translates it to pirate talk true PHP
PHP feeds that to a cache and then just
displays whatever data is with return
from it where is that party tonight yeah
PHP GS Frankenstein is a pretty goddamn
good express a good way to explain it
sorry I'm not mirroring this place
alright so let's see here its a mix of
node.js but you can also see the
incoming requests for PHP so I actually
only started learning express last night
because I said I don't write JavaScript
I don't write those crazy stuff and I
was the first version of note PHP was
only a server you would basically run
from your directory and it was finally
index PHP and it would run but last I
decided if I could use Express that
would be interesting because I could
manage my rug and just send that
directly to your fast cgi so right now
what it does is it mixes the PHP outputs
it's all event driven and very fancy and
for those of you that don't actually
know PHP as it actually has some of the
event-driven methods for instance you
can write all your sessions
synchronously using the new minecraft
extension you can write the files online
use a synchronously using the event loop
there's even live events
that I'm not going to talk about because
it's absolutely huggly not ugly holy so
let me just show you a little bit of
code because I like to show off what we
have now in PHP so this is absolutely
overkill don't worry about this such as
the requirement CC we have we have
namespaces that's right that's right huh
and check this out we have lambdas as
well that's right you can associate
functions the so variables this is
sweet so what we do is we
essentially retrieve on the cash if the
word that yours passing is in the cache
it finds it otherwise it will ping some
URL that's up there post like pirate
calm which is kind of self explaining
say self-explanatory and yeah that's it
that's that's very it's very it's very
basic it's not complex but you can run
your PHP script true you know Jas which
means you might have like I said you
might have some real time chat and other
things that you want but at the same
time when someone comes you have some
business logic behind you send the IP
process the financials how much they owe
you and all this stuff you can all do
this and that's what I find beautiful
about technologies you can start
interacting together like this i'm not
saying this is something that should go
in production far from it but it shows
you that nodejs that was created pretty
much as its own language can interact
directly with other languages you could
run python scripts from this you can run
Ruby because I think there's a ruby ish
nodejs thing that interacts and that
that's very sweet let me just show you
another little piece of code see
namespace huh how sick is that so hold
on where am I
yeah let's do this for that
so in conclusion III don't i'm not
saying use PHP I'm not saying use Python
i'm not saying use nodejs I'm saying
pink and stop fighting stop fighting
between languages because as I said our
users are worth way more way more than
our technology and it's it saddens me
every time I see posts on Hacker News
are on TechCrunch ER of tech rush
doesn't really count as a tech blog one
on how can use that bitches about other
languages I think it's very important
for us as a community to to start
talking together that's something I've
been doing or trying to get going for a
few years now it's trying to talk with
other languages trying to see what
they're doing trying to see how we can
interact out to make a better
interaction for our businesses and our
money and our lives because you know
there's not enough time in life to fight
all the time so hopefully you weren't
expecting some kind of in-depth talk
about note PHP because that there's not
much to be said really it's just an
interacts with fast cgi true note PHP
it's all invented and it's all very nice
everyone's very happy so think next time
you start bitching about another
language or you start bitching about
some technology think about it think
could I can I use it how could I use it
do I have to rewrite my script do I have
to hire someone else to redo the whole
thing or is that the right use case for
me no SQL is a great example of this no
SQL has so many different no SQL I hate
the term just saying it gives me shivers
there's so many no no SQL database and
they all have a different use case so
don't say don't say react is much better
than couchdb for everything because
that's not true for some cases it's
gonna be better pink pink pink think
outside the box think as well that's if
there's one thing you have to get back
or taking bring back from this talk is
you have to consider other possibilities
don't be self restraint don't don't
impose constraints on yourself impose
constraints when you're developing but
not when you're thinking it's not only
engineering it's arts remember that
so we're going to take any questions or
something i think i have five six
minutes left according to my timer so if
anyone has any questions
no questions yes no next
I was there
so the question is is no PHP actively
maintained um I don't use it for work
i'm i'm one of the co-founders of a PHP
platform called orchestra and obviously
we don't use this for production because
it's a test but what i did is my wife
and I are very competitive to say the
least and we like playing games online
against one another and it's really hard
to do this on miniclip and such so i
wrote this battleship game that we can
interact together but I have some old
code for a card game that I'm doing now
in PHP that I wanted to use to note so
as I said I'm a perpetual learner so yes
it's still maintained I i use this
pretty much once a week and even the
reason why i actually started know PHP
is because prior to PHP 5.4 PHP didn't
have this very nice built-in web server
so you have to install apache create a
new feos create a new host name entry
whereas now I could just type node
server PHP boom and start right from
there and start developing so I don't
only use this for games or fun I also
use this for development on my own so
yeah there's that there's a bug right
now because since last night because I
parted half of it to express the jas and
the other one is imported but uh yeah
it's on github if you want to go I think
if you go to the lanyard page I added
the slides and at the link to the getup
code you can you can see how their the
examples are there and you should see
note PHP from there as well any other
question come on all right so just how
much time left previous ah good stuff so
I like to talk to people usually and
that's something I didn't do today
because i only have 30 minutes so i
tried to cut it very short I I like to
know about your experiences what who
uses more than one technology on a daily
basis what what kind of what kind of
technology mixed you like say Joe
see that's the same thing joe says he
uses JavaScript Python PHP and as I said
we have a PHP platform caloric Australia
and the funny thing is pretty much
everything that's that's in the back end
not the API but every job everything
that interacts with Amazon is all
written in Python because it makes more
sense there's a this is great library in
Python called boto and boto is is well
maintained and it's super slick
sometimes it breaks but it works most of
the time and see I think I think Joe
just just a spark of this this good idea
in me because or extended the idea and
my view and mixing technologies
sometimes you have to it makes more
sense from an economics perspective and
from just technology it's it's fun to
learn new things anyone here it doesn't
like to learn new things like people
walking in kind of thing sure John a
chair though anyways thank you very much
for your time and if you have any