my name is Jared and I'm here to talk
about JavaScript what could have been so
who here hated history in high school
come on more than you in that either you
had very good teachers or I went to a
crappy high school it wasn't until I hit
unique that history sort of started
coming alive to me mainly because it was
fairly violent I mean the Trojan horse
is a good example of this I know it's
not real history but still so the
Smithsonian has recently started trying
to get people interested in history I
have any of you seen these ads it says
50 cent got shot and steal White's about
it on stage Teddy Roosevelt got shot
mid-speech and didn't leave the stage
until he finished Ozzy Osbourne study
language rubbed off on his kids andrew
jackson was so vulgar as parrot was
ejected from swearing at his funeral
Bret Michaels got with every chick on
the load bus Genghis Khan got we assume
that so many chicks as a 50-percent
there's a five percent chance that
you're related to him so hopefully I've
got you excited about history so we're
going to take a step back in history and
in the beginning God created the heavens
and the earth well that's probably a bit
too far back we probably need a computer
to be invented for it to be relevant to
this conference in the beginning brendan
i created the javascript now the
javascript was formless it was spread
small talk was spread throughout the job
that the computer science community the
spirit of self is hovering among them
and java reg has been created actually
you've all heard that story a thousand
times before you are the JavaScript
conference so what if how many of you
asked the question what if like what
would happen if a rapper bought through
that door we'd probably be all screwed
since it's only one way out windows but
you never know so what if Cleopatra had
been ugly would we all be living in
cities like this because she hadn't led
to the downfall of Rome what if Steve
Jobs never took acid would it be such a
guy Connie
company with all the hipsters be using
PC's instead of Max but here's the thing
about history it's all well and good to
look back at the past and say well you
know what if that happened but hindsight
is always twenty-twenty this is a photo
of the Brisbane River just keep that in
mind so bit of history of myself for a
year and a half I was the I was one of
two JavaScript developers in the company
of 200 java the java developers so i
often saw this image get passed around
to me we've all laughter did I ended up
what starting to retort with this
effective Java we need a book to be good
you guys need an 800-page book just to
be effective with your language but this
gets me thinking what is it about Java
developers that are so violently
defensive of their language yet
javascript developers generally can we
can generally tell you whether our
favorite miss feature is I mean dr.
Crockford books is full of it don't we
all have our favorite miss feature
things like automatic semicolon
insertion type coercion things like that
when you ask a Java developer what their
fate that their least favorite thing
about the language they often stare at
you blankly like it's perfect what
you're talking about and yet who here is
a Java developer by any chance what do
you think of the language
so this is that's because you're a
JavaScript your conference you've
obviously seen the light I often
adamantly have to defend JavaScript a
paper like you know it doesn't have any
typing it doesn't do this I do it's like
you guys don't actually have first-class
functions yet and you spend so much time
writing things to get around this like
Google's Oh like sort of semi functional
library food Java has an interface
called function which returns a function
it makes no sense that but why is it
that Java can do that to a job a defense
that despite all this and JavaScript we
sort of let people attack our language
every day and I think it is simply
because we don't we as a job developer
they knew what it was like they came
from languages like cobalt so I'm gonna
try and install in you the hindsight
this is the Brisbane River after the
Brisbane floods I bet they thought that
building on the bed of a river wasn't
such a good idea now so I'm going to try
and give you that hind side today so
what would have happened if Brendan Eich
hadn't slept with his coffee as a
structure interpretation of computer
programs what would have happened if
back in 1995 Microsoft happenings of
decided to ignore the web and actually
decided to embrace it and not release I
four five and six so let's take a step
back into a new reality we're going to
take a step back to 1995 and see what
would have happened if someone like
Microsoft would have created JavaScript
from the popular languages at times so
what was popular in 1995 cobalt
as you all know Kobol is responsible for
the famous y2k into them where we all
ended up living in volts like this it's
my own reality i can say that that
actually happen so we can probably
safely say that cobalt was on its way
out by now this book was released in
1994 that means it's all nearly old
enough to drink in nearly every country
in the world except for the u.s. does
that make you feel off it certainly made
me feel old when I looked it up but this
book is all about the object-oriented
patent so I think it's fairly safe to
say that the object-oriented thing was
well on its way up and for better or for
worse the seminal object-oriented
language at the time which was John
Strauss helps C++ so C++ it's an
iteration on see obviously that's the
joke there it's object-oriented it has
no garbage collection and templates any
C++ developer will tell you how much
they hate templates this is generally
what C++ looks like well this is
actually a fairly good example of C++
this is the code for query selector roll
from WebKit they've done a fantastic job
of maintaining their code base but
generally C++ ends up looking something
like this
this is the code from the standard
templating libraries push back for
vectors so it's not like I just pulled
it from the most horrific piece of code
i can find this is in use every day and
i can't really read it okay garbage
collection so this is 1995 garbage
collection is a fairly new singh c++
certainly doesn't have a garbage
collection so if we're going to create a
language garbage collection is probably
out so how do we manage our memory well
c++ does it through two keywords new and
delete just like in javascript new
creates a new object it's so that says i
have an object it's this size i need to
i need someone to put it the operating
system will go okay here's a chunk of
memory from the heat right to here which
is all well and good so we use that
object but we have no garbage collection
so we have some when we've done with it
we actually explicitly have to say I'm
done taking away from me operating
system goes okay freeze up that piece of
memory and then tells the rest of the
rest of the applications that you can
now write here as well so this comes
with a whole range of Poland this piece
of code has a subtle bug in it does
anyone know what it is so maybe Cepeda
said anyone though yeah so we allocate
the new array of size 42 we then till we
load through it push a bunch of stuff
onto it and then we delete the items but
this is actually leaking memory because
we are locating 42 new strings and
pushing them onto the array the array
has no idea who are in those objects it
sort of says I know I've got memory
allocated to me but you might not have
finished with it so I can't delete it so
when you delete items that just simply
removes that that initial pointer so
we've just like 42 strings
and that's the things that C++ still
others have to deal with oops so it's
into it running backwards in time we may
as well go to the next popular language
in around in 1995 see oh it's basically
a DSL for assembly it's a lower level as
you can get see like syntax obviously so
in JavaScript a piece of feature
detection generally look something like
their sisters from modernizer we exploit
type codes and tie portion is one of
those things that everybody uses in
every single piece of code base yet
every single person who writes a blog
complaints about it I don't know so here
we're sort of set we're just sort of
coercing the fact that undefined becomes
it can become a boolean and returning
that as an object but this is witchcraft
basically in the sea world see has the
concept of macros and not with good come
from Lisa macros basically is a pre pass
of the source code before it hits the
compiler we define the token there Sarah
the compiler can also define a bunch of
tokens for you and this is what we're
going to use for feature detection in
your language so this is how it's done
now sorry about the escaping code mara
did some weird things and I couldn't fix
it I knew better to touch my slide 10
minutes before they start um so we're
creating a new element we're creating
new div and then we attach an event to
it but this isn't done at run time this
is done on build so by if it was running
on firefox firefox would see this and i
even see that which you may think looks
okay and there's no problem without it
it's workable but it can introduce some
sort of bugs as well so we defined a
variable for 100 we only critical to it
and then we in the Mozilla block of code
because we're looking at the code we see
we'll see a variable called a then we
look at the and someone comes along as
well I need to I need to say let's
increase the padding on this element for
Mozilla so they work in another if
defined and then use a but this is now
Creek introduced the bug into our code
because it's not actually defined for
Mozilla so we becomes a maintenance
nightmare on the object on the subject
of events obviously the web is in
invented system it's quite obvious we
click something we wait for a user
interaction we do this so if Microsoft
was creating this language they
obviously know that we need to run the
vent somehow so if you take a look
around in 1995 and see how other
languages were doing events win32 is the
obvious thing to look out here because
it's the same sort of thing we wait for
a user interaction click a button to do
this do that so how this win for you to
do it to avoid confusing i'm going to
explain it how she does it natively
rather than trying to computer so this
is the stack we've got two pieces of
data they look identical this one's a
this 165 they're exactly the same piece
of data so how is that possible using a
thing called pointers it sort of says
there's a piece of memory on the stack
it contains some sort of data when we
pull it out I want you to interpret it
as a character or in the case of the
body one I want you to interpret it as
an int so you can get to the same piece
of memory can return to get very
different results so pointers point to
an address of memory and it's up to us
to how we deal with it hard to follow
most of the time we got to reference
some Andy referencing other way to end
up dealing with the address not the
dollar ugly syntax uses the star symbol
function pointers it's the same sort of
thing functions are created on the stack
and all we do is we all we all we're
doing is we're going to use the the star
syntax to say there's a function that
sits here when you run execute that
function and here's a simple example in
C so we've got the main and then we've
got results
the top there is how you define a
function point of the inter that embrace
a bracket start fallback star in so that
says I'm a function that takes an int
and I return an int it's that quite hard
to read quite hard to use and introduce
a lot of fun problems what so what if i
said if any of that went over your head
good that's kind of my point these are
the things that we as javascript
developers take for granted every single
day we don't have to know any of this
it's all taken care of us by our
interpreters so the guys at v8 and
Mozilla take care of this for us we
don't need to know about memory
allocation well unless of course using
host objects in native objects inside
ie6 and that's a whole different kind of
worms so yeah and then so we've got
we've got a way to deal with a feature
detection forgot the way to deal with
events where the way to create objects
but we don't have the rest of our syntax
so VB is the big beginners language we
want the web to be accessible to easy
it's a new programmer so we're still the
syntax from VV built for easy
development of goose that's what we want
very basic of your engine in which some
typing through through the dim of
keyword so this is vba it's a dialect of
the visual basic for working with frame
applications things like access excel
things like that and it looks fairly
similar to what we do day to day we
create a connection to a database or
form a document same sort of thing we do
so it makes perfect sense at this
language we should use this language for
syntax so
we're going to steal dim typing if-then
and anything else that's not to do with
objects or events from visual basic and
so this is what the language could have
looked like had Microsoft developed it
this is a fairly simple event system
that you know we write a lot in
JavaScript and look at my syntax there
is just to create an event and it
doesn't this doesn't even have the
trigger it just simply has the adding so
we've got no effort no hash table so we
can't do things like we have to look
through a raise to see if there's a
unique thing they're all in all not very
pretty so do you feel lucky yet I mean
it could have been much worse sure
javascript isn't perfect but a lot of
the things that we do we take for
granted day today the things that we
complain about day to day I actually
felt were fairly rare for a language of
1995 so where is the JavaScript
community should start playing up to
this lock and just to prove a point
here's the same piece of code in
JavaScript much cleaner much easier to
read
so to me it feels like there are already
people who are playing up to take
advantage of this lock that I think we
have other than j.crew as much whatever
you feel feel about the language
personally you can't admit that it it
brought a whole new world of JavaScript
developers to the JavaScript community
it took away what every JavaScript
developer dreaded and that was working
with the inconsistencies in the DOM and
here's what j.crew would look like if we
had to write it in this language and
then introduces a so this here the 13
lines of code introduces a memory leak
we have to declare our function before
we use it even though it's a simple
one-line function we can't use an
anonymous function we have to declare
our type of funk call back before we can
use it ugly so and then we introduce a
memory leak here because we still have a
piece of reference to the old jquery and
then we override it I wouldn't want to
support this code
so no Jas it's a few years old now do
you think nodejs would have been as
popular as it was if it hadn't been
written on JavaScript well I have the
answer for that nodejs is written on the
vented library from C called Lee BB and
here's an example of a socket server
written in li BB would you come to a
note with you have come to a live event
conference about Lviv conference no
probably not because they don't exist
would there have been a thing like Libby
v knockout no because there isn't an
live EV was first written in two
thousand so the JavaScript community is
hugely lucky that we have and the thing
that enables this is the fact that
JavaScript it was written the way it was
and that's the same piece of code
written in node sure there's an
abstraction layer in between but the
fact that no one came up with this
abstraction layer says something to me
says something says that we as the
JavaScript community are very lucky so I
want you to defend JavaScript there are
things like Java developers who feel the
need to write GWT so they don't actually
have to learn JavaScript so why why do
we do things to try and avoid writing
JavaScript we should embrace the lock
that we've been given by Brendan and
work from that this is the sister though
for animation fro from the Roman times
it was hugely successful it devastated
most of the armies that they encountered
and as you can see they basically just
walked arms interlocked shield
interlocks straight up to the enemy a
well-trained unit was actually so strong
that they could put them into a ravine
and have horses right over the top of
them so this is what I want from the
JavaScript community I want us to start
walking in the same steps walking in the
same direction so that we can become as
strong as this formation so how can we
do that community JavaScript as a
community like no other I fairly active
in let us say the Python community
it's nothing like the JavaScript unity
I've never seen people who are so
friendly we need to keep this up so you
need to contribute to the community next
year you need to flood yawns email with
the torque submissions you need to a
flood cruces email with talk submissions
for JS conf us if you if your city has a
JavaScript user group attend speak if it
doesn't start one we started CJ us about
a year ago now and it regularly gets
about 150 people in and it's growing
every day so contribute to documentation
the way for new people to get involved
in the community is through
documentation contribute to things like
html5 rocks see yarn if you want to and
mdn as well there's a doc sprint
happening downstairs go contribute go
harass them and ask how you can
contribute to the documentation to make
the job to make the new people in the
JavaScript community welcome and avoid
w3schools how many here have you use
open source projects good everywhere
have single hand is here how many people
here have complained about an open
source project every single hand should
be up as well so instead of complaining
why aren't you creating pull requests in
github or bitbucket start by
contributing back to open source
communities instead of complaining and
showing weakness in our armor we need to
stocking like you have a feature you
want add it yeah documentation you think
slacking fix it and join their community
jump on IRC everything every little bit
you can but most of all I need you to go
forward and be awesome with JavaScript
so Who am I blah blah
and you might be asking yourself who is
this guy why is he standing in front of
me telling me to go do stuff that I've
never seen him do and you're correct
I've been so busy with work well at
least that's my excuse as I haven't
stepped forward and actually contribute
to the JavaScript community with some
bit unless you in Sydney and there's
slides missing there it does say ballet
on one but one man so I couldn't in good
faith stand in front of you today and
request all this from you if I wasn't
willing to stand up and step up and do
it for myself so I recently lost a fair
bit of weight which I hope you can tell
from that image it was hard work
I'll tell you that and I couldn't have
done it without the pressure that my
friends and my family put on me to keep
it up so I'm going to stand in front of
you today and ask for peer pressure if
it in two months you haven't seen me
contribute to a blog you haven't seen me
contribute to an open source project you
haven't seen me contribute to
documentation use those contact details
previously and harass me harass me until
it
and I'm going to ask you as well that
each of you turn to the person next to
you and ask them to push you to be
awesome as well any means necessary use
a stick to beat them figure out what
projects they were working on it that
work that could be open source if
they've been talking about fixing some
bug in an open source language that open
source project then push them make them
do it we need to embrace the lock that
we've been given we need to just
basically be awesome so that we as a
JavaScript community look as strong as