oh my god
[Applause]
[Music]
my name is Dennis and I have a problem
though I'm not an anonymous alcoholic
and let's make it clear from the start
I'm not even public alcoholic I nearly
don't drink my problem is different I'm
I'm a developer there are a lot of
questions without answers in my head why
do we calculate padding's based on
parents width even for top and bottom
values I don't know what do peak angular
or react polymer or View vanilla GS or
mean GS with chocolate chips
I don't know now when we are writing CSS
and JavaScript is at the time to make it
even and starts writing javascript and
HTML and CSS I don't know there are many
more questions that I have no answer to
exactly they did C won't be covered in
this talk today instead I want to talk
to you about us us as human beings us as
developers we developers are all very
different
some like CSS others prefer playing with
the latest JavaScript framework some
like aesthetics and house enjoy a
skillfully designed websites
others prefer building unique user
experience all the way from the ground
but no matter our differences there is
one thing we all share in common we all
want to be professionally successful in
whatever we are doing and the wish to be
successful to be the best is not bad at
all
this is how evolution works the problem
is that a lot of people take this wish
to become successful way too serious
in 1982 physician Robert Goldman post a
question to elite athletes in power and
combat sports asking if I had a magic
drug that would be so fantastic that if
you take it once you would win every
competition you would enter from mr.
Olympia to Olympic decathlon for the
next five years but it would have one
minor drawback it would kill you five
years after you took it would you still
take this pill I'm sorry the problem is
that more than half
the respondents answered yes they would
still take this bill puzzled with this
result goldman repeated the same
question for the following 13 years
until 1995 and during all these years
the results were consistent people were
willing to trade their lives for just
five years of success we developers of
course are not athletes frankly a lot of
us are as far from sports as is possibly
could be and thankfully this bill
doesn't exist so we all have to find our
own way to professional success but no
matter whether we are different and
whether we take different paths on this
path to professional success we all face
the same problems and exactly about
those problems I would like to talk to
you today we'll try to see what those
are
we'll try to analyze them and hopefully
we'll try to see what we can to do about
those a lot of modern physicists
sincerely believe that the world around
us is nothing more than just huge
computer simulations so we all live in
matrix so for the purpose of this talk
let's assume this is true so let's
imagine and think how would an average
developer could look like in the form of
let's say a JavaScript program it all
starts here we are born and raised and
at some point we get to the first hour
our first milestone as developers we
read our first book in my case it was
it's really hard to see here but in my
case it was designing with web standards
by Jeffrey Zeldin the first edition of
this book you enjoy the book and you
want to apply this new knowledge so you
get into your first project probably for
yourself or for a friend
probably it was rubbish and probably you
didn't get paid but you really enjoyed
the moment and the idea that you can
create something once and it will be
instantly available for millions use of
the users around the world so you want
to go on and you get to your first job
as a develop
and things go on and on and on and on
until something goes wrong take a look
at the console the program representing
us as developers starts throwing errors
let's take a look at what those problems
are there are only three here for the
purpose of this talk there are many more
but exactly what these three we are
going to talk about today so the first
one is perfectionism next slide I will
just show you some pictures I'm not
gonna say word I'm interested in your
reaction to those I will let this one to
stay on the screen for a while of course
this is not a scientific research but
from your reaction I might consider that
some of you consider yourselves
perfectionists
I remember in 2013 when I company I was
working out back then was about to merge
with another company I had a
conversation with my background boss
about how this merge might affect my
style of work
danny's he said your style of work is
like champagne it's long processed well
thought and expensive the style of a
company we are about to merge is more
like a Prosecco it's faster it's
probably cheaper and probably less
quality lower quality we both know that
but when both drinks are poured in the
glasses at a party most people won't
tell the difference anyway even though
later this company decided that their
front-end works on the unicorn sparking
magic and they don't need in-house
front-end developer at all I still
remember this dialogue as a good example
of how the work of perfectionist and non
perfectionist is perceived by normal
people and yes I used to think about
myself as perfectionist but what do we
want it or not perfectionists are a
completely different breed when it comes
to work long perfectionists
consider work to be just that when it
comes to perfectionists we consider work
a challenge we consider it as a way of
expressing ourselves and challenge
ourselves there is an approach
all-or-nothing in our work we do not pay
attention to deadlines to any obstacles
before we get to this perfect result
there is no room for mistake in the work
of perfectionist so we do anything we
can to avoid even slightest hint to
criticism because criticism is the worst
enemy of perfectionist
and when the work is done according to
how perfectionist intended it to be this
working truly shine so why exactly
perfectionism is marked as a bug in our
program don't get me wrong
perfectionism is really good for example
it's great when like yes the problem
with perfectionism is that there are two
different types of perfectionism
according to modern psychology there is
positive perfectionism or healthy
perfections and there is negative
perfectionism so positive perfectionism
is the moving force for of a lot of
industries because it helps you achieve
outstanding results in whatever you have
passion for it's wonderful for example
when your dentist is perfectionist or an
architect that built a house you're
living in or it's really great that
Steve Jobs was such a perfectionist that
with his attitude to perfectionism to be
perfecting things he set the bar for the
whole industry but there is a pattern
here perfectionism is always good when
you are a consumer believe it or not
when you create things perfectionism can
really stand in your way the same Steve
Jobs as classical example of
perfectionists was really hard to work
with in 1977 when he was working on his
new Apple 2 computer he had to pick the
color casing of this computer and the
Pantone company sent him two thousand
shades of beige to pick from
not two not 20 not two hundred two
thousand shades of beige now we're good
enough for Steve Jobs
so he was desperately willing to develop
his perfect beige color for his perfect
computer he was so obsessed with this
idea that Michael Scott CEO of Apple
back then had to interfere and stop jobs
from doing that negative perfectionism
can make people really aggressive when
somebody challenges their ideas or the
way they work I will show you a short
clip from a sitcom Silicon Valley that
most probably you are familiar with but
it nicely illustrates the problem that
I'm talking about sure what's wrong
nothing nothing literally it's all good
right you really hate space no no no no
I don't it's not hate hates a strong
word
um truth be told I do have a slight
preference for tabs but that's only
because I'm anal and because I prefer
precision well not to pick a fight here
but if you really care about precision
when you use spaces but whatever once it
goes through the compiler it's the same
thing right yeah yeah technically yes
I guess I just I just don't understand
why you anyone use spaces over tabs like
if it's all the same or why not just use
tabs because it could look different on
other people's computers tabs create
smaller file sizes alright I run a
compression company trust me I've
devoted my life to minimalizing file
sizes it's what I do I mean I do not get
why anyone would use spaces over tabs I
mean why not just use vim over Emacs I
do use vim / Emacs oh god help us so
it's funny right but in addition to
affecting our personal life negative
perfectionism can have real effect on
our work life and it can take different
forms in our day to day job but we are
gonna talk about the most common ones
the first one is called perfectionist
paralysis we all know what is
procrastination aren't we the problem is
that different people procrastinate due
to different reasons some are just tired
some want to make the mental shift but
perfectionists procrastinate because
they are waiting for an ideal moment to
start working on their ideal project
well at least that's how perfectionists
think about this process in reality
perfectionists just afraid of not
achieving perfect result after all it's
the fear of failure they try to think
about not existing problems every task
they're working with this over complete
overcomplicates
even slide even smallest tasks and
naturally enough perfectionist needs
some time and some strength to fight
this huge monster that eats their time
and resources but let's assume that in
reality this ideal moment never comes
before it's too late right but let's
assume that miracles happen and you've
got your ideal moment so you start
working on the brush I'm sorry on a
project or simply a deadline is knocking
at your door and you have to start so
you
start this and then you get into the
next problem of negative perfectionism
that is called picking a detail so they
wish to finish every task perfectionist
works with necessarily with perfect
result leads them to pick really small
tasks that they would be guaranteed to
finish with perfect result but while
working with these small tasks
perfectionists dive so deep in this task
that they completely lose overview of a
project that still lives around this
small task again let's assume that you
have perfect project manager who is
familiar with your style and reminds you
from time to time about delivering the
result so at some point you're ready
you're ready to deliver your feature
your project your application whatever
and you get to the next problem of
negative perfectionism that is called
unnecessary task or as I call it a
cherry on top the moment you're ready to
deliver your feature your project your
application whatever an evil idea comes
to your mind
hmm this thing might be improved a bit
and you start with just taking a look
and another evil idea comes to your mind
mmm this is not hard
shouldn't take more than 10-15 minutes
now and you dive deeper and deeper and
deeper and at the end you spent the
whole day for something that at best
doesn't bring value to the project at
worst you Ron get recept hard because
this feature works unpredictable and
predictably I'm sorry or just ruins the
whole project and only then you realize
how stupid this day was so we see that
negative perfectionism brings a lot of
troubles into our lives into the lives
of those we are working with and those
who dare to live with us but what is the
solution a lot of resources advice to
just stop being a perfectionist
this is much easier to say than to do my
solution is to convert this obsession
driven negative perfectionism into the
positive perfectionism how we can
achieve this let's get straight into the
examples let me tell your story
by the age of 40 before establishing one
of the most profitable and well-known
companies in the world Henry Ford had
established two other car companies and
failed with both moreover the management
of the second company had to push Ford
off the company just four months after
he established it a lot of resources
attribute these failures to Ford's
craving for perfectionism according to
the story of this second camp car
company that is now called Cadillac Ford
was constantly working on perfecting the
designs of the cars completely ignoring
deadlines and postponing production of
the real car but no matter his craving
for perfectionism the first cars of his
third company that now is known as Ford
Motor Company we're just on par with the
competitors neither better nor worse
they were just rich cars because of this
Ford insisted on postponing production
of the cars before they get perfected at
this moment the investors had enough of
Ford and insisted on implementing the
paradigm make sale now fix them later
had it been not to the healthy attitude
to perfectionism from the investors of
the Ford the world might have never
heard of Henry Ford he would just push
his third company off the bridge as he
did two times before that but let's take
a look at the difference between
negative and positive perfectionism in
our industry two statements the first
one my product should be perfect I'm not
going to you release develop a feature
commit before I'm sure it is perfect and
the second one my product should be
perfect and this release feature commit
moves me one step closer to this perfect
result
well this example is really easy to see
that to notice the difference between
unhealthy and healthy attitude to
perfectionism and see how the negative
perfectionism really blocks us when we
create things we have to accept we have
to learn ourselves to get to this
positive attitude to perfectionism
we have to accept that our products can
leave in any version alpha beta 0.1
anything they should not be perfect from
day one they might be even incomplete
Jim Bouchard author and motivational
speaker tells this about perfectionism
perfection is not a destination it's a
never ending process enjoy because if we
do not convert into the positive
perfectionists we tend to grasp all the
information we have in our industry in
order to just understand what is perfect
and what is not and then we tend to fall
into the next bug of our program that is
called impostor phenomenon I bet some of
you are sitting and asking what
phenomenon and would be right until
recently this topic has not been really
covered in our industry but scientific
research shows that two out of five
successful people constantly suffer from
it and up to 70% of the general
population has experienced this problem
at least your during at least one period
of their professional career so let me
give you three statements and then I
will ask you to raise your hands let's
start with the first statement you think
that your success in something is due to
luck timing or any other third party
power not your hard-working your
intelligence or your talent the first
one the second one you think that others
might discover that you're not as
skilled as they think you are
wait a second wait a second wait for it
the third one you think that others are
more intelligent than you are and now
it's your time who can say that please
something on this list applies to them
wonderful take a look keep keep the
hands just like those and front
take a look like almost the whole
audience
welcome welcome to the club of Impostors
and let me congratulate you because we
are all in a really good company you
think why would anyone want to see me
again in the movie and I don't know how
to act anyway so why am I doing this
Meryl Streep actress 389 nominations 156
wins three Oscars as Best Actress I
always feel like something of an
imposter I don't know what I'm doing I'm
not a writer I've been fooling myself
and other people John Steinbeck and
writer 27 books Pulitzer Prize for
fiction Nobel Prize in Literature I
still doubt myself every single day what
people believe is my self-confidence is
actually my reaction to fear
Will Smith actor musician six American
Music Awards four Grammys two Oscar
nominations as Best Actor so technically
impostor phenomenon is the inability to
internalize your own achievements that
leads you to the feeling that you were
less competent than the rest of the
world believes you to be the term
imposter phenomenon when I first heard
about it I had my WoW moment because I
didn't even know that the feelings I had
had a name but it they had and quite
established name the term impostor
phenomenon first appeared in the
scientific from 1978 dedicated to high
achieving women in academics that's true
for many years scientific community
believed that this phenomenon is highly
confined to high achieving women but the
very same same scientists now believe
that this feeling the feeling of being
proud is much more universal and it
might be even more problematic for man
because naturally it's much harder for
man to confess like insecurity and
incompetence hence men end up hiding
their fears being unable to unburden
them and seek help
when we do not pay attention to our
imposter syndrome what can happen from
simple psychological discomfort that the
insecurity brings it can lead us
straight to failure only a couple of
years ago I had several applications of
to read functionality in my portable
devices like pocket flip board
Instapaper and I was sending saving all
the news all the interesting things you
know in our community right then there
were magazines Smashing Magazine at
least the part net magazine those
constantly brought me the latest how-tos
and tutorials and news from like
interesting articles from the world of
development from the from the web
development then we have Twitter reading
Twitter might be depressed on its own
because in so many talented people
bragging about their achievements and
their success doesn't help fighting
impostor syndrome at all but my story
doesn't end up then here of course there
were also RSS feeds newsletters like
HTML weekly JavaScript weekly there were
videos from the most recent conferences
and these constantly brought me new
information and I tried to consume all
of this information but in the flow of
all of this information I also have to
find time to do real work that paid my
bills so naturally enough one day I
figured out that I don't read those
articles anymore on the past days I
would just glance through the titles
pick two or three and they would stay
opened in my browsers in my browser
usually untouched for days so why did it
end up like this why didn't I feel
myself more competent after consuming
all of this information the answer is
that it wasn't me
who was interested in all this
information it was my imposter syndrome
pushing me to learn all these things so
that I wouldn't feel myself an
incompetent fraud so what impostor
syndrome really does is instead of
pushing us to learn new exciting things
that we can apply in our work it leads
us to the state of frustration but those
who have ever experienced this feeling I
have good
you see for you the irony of imposter
syndrome is that true frauds seem to
rarely experience this feeling as simple
as that or as English philosopher
Bertrand Russell puts it in a more
poetic way the trouble with the world is
that the stupid our culture and the
intelligent are full of doubt so one
interesting thing of imposter syndrome
is that we cannot really fight it we
cannot change the situation because
nobody can guarantee you that you are
competent enough to be in this industry
nobody can guarantee that you are the
smartest in the room it's impossible so
instead of fighting these things that
drive us into impostor syndrome what we
have to do is change our attitude to
this feeling and the first thing we have
to start with is embrace impulse train
Pacific Standard magazine puts this says
this imposter ism is for many people and
natural symptom of gaining expertise and
this makes total sense when we gain
expertise we extend the perimeter of
what we know but at the same time we
expose ourselves to even more of what we
don't so next time you have an attack of
imposter syndrome do not rush to get the
new information instead just stop stop
and enjoy this moment because most
probably this is the sign of you gaining
expertise you gaining wisdom to realize
that there is much more in this world to
discover and there is much more in our
industry for us to discover yet but I
deliberately say most probably because
some people confuse stupid bravery to
expertise and this is completely
different story another thing I would
tell I could tell you to change our
attitude to impostor syndrome is measure
yourself with your own yardstick it's
very easy now industry to be consumed by
comparing yourself to others but this is
the game impossible to win instead try
comparing yourself
to yourself compete to yourself where
were you a year ago six months ago can
you see the difference can you see this
progress if you can there was a
wonderful talk at the recent smashing
conference in Barcelona and the Yuko
wonderful illustrator it said if you
look at your pop works and they look
probably you're on the right track
this is exactly this feeling like if you
see that now you're much better than you
did a year ago you're on the right track
and last but definitely not least I can
tell you communicate your fears this
might sound a bit scary but Neil Gaiman
an acknowledged author of comic books
and movies and different books it has a
perfect anecdote to soothe anyone with
impostor syndrome let me read it for you
some years ago I was lucky enough to be
invited to a gathering of great and good
people artists and scientists writers
and discoverers of things and I felt
that at any moment they would realize
that I didn't qualify to be there among
these people who had really done things
on my second or third night there I was
standing at the back of the hall while a
musical entertainment happened and I
started talking to a very nice polite
elderly gentleman about several things
putting our shared first name and that
he pointed to the call of people and
said words to the effect often I just
look at all these people
what the heck am I doing here
they have make amazing things I think
that counts you something and I felt a
bit better because Neil Armstrong felt
like an impostor maybe everyone so do
not be afraid of communicating your
fears next time when you're in the
office and afraid of being found out by
your colleague that you do not know as
much as they think you do tap into the
knowledge that probably the people
around you might feel inadequate as well
they might have exactly the same
feelings even even your boss because if
we do not change our attitude to
impostor syndrome it pushes us to work
really hard in order to prove ourselves
and then we tend to get into the third
bug of our program that is called as
simple as long hours let's start with
raise of hands I will ask you three
questions the first one have you ever
worked long hours like developing
something or writing CSS or JavaScript
or like you work the whole day and then
you extend this day and then keep going
after midnight or something how many of
you had to have done this at least once
wonderful what a stupid question I ask
huh okay how many of you do this on a
regular basis okay now the main question
how many of you the day after putting
these long hours like writing CSS after
midnight or JavaScript after midnight
realize that the things that were
written that late have to be tossed away
they are either buggy or not functioning
well or they completely break project
please raise it okay good so long hours
are nothing you know industry but I
haven't made that I have never
heard of cases of people on the death
path saying something like oh god why
was I working so ladle conversely
palliative nurses working with anta life
care state that one of the most
mentioned regrets people say on their
death bass is that they were working way
too much and again long hours in our
industry is nothing new from touch time
we just have to put long hours because
we have to finish some something or do
some some really really urgent work
right so long hours per se are not a bug
there are two different types of long
hours though temporary long hours this
is the type of long hours that we
usually put one for example in you
exciting technology is out and we are
willing to figure out how this works so
we are willing to put these long hours
in order to be smarter to be to
understand how this new thing works
another case of course is around
deadlines because we all know how good
we are with time estimations aren't we
so this type of long hours is typical
for somebody who we would call hard
working developer but there is another
type of long hours that is more
permanent and perfectionism and
impulsive syndrome as problems set us
straight into this category of long
hours this type of long hours is typical
for somebody who we would call a
workaholic
it's kind of hard to see the difference
between hard working people
and workaholics but I like how Brian
Robinson psychotherapist puts this hard
working people usually have some balance
in their life they might see that they
tasks and think about skiing while
workaholics are on the ski slopes
thinking about work this this problem in
our industry is dictated by our
privilege we are privileged in our
industry because we can work from
anywhere in the world anytime and for
some developers and more so for some
employers this means all the time but
the question is do we manage to do more
during these long hours maybe we are
more productive in the beginning of
1920s an American company conducted the
research including their own employees
and figured out that 20 hours in
addition to the average 40 hours week so
60 hours week in total indeed leads to
increased productivity 60 hours a week
increased productivity but it takes only
3 to 4 weeks for the productivity
actually to turn negative so this
research has been conducted by the Ford
Motor Company one of the earliest
adopters of 40 hours week so as we can
see the fact that we are busy during
these long hours doesn't really mean
that we are productive during these long
hours why let me introduce you to our
front brain
no matter the unexplored potential of a
human brain in the simplest form it
still behaves like a simple muscle and
when we put long hours as a regular
muscle our brain gets tired when our
brain gets tired it's prone to making
errors in the world where we crave for
perfectionism where we want to deliver
the best possible results this leads us
to mental record it all starts with long
hours as an attempt to achieve more to
be more productive our brain gets tired
and we make errors in our work when we
make errors we cannot be satisfied with
the results so we lack the feeling of
accomplishment and in order to regain
this feeling of accomplishment and we
fix all these problems again we put long
hours this mental recursion and long
hours instead of making us more
productive actually leads us to the
state of stress but stress and it's
heavier forms like burnout are not only
about productivity
Hiroshi in Japanese in technically means
death by overwork according to different
resources in 2015
10,000 people died in Japan solely due
to overwork 10,000 people but even then
these terms tells nowhere near another
term ghoul Allah see that technically
means the same death by overwork but in
Chinese every year China loses about
600,000 people due to overwork this
results to 16 deaths every day due to
overwork we're not talking about people
working with sharp objects or guns
majority of these people are white
colours sitting in the offices in order
to understand why stress is so dangerous
to us we have to dive a bit deeper into
our friend brain so when when we feel
stressed our brain sends signals all
over our body to enable the protective
mechanism among other things this
mechanism consists of two chemicals
adrenaline and the so called stress
hormone cortisol combination of this is
brilliant it helps us make really fast
decisions when we are in real danger
this combination is very similar to
adding important to your CSS files it
overrides everything else our body
forgets about how to plan our life for
the next 10 years because it's busy with
thinking how to survive the next 10
minutes this is what stress does to us
this mechanism is vital for hours for
for us to survive right and it might
even bring this creative adrenaline kick
to those hard-working developers to
finish that one feature before deadline
but the same mechanism applied for
prolonged periods of time to our brain
can severely damage our brain recent
research in Berkeley California and
Sweden show that
our brain physically changes its
structure under prolonged periods of
stress this is what happens and McDonald
region is increased thinning of the
prefrontal cortex shrinking of the
hippocampus and the only question we
might have here is what the heck does
this mean so let me translate this into
human readable language it means
premature aging of your brain
significant drop in learning abilities
and weakened memory and make it
ridiculously obvious these three income
in combination are the signs of mental
disability isn't it amazing we do work
hard we want to achieve the best
possible result we learn new things and
the paycheck for all of this is early
dementia or Alzheimer's we have to do
something about this I'm pretty sure
that you are familiar with the most
common ways to fight stress like
physical exercises or meditation simple
as simple things as chocolate or
ultraviolet light can help you find
stress a bit but today I want to talk to
you about another approach approach that
would help you to prevent this severe
damage to our brains let's talk about
Harvard Howard University we all know
about Harvard right it's 133 Nobel
laureates 35 current billionaires 8
presidents of the United States it's the
birthplace for Facebook and Microsoft
it's also active universities in the
world in 2017 only 5.8%
applicants a gained admission to this
university because in the process of
admission things not directly related to
studying are taken into account as well
like achievements and music achievements
and supports owned startup business and
so on and so on so it wouldn't be an
exaggeration to say that anybody
studying at Harvard has to leave
completely crazy life dedicating every
minute of his or her life
to either studying or self-development
and a lot of them do in 2004 there were
it was a meeting between students
the management of the University where
students raised some concerns quite
weird concerns I must say so some
students claimed that they want to take
two full-size courses four-year courses
and pass them in parallel others wanted
to take the full four years course and
pass it within three years so
technically what students wanted was to
do as much as they possibly could while
they are at Harvard what a pleasant
thing should it be for management of
university to hear these things from the
students right but instead of being
impressed Harry Lewis Dean of Harvard
undergraduate school back then sent a
letter to all the students in Harvard
titled slow down getting more out of
Harvard by doing less in this letter
Harry Lewis appealed to the students
that instead of increased mental
pressure what they really need is to
slow down he advocated to for students
to take some time off Harvard and not
just an evening or a week but take the
whole term or the whole year of Harvard
naturally enough the parents of the
students were furious reasonably
believing that after spending one year
of Harvard students won't be remembering
anything they had they learned before
leaving Harvard or they just won't be
willing to get back to Harvard right but
statistics tells us 96% of those who had
full year of Harvard came back gained
grad mission and successfully graduated
Harvard Harvard calls it this slow
learning drew faust current president of
Harvard University says college can help
you learn how to think more than what to
think how to think more than what to
think and I believe this is exactly the
problem that we have in our industry we
have tons of information telling us
to think even if it's titled how to but
we have to learn ourselves how to think
today we have seen that a program
presenting an average developer has a
lot of box we have covered just the tip
of the iceberg there are many more
problems in this program but unlike our
projects we cannot postpone fixing this
box for later because unlike our
projects this program has no versions
other than 1.0 and debugging and fixing
problems we have to do we have to do it
straight in production does our industry
need more professional successful
developers frankly I don't know but what
is certain is that our industry is more
healthy more happy developers my name is
Dennis I am a developer and I have a lot
of problems because of this but as
psychiatrists say acknowledging a
problem is the first step to mental
health
today I have shared some problems and I
personally have but I'm sure they have
resonated with some of you because even
though our friend the doesn't mean we
cannot have the same problems Department
these problems to your production stay
healthy stay happy thank you
[Music]
[Applause]