my name is constant k fur I'm going to
talk about not writing notes as
extensions with c++ and the v8 API you
can find me on get up and twitter under
the username of kk fur so I work for oh
yeah this is the page you want to show
you I work for a development seat we're
a small shop based in DC and we do
mapping stuff our project is called
matte box and it allows you to create
maps we all have tile milk which is like
I'm at the sign application you can
change the color here to basically
create your own maps I'm going to talk
about c++ and how you can use it to
write no extensions so we all know that
people's bus is faster than JavaScript
right that's what you learn is cool
right anyone agrees with that the
question is is it really faster and
turns out the v8 guys did a really great
job at making JavaScript run very fast
and I did a little experiment to really
find out whether it actually makes sense
to write C++ extensions for node and if
you can do what you want to do it all in
JavaScript you should probably do it in
JavaScript because it's probably going
to be faster not always but most of time
the reason for this is that crossing the
boundary between JavaScript and C++ is
very slow and the ape compiles the child
strip code you write into a native
bytecode that it's usually faster to
execute them like just run your
unoptimized C++ code so for my little
test i use this functions which is the
formula for calculating the answer to
everything and so when I write this in
native she has an executor I get about
80 million calls per second on my crappy
three year old laptop it's pretty fast
right is there at the same thing in the
aid as a node extension I only get 13
million code calls per second which is a
lot slower if I do this asynchronously
like if I pass a callback function Jim I
v8 function written in C++ I only get
one point seven and if I go through the
thread pool light I'll float the
calculation to another threat if you
will it's really slow so if like if what
you want to do that's like you can write
it in JavaScript if if you can't do that
otherwise I'm going to like talk to you
about how you can do it in C++ so why
would you do c++ if you can write
JavaScript so there are a few reasons
here the biggest reason is yayness
written in C++ to kind of have to write
C++ to write node extensions but why do
you want to write node extensions tab at
all so pretty much the only reason for
doing that is to wrap existing C++
libraries right you don't want to
reinvent the wheel of light someone else
has probably spent a lot of time and
effort to build existing libraries like
sequel I'd like coelom you don't want to
really implement that again in
JavaScript and maybe one of the biggest
reason is javascript is single trip at
single-threaded pretty much so if you
have this big beautiful eight core
machine that you want to use and you run
like JavaScript code or just chose to
code it on it you can't really use more
than one processor one core at a time so
by offloading work into another threat
you can use more of the CPU so
this is actually all there is to writing
a C++ module four node this is all all
the code you have to write to be able to
get started so there are a few things
here you have to include the header
files of course if it register module
function you can really name that anyway
you want us just let use that name and
you registered your module lower like
the register function with node by using
the node module macro and use this
boilerplate code to compile it just like
save it as w script in the same
directory and you're good to go so if
you want to follow along you can go to
github.com / kk for / node CPP modules
which sold a sample code and contains a
lot more comes as well so you can like
go back there later if you want to check
that out anyway so let's compile this
compelling is pretty easy with node you
chose type node Wow configure and it
configures all your stuff and to
actually compile it if you run the same
thing with build or nothing at all and
it compiles in links or module and saves
it as a build / release / module named
of node or whatever you named it in uu w
script file so let's run this code like
this is just the nine lines of code that
I showed you on this slide this is all
we compiled now so you can just require
this module like any other node module
and what you'll get back as an empty
object that's all there's there's
nothing you can do nothing with that
object could have done this in
JavaScript right but we'll get to some
more examples in a bit so a few general
recommendations for developing I
recommend using si Lang and that makes
it a lot easier because ceiling has
easier to comprehend error message
than GCC but you should also compile
your stuff we're test your stuff with
GCC because many assistants many users
still use GCC they don't have ceiling
installed and if you publish your module
in npm most of the people who will
download and install your module will
probably use GCC right so let's get to
some more interesting samples to let
create a function in JavaScript or in
C++ that you can access from JavaScript
you just like to find a regular c
function or c++ function and there are a
few things here I'm it returns a handle
a handle is like basically a wrapper
around some sort of value um takes arcs
or arguments which is pretty much the
same thing as the arcs arguments options
that you get in JavaScript functions as
well and there are a few things that are
new here so in line for we have the
handle scope the handle scope is
basically sort of a safeguard that keeps
track of all the handles that you create
of all the variables that you create in
this c++ function and cleans them up
after rewards so you don't leak any of
the any of the variables that you create
and when you want to return stuff you
don't want V 8 to clean that that
because like the child script that
expects the return value still wants to
use this right so you want to make sure
that it doesn't get cleaned up and the
way you do this is a call scope that
closed around this and return the result
of that so we still have to register
that function that we defined with our
node module and in the register module
function which just call them Acura note
set method and just like use an
arbitrary name that we want to and use
our function name and that's pretty much
it
the target parameter of the register
module function is pretty much the same
as the exports object that you have in
native JavaScript modules so you can
just add stuff to that to that object
and it'll show up in the c++ extension
when you require it so it's compiled
this compelling works the same way as
before with no left configure note with
build and when we require this we see
the function as expected right okay we
can call this and we get the return
value that we defined in the function so
accepting arguments is not that
complicated either usually is a good at
here to check that you actually like the
user actually pass arguments to the
function similar to the Chava script
arguments objects we also have that
length function or that length a way to
find out the number of arguments and we
can throw exceptions and yeah just like
return create a new error object
exception that hyper is basically the
same as new error in JavaScript to
create new JavaScript strings use string
down you and that way the user will get
a JavaScript exception when when they
try to call the function without an
argument so once you're past the check
and the user actually parsed an argument
we can convert that to integer and there
are a bunch of two functions that you
can use to convert the stuff convert the
variable unica the user pass to any to a
particular type that you want to work
with or that you expect so let's look at
the at the documentation of the v8
documentation
and we kind of see the datatype tree
here so this is pretty much the same
things that you know from javascript
because we're after all writing
JavaScript code just in C++ we have an
array we have date with this weird
things like the boolean object so I'm
sure most of you know that they're like
Williams and actual objects which are
not type of boolean and with strings
numbers you can go down there and the
interesting part is that the C++ API the
v8 C++ API actually have several number
types as opposed to JavaScript where you
only have a number the eight actually
supports like native integers which are
subclass of the number type so there's
just something to be aware of mmm okay
let's get okay so when you do when you
want to run stuff asynchronously you
usually accept a callback function that
you called when you are finished writing
your work and the way to do this is to
check whether it's a function and cast
this to a function basically very
similar to what we did before when we
casted it or converted it to an integer
then we just do our stuff our
calculations in soup or pulling out to
smc libraries or C++ libraries and when
you get an error this is just note
convention but it's probably a pretty
good idea to follow it because most
users are familiar with that convention
is the first argument to their callback
is an error object if an error occurred
otherwise it's no so when Noah record we
just create note for the first argument
when an error occurred we create a new
exception object and pass that as the
only argument right so we call the
callback function with one argument here
and with two arguments and the second
argument being the result you might have
noticed that we don't use scope to close
here and there are a few things that you
can return from C++ functions or from
the 8th C++ functions that you don't
have to wrap in scope the closest or
undefined no true and false I'm not sure
whether more but at least these you can
just return without wrapping them and
scope that close so oh and one thing
when you call a function you don't have
to somehow make sure that the handles
will stay around because the call
function automatically make sure that VA
doesn't garbage collect or destroy them
any other way before before the call
function you're calling returned so oh
and one thing you really don't want to
forget the handle scope at the top
that's a pretty important piece if you
don't add that you'll run into troubles
and like your code starts or your module
starts to behave in a weird very weird
way and you run hard to debug errors so
make sure that you always have the
handles code but most of the stuff we
did so far as cereal right we just
implemented the same stuff that you
could have done in JavaScript and C++
let's do some stuff asynchronously
because like even if we just like call
the function here this is still
synchronous like the original call to
the callback function block until our
stuff is done so note has a thread pool
that we can use to offload work into
other threats and the way this works is
we have one main threat the eight threat
we're just running all the child strip
code and no it spawns a couple of worker
threads that you can dispatch work
requests to do this
you have to create three functions the
original function which takes all the
arguments and converts it to a native
p.o.d types or some other civil plus
types that are independent of v8 then it
is statuz that to the worker function
which runs in another thread and
afterwards when you're done when the
work of function which is the blocking
function returns you can convert it back
and call your original call back so like
I said it's single-threaded that's why
it's a pretty good idea to do any kind
of i/o and CPU or heavy cpu usage in the
worker thread function so you basically
have all the main thread like for plain
JavaScript functions for accepting
server connections and handling all the
blue code kind of work that's a pretty
important bit you should not ever access
any v8 variables any kind of handles
from the work of functions if you do
your program is probably going to crash
sooner rather than later so we still
want to get our data that we pass into
the original function to the work a
friend the way we can do this is to just
create a struct or class or whatever you
want to do like the convention here is
to call it baton but you can really use
any other kind of name or you can also
use just like passive arbitrary pointer
whatever you come up with but I found
that this works pretty well and you can
do most things with it it's a pretty
good template so beef if you think's
here the work request allows you to
dispatch the call to another thread we
have the callback function that we want
to keep around so that we can call the
callback function later once we're done
with the work and this is just some arab
tracking code
so when our work if function fails we
can store those error messages with a
record error codes here and then create
error object when we're back in the main
v8 thread to give the user some
information so like I said this is just
a convention you can use any other kind
of scheme that you come up with one
important piece is the persistent handle
regular handles are not persistent
they're cleaned up at the handle scope
when you exit the function but we don't
want our callback function to be cleaned
up because you want to use it later on
again to call the user with the results
of our stuff right so this is why you we
use the persistent type of the handle so
this is basically how starting a
starting a worker process or at work a
threat looks like you just check that we
have a function here and convert it to a
function handle and create a new baton
of doing some set of work and create a
new persistent handle so that VA doesn't
clean this up and just NQ the work
request into the lib QV q and we pass to
function names this is a sink work this
is our worker function and this is the
aftra function which is called once the
async work function returns so the work
effect is pretty pretty easy or looks
pretty lightweight actually sorry just
convert the data which is like a
reference or a pointer to the bathroom
and you can basically do any kind of
work here what it can do is use any v8
stuff so you have to convert any kind of
data that you pass into the worker
thread in
the first function to some some sort of
native type so this fence is blocking so
you can basically do whatever you want
you can do long-running network
connections you can do file access you
can do expensive calculations and it
won't block the main v8 Fred like I said
don't don't don't use any v8 stuff in
there ok so once you're done lip UV make
sure to call your after function do the
same thing this time with a handles code
because this is executed back in the
main threat and do the same thing check
whether we had an error and when we did
just called a call back with an error
object or exception object otherwise
we'll pass the result back this is what
you also have to do because we created a
persistent handle of the call back
before we have to manually dispose of it
to make sure that that is cleaned up and
just like delete our delete our object
so yeah ok one thing that you have to be
aware of is when you call a callback
functions in in an after function that
returns from the GV is called the top of
the event loop of notes event loop so
this time you've to wrap it in a c++
try-catch or leg at the eight try-catch
so that it's possible for modules to use
process on uncaught exception in the
case the callback function fails so some
some words on API design the problem is
that most of the time you want to
convert a synchronous API that is
implemented in C or C++ into some sort
of a sink a way so they can use it from
JavaScript there's some patterns that
you can use here
the event emitter pattern if sometimes
pretty useful when you can fit your fit
the API the original API into the event
emitter pattern that's a pretty good way
to go cheney book hauls like jquery are
often a very useful thing to do and when
you do this you can like manually cue
the work requests in your original fed
before you dispatch them to the thread
pool and i'll show you an example for
that in a bit some previous or some
examples basically create objects with
new for any kind of things you can also
just create a native function or like a
plane function you don't have to wrap it
an object so it is just a simple API
call just like write a simple function
doesn't have to be complicated and this
is probably the most important bit of
advice make it very hard to misuse so
JavaScript programmers usually expect
that like the program doesn't crash
randomly so that they have to like call
things in a specific order so antigua
and c and c++ api's are different so
your program can crash if you don't use
the C++ or C API in the correct order so
your code should make sure that it's
impossible that the program will crash
and and even if you misuse it just throw
errors as opposed to crashing and yeah
just like make you feel as JavaScript as
possible that's what I usually do when
starting to write a note extension yes I
just like open up my editor and come up
with an API or like write some
JavaScript code that should be the API
and then see how it can implement it in
the aid or node c++ code so that it
looks like a good API
some examples for this to like show you
what I'm talking about is the notes to
collect three API to create a new
database object you just call the new
operator on a view there's no open
function or anything because when you
create a new database object like
openness pretty much implicit you like
don't want to open it separately that
eliminates a few staff you like things
you have to check for like you don't
have to check when you run a query Oh
has the user already called open because
it's already open implicitly and all of
those requests are cute so that they're
always executed after the database is
actually open yeah and there's also no
need to close the database handle
because once there once the once we ate
garbage collects the DB object here we
automatically close the database handle
so the user doesn't have to call close
manually and one other thing that I
implemented here is if you don't pass a
call that function like in this example
and the query can still failure right
and in that case I just omit an error
event on the database object so a note
has some code in there that
automatically like throws errors when
there is an uncaught error object on
some other object so that way like you
can still catch those another example is
no blend which the module dead just
blends together two images and we don't
have to like create a new operator here
which is called a function with two
buffers and we get a buffer pack so
there's no need to instantiate anything
here like we don't need any state so
there's no like various plant states so
we just like take images and blend them
together um there's some more
documentation of these links here
and yeah I check out the github
repository there are a lot more comments
in there there's also some samples for
creating objects in there like the new
operator and yeah thanks to mr aleph and
ice axe and orlando for for some of the
examples that I used and some of their
modules and yeah any questions
you mean like as opposed to using run
and get I did consider that the reason
there are different methods is that
symptoms you'd like just don't care
about the result you don't have to like
step over the result object so when you
don't care about the result you just use
run if you wanted to get just a single
value you can use get and there are some
where methods as well that are described
on the module website so that's the
reason for it you can also just always
use all or get there's no look no
damaging that