so I'm talking about caste and nodejs
how the agenda two things I want to
really cover it's kind of almost two
different presentations in a way is an
introduction to cast and then kind of
things we learned as we as we built cast
as a project on top of nodejs so you
know the background of this is auto
scaling is mostly a dirty dirty lie it
doesn't really exist in the real world
some people do it you can Auto scale web
servers but overall most companies that
aren't Google or Facebook or you know
have massive investments in
infrastructure don't really have auto
scaling solutions but on the other hand
resources like servers or storage are
getting easier and easier to acquire but
the apps themselves are just not ready
to auto scale so what we start looking
at was what infrastructure is missing to
make this work and we really felt it
focus around deployment and service
management and that is very different
than configuration management there is
some overlap especially the closer you
get to service management with
configuration management chef and puppet
and such but we felt there's big enough
difference there it's you know you can
focus just on this deployment and
service management part and be very good
at that so at the time we're all working
for a startup called cloud kick and
we're like well screw this let's just
start writing code and do it so that's
what we did so a cast at the very
highest level today is deployment as an
HTTP API you can install applications
you create a tarball you upload it and
it goes you do things like upgrading it
once it's deployed start stop restart it
has built in monitor native applications
so you can tell if your application
actually started it has built an access
to the log files of those apps create
and then in a long run we want to do
things like full app configuration
across the cluster which is kind of a
miniature zookeeper
so at a high level this is what we want
Cass to look like in the long run it's
not all the way there right now but
basically have a series of agents that
install on your servers wherever they
are cast doesn't really care then
there's a set of rest ap is that used to
communicate with those agents and those
agents within cells are kind of
self-organizing talk to each other over
peer-to-peer protocol so basically your
cast client or a web app or whatever
interface you want talks over this rest
api to your servers which is very
different compared to the interaction
you have with a traditional system like
puppet or chef where it's generally you
have a central repository of your
configuration you know this puppet
master and there's all these puppet
agents that pull down that configuration
it's just for deployment stuff you want
much more control over when things are
happening you know when you do a upgrade
of your web app you want to all happen
in all your web servers at a specific
time we're doing incremental rolling out
of it which is just not how most
implementations of puppet and chef are
done so cast has been in development for
a while our first release like public
release that we actually think is usable
was about two weeks ago it's focused on
the single mesh machine experience which
means we don't do much stuff with multi
machine at all right now but it's
focused on giving you a REST API to
control your apps on top of that server
it's you know it's open source and
there's a big website and all that kind
of stuff so I wanted to give a little
mini demo of cast so I'm going to start
the agent oops
okay so it started an agent on my laptop
and the command line client just a
simple command line client that wraps
with things on the server so for example
services list shows my running services
then I can go to that service and tail
it and if I can do things like curl that
URL it you know the server logs that
request you know and you can see it over
this command line client so that's the
simplest things you know standing
started with cast you can do it has a
lot more to it well a lot more to it in
the ways so like how you make something
a cast project as a thing called cast
that JSON which defines you know general
things about the server defines how you
get into the service this example is
server Jas is Ritu nodejs but it could
be any app you know you could have a
rails thing there or a hmong girl or
whatever you wanted it's not really no
Jay a specific the actual thing you're
deploying it also has things like
built-in health checks so we know that
this service should create an HTTP
server on this port and we expect it 200
from it if we're not getting that we
consider the services down as a problem
okay so there's a little bit of history
to cast it's been kind of in development
for about 10 months and you can see
developments been up and down there's
some reason behind that the first thing
that happened why development kind of
paused I would say is we got our start
up got acquired by Rackspace and so all
of us were distracted with things like
you know lawyers making sure our source
code didn't have the wrong IP in it and
you know that kind of stuff and then we
got busy began year and then what really
changed our development and well we're
ready to go back on and work on it but
no Jay s04 came out and it really
enabled us and fix a lot of the issues
we saw in earlier versions of node and
so we kind of have this 10-month history
of
30 for you know we did a lot of
prototyping a lot of dev work but after
04 we actually have something that we
feel that's like usable by people so I
want to go through a lot of just our
lessons learned with building cast as a
node.js application because I think
that's where there's a lot of value for
people is you know we made a lot of
mistakes because we started 10 months
ago and there are lots of different
things that you do differently nowadays
the first one is just use NPM when we
started there were like three other
package managers and none of them were
particularly good and to say the truth I
don't think NPM was that good either at
the point but at this point there's no
reason not to choose em p.m. today
things like the local module install so
you'd bundling entire app into one we
put you know one set of node modules is
a huge improvement it makes it very easy
to move apps around servers the other
thing we've used a lot is internal NPM
registry cloud kick because we have some
products that are not open source but we
have so we want those modules use the
same pattern though so that if we ever
do make them open source is very easy
it's flipping a switch so one thing
about using things for mpm though is
that the community part of a module is
the most important thing careful of
single author you know I'm learning
nodejs modules because there's a lot of
them what you end up if you just have to
know that if you know this guy goes away
you're going to own that module and
we've done that a couple times sometimes
we submit patches they just ignore them
other times they're active and they take
them back but just be aware there's a
lot of modules out there that don't have
a lot of active maintain errs so a big
thing we learned when we started doing
node is you know we were originally a
twisted Python shop and so we had a lot
of unit tests already we're doing a lot
of heavy unit testing but it's very
important with JavaScript that there is
no compiler so you really need test
cases to show that you didn't break
something we started using expresso
which is pretty common for most people
and we felt it was great for little web
apps but we felt for our service
especially with the agent has a lot of
state in it it just wasn't sustainable
to keep using expresso so we wrote
something called whiskey which is a
you know test runner but does a lot of
things differently every test files ran
in a subprocess for example so if you a
lot of like global variable state or
state changes inside your app you can
test that in whiskey I mean need a lot
more isolation between processes which
was really important for us because our
a lot of our app is you know downloading
a file you know spawning a subprocess to
do tar things like that which are not
very easy to do in expresso so I want to
show one thing from expresso which yeah
internet it's not there good so one of
things we built on top of expresso is
test coverage sorry buildings have a
whiskey is test coverage so if you've
seen like coverage up high for python is
a very similar system you know so you
have the overall report of you know we
only have sixty-three percent test
coverage which is pretty terrible and
we're working on fixing that but the
cool thing is you can see exactly what
lines were run as part of whiskey so you
can see you know it parsed this this
file so this this line was ran but the
actual function was never called so this
line was never ran so it's you know very
easy to see how to improve your test
cases so that gets to like lint you
should also use Jace hint or jslint
depends on if you believe crockford is
right all the time it's kind of your
choice there is no J's hint which makes
it very easy just MPM install so you
know use that the one project we've been
using a lot of though is Google closure
linter which is actually written in
Python but in and it enforces code style
according to google's coding style
guidelines which if you don't like well
you probably shouldn't use it but we
felt we found that it was very helpful
just to have us you know coding standard
and we're just gonna here to the Google
coding standard and closure Lintz a very
helpful tool for maintaining that now
one thing you hear a lot about on the
front end side if you'll using the
closure compiler to you know detect to
do compile the JavaScript it's a single
file right and compress it but we're
using it as a linting step as a static
analysis tool
so right now it works great for single
file statical analysis but it doesn't
understand yet like the node module
structure or things like that we're
looking at how to do that so that you
know it understands cross module errors
so here's an example of what it can do
today very easily you can detect things
like inconsistent return types from the
documented types you know unused
variables in a lot of kind of basic
static analysis stuff that you just
don't have normally in JavaScript and so
it's a very easy tool to kind of
repurpose from the front end Express you
should just use it when we started we
thought oh HTTP is really easy there's
all these simple examples we'll just you
know right use HTTP router and do our
own thing and that was like totally a
mistake you know you should just use
Express there's no like it's so small
and the scale of things you know you
should just use it it has a lot of
utilities it's going to keep getting
better whereas if you just do your own
thing it's you're always going to come
be stuck in your world so a little story
about TLS when we started it frankly
didn't work well we started using just
HTTP which you know was easy but it just
didn't you know and then we like oh
we'll just turn on SSL one day when
we're ready and we turned it on and it
completely bombed just nothing would
work at all so that was 02 back in like
september-october last year and we're
like well okay so ice works with Ryan
Allah and Ryan did a lot of the work to
to rewrite the whole SSL stack and you
know we did it and it mostly works in 04
if you using since 06 for six or so it's
actually generally works for everything
we haven't found many bugs since then
but if you find a bug please let us know
we'll fix it streams so especially pries
ero for we had a lot of problems with
streams the API wasn't well defined
there's lots of other issues for example
we would untie our file or cat like over
sorry uploading a file over HTTP
streamed up pipe into the HTTP stream
and I would have like you know a twenty
percent chance of working successfully
that's not the truth anymore there's no
reason to like reinvent your own
streaming API if you're like moving
files around with HTTP you should just
use pipe there are some issues with
error handling so it's not great but
there's been a discussion as we
discussed yesterday node commit was kind
of trying to improve some of that stream
error handling I want talk about flow
control for a minute people come to node
there's a lot of people talking about
promises and other you know node fibers
and other solutions we've tried to stay
away from them as much as possible you
know it's not JA it's not javascript is
not VA it's not node at that point we
focused on using a sink is one we use a
lot we found that very good for our use
cases provides you know 20 odd utility
functions like parallel serialized map
that prevent you know the callback
chaining madness the other very common
popular one is called step you know be
so basically pick a way to do
asynchronous things that's not just
chaining callbacks you know pick a
library that gives you a little bit of
extraction but I wouldn't recommend
going off and using node fibers or
investing really having promises right
now kind of one lesson through all this
was just send patches you know Ryan is
very receptive to patches that fix
things you know when we started you know
different people on our team who
contribute quite a few patches at this
point and it's actually pretty easy you
know make a test case that breaks people
you know then he'll accept your patch
fix the code and make a pull request and
at this point the most important thing
for most people is it's mostly
JavaScript there's very few well there
are bugs we have to go to look in the
sea world but a lot of times there's
pure JavaScript bugs that you don't have
to look at you know you just use
patching javascript thing so it's much
easier and more accessible than most
people so as part of rackspace we've
kind of been leading the way inside
Rackspace to trying to do more and more
nodejs we're building on our team in San
Francisco just due to do
we've opened source a bunch of things
cast is the main one it's a ton of code
but we also open source things like our
node Cassandra client and we're doing a
bunch of things with our are we have a
serialization layer on top of Express
that we're open sourcing as well so I
just say go check out the code and if
there's any time or any questions I
guess okay so the question I think is
just our using cast in production right
now okay we are using it in kind of some
staging environments and playing with it
it's not yet in production and a large
scale our goal was really right now is
to get zero one out and we just kind of
finish that and then our next goal like
402 is to get cloud cake production use
as many places as we can so that's kind
of our next part of the project is we're
going to use in production and start
that feedback loop of you know that's
broken you know make the user interface
better because you know right now that
for example the cast client corresponds
very well with like the REST API but
like that's not what you want in a high
level client you want you know make this
thing go you know you don't want it to
match the rest api necessarily directly
so that's kind of our next big part of
the project is to production eyes it and
make it easier to use the question is
why didn't we use Express the first time
and that was you know last year it
wasn't even clear that sir that Express
would like win you know like 10 months
ago it was like there's a lot of the
million modules and all of them are kind
of crap and that's not the case anymore
you know and we said oh well HTTP is
really easy we'll just make out a little
router with a few reg X's you know what
you certainly could do it was fast but
like it's just not maintainable in the
long run right and you lose out on all
those middlewares you just want to you
know oh look someone may have sweet you
know rate-limiting middle where I want
to go pull that in well it's you know
not quite that easy so you end up you
know carrying a lot of burden in and
maintaining your own thing when Express
just gives you a lot it doesn't cost you
very much like the cost of using Express
is very low
overall that's why I think people should
just use it by default at this point any
other questions