thank you very much so as Marcy said I'm
Erin and I'm a web standards and
accessibility advocate at Microsoft some
of you who've been around for a bit
probably know me from my work at a list
apart I'm currently editor-in-chief
there I also was a manager of the web
standards project back in the day but
today I want to talk about something
that's kind of near and dear to my heart
that I'm getting more and more excited
about so chat BOTS and digital
assistants are kind of becoming all the
rage now and most of these if you aren't
aware work from specially coded data
sets and models but there's more than
four and a half billion pages of content
stored online trapped in many cases
within our websites articles stories
blog posts educational materials books
and marketing messages all on the web
but for the most part an untapped
treasure trove of content that could be
useful in a non-visual context now there
have been a few projects search engine
spiders probably most notably that are
working to turn that often unstructured
mess into something usable right but we
can do more a lot more to enable our
pages to be usable both by real people
and the computers that power voice based
user experiences and that's what I'm
here to talk about I want to release
that content from the screen and empower
it to go anywhere and everywhere I want
it to find its way into virtual
assistants and other voice response
technologies and even into voiceless
chat BOTS without requiring us to code
and recode over and over again into
multiple redundant formats I also have a
dream of enabling our users to actively
engage with our content by filling in
forms or manipulating widgets just with
their voice and this sort of stuff is
becoming possible specifically I'm here
to talk to you about how we can use HTML
and Aria to make our content structured
sensible and most importantly meaningful
and it all begins with the humble
element so consider this M element sure
it's visibly rendered as italics but it
also adds emphasis
to the content within hTML is just
chock-full of elements like this that
convey meaning nuance and relationships
and being aware of these enables us to
author more expressive documents and
ignoring them can actually undermine the
usability of the content that we're
marking up when we create a webpage we
need to be mindful of the conversation
that we're creating with our customers
in that process and we need to choose
the elements that we use with intent and
care one of the best indicators of how
HTML will make it into our Virtual
Assistants is another assistive
technology screen readers write not only
do screen readers do as their name
implies but they also enable users to
rapidly navigate a page in various ways
and they provide means to translate
visual design constructs such as
proximity proportion and so on into
audible cues at least they do so when we
author our pages thoughtfully so that
further ado let's jump into some solid
examples of how we can create more
meaningful documents and empower them to
be more usable in a headless UI context
we'll start by looking at what are
called phrasing elements the emphasis
you saw earlier was an example of this
and we used to call them inline elements
because by default they're visibly
inline text but phrasing is more
accurate as a description because well
they mark up phrases right so we saw
this example earlier here the word
really is marked up as emphasized now
when spoken by a virtual assistant heads
up none of them quite do this yet but
I've mocked it up with the speech
synthesis API in JavaScript it could
sound something like this
I'm really happy to see you which is
kind of cool
now sometimes emphasis is not enough
when we want to indicate that content is
very important for our customers to pay
attention to the strong element is the
right way to go because strong means
that something is of strong importance
now visibly M and strong are displayed
as italics and bold respectively and in
the early days of the web when I first
started out we had the I and B element
which were rendered exactly the same and
so many of us just thought they were
interchange
Abell and with B&I being shorted or
right they proliferated on the web
semantically however these elements are
quite different from their doppelgangers
the AI element is similar to the
emphasis element but it's a bit more
generic it's used to indicate an
alternate voice or mood it could be used
to indicate sarcasm or idiomatic remarks
or shifts in language so it's a terrible
movie and it made 200 million go figure
right now in the second example here you
might notice that I've indicated a
language being shifted too from the
natural language of the document this
indicator is a simple mechanism that
could inform a voice synthesizer to
shift pronunciation here's an example of
how that might work
she has admired for her energy and is
whether the Yvonne not perfect but we
only have a couple of things that we can
work with a couple different voices we
can work with in speech synthesis right
now but it kind of points at what's
possible the B element is used for
content that should be set apart or in
the parlance of the spec stylistically
off set but it's of no greater
importance than the surrounding text so
I like to use it for the names of people
or the names of products things that
would be like keywords within the
content that I might want to mark up in
some certain way or might want to
visually call out in some certain way
books films and and things like that
have their own element the site element
which will see an example of shortly and
functionally the B element is a lot like
a span which is for generic phrasing
content but with a shorter tag now HTML
has other specialized phrasing
constructs - such as a abbr for
abbreviations and acronyms so in this
case hTML is the standard markup
language for creating web pages and web
applications and here I've given a title
for hypertext markup language which is
what HTML is an abbreviation for or an
acronym for rather now sadly as with
many things on the web
black hat SEO folks used the title
element - or the title attribute to put
all kinds of awful stuff into pages in
order to boost search engine ranking so
that basically spurned screen readers to
stop reading it because this will give
you a sense of the time people just kept
putting panel and
name in there over and over again visual
browsers still do provide tooltips so
there is some utility to the title
attribute they're not completely useless
but screen readers don't pay attention
to it and it's pretty unlikely that they
will be surfaced by a virtual assistant
to be honest it's probably best unless
you want that tooltip to just avoid
using title altogether for the purposes
of absolute clarity in our content you
should introduce and explain important
abbreviations and acronyms the first
time they're used and there isn't
there's even an element that actually
signals that defining context the dfn
element so in this case hypertext markup
language and then in parentheses hTML is
the standard markup language for
creating web pages and web applications
finally there's the span element which
is used for generic phrases it's a
meaningless element so it wouldn't be
spoken in any other way differently by
default there are a bunch of other ones
but I only have so much time that I can
talk to y'all so I'm gonna try and keep
it a keep it brief here links are also
phrasing elements but I want to call
them out specifically because they're a
much richer interface and provide a lot
more opportunity for fine-tuning how our
users interact with them the primary way
we use links of course is to link to
related content right and it's important
when we do this to actually choose
meaningful words and phrases as our link
text because when assistive technologies
hit click here or read more that doesn't
tell them anything about what it is that
they're actually accessing all right
those are not useful especially if
there's several on the page and when
people skim via those links which I'll
talk a little bit about shortly that
gets really painful so in this case I
wrote the book adaptive web design and
I've got it in a site element as well as
an anchor so that's a pretty good
example of that instead of saying I
wrote the book adaptive web design click
here to learn more about it right we can
also use links and I think that we
should do this more frequently to
reference content within the current
document or even it specifically
identified places within the document so
if you if you are referencing a table or
a figure of some sort
give that figure an ID so that it can
actually be linked to from
than the content of your pages same
thing for headings please God if you're
writing something on the web put IDs on
your headings so that if I want to
reference something that you've written
I can actually point to at least the
section that it's in don't make me just
go to the generic page and have somebody
have to hunt for where that quote is you
can even use them to inform users about
the language that's in use on a linked
page using the href Lang attribute so in
this case it's switching to a Spanish
version of this page and you can
indicate the kind of content being
linked to using the type attribute use
mime types for that and in a relatively
new addition to the HTML spec you
actually have the download keyword which
can inform the browser that the file in
question should be downloaded rather
than presented again it's a simple
attribute that makes an HTML document
capable of so much more it's worth
noting though for the download attribute
that would be ignored on any
cross-origin you are eyes so it has to
be same domain anchor elements also
support non web pseudo protocols to the
most common or mailto and tell so email
and phone numbers but SMS and web quel
are also quite quite common and some
operating systems and browsers allow
installed apps to also register custom
protocols that serve to access in-app
functionality but I want to just throw
it out there that you should be cautious
about using that approach because if the
protocol is not recognized then the
operating system will often prompt the
user to try and find an app that can
actually use that which just adds
friction to the experience there are
other ways to direct URLs into
applications so I recommend looking into
those now all this phrasing contents
great but I've spent a little while in
the weeds the minutia and I want to kind
of pull back and look at documents
themselves because I need to I think we
need to think about how we author are
our documents and our web pages on the
whole now as you're probably aware
headless you eyes place a greater
cognitive load on our users it's hard to
keep track of where you are in an
interface and it can be even more
challenging to move around when you
can't gather information about the
interface from visual
and the more complex and interfaces the
more challenging this becomes now the
same is true in visual interfaces too
which is why mobile first was such a
great boon for us because it told us we
needed to focus our pages on on single
tasks and helping users to accomplish
those things it reduced the noise and
raised the signal but most webpages I
think you'd probably agree are the
antithesis of clear and straightforward
as our screen sizes enlarge we just keep
shoving stuff into that space sharing
links related content cross promotions
and so on sometimes it's easy to lose
sight of what is actually the content of
the page to combat this screen readers
provide numerous mechanisms that enable
users to gather information about the
current interface and then move
efficiently through it to find the bit
that's most relevant to them in the
current moment so one mechanism
available for skimming a document
involves moving the focus caret from one
interactive element to another now
traditionally that movements done via
the keyboard via the tab key but it can
also be done via voice by saying next or
previous or similar commands now in most
documents this means moving from link to
link which are shown here in green and
supporting skimming in this way makes
the the text that we choose for links
even more critical in ensuring that our
users get a good experience for Mela
mints and buttons are also focusable and
I'll talk a little bit more about forms
towards the end of the session now you
can add elements that would not
traditionally be focusable into the tab
order by adding a tabindex attribute
with a value of zero that's very
important to only do zero or negative
one never go over zero but this ensures
that critical interface components are
not accidentally bypassed by users who
are using tabbing to move through an
interface and incidentally it also
enables sighted users to interact and
scroll elements via the keyboard so if
you have a scrollable div or something
like that somebody who's using a
keyboard can actually scroll that even
if they're sighted now another
navigational mechanism is browsing by
heading the various heading levels in
HTML create a natural document outline
and assistive technologies can enable
users to skim content using these
headings since only the contents of the
heading elements are read out loud in
this mode I highly recommend that you
avoid using cutesy marketing phrases and
stick to just summarizing what the
contents are of each section and then
the final way users can traverse
documents is via what are called
landmarks so the concept of landmarks
surfaced in the development of the Aria
spec and the idea is that you could use
the the role attribute to define
specific regions of the page based on
their function now in the example I have
up on the screen here the author is
isolating their navigation in a div
element with our ID of nav now that
might be meaningful to us as front end
designers and developers because we we
know that nav means navigation but it's
not exposed to assistive technology as
navigation when we explicitly add a roll
of navigation to that div however that
function gets made explicit to assistive
technology and there are a ton of roles
one out of time there's a there's a
handful of roles that are landmarks and
I'm going to show you a couple of these
in action if you have not checked it out
24 ways I think it's twenty four ways
org
twenty four ways to impress your friends
it's an advent calendar for web
professionals and it's a magazine but
it's highly interactive and it's very
accessible and they actually use
landmarks to identify all of the key
areas of a page such as the primary
header or the banner of a site the main
content of their site the content
concerned with easing navigation through
the site and information about the
content such as copyright designations
and here's how users in a non visual
context can actually experience that may
unlock 2015 heading level long
navigation I'm not browse 24 based
heading level 1 Sun factor 24 ways
content info not copyright 2005 2006 T
so landmarks also give users the
opportunity to jump directly to a
location with an interface which is
incredibly helpful in a voice context a
user might be able to ask the assistant
to read me the navigation for this pay
or search for way baby wooden baby toys
and the assistant could use these
landmarks to quickly respond to those
commands all without any additional
programming now it's worth noting that
many of these roles these landmark roles
have equivalent HTML tags and that's
because html5 and Aria were being
developed at the same time and sought to
to solve some of the same issues and
limitations of the web at the time so
banner is automatically assigned to the
first header element that you use that's
not contained inside of a sectioning
element navigation is automatically
assigned to nav main is automatically
assigned to main complementary is
assigned to aside elements and content
info is assigned to the first footer
that is not inside of a sectioning
element one last bit I want to touch on
before I discussed forums is the div
element we often see divs employed in
web pages when designers want to group
related elements together or they just
don't like the natives excuse me the
native styling of a particular control
like a button now organizing content
using divs is okay but divs are
meaningless elements and they add
nothing to the interface in terms of
context by contrast there are many
organizational elements that do add a
ton of context for our users things like
paragraphs things like lists description
lists which are vastly underused figures
Figg captions and then in terms of
grander stuff we've got articles
sections headers and footers which I've
mentioned nav and aside there are a ton
of meaningful elements out there that
can enable our assistants to do more for
our customers and the more we use them
the more useful our assistants become
and the more powerful our users feel for
instance using article and heading
elements can actually enable voice
commands like readme all the news
headlines on the front page of the New
York Times without involving any sort of
specialized data feed the generic div
gets you none of these benefits as you
see HTML has a lot to offer in terms of
enabling our interfaces to operate
effectively in the world of headless
UI's beyond just content
though it has the capacity to streamline
interactivity such as the kind we see in
forms now forms can be a bit of a
necessary evil we need them in order to
gather information in the service of our
users but often they're poorly planned
and even more poorly executed which
leads to poor user experience for all of
our users regardless of how they're
interacting with that form thankfully
HTML has our backs thereto enabling us
to make necessary Corrections or
necessary connections in order to
clarify the purpose of a forum and
expedite the completion process but
let's start with something simple field
labels so while it can be seemed
perfectly reasonable to mark up form
fields like this with text and then an
input below it there's no Association of
the question what's your first name with
the text field that follows to create
that Association you need to use a label
element that will ensure the label can
be read by assistive technology when the
field is focused and labels can be
associated in one of two ways either
explicitly or implicitly so explicit
relies on using the for attribute which
is an ID reference to the field that's
associated with it with it so you see
the foreign ID there in teal and they
need to match implicit Association
relies on the label element actually
containing both the label text and the
field itself you can combine these two
approaches but generally explicit
Association is the simplest and clearest
choice for most interfaces now once you
have a good label it's time to turn your
attention to the field itself and the
type of field that we're using there are
a bunch of options available in HTML now
and it's important to choose the right
one for each job so if you're just
looking for a simple response from a
user the text field or you could even
leave off the type if you want to
because text is the default input type
that's gonna be your go-to but if you're
asking for somebody's email address
there's a specific field type for that
it looks like a text field in terms of
its visual display but browsers that
understand type equals email can also
validate that field for you
automatically without involving any
JavaScript but if a browser doesn't
understand the age
Millfield type of email that's okay the
field will simply revert to being a text
field and you can and and should still
be validating to see if it's a valid
email address either on the client side
or the server side we'll discuss that
stephannie in a moment but this is a
perfect example of progressive
enhancement which is a topic that's
quite near and dear to my heart so much
so that I've I've written two books now
on progressive enhancement both called
adaptive web design the first edition is
actually free to read online it is
available as a progressive web app so
you can even install it to your home
screen if you want to read it over time
and then the second edition just came
out relatively recently but back to
inputs so we have the email we also have
the input type URL this is another
common one that we often have to do
especially in social contexts and as
with the email field type browsers can
handle validation for you on this
automatically which is pretty cool and
in both cases in both of those instances
visual browsers that have a virtual
keyboard can actually provide a
specialized keyboard that can enable
sighted users to more quickly enter that
information there are a ton of other
field types I could talk about but
there's again there's only so much time
here and there's a lot more I want to
cover so UX design is concerned with
reducing friction of accomplishing tasks
right so as such we should look for
every opportunity to do that in our
forms so consider this form construct
which is asking for a u.s. phone number
if this is a fairly common thing instead
of a single field enabling a user to
continuously type their phone number the
designers chose to break it apart into
three separate fields they probably did
this to ensure consistent number
formatting right to make sure that every
number came back in the same format but
really that's a back-end problem right
you want to sanitize that information
when you receive it from the customer
because going down this path the
designers have placed the burden on the
users rather than the developers and the
experience actually suffers for it sure
you can write some JavaScript that will
auto auto advance you from field to
field
but without JavaScript users have to do
it manually and even if there is
JavaScript available and they get that
enhancement it can limit the ability the
user's ability to edit one of these
fields if they make a mistake
furthermore when it comes to using this
interface via voice users are required
to supply three separate values not only
that each field then requires a label
most developers are only going to know
how to label one of those three the area
code and actual users would probably be
baffled if you ask them for their
central office code or line number for
all these reasons it just makes sense to
work with eight what HTML gives us
there's a field for telephone numbers
input type equals tell it doesn't
validate because there are too many
international phone number formats but
that's okay it's inconsequential for us
to actually write the code to sanitize
and homogenized structured information
like phone numbers and Social Security
numbers and the like and honestly we
should be writing that code anyway
because you can't trust the client even
if you enforce the structure and
inconsistent consistency with JavaScript
on the front end we can still end up
with bad data coming in to the back end
we'll come back to that idea in a moment
now forms can be incredibly frustrating
to fill out especially if they're
particularly long as designers were
tasked with reducing user frustration
and errors happen right it's a fact of
life but we can help our users avoid
errors by taking a few simple steps
first of all most browsers allow users
to store information to be auto filled
into forms some watch for common data to
be filled in and then prompt the user to
save it to be auto filled later some
even goes so far as to take the values
you enter along with the corresponding
name or ID attributes that are on that
field and they'll prompt you to fill in
that same information later on when they
encounter that same name or ID for this
reason it makes sense to turn
autocomplete off for any fields that
deal with sensitive information like
passport numbers credit cards and the
like it used to be that all we had was
on and off though and we've actually
been granted a bunch of new values that
allow us to get very granular about the
sort of information we're expecting to
be auto-completed into these fields and
there are a ton of tokens for doing this
I'm not going to get into all of these
but I will walk you through an example
here I've got a question is there a
mobile
we can reach you on regarding delivery
so in this case we're doing an
autocomplete of shipping mobile tell so
we've got three modifiers they were
asking for a telephone number that's
associated with shipping right a mobile
telephone number thus associated with
shipping so we've actually got some
direct connections between the label and
the autocomplete tokens we're using as
I'm sure you can imagine the sort of
affordance can do a ton to reduce the
friction of filling in forms and if
you're keen to learn more about these
autofill tokens Jason Grigsby who works
at cloud four down in Portland he wrote
a very lengthy piece about these on the
cloud floor blog so I highly recommend
checking that out so we can help users
fill out form fields more quickly but
what about everything else well first of
all we should always let users know when
a field is required a common approach is
to provide a visual indicator if not all
of the fields on the form are required
and obviously it would be best to avoid
the situation altogether and only have
required fields in the form then you
could simply introduce it saying all
fields are required regardless of the
way you go however the required
attribute should be used in order to
ensure modern browsers can't allow a
user to submit a form when the field is
empty and then you use the Aria required
attribute to actually inform assistive
technology that the field is required
unfortunately browsers don't map them
automatically you should also provide
helpful hints to users in order to help
them avoid issues before they encounter
them so here we're asking for a complex
pattern for a delta flight number with
DL followed by two or more numbers and
so I am giving a placeholder to indicate
the sort of content that I want and then
I have the pattern attribute which is
actually creating the regular expression
to validate against for the browser
round trips to the server expensive so
especially on flaky networks so we want
to help our users avoid these things by
doing validation in the browser as much
as we can and we can rely on these tools
in order to do that so it starts with
the required attribute so that we don't
have empty fields being submitted if we
need them and then it comes to choosing
the right field type as I mentioned so
that we get native valid
if we can and then we can fall back to
the pattern attribute if there's not an
native validation scheme and then
browsers that actually implement the
html5 validation algorithm will notify
users in line of fields that have errors
and so often they will highlight the
first error and then have the user work
on fixing that before it can be
submitted there is also the html5
validation algorithm on the JavaScript
end and you can take this stuff over on
your own and and manage that experience
for your users all by paying attention
to those attributes that have been
assigned even if the browser doesn't
understand html5 validation you can roll
your own JavaScript library to do it in
I don't know I did it in like a hundred
lines of code very very spaced out and
commented it's really simple and then
once you've got inline errors when
you're wanting to highlight those
yourself you want to mark them invalid
using the Aria invalid attributes so
assistive technology knows there's an
issue here and then the error message
can be associated using Aria described
by which is an ID reference much like
the four attribute and so you can see
that here in orange your email star
edits required invalid entry your email
address is required blank so that's
pretty helpful right eventually I
already described by will be replaced by
Aria error message in this context but
the supports not there yet so that's
something down the road now client-side
validation is great but there's no
substitute for doing some form of
server-side validation and there's a
good reason I'm going to tell you a
quick story because I know we're at time
here but back in 2001 when the original
Xbox was the game system to drool over
we as an industry put a lot of faith in
the browser and didn't realize how our
sites could be manipulated or hacked and
I remember an instance where a major
vulnerability was discovered in an
e-commerce site and involved this gaming
system and the infinite wisdom the
developer had actually put the price of
the Xbox in a hidden input and since it
was hidden no one could see it an
enterprising web designer could view
source and see it but these were the
days before browsers actually had tools
for web developers to manipulate
documents in in real time but they did
have this thing called
save so you could save a web page for
offline viewing
so one enterprising person did that very
thing edited the file and change that
value to a dollar and then they loaded
the HTML document in their browser
submitted the form and they got their
xbox about two weeks later for a buck
the developer didn't have any checks in
place to make sure that products
couldn't be sold for less than the e
value that they listed as the price they
didn't realize you can't trust the
client you should always validate on the
server side because even if a user has
JavaScript turned on has a browser
capable of doing html5 validation you
can't assume that the validation
criteria was actually met it's totally
inconsequential to change a web pages
markup to adjust scripts to adjust forms
or otherwise compromise a web page using
only only the tools that are built into
virtually every browser out there how
many of you have changed a form in order
to actually be able to submit it yeah
this happens all the time right we need
to actually never trust the client we
need to always make sure we're getting
what we're expecting and since the
server side is your last line of defense
we need to be ready to to go back to
that form again and provide information
about what the errors are that we
encountered so we want to server
summarize those server-side errors in
some sort of message at the top put it
at the top of the form start with a
helpful introduction there were some
errors with your form submission list
the errors and the orders they're that
they're presented in the form and link
to each of those fields that have an
error the nice thing is we've got anchor
references directly to those fields
because they all have IDs on them right
so that makes it really simple to do so
and if you add a roll of alert in some
browsers although the this is kind of
abdomen and changed over the time but
some of them do something cool like this
when the page loads contact retreats for
geeks there were errors with your form
submission one message is a required
field two name is a required field three
email is a required field how friggin
awesome is that that's so helpful when
you can't visually see the form right
then use the pattern I showed earlier to
make sure that you indicate in line with
the actual problem with is and help
people to solve that and of course make
sure that you bring back the value that
they entered in case they just have to
make a slight change to it
so hTML is a truly robust and expressive
language but it's often overlooked and
undervalued but it has the incredible
potential to nurture conversations with
our users without requiring a whole lot
of effort on our part simply taking the
time to code web page as well will
enable our sites to do more thereby
enabling our users to do more hopefully
this rather brief overview has opened up
your eyes to the wonderful world of HTML
and how semantic markup can make our
content structured sensible and most
importantly meaningful and if you are
already a true believer I hope you walk
away from this session with a few new
techniques that you can put to use in
your own work thank you all very much