hi guys how are you can you hear me well
awesome okay so my name is Shannon
Foster I'm from Baltimore Maryland I'm a
techie and I got invited to do Cascadia
only a few weeks ago so I'm really
excited to kind of be like the
last-minute speaker but also kind of
show you guys some of the things that I
hope that you can learn from this talk
as far as web PR goes from a show of
hands has anyone doesn't work with web
PR before I see like five people
okay that's still cool has anyone used
VR in general before headset oculus rift
daydream cardboard okay alright so it's
a good group of people and a good
dynamic I would say so with this talk as
I mentioned before kind of want to give
you guys a deep dive kind of a little
bit of an overview of what is happening
and what can be done what whether you
are a little bit beyond the scope of
gaming but more so per se you know
shopping or maybe even banking in VR or
AR and so upon creation of this talk I
realized that there was an error in my
talk title so instead of it being down
the rabbit hole with VR it should say
something else but I'll dive into that a
little bit later as we go through this
talk here yeah sorry give me one moment
here okay yeah so web VR sparked my
interest at go IO 2017 it was this new
thing that browsers are trying to adopt
and get started with not too many people
still know the difference between
regular VR and web VR and who can blame
them it's you know kind of the not
really the same title but when you hear
web PR you're just kind of like okay
what big differences can this be exactly
you know what exactly can I do with this
that I can't do already primarily with
the hardware device and so I'm hoping I
can show you that difference here so
let's take a look at a few examples
see if I can get this to play okay cool
so see it's playing oh there we go so
this is if you guys have heard of the
awards this is one of the nominees for
the best web be our example sites
I'm created by this guy called a cubic
photo cubed a German developer and a
group of designers this really stood out
to me one because it's not just a game
but the interactivity along with this
just looks really cool and if you look
here yeah and when you look away when
the user looks away or pulls away from
the view and the scene it has some sort
of timer or math going on here where it
knows like okay users looking away head
his turn turn back game interacts or
this component interacts so that's just
something that stood out and this was
tagged with three Jas WebGL Babylon and
a few other things and I just thought
I'd show you guys so another example
this is also another awards one that we
have going on here and this one was more
so if you've ever been to they have
these new things called AR art art
exhibits we have this thing
ar Tech or something in DC where it's a
nightclub and you can you know have a
little martinis and use your phone to
see like the AR pop up on the martini
and so this is a photo gallery and it's
in virtual reality and this is me
scrolling through it through the browser
of course and this person created it as
a portfolio and I just thought it was a
good way to kind of show you guys like
how we're stepping through into the
mercy of Technology on the browser and
you know just what we can do with it and
the cool thing about this is the user as
you can see I'm obviously not using a
headset I'm using my laptop to access
this the cool thing about web PR is all
you need is a URL to get access to this
game or portfolio or design or anything
like that you don't need
fairly a overpriced or over expensive
oculus rift or HTC vive just to
experience this anyone can do it which
is why I love the inclusivity of web
they are another one just a showroom
example if you've ever used like an IKEA
app or oh gosh there's another one
that's also a furniture store app where
you can place place things in the room
and furniture or even Amazon now when
you shop on there you can use it with
reality to kind of see what things look
like in your actual space and so for
instance this is just another example
that just shows like this is a showroom
that you can see online of course just
type in the URL and just kind of tour
the area and something that really stood
out to me is you can click on each of
these 3d objects that are placed here
and the user can decide which types of
textures that they want to add to the
object which I thought was pretty neat
using these different spheres so if you
want to test it out there is a link
right there on the bottom and just one
more this one I grabbed off of Google
experiences they demoed this last year
at Google i/o 2017 and again it's just
like the whole introduction to just
using web BR and this one this one's
actually really funny because it just
kind of dives into why there was an
error in the way that I named my talk
and why there's any need for me to
rename it so
get excited ready to start and play this
game and then suddenly it tells me like
hey by the way like we're no longer
using what BR we're moving over to web X
R and so that's where the area's error
is in my talk I miss name this talk
completely so I decided I'm gonna change
it to down the rabbit hole with Webre R
or V R on the web sorry
and so turns out the web BR version 1.1
is deprecated there's only a few
browsers that still use it and you can
probably guess which ones are the late
bloomers that probably still use it
maybe per se but you can if necessary
absolutely necessary you can go back
through the API list or documentation
and see you know okay I want to use the
specific version of this and try it out
great it hasn't gone obviously very far
it's still something if you want worth
looking at but it's been replaced by the
webex our device API which I'll dive a
little bit into a little bit later and
as I mentioned before currently
available on some browsers web PR of
course is an experiment and of and of
itself as we have so many different
groups trying to work and develop their
own standards of it and just see how far
can we go with this technology and so
there are multiple iterations that it's
going through we also have open XR which
is not really competing but they're also
trying to develop this new standard of
again web VR on the web and so they're
the open source community and major web
browsers are allowing all different
types of work for the web we are in a
full web standard as I said before oops
too far
and if this gives me back my mouse
that'd be great okay so anyways so when
you try to open up a web browser
web VR applications that are using this
API that has been deprecated the user
will usually get this error at the very
top of their screen so they can't really
do much I know disappointment so it's
currently this is what they'll get with
Chrome the developer model as well as a
coronary and as well as the Samsung
Internet and a few others I know with
Safari any Apple device mostly because
I'm positive they don't support most of
the web VR features they're mostly with
what is it AR core I think is the way
that they're going and so that's why you
probably won't see a lot of support or
and or don't get this error message and
as far as those that still support it
they'll also be able one to use the
application and they'll also get this at
the very top of it and the VR displays
not found it's just a function that we
can go ahead and input into our system
that displays a little icon that says
okay here you go you can use the VR
functionality for your device or the
supported device and of course we're
Internet Explorer when trying to use
what VR they're gonna get either a blank
white screen or a blank black screen so
I don't know why they're always so
behind but be cool if one day it can
catch up all right so that brings a new
talk title I guess down the rabbit hole
with WebEx are and let's just dive more
into exactly what is WebEx are so WebEx
are can be called by many different
names from extended reality to cross
reality but according to those who are
the main contributors to the device API
for WebEx are they want X to mean
something else
ideally it's whatever whatever you guys
want it to be think of it as a variable
of sorts
whatever you create this can be the
definition of that so it's open source
API of course as I mentioned before it's
currently in an experiment as I
mentioned earlier we're testing out the
limitations on what we can do with what
we are how far can we actually go with
this technology and what can be done
what are the different use cases I
mentioned earlier that a few of us are
trying banking and augmented reality
where we have your card and you just
hover your phone over it your camera
just pops out with a graph interactive
graph of you know this is your spending
habits this is how much you spent this
money your limits this is what you went
over this is your goal things like that
just to teach people better spending
habits as well as shopping in augmented
reality we're also trying to disrupt the
fashion industry last year also at
Google i/o they introduced this new gap
augmented reality application where you
can see the textile and the 3d object of
the model or whoever wearing this
clothing pattern and you can interact
with it change the different sizes of it
and you can do it in browser as well to
make it much more accessible to all
users versus those who just have to have
a specific type of phone I can remember
the phone that they tried to pass with
the last year just to get that
application going it was a Verizon thing
I don't know but uh yeah and it also
simplifies creating on VR and x vr XR AR
applications on the web for any
supported hardware device so whether
it's a Google daydream cardboard vibe
rift this simplifies that by allowing
developers to have easier access versus
using or manually inputting OpenGL or
yeah OpenGL WebGL or whichever to get
this going so this just makes life
easier for all of us
of course it's not open X are so open X
are is you can I guess you can consider
it a competitor and a competitor in a
way except none of these companies are
well groups are they're open sourced and
they're not making it to it some money
so open XR is another API that's created
by the Khronos group which was
previously called the Kronos VR
initiative and that's basically a group
of engineers from Google Pluto I think
also oculus that are pretty much the
same people who also work on the WebEx
our platform and they're all just again
we're all just trying to work together
and develop these new standards for this
technology and to see how far we can go
so this is an example of one of the
first applications or mobile
applications that's using WebEx our if I
can get back to play and so yeah there
was one of the first organizations that
are actually getting this going and
they're actually using the WebEx R as a
platform to help developers I believe
like you to build augmented reality apps
and XR if it's big enough
I'd have to I'm scared I might break
something and so they're just tracing 3d
objects with an interactive menu and
it's all again using that WebEx our
device API
okay so one of the things with though
again the WebEx our API is you can
detect query whole display and what this
means is that it enables XR applications
on the web by lying pages to do the
following again detect query poll
display
detective capabilities are available
query the XR capabilities poll the XR
display and associated input device date
on display imagery and on the XR device
at the appropriate framerate and some of
the goals I guess these are primarily
the goals of what they're hoping to do
with this API and I know that some of
the non goals they've made that very
clear is defined how virtual reality is
to not define how virtual reality on
what reality works on the browser and to
expose every feature every feature or
every piece of VR and AR hardware to not
sorry and to not build the Metaverse I
would hope they're not exposing anything
on the hardware and so this is just
another example of another experiment
using a XR device API
um this is primarily for iOS but I
clearly have an Android so it works on
here so let's see if I can play this
example and so this is just again it's
just showing what you can do with this
API and I can show you guys a link in a
second on how to get access to this and
it's just an experiment of just like
trying it out and just see okay cool
we're just building doing this building
block game what else can we do with this
oh yeah this is the one this is sorry I
work at a cybersecurity firm so it's
this is the one that's like hey you can
access the site but anything if I go
back to the slide here
okay all right so again one of the
things I mentioned earlier is what's the
difference between what VR and VR one of
the main difference is virtual reality
is something that we can well use to be
able to just maintain or keep within
hardware devices so only those who had
access to VR or even sometimes AR it's
just if they had these very expensive
hardware devices so one of the benefits
and beauties of web VR is that we can
make it accessible and inclusive for a
lot of different people to use it and
it's a good way to think about it
another way to think about it is that we
can scale our applications you know from
being these basic ecommerce site to
something where the user can actually
look at the item this 3d model spin it
around and even walk around it and just
see like okay is this something that
actually went in my home is this
something that actually wouldn't wear
you know the browser in my opinion it's
getting a little websites are getting a
little boring nowadays and I feel like
there are just so many different
interfaces that we can add more
interactivity that we can have that
keeps a user engaged and coming back to
our sites for more one of the companies
I used to work for Under Armour we
didn't enable 360 view of our sneakers I
think until 2016 I believe and even then
it's still not enough for the youth for
our customers they call us and they ask
us hey like what what what's the exact
color of this because sometimes the you
know colors are off or what's the exact
material this or you know what does this
feel and look like and in some cases
unfortunately for us we can't really
explain it though you know we work there
we still don't technically violate them
even if you work in underwear you don't
really buy the shoes to be honest with
you so it was just really hard to you
know it's just really hard to explain
you know what this material would look
like for the customer and so imagine
this if we have this VR application or
even an AR again they can look at it and
technically not feel it or smell it
that'd be kind of weird but still they
can just see like okay this is what this
product looked like looks like
okay yes this product can definitely be
for me just the way to consider it and
there are companies that are doing that
I can link you a few later on and so
just to dive into again with Web VR we
have usually if you're on YouTube on
your mobile device you'll see this
little icon in the corner that says okay
do you want to watch this video in
virtual reality and then you'll get
these two little lens that will not lens
will screen that pop up that are split
but they're showing the same exact
content for when you put the ear headset
on and then of course what VR it's the
same thing except I mean you can use the
st. the same exact devices for viewing
web PR and so the idea of the future of
web VR is that we can browse the web or
browse the anything really using these
same exact devices but the best way in
my opinion to do this is to just either
have the option to yes you can use the
hardware device or no you can just use
your phone or the browser to get this
done and just to dive a little bit into
WebGL because I figured okay hey yeah
sure let's go ahead and touch base on
this just a little bit so WebGL is
basically what I described is just
simply oh dear god that's cutting up
it's just the canvas canvas we're just
building 2d and 3d graphics the great
thing about today's available libraries
of just frameworks is that you don't
necessarily have to do this you don't
have to manually go in and type all of
this obnoxiousness and in your HTML
because there's something that's already
there that does this for you I'm just
gonna I mean if you guys want to see it
I can show you this later but there's
oh wait to far okay okay yeah so I guess
that cut down to the last one weird but
anyways if you have questions feel free
to reach out to me on Twitter my name is
Shannon Foster I'm a junior software
engineer and also a full-time student
web VR is something I've been doing for
the last year and a half or technically
after the launch of I would say Pokemon
go is when I got into augmented reality
I was like yeah I gotta try this out
but anyway it's feel free to reach out