so I'm going to talk to you guys about
circuits that's the title my talk what
our circuits circuits are like streams
and streams are like circuits and they
all I mean they both represent the
notion of something that receives a
value and can emit a value so this
yellow box here is the construct the red
arrow is whatever input can it can
receive the blue arrows whatever output
it emits um so if you're lying down at
the moment this talk may put you to
sleep so if you could sit up if you want
to listen otherwise just go to sleep you
know it's cool i know its second day I
was out last night too so and plus you
know as you're sleeping the mind is
vulnerable and I can just say anything I
want uh so how I started down this track
of exploring circuits was through
asynchronous function so I do a lot of
JavaScript programming where I have to
wait on something to to to basically
happen before I can act on it so how
this is represented a note is through a
call back where you have the first first
parameter being an error in the second
the result right so everyone knows you
have a function foo it does something
calls back and then it you do stuff with
whatever the result is is that that
clear some guy's face is like he doesn't
understand this but if you don't
understand this this is going to be
tough because it's like the very basic
thing if you want to use foo with
another asynchronous function bar you
know you got a nest them right so use
foo calls back into bar and then you
pass it another callback and then you
finally do stuff with both the results
this is this is I mean it's quite simple
however I wasn't I wasn't really happy
with this because if you have to keep
composing asynchronous functions
together with other asynchronous
functions with others asynchronous
function
then what happens after a while as you
get callback hell and everyone's
familiar with that right it's what when
your code is moving off the side of your
screen it's also really hard to sort of
follow so call back he'll I talked about
call back hell in El xjs and and some
people said basically that they had
never experienced it so I was really
surprised because this is sort of one of
the patterns that you first encounter
when you start with JavaScript so I I
looked into it I was like well maybe
this might be something a phenomenon
that only I am experiencing so i looked
at the top 10 node categories and you
know the control flow async goodies
that's you know that's a sizable chunk
it's you know a third of the size of
third of the size of web frameworks
which is like the top module category so
control flow goodies what are they
exactly i was looking at npm and the
third most dependent upon module is a
sink so if you're not familiar with
async async is a utility module which
provides straightforward powerful
functions for working with a signatures
javascript so I just got that from the
readme right so other people are
experiencing callback hell as well
that's why there are so many modules
around that try to tackle asynchronous
control flow so I think I think um hell
is real callback hell is real so I mean
if you're experiencing this then this
talk will be interesting for you because
you'll have like a lot of I'm going to
try to give you like some other ideas
about control flow so one of them is
streams and I think James talks a lot
about streams but I want to give you
some other ones too taken from you know
category theory and functional reactive
programming and all that good stuff so
right so I want to start with
drag-and-drop so this is how to create a
drag-and-drop behavior just using normal
JavaScript with
bit of jQuery in there because it it's
it's a it's a good piece of sugar so
basically you have a function move it
takes a Down event and a mouse move
event and then it updates your the Dom
element style that should be pretty
straightforward so now in the
drag-and-drop function it takes a Dom
element it listens it waits for a mouse
down and then it um waits for a mouse
move calls move each time mousemove is
emitted and on mouse up it kills all the
other callbacks right so we can we can
actually test this out um so right here
I pretty much it can use is a screen
shared so can you oh I don't know how
much bigger this can go but I mean it's
exactly the same code right so if i run
that you can see you know i can drag
this thing so it's you just have to
trust me i can i can even taste it for
you but you know what I'm not going to
do that you're just gonna have to trust
me so that is exactly the same code
that's in the jsfiddle and um it it's
pretty succinct uh if you've ever tried
to program like if code drag and drop
behavior before I mean I don't know if
you can get it down smaller than that
maybe maybe we can like take off this
mouse down event actually but so if we
think of it as a faz a state machine
this is how it might look we have like
two states one is idle and the other is
dragging and you move between the states
via mouse down or Mouse up so how might
this look with async since you know
that's the module that everyone uses for
asynchronous control flow so you
represent the first state q0 with by
just waiting for a mouse down event and
then when that gets called it
moves to the second state Q 1 which
waits for a must move event so this
should be pretty straightforward so
what's happened here is like instead of
having everything together like in the
same drag and drop in the same drag and
drop body function function body I've
basically just separated it out into two
states one is one is idle and one is
dragging so this is how it would look
when composed together so the big thing
about this is what you're doing is
you're you're you don't have that
nesting that happens with with the
normal call back in like nesting
callbacks but what you do lose is maybe
like how if we didn't have a sink we
might have to compose them in a
different way that hides the execution
flow of each of the callback handlers
but async sort of allows us to grab them
together and sort of describe them in
one place drag and drop is a waterfall
of q0 and q1 mouse down and drag
everyone's like going but you get it
it's so awesome right okay so if we look
at both of the code site like both of
these pieces of code side by side you
can see that the vanilla JavaScript is
pretty I mean it's pretty readable async
sort of clutters it up a bit um but we
are allowed to separate the state's q0
and q1 which sort of it lets us do other
things with them for example if we
wanted to reuse q0 for something else
like a mouse down something else is
waiting for mass now we can we can use
that so it's modular however it does
sort of like make the code a little bit
it's it's sort of fatter right now the
async code so Michael said javascript is
done like in LX yes I mean paraphrase I
wasn't actually there but Brian McKenna
tweeted something like this language is
done
the script is it and you know what maybe
that's true because I mean there are I
mean if we just wanted to do drag and
drop why would we why would we have this
a sink module that that clutters up our
code allows us to separate the states it
makes it more modular but what if we
don't ever want to use Q 0 or q1 just
independently it sort of doesn't need to
be done so I do it right so this is sort
of like the important point of this talk
so michael says you know there's a point
where something is good enough and we
move on to more important higher-order
things and I think that's really
important here like some people use
JavaScript for a set of problems and
javascript is totally good enough for
that why why change anything it's it
solved my problem right but then there's
a lot of other people I guess who for
them javascript isn't good enough
there's always like there's something
that they do every day that JavaScript
just sort of falls short of a little bit
so this talk is for for those people um
basically this is an advanced topic and
I'm not going to tell you whether to use
one method or another that's something
that you have to judge for yourself you
know I'm just going to give you some
tools and then you can decide if that
tool is good for what you're doing sound
good all right so everyone's familiar
with streams I'm just or at least I
think so after James's talk pretty much
I've heard streams until like it's
coming out of my ears like I was a tell
xjs and I saw so many stream demos but
I'm going to give you a stream demo just
to like really nail that right in so if
we turn this drag-and-drop problem the
state machine into a stream how might
that look so I've got this piece of code
there um we have a readable stream that
basically emits uh we've encapsulated
the whole mousedown mousemove state
machine and it only emits what does it
emit it only emits mousemove events and
in fact it admits it in pairs of a Down
event
event because we need the down event to
sort of offset where we're going to
change the the you know the coordinates
of that element so it's a little
cluttered but you can sort of see that
it's very similar to the vanilla
JavaScript it just sort of like hide zet
and it only emits it in the stream now
you can see that this RS emit part right
here I can't highlight it but you know
you can see the can I use this thing
nope I don't know what this laser
pointer is here for it's not really in
venues but if so I use this thing called
bind I don't know if everyone uses bind
but it's basically a partial application
of some parameters so it's really just
the same as having mousemove receive a
call back that calls RSM it with data a
zero which is from the mouse down event
and then gets past the mouse move event
which would be e1 and then we end up
sending a zero and a one into the move
function which earlier we defined as it
just moves the thing you know it updates
the XY coordinates so this is how drag
and drop would look as a stream so
remember we looked at it as just jQuery
code just JavaScript and then we looked
at it as an async waterfall and it
looked a little different we got some
different semantics out of it we got to
separate the states into q0 and q1 and
now we're looking at we're looking at it
as a stream and I don't really know how
to assess this it's just kind of cool
it's a stream we can even stream fi the
move function and pipe mouse mouse
events into the move function so that
every time it admits something you know
it just moves so that's kind of neat you
know like thinking of some sort of
emitter of events getting piped into
just a normal function um except I can't
really do that streams
so the thing with streams it's a little
weird you can call our RS emit data and
you can pass it any number of arguments
but somewhere in the stream code and I
mean I could show you this just you know
what it's not it's not important but
somewhere in the stream code it only
passes like one argument I hope someone
fixes that so right now have to like
wrap it just in like a parrot uppal and
and then i can i still have to change
the move function here so what's what
would be handy if i didn't have to
change a move function is that i could
just you know use the same function with
any kind of control flow construct
whether it was a waterfall whether it
was jquery whether it was a stream i
could just use move with d like down
event and mouse move event but you know
until that changes um so what we have
here is we can see the stream as a pipe
between two processes one is a something
that emits and the other is something
that receives and I drew boxes around
them because so basically the the state
machine here it's separated right and
what streams allows us to do is it
allows us to use anything that is
readable and smoosh it together with
anything that is writable and we don't
need to think about what's actually
friggin inside the boxes and that's
something that's really cool you know
because it's very so I I don't remember
who talked it was but someone was
talking about how when you have a really
heavy framework like a plug-in system
everything has to follow this same
everything has to like identify like
identify itself as a plug-in and
sometimes it can the interface can be
really heavy weight but streams
interface is really quite simple so a
lot of things can be streams and as you
can see like to make something into a
stream it's not a it's not it's not
super heavyweight you know you just
create a just instantiate a stream
declare it like it set it to be writable
readable and then just start emitting
things
so the interface is really simple
streams what do we get for free we
really get this pipe for free so if we
if we stream if I whatever components
we're using an hour control flow we get
the pipe for free and this is really
important because pipes are kind of
their kind of like a composition a
operator right so it allows you to
compose two streams together into one
and and the result of that is itself a
stream and then you can use that in
other streams and so the whole lure of
streams and pipes and compositions is
that you get like this really you get to
I switch the slide too early this has
nothing to do either one talking about
right now but but hey it's a burrito so
what you get is like what I like to
think of a piece of code is as is
basically a composition of just
different bits smooshed together right
so everything can exist independently
like a function or an object or whatever
and depending on how it's composed
together is what makes a program
different so pipe is a sequential it
basically sequences things you you have
the first thing sequenced with the
second thing a pipes to be that means
something has to go through a to get to
be um and that's just a really simple
Combinator the pipe is a sequencing
Combinator there are so many other ones
out there and this is what I'm going to
try to tell you guys today so let's say
you have this thing called em right and
it has just two things right so a stream
it has a what's a stream it just it's it
emits something or you have a right
function so that it can receive
something right so that that's the
interface of a stream so the interface
of this particular construct that I'm
showing you now M
a you have to you have two functions so
you have it then which is also a
sequencing Combinator and then you have
a unit so what then does it's something
very similar to what the pipe does it
takes one kind of this ma takes another
mb is just smushes them together this
unit function takes some raw value and
then it puts it into the context of em
so if you think of this as a stream
actually is that no let's start with a
list because everyone's familiar with
lists right so a list is of a type ma
the then function you can basically it
takes it takes a function and then it it
basically like runs this function on
each of its you know what I'm have you
ever like written some code and come
back to it and not understood what the
it man this is what I'm
experiencing now but it totally works I
promise you just get so let's look at
unit because unit is pretty it's pretty
simple it's much more simple than the
then Combinator for list but basically
you pass it in X so it could be a number
it could be like one it could be a could
be a string and then it just puts it
inside of a list the context em right so
remember unit takes a raw value and it
puts it inside of a context and that's
exactly what this is for the list the
then function I think what it does is it
takes many lists and like if you take
two lists and then you put them together
basically like concatenates the whole
thing plus there's a mapping function so
that's what it's doing there the idea of
a continuation so this is like an
asynchronous function so this can
capture a a synchronous functions it
takes to asynchronous functions and then
it commits sequences them so it calls
the first one first foo and then bar if
we pass in foo and bar into here it
would give us another
asynchronous function that would be
called back after bar was completed and
the unit definition here is to take some
X and then put it inside of a call back
so that when you call that thing when
you call this function and pass it a
call back it just gives ex back to you
so that's the context here um now
streams we're familiar with streams how
may streams look as a type ma what we
have is we create a stream that
basically emits data when this is
actually its again this is confounding
me but it basically emits data based on
what's happening in the two streams that
it's supposed to compose together the
unit basically is a singleton and it
just emits like One X so you can see the
stream really as maybe kind of a list
right so it's a container for values and
that's exactly what this ma thing is
it's it can be it can capture containers
like lists or streams but it can also
capture computations like a synchronous
functions so what do we get with this
right so if we have an object and we
implement then and unit what do we get
for free well for instance we can get
this function chaining thing that I
wrote that sort of totally ripped off
fab guess but whatever it's really cool
it's sort of a way to look at let's say
if this was an asynchronous let's say
wasn't stream it was like I showed this
like demo and alexius and it had a can't
operate an asynchronous function thing
to it so it but it's exactly the same
API so we have a stream that when that
we we we emit rabbit basically we emit
rabbit we store it in X and then we call
generation on it you know this you're
just gonna have to trust me that it does
what I'm saying it does and when when we
run this app it basically like oh I
didn't
I didn't define generation hear about
generations basically a replicate
function with a partially up applied
three to it so it just returns three
rabbits and you know you can keep on
doing this and the ill returns you know
six rabbits or nine rabbits or whatever
so but what I wanted to show you here is
you get this function chaining API for
free that you can use with a stream with
a cons Oh with a list and you it doesn't
matter like which kind of thing it is
because it's just a general ma construct
that this function chaining can work
with all of them so that might not be
the biggest selling point but I'm just
telling you right that again this is one
way to compose asynchronous functions
and other kinds of control flow and you
decide whether it's the right tool for
you so if we go back to comparing the
vanilla and the async style of code how
might this look as a continuation with
function chaining so what we can do is
again we have the move function which is
just like a normal function it takes a
Down event in a mouse event and then it
updates the Dom element and we have two
states mouse down and drag so what we
see down here in the drag and drop the
execution flow is that we you know it
looks pretty sequential like the first
thing that gets called as a mouse down
and then after that gets called it's
just drag and then you can like you can
actually keep looping that I don't know
if I have that Combinator here but
basically there's this thing that yeah
this is function that I had forever that
takes any kind of ma construct and then
it can join it to the top of it again so
it's sort of like if you wanted to run
something forever it could take the end
what the last operation and then after
the last operation it goes back to the
top operation against so it's kind of
like a looping construct for any sort of
MA so I did want to talk about another
kind
kind of construct it's called ABC really
actually it's not called ABC it's called
an arrow but it has three parts to it
one is the context the other is some
sort of notion of input and see is some
notion of output so what kinds of things
follow this pattern a function follows
this pattern of function receives some
kind of input it gets supplied to it and
then it returns some sort of value see
streams do this to you I mean
bi-directional streams do you can write
something to a stream and then it that
same stream can emit can emit a value so
in JavaScript I mean we don't really
care about types so much though it's
becoming more and more something we care
about it's a it's actually something
that can receive anything and I can
admit anything streams as one of these
ABC constructs as an arrow basically you
need to define two things actually it's
three things yeah three things r dot and
first so you can see visually what
happens here the our function takes
takes a it takes any function right and
then it creates a conveyor belt out of
it so those squares next to the f think
of it as like a belt moving from left to
right so as each item comes through on
the left it calls that function and then
the value that's submitted this gets you
know pushed down the belt you can
connect two of these arrows together
with this comp combining operation dot
and what you can do is if you you can
this also this notion of like a pairs so
lets you get you get basically a
conveyor belt that works on pairs so
first basically works on the first item
of a double and doesn't do anything that
is the second item so this is pretty
abstract so what can you actually do
with this right
I don't know if you want to go through
the you could probably look at that
later but it's it's pretty interesting
what can you do with that well you can
there's something called functional
reactive programming that's sort of like
there's a lot of interest for it in the
high school community because functional
reactive programming with this sort of
arrow Combinator thing is a pretty is a
pretty like intuitive way of thinking
about streams of data and events and
things like that and i want to show you
how i want to show you how it works but
uh I actually didn't get to finishing
the demo but I'll show you I'll show you
what I got with just plain JavaScript um
like in oh we're not gonna see this what
control shift up what does that do oh no
way okay um I did it but control shift
you know what it's not going to work but
it was like a pretty sweet sort of
broken game of pong why isn't it working
that's weird uh well just come over and
I'll show it to you guys like if you
want to see it but basically we have
actually let's just look at the code so
this isn't happening this fiddles dead
ok back to this so basically what these
arrow Combinator's allow you to do is
express something kind of like a graph
which is sort of what like the big win
is except I couldn't show you concretely
but you'll have to use your imagination
which shouldn't be that hard I hope we
just started from the start again but
her ok wow that was lucky um
so if you think of like the first the
first thing that triggers all these
things it's like a game tick so for this
piece of code was requestanimationframe
so the tick basically emits it emits a
value to key and ball position right and
these things emit their own values
because their streams play pause and
ball pause they get paired into into
like one of those like conveyor belt
things like like in first um and then
they get sent into this render function
which basically is just a normal
function that will draw the rectangles
on the screen so i did want to show you
how that would look in code actually no
I do have a thing right here so one way
to do it is with the fan-out Combinator
so remember when we so I said our
connect and first if you implement those
things you get other things for free
just like in streams if you create a
stream what do you get for free you get
the pipe Combinator if you instantiate
something as a as an arrow you get a
whole different bunch of Combinator's
like fan out fannin and we can even do
something crazy like that fab GS
function chaining and express the
execution flow of the game like that
except I whoever wants to see it in
action just come over after but
basically this is what I want what I
want you guys to take away from this is
that streams yes they're a great
abstraction but don't just stop there
like streams give you pipes pipes are
great keep on going like look for other
abstractions there's I mean so it's it's
sort of like a thinly veiled thing here
but like what I'm the MA construct is is
from category theory it's a monad and
and the ABC contract is an arrow and
they adequately these things captures
certain control flow things that
JavaScript programmers face all the time
it's just they haven't I don't know
people just sort of skater of mana ads
or something like that but don't be you
saw exactly how much lines of code it
took to instantiate something as a monad
it wasn't a whole lot um so basically
yes abstraction is a great go and like
don't don't stop discovering other
abstractions that may be great tools for
what you're doing keep on like learning
and streams are great but just you know
look forward from there did I just all
right and these are the on you know I'm
going to publish these slides but all
the J's fiddles are on these links and
and here's the attributions but I hope
you took something away from this my
name is Newman Vong and I'll I'll say
for questions thank you thank you
any questions this one guy at the front
I'm so much the guys at the front how
would you compare this kind of like
using this any of these approaches for a
sink programming to like using something
like deferred zand promises so different
so I think I think they're you know
they're for each use case differs there
could be use cases where different
promises may work really well you just
have to go an experiment with them like
the jQuery uses deferred internally and
I think it works really well for I don't
know I guess it works kind of well I has
anyone used the first I haven't
personally used efforts but I mean
there's a this this is the overhead of
the abstraction right um I guess it does
make things more modular anytime you
separate out the states and not have
these nested callbacks you make your
solution more modular and you can change
it and reuse certain things that you
wouldn't otherwise be able to do so I
think streams I think streams are good i
think deferred zar good don't stop there
like again like their other there are
other like other disciplines that have
researched and try to solve these
problems for a very very long time
before JavaScript so you know I think it
would be good if everyone just everyone
that was using streams everyone was
using deferred how to look at some
category theory principles as well so I
don't know if that answers your question
but they're just another tool in the
toolbox yeah great okay okay Thank You