[Music]
hi I'm flaky I'm I'm a missile attack
speaker and I'm JavaScript developer and
do a bunch of other stuff and do a lot
open source stuff and some of the open
source stuff on different missile in
most developments
I do not develop anything that aren't
gonna be talking about bad but I think
it's super important to talk about this
so who is Mozilla right missile is this
cooperation that everybody knows about
their foxes and browsers maybe like
Mozilla Firefox but it's actually a
champion of the open Internet and you
know there is a thing about the Internet
80% of probably all Internet traffic is
video and the problem with video is that
it needs a lot of data to transfer
moving pictures of kittens over if you
don't want to do it over compiling those
two gifs or gifts shoot me so Mozilla
figured that they they wanted to make
sure that there's image compilations
work out faster than usual and work with
a better compression ratio so the digit
started videos they actually started
with audio has anybody heard of opus
here there I go
yeah exactly so you probably had an mp3
player and now we are super happy
because MPV is the patient's and mp3
codecs which is an audio codec has
already expired but that wasn't the case
so you couldn't really use the mp3
encoding and decoding freely and so
missile have figured out hey we are
gonna do like an audio codec that you
can just use freely and it kind of
worked so they were like hey why don't
we just do this for video as well so
they started working on dala which is
the super amazing video technology but
they couldn't pull it off alone so what
they did is actually onboard and a bunch
of other vendors
created a vivan a v1 is actually by
alliance of open media and it's a
shortening of alliance of open media
video 1 and it's a open and royalty free
open-source codec for video and coding
and video transfer so the good things
about its royalty-free inverse you know
for hav C or h.264 or all the other
videos that are currently dominating and
the internet vendors have to pay like
hundreds of million dollars to be able
to use that this is completely free to
use and it actually achieves better
compression ratio that state-of-the-art
codecs can if you have been watching the
news
Apple has just announced that they're
going to be supporting HEV C which is
like the newest generation of video
encoding this AV one actually has a
potential to go 30% below this size of
the equivalent HEV C codec it has a
bunch of other things to it it also has
a bunch of drawbacks so the one of the
reasons that you have probably not heard
of it it's because it has been a
research project for a long time and
this the bit same has just finalized
that means you're going to be seeing
this pop up in browsers and other places
more and more
what are these places in the first place
Wow there's a lot that's that's a lot of
that's a big vendor list the big thing
about this is video and your internet to
pull this off actually you need adoption
actually a lot of the browser vendors
that you consider important including
Apple are onboard in this actually
Google has contributed their vp9 codec
and they merged it into the code base so
Google is also in there Netflix is
planning to push video content out as we
speak so you expect
do you have it in content providers as
well and Mozilla already has this in
Firefox nightly you can try this out
missile also built a bunch of open
source tools to work on this project and
to pull this huge project off so if you
want to learn more you should probably
figure it out and search for a b-1 and a
om thank you
[Applause]