[Music]
thank you
hi my name is Victoria I'm a front-end
developer and a chapter leader for
something called view vixens view vixens
is an initiative that helps women and
those who identify as women learn view
jeaious in a supportive and inclusive
environment and I'm here to tell you my
story with the V vixens and what we do
to help other women so just so that you
know where I come from I started so
three and a half years ago I graduated
from University with a Bachelor of Arts
in Japanese and German and linguistic
studies and as I was holding my diploma
I realized and I was taking graduation
photos with my brother and my
grandmother I realized I have no
idea what to do next so I moved to
Germany and after trials and errors with
design school and a master's degree I
decided to embrace the challenge of
becoming a web developer but I realized
that if I wanted to become a web
developer I would be much better off
doing that as part of a community so I
started using Twitter again and joining
the developer community on Twitter fast
forward a year later I was able to get
my first developer job and also was
granted the privilege of attending
conferences like this one I also became
more active on Twitter and as a result
of me using view at work I also joined
the view community on Twitter on Twitter
I also stumbled upon view vixens and I
didn't really know what they did all I
knew was that there was helping women in
tech and they were awesome and there was
someone called Jenn looper and she's the
CEO of the view vixens and Natalia the
CTO of V vixens a few months later I was
able to attend vue.js London a community
conference and finally had my first
meeting with the view community there
natalia the CTO of u vixens had a talk
where she talked about all the things
that the view vixens
in 2018 so a little bit more about the
Vixens community it was founded at
vue.js Amsterdam in 2018 and since then
we have done over 50 events worldwide
including workshops meetups and smaller
conference Lex events where we help
women build view applications or just
generally support them in any type of
developer or personal or professional
questions that they might have so I
joined the view vixens as a chapter
leader for Germany and now I'm building
pubic since Germany with a great team of
other amazing women
we now have city coordinators in Berlin
cause with Munich hamburg frankfurt and
we are doing a bunch of cool stuff like
this thursday we were here in berlin
organizing a workshop where we had 13
women coming together building a view
app and many of those women are here
today and also i have a few of my
coordinators here with me today sitting
over here so we have a slack community
that's very active where you can post
questions about anything that you might
wonder about code you can share photos
of your pets you can ask about women's
health issues in the ladies channel or
you can get help writing your talk
abstracts or anything that you might
need that vixens are happy to help and
they're always there if you need them so
if you would like to know more about the
view vixens
attend one of our events you can always
join us on slack we're at view vixens
slack org
we're also on twitter at view vixens and
we're always open for more people to
join us and more people to attend our
event and help us out and remember
always pay it forward and thank you so
much for everyone who's always making
the effort to help everyone in our
community thank you
[Applause]