you make it really hard to be nervous
because you're also super friendly so
thanks my name is Jani not imac
organizer of jazz convey you you all
know this already when I'm not doing
that I'm a developer from Berlin and I
work on a JavaScript library called
hoodie a database called couchdb and I
also did mustache jas but i'm no longer
maintaining that first and foremost i
have to express how honored I am to
speak here at jazz conf last call and
Jess confessed changed my life
significantly for the better so thank
you for having me you all know that this
is the last jazz come that the family
Williams was going to do for the
foreseeable future and while there are a
lot of reasons to be sad about this for
the next 20 or so minutes I like to
focus on the happy parts selfishly i'll
start with my own story the years 2008
and we're just all getting used to
iphones and having our digital lives
with us at all times I'm instant
messaging buddies with Chris because
that's what you did before Twitter even
though Twitter was around it wasn't as
they get so um being instant messaging
bodies with someone from the east coast
coming from Europe means that lots of
late-night chats for me because I'm six
hours ahead oh I wouldn't one night
chris is just back from Ruby fringe a
ruby conference put on by Pete Ford in
toronto canada and chris mentions two
things number one he's been to a lot of
industry conferences but now that he's
seen a ruby french how it can be done
right he concludes that a lot of
conferences are not very good and if you
know Chris you know he phrased it
slightly differently nevertheless I
agree second he asks what do you think
about a JavaScript conference and I
consider for a moment well they are
probably a lot of JavaScript developers
and that doesn't seem to be a conference
so maybe that's a good idea so I say it
is and he said I'm glad you say this
because I'm organizing one fast forward
a few months it's three a.m. in berlin
and we're chatting as you do insert the
noise and chris says the tickets are not
setting very well
they might have to cancel and I'm trying
to encourage a friend and it's also 3am
so in Sleepy Hayes I say if Jays gone
visit success i'll take it to europe
fateful day couple of weeks later it's
time to tell the venue that they had
booked that they vent us off that the
Williamsons need williams's need the
deposit back as it turns out they had
back there more headed back by the
mortgage and they don't wanna lose the
house and because Chris doesn't quite
know how to phrase the this was a
failure message and because he doesn't
want more people to sign up he quickly
changes the website to sold-out calls
his ticket sales and drives to the venue
the drive is about 45 minutes nearly
there he checks his email again remember
the iphone is just new and whose other
and complete surprise there's an email
that asks about how to maybe get one
more ticket pretty please and another
email and another and until there enough
inquiries to put jay is coming over the
break even point if all of the inquiries
buy one ticket so instead of canceling
the event and getting the deposit back
the willing zooms confirmed us conf on
the spot and the event is on that's good
good origin story there so the days here
and we all gather in a hotel ballroom in
Washington DC during my work on CouchDB
and I get to talk to all the different
language communities as being the
database person kind of a privilege to
like learn from all the different
communities so I'm seeing a lot of
familiar faces there are a lot of Ruby
developers who do javascript on the side
there are a lot of Python developers who
do javascript on the side and there a
lot of PHP developers who do javascript
on this side and a lot more other
developers who do javascript on the side
and after lunch and listening to half a
day worth of just JavaScript talks the
mood in the ballroom like nearly
physically changes you can see the mood
changing and we're starting to realize
slowly that we are JavaScript people who
do Ruby on the site and Python on the
side and PHP on the side but primarily
we are JavaScript people and the first
Jess confess since been described as a
homecoming of a community that didn't
know
it existed and that's exactly what
happened we now had a JavaScript
community there wasn't one before so at
the end of day two when Laura and Chris
do the closing remarks Tris asks me to
stand up I get up completely oblivious
to what was about to happen so he
thanked me for supporting him through
tough times and he also said that one of
the things that I had said to support
him was that if Jasmine was a success
i'll take it to europe and he continued
addressing the audience you will have to
decide whether this was a success but if
you think it was let you know because
then he'll take it to europe and of
course thunderous applause when i go out
haha yeah fateful day indeed luckily I
admit malta and hoga at the at the bar
previous the previous night so that was
where the original curators came
together how that was formed we have
since been joined by Tiffany Connor and
Carolina sure who have been fantastic
additions to the team we had a good good
fun running a bunch of events um a
couple of months later we run jazz
confit you in Berlin still in 2009 and
of course or first because John Resig
because that's what you do and also ryan
doyle introduces no jazz for the first
time he uses my laptop for this i'm very
proud of this also just just mike my
conference is also good enough so that
started the whole know jazz thing which
is really really cool and two chaps from
Ireland Paul and Eamon they they attend
and they think well if our friends can
put on a conference we can do it too so
they went on to do the legendary funk on
series of events where things like these
are just to count totally normal if you
can't see in the background that's a
DeLorean there's donkey there's a clown
juggling and lots of other shenanigans
going happen to happening this is also
completely normal this is just the
engine yard team photo that you do and
and fun converse planned as a trilogy so
that is over now but Paul still runs the
conference called all which is also
inspired by jazz confident way
and Paul also went on to build Tito the
world's favorite conference ticketing
system so if you ever put on a
conference use Tito everybody will love
you for it I'm not getting paid for this
I may get paid for this a few years
later one of the organizers of the front
trans conference and also speaks in
Poland of course pics at Berlin JS our
local javascript meetup that we put up
every month after we started Jas conf
which kind of was the inspiration for
the whole bar ojs story that jet told
yesterday we but forgot to
mention but don't worry about it no he
said so many nice things about our event
so I may actually not there's no grudge
here afterwards we talked and he said
well he went to Jess come for you and
the friends to you and they wanted
something like this at home and I
started looking for people who could
they could ask they could you run this
event for us they couldn't find any so
they decided to do it on their own and
they're not alone these are just very
few of the conference would have spawned
from jas kana and have been inspired by
Jess conf and the one thing that brings
all of these events together is the deep
care about the community communities
that they are organized for about caring
for people trying new things not
following the same old patterns or
running soulless events just for profit
putting people first attendees and
speakers everyone and that focus comes
from laura's and Chris's dedication and
craftiness to put on an event that
facilitates a community coming together
over and over again while writing this
talk had dawned on me that feeling that
we had at that very first jazz conf in
Washington DC when we realized what we
didn't know before that we were the
JavaScript community every event since
that jazz conf in 2009 in this lineage
is an attempt to recreate that feeling
of newfound companionship and to allow
an ever growing group of people to
experience the community for the first
time and feel at home front trends has
now been running for five years has had
over 2,200 ten days jazz confused on
seven editions and lockstep with us and
has had over twenty five hundred
thousand 2500 2 10 G's
4010 is that's way too many now the
kicker the there are over 50 events
including a JS conf run every inhabited
continents and sometimes more than one
and way more than one and they all have
a similar story than the one above its
they're great this is great I want to do
this I want to have this at home or this
was great I want to do this with a
different context where the whole series
of CSS comes that's now spreading over
the world's coming from this and over 50
events with well over fifty thousand
attendees over the past seven years
alone have come out of Loris and chris's
commitment to this community and that's
just the in-person events our joint
video collection on YouTube has received
nearly 2.5 million views and over 50
million minutes of viewing time that's
an achievement that we as a community
can be very proud of but that we have to
be that dub sorry I'm very proud and
that we have to be thankful for for
Chris and Laura that they did that for
us so I talked to a bunch of the people
behind those logos what motivates them
first ones Robin mania he runs reject
chest which destiny was called reject
Jess for people who got their talk
rejected from jay s con and people
initially thought they were like RJ's
compass evil but behind the scenes we
all work together so that was quite fun
and so and reject itself then has
inspired other conferences that like
this alright so this is you see that's a
lot of lot of forking going on and so
Robin says we wanted to give more people
the chance to become part of the
JavaScript community Tiago Rodriguez who
runs alex j s in lisbon portugal says we
wanted to bring something similar to
jazz comfort approach ago and there was
no JavaScript commune in Portugal so I
had to go into it through Quilly who
runs web rebels in Oslo know for the
fourth year says we felt the Jays
confetti community feeling that no other
conference around us had and finally
douglass campus who runs jazz from
brazil says hey I got blasted away with
the awesomeness of the experience I
wanted to bring this home they have all
the say like they have the same
motivation they wanna they see their
something special now I want to bring
this to that particular community so
let's see what they got out of what they
achieved
brault organized of and yet conf
real-time con frio Trigon because when
why not run conferences like for
conference at the same time and says we
created an entirely new community so he
took the idea of jazz convent of the
cultural spirit behind and applied to
different scenarios and like we did in
2009 created an entirely new community
where people coming together around an
idea how great is that fantastic Thiago
says it spawned and brought together the
JavaScript community in Portugal it made
more people get involved start doing
more JavaScript work for noon and
international companies nowadays as a
regular meet up in Lisbon and a number
of note schools around the country
awesome Tiffany Conroy fellow organizer
of jazz confused as we made a visible
presence of women and under up and other
underrepresented groups and expected
part of a well-run tech conference and
I'm very proud of that to this industry
looked a lot different seven years ago
and we have made a significant
improvement to that there's still a lot
of work but we're on the way and at
and at this point I have to apologize
for the poor representation of women in
my list of quotes the reasons for these
are beyond the scope of the stock but if
you're interested chat to me later p
tight conjunto JS and edinburgh says we
now have a JavaScript community in
Scotland with both meetups both in
Glasgow and Edinburgh that didn't exist
before and he continues over the years
we have been able to give a platform to
newbie speakers that have gone on to
become amazing at sharing the knowledge
in case in point and who's seen Phillip
Roberts's talk what is the event loop
anyway alright there's a few people in
this room that are going to have their
minds blown when they watch this talk
but and so he gave a similar target
Scotland jazz in spring 2014 and we
liked it so much we invited him to give
a revised and updated version and two in
September of the same year and the talk
has gotten is very popular like nearly a
hundred thousand people watch this this
is a blockbuster for tech talk on
youtube like this is a big deal and it's
it shot straight into the top three
talks of all Jas comms ever and this is
from a conference that ran for the first
time inspired by Jess conf in a local
event and in the local area and found
someone that we could bring back to the
community and that now like does what
Pete s like become amazing a chair in
the knowledge and this just shows how
how well this community thing works and
how well they this stories is
helping us that we can bring ideas and
cultures to a lot of like places in the
world and they come back things come
back to us through the same channels and
I'm just very proud of this and Robin
who else around sorry i'll skip to the
second so Robin also runs the node
copter series of events which if you're
here you've definitely seen and he
relates an anecdote that when I asked
them to open up a txt file they opened
it up in Microsoft Word but at the end
of the day they were had they had a
flying or the program to flying robot
that acted like a jellyfish complete
with flying patterns and everything so
this community does cool stuff and does
it allows a lot more people to come in
and teaches them
and click for says there was no
community before there was a huge java
community in Oslo and I think we have
disrupted that I think that's very good
and then Thomas Carson who is over there
who runs Jess fascia and Singapore and
other places he also relates a story
about the working conditions of IT
professionals in Asia and sweat shop is
a word that I've heard many times
salaries are low and work is grinding
and uninspiring I do believe our little
and growing community makes a difference
how awesome is that fix Asia good job
and so I couldn't just like say all the
things that are great about this without
also mentioning that it is a lot of work
and Tiago has the perfect template for
the series of responses i'll i'll show
you now it was a lot of work but i met a
lot of other great people the pattern is
it was a lot of work was the hardest
thing I've ever done whatever peril but
some gratification so neck whose real
name I'm not trying to pronounce who
runs jazz combo depressed and hungry
says one of the most stressful and
exhaustive things I've ever done but
seeing the enthusiasm of our attendees
and making friends and helping others
totally worth it Carter obey sir who
runs the Cascadia Jas and then Cascadia
fest in the Pacific Northwest in the
canada and the US says the hours are
long and the rewards can seem fleeting
but over the last four years I've met
some of the brightest kindness and
hardest-working people I've ever known
so if it's that much work why do they do
this encounter continues to me JS conf
is the conference that taught me that
being a better programmer starts with
being a better person Robin em who kind
of has a tendency for taking things over
the top and he got married in 2014 and
then came here with his lovely wife
and through continuous we had we have
picked up excellent skills and emailing
spreadsheet management and dealing with
the constant guilt of being behind tasks
behind on tasks you love you never
organized a conference this is the non
funny part abso Pete and Pete from
Scotland sums it up perfectly though
running a conference is an awesome
exciting stressful and incredibly
rewarding experience and it has been
that for crew Laura and Chris since 2009
and for every year since and they didn't
do this for the first time in history
but for the first time for this
community and they kept added and we owe
them so much for the hard work and
persistence and everything else that
they brought into making Jess conf what
is today an inspiration for a generation
Thank You Laura and Chris