two minutes
a very special
they would
you'll find something that looks for
instance like this maybe not
you have this do X variety of stability
polynomial yes doing is everything is no
visual details that is certified
accessibility internationalized and
proposals on
which is visual like the hell predators
it's part when love is a mighty not
working any ID the most impersonal
process most
possession
quite severe
they going to a certainty
and each of these voters have their own
doona test which can basically but it's
not as easy as making love can be quite
hard the idea is that you can really
cover these and months ago that it will
induce most basic for your examples so
if you see something interesting just
grab it on the truck I'll the supported
platforms
working process there the some things
the friendly
well but in normal reference
is class for
sort of movement and the way
from
words in ladies
and
and the particle beams
go in graphics will take times when
running and
is that
customers installations and yard
four sequences
right
that was
or not
so where is the eye can see light and
the judgment is
in order to practice in my phone
so
whimpers
perhaps you're using a desk in
environments and using kinda like a
moving service and boy times the
difficulties of because I see
nestles is kind of very short of desire
vegas by plans
fire department vs bus and there are
editors do that or you just put it right
into daughter GFX if you want so
everything begins with a surface
hair that most Africa
fun so you're busy
inches
the right composer is it okay sir
right through the space base
I
yeah nice
that were estimated oh you when I fix
the code so you can do quite nice things
the thing that you did not see looks
like this useful services looks like
here I service
here we go
by these things
great service
pencils are we
mr.
this one where
and also if you have any questions
please interrupt me immediately I don't
have to say because you always forget to
the last minute what to our school I
directly so and if you have this surface
ships are regular server waves like
Providence and this hall hundred
straight down
just
worse
and even weather has also very nice mr.
for this
what
wrong and
we have seamless
they don't know
producers
so
if you have a very very picky client
this is one way of us on that problem
and all that the cords the text the
functions are for absence
there's another place
works thanks but
that's a quick look at this time
my name is very good
so
there is a
let's see there are several programs
there's one called to put a little
blooper dupa dupa tub inkscape vector
graphics editor where can actually draw
stuff import them and fill with them and
respond to see how this
there is no class ring as I did actually
him to this kind of crap odd stuff and
there's a demo
using circles here we have 100 random
eye circles and free circle I've created
a movable object that makes or draggable
and to the strike of the object i canna
see you driving under this was kind of
beautiful and it's really simple to do a
sew in the my weight I think I have some
kind of residence here with my voice I
try to speak more more in a light voice
no didn't help either
greatest
and for the service
NJ
or where
even said that same study
and what
they're complex objects is writing the
things of the sort of
but it looks this is one example
our key
and we're going to values that we find
there
this is universal
x
and we also have the normal kind of them
work has work
Andy what there is something more
slightly more interesting we can't my
thing well that was that one
for her supper
we can use the five days ago ancestor
gets on the percent of legibility and
this of course the much much slower in
his for safety password so in your
simple things or amex starfish
okay you can probably work stuff from
flash or C++ or Java or small language
they find these cool devices don't bite
to it because the graphics API are very
similar and the code for that is
about here
no questions of work
okay um then we go to the next part
that's there and I mentioned this before
them you ever say
second call came so soon a
stay Pacific missions we need
confirmation students
so
Oh
I
always available
and I even think about this is we have a
quite lot of documentation in the Doyle
campus so if you go to tops off work
amazon for the last year and norms of
effort
examples of how to cook days as a link
just described yes
and this door campus is riddled with
these kind of the resonating voices it's
through these kind of squares that are
really you know you have a demo your
copy and paste what's you have a spread
which day summer was to CSS so for
everything that you would like to show
this agree the kind of femur not
everything is turned on you can use this
for player of these inversions of oreos
so their camps is real nice
then again you might
nations to them to have powerful objects
than whatever say the same time
dancing
ever bring to form bring your phone to
bring tobacco for all of the excitement
or inside
Endora convey some of noisy for their
party were
other ways then
as I say
so
you have a shape stroke definitions
you
office lips
so
so moving on to events animations I
didn't really really simple example
for years of service and
and
this
this low voltage is actually a kind of
the force the habit
and it will
this so when I move over this is it
creates very nice and then kind of
watery feeling where it wouldn't it I
didn't have time to do anything else
with this december's some horses and
what's happening here is what i call
this public function i have an animation
going and this animation was something
that Nicolae touched upon the event
yesterday today's elimination packages
that are separated what's work on just
using harsh movements so this kind of
not bouncy effect is used elsewhere for
bottoms wood or menus would have shown
in the animation in separate that we
have a whole slew of so it's a very good
separation of concern on that aspect
actually see and the function that is
using these is they're from
kind of
destinations
really
and
looks kind of wave is really kind of
unaware we have weird questions
wonderful another some an enormous
amount of effort has gone into the next
example but I wish already that's it
because how do you see what I showed I
had this customer in New York who wanted
a process visualization assist I was
really impressed by the coding every I
the Novus transport and it worked very
well but when you show it gesture hey so
wait we'll have this another oh maybe I
have an idea this is
usher in the Red Square at population
this project is argue but they are
spread everything
graphics and early
side this time 50 grams there's no
just because
so until i have i use these events to
anime so give some feedback and when i
click on one mode use a little circular
very common dialog this text another
I was dirty from the world
and the continuity is the end it really
looks very stern design-wise so this is
the specification from the customer this
is not really my idea that it should
look like this but which is possible and
I was not and that's it six month
of time work that we realized
I couldn't have ever heard of a toy I
mean because I'm constrained by the
module system so I load up there to sort
of at them and then we're moving into
shorting and this my contract package
and what to expect for a bamboo
updates i express my expertise and one
positive things
turtle backwards the worst
and let's say you would like to have a
short there's some concede media
absolutely the game next up we can years
ago
tractor
the first mine
motion
what I said
graphics that are zooming soldiers and
it was shortly use
see you know
and that's kind of mystical so
double-time understand
just because you have
from very simple
but just
John
here's the lease
some of that's he may charge
add both just notice even my shot
I'll get access exim by this is named
we
ever made minor michael takes this
algorithm
this
data and this
Pegasus
survey
that
vessels yes
this
person
there's a service
sir
person
oddly they did you know be a URL for
that ok so but we have all days ok but
it was a very good idea i'll try that
see
Oh
I'm not sure I'm ready to find that
this is
ribbit are respectable score
we have an end a local team actually I
was going to show that it's not using
not a communicator with the servers
using a store in very much the same way
so maybe we can take a look at that
and we go to the unit tests again so
these are just a normal test that is
used but all your data
so if I changed something here
then he should update
we didn't take that it
so it's
otherwise
one
and there's quite a number of it across
arias course I think the easiest ways to
just show you these from a d-mail
it's a basic short
more fancy one a speedy
Thanks we also have a small we'd get
called a vertical it a legend so if you
have another series added the legend
will detect a series of amazement at
this rate this is very sweet and you
probably want to do that so and we have
the eventing stuff automatically tied in
to can say that you want to switch
which kind of data so these are stacked
bars and Collins different shapes your
free series
it was very refreshing to play around if
you climb them and we have also
here's another theme I think you can
actually no it's up here but
they are
the second
not using
one is almost
there was
this
workers even
song
Oh
I have shadows and lots of really doing
it doesn't matter how many charts will
make it is always fun with his head
don't have this kind of spider shark and
we don't but there are the kind of
shocked Spencer
another interesting feature is that you
can take a short and you can scale it
and you can pan inside the short and
this of course an edge case can be seen
i think is still pelikula where
they become
that's really great of a certain kind of
the customers applications okay we can
also have multiple access that's also
Maya
and maybe a time series you don't want
to show the actual value very
here's here's
sir
conscious as well
and all of this is quite fine because do
you want to start the translation enemy
I'm not comfortable with this room I
think
and I does know about the date on the
find out that the easiest ways is hardly
the HMO very costly and sometimes you do
so
loves options to disease all right lace
conscious of the charge is specifically
six horses
it was twice
including hunting I love the pencil and
some color theming most horrid things
dark men
the screen
and then we have the short appearance
and as it some of the short dress you
have
that mankind
so the disease
and that's more
yes
HYFR
that serves I haven't even woken up yet
and I get some good links and sweet
again for you
oh yeah
thank you
what and one could easily think that I
should have talked about but I
University
No
this
stories
ah just a policy if I can
I thought I started that but may be able
to come weird
is it oh yes it is thank you
I'm in shock uh-huh okay we had some
difficulties would be reacting stuff so
if I do something I don't didn't know
this program so so please be in for the
other one thing but I think I would do
me busy occurred here something very
simple and then i have this
does Emma know this program river no you
don't have to come I didn't
you could be not zoom display male but
there's there's a button the host using
called the show xml or something like
that
no there it is
so
if you just copy this which actually did
I had that one very small example but no
not six
yes but I did I introduced in bogus
but here's the source code that were
kissing
that's right
so I'll other questions
I
No
see
alright
there
Oh
we have some stuff like that but I'm
actually like to see exactly that's kind
of a PCO can start to move around we
don't have that I think yet anywhere but
there is one Dima that is slow Yeah
right thank you we have that sorry just
in from but we let's say drawing and we
have the unit us from that I think and
they say path test no wait
there we go so a visit here and this
here is this the right BMO
yeah but if we have some kind of
connector here we are I don't know how
to connect this to another object i'm
not certain whether it's worse that at
the moment
you
problems that
with Holly
a special duty
they're currently so much and even those
Americans below an 80 minute response I
don't even want witters so it's really
quite a lot but I think there is we just
quickly quickly go to back yeah but I
remember that we have one
here's one very simple example yeah so
Andy but what happens is that as soon as
a loon years
rear ender realism
many people does melody
bro
you
me
right
now
so
Marcy