so hello everyone my name is Gonzalo
Cordero and i'm here to talk to you
today about why why mobile development
so before I before I go I want to get a
sense how many of you are familiar with
Yui cool how many of you are familiar
with any of the Yui mobile features cool
even better so hopefully you'll learn
something today so when I'm gonna be
covering is I'm going to talk about some
of this stuff you can start using today
to in order to create a killer mobile
apps using Yui I'm gonna show a little
peek into the what's coming to the
future and as well as you know i'll show
you a couple of cool demos as well too
so a couple of statements first Yui
philosophy in this mobile environment is
that we think that you should not be
having to write your code depending on
which device you'd apply the deploying
to we believe that you should rather
want and that cause you just work across
all your different devices and the
second thing I would like to say is that
everything that you need to create a
killer molap it's already out there
using why why so there's nothing
stopping you for creating really good
experiences on your mobile applications
and I'll show a couple of examples as
well so some of the features that you
might want to be using when you're
designing your model applications are
some of these guys right here so the
loader 414 that this is you who are now
familiar with what the loader is and why
basically what it does it's just that it
brings it lowes to your page whatever
modules you need and on the man as you
need them not only that but the loader
it's so cool and so sophisticated I will
know which device you're deploying to
and depending on what you are it will
just give you the set of files and
modules that you need just for that so
what what this means to you is a let's
say that you on your coat
the note component of why why so if you
deploy this up on the desktop then it
will give you all the desktop necessary
stuff that you need in order to work but
if you were gonna deploy your app on a
mobile device it will know that it's a
mobile device and they'll all these
serve you they know the specific stuff
that applies to that device so again
it's a pretty cool stuff and you can do
it's actually it's gonna it's about to
get way better because we're going to be
introducing soon why LS so while it is
something that we're very excited about
which is we're taking back the loader
back from the client to the server and
so basically what without it's going to
do is a all the dependencies calculation
is going to happen now in the server
which means we're gonna it's going to be
way faster is using kno jes and if we
also have this cache layer on top of
that we're basically if you request a
module that someone else has requested
before it will serve from the couch gosh
so it's going to be extremely fast and
we think you're gonna love it and so
keep an eye for that on 3 4 wireless
alright so let me just talk about the
modules some of the widgets that I think
I apply for more a while a little bit
the first one I'm going to talk about
transition so the transition module
basically what it does is a you will let
you define some sort of visual
representation or behavior when you move
from point A to point B or from when you
move an element from one state to the
other say you you know let's say you you
know you swipe or you flick and you want
to navigate to the next page and you
want to show some sort of feedback to
the user that you're navigating so
transition model will do that for you
you know again although the cross
browser staff and you know if it
hardware acceleration is they will use
it so you know what this means to you is
in certain
do something like this where you're
going to have you know to manually set
all these different properties for your
transition then you can just easily
apply in all of these into the node
itself that you wish to transition from
so again much simpler much cleaner you
specified the duration the value that
you're going to and this is using css3
when available on the back as well so
it's similar to that for you and the
developer you don't have to worry about
browsers vendors specific prefixes and
yeah just making your life simpler same
fashion the history API or the history
module what this does is a will let you
tweak the back and forward button on the
browser so you can apply custom actions
to those to the 22 to the buttons so
imagine that you have some sort of
built-in navigation control your mobile
app and what you want is when the user
hit the back button on the browser
button which is kind of like common now
on android devices you have the actual
physical keys to go back and forth so
what you want is just so in navigation
within your app so you can do this with
done using history again you know just a
little bit of a code example it's pretty
simple all you need to do is instantiate
the history object you can passing an
initial state if you want you don't have
to and then you can modify as you go
with add and remove all so it will give
you all these different events you can
you can subscribe to to detect
interesting moment and to change you
have to so priest and ER if you use Yui
before on how we you know we'd always
publish all these events for you to
tweak your application so let me just
show you a quick demo online on this too
tavion history so so in this case let's
say you know I created this tab control
right I'm by the way all the all the
examples are going to be showing off
today are available in the YY library so
you can just you know look on your own
time and then play around with it but
basically let's say I have a some sort
of navigation like this where it's gone
it's gonna navigate through the content
so as I go and I want to go back instead
of going back to you know the previous
pages are visited on the browser history
it's just gonna let me navigate through
my little widget here so I think pretty
honey if you're if you need to do
something custom for your mobile
application in terms of navigation and
I'm going to be showing them at the end
that kind of capsule is everything it's
like a real life example so just holding
their hang in there okay so now we're
let me talk about events a little bit
now because I think this is a pre
interesting so event we provide you a
set of the regular events are available
right now for all the devices out there
like touch move and touch star and then
all the iOS specific ones you know
gesture star on your gesture change and
what not but on top of that we also
giving you a set of synthetic events you
can subscribe to so two of the most
interesting ones are the flick giving
and the other gestures so let's say you
wanna you know you have a something with
with media alright like like like a
carousel with pictures or something and
you want to be able just to swipe make
flick like that and just like navigate
so why why we'll give you this event
called flick you can subscribe to pass a
set of different properties and again
this is very highly customizable and you
can really achieve need
look and feel if you tweak with those
settings a little pain but then I mean
that's it's pretty simple you just pass
in the distance and the velocity and why
not and then you know it will behave
like a native if you want to have more
control what's happening on that flick
event we also provide you events you can
subscribe to take when the gesture
actually starts and when it moves and
when the user lifted at the finger of
the of the other mobile device and then
you can react to it and do you know
whatever you need to do so again pretty
highly customizable and you can
definitely achieve a lot of the native
coolness with just using web let me show
you a quick demo on the flick stuff then
you having the simulator
okay so in this case we have this little
list you know it's pretty pretty common
where you have on your mobile devices
like a list view of items right and this
is again all HTML CSS and why why what
you want to do is uh you want to show
pressing the user like I made like a
shortcut to be able to delete these
items as the user navigates really so
just going to have to use the mouse but
again get worse with your your finger on
touch event as well but as you strive to
the left we're presenting this delete
button here right here and as you delete
then we use in transition to collapse
all the list so you know not too fancy
but you get the idea and you know this
open the door opens the door to a lot of
things on your when you're thinking
about creating your mobile application
and you know you're presented with us
aspects or marks and behavior you can
question if do you really need to do it
using native control when you can just
do it using web using why I for example
and then it will just work across all
your devices and don't have to maintain
different code bases so
and the last which I want to talk about
before going to the demos is the
scrollview widget so scrub you basically
what gives you the scrollable content
that reacts to swipe events or touch
events you can make it horizontal
horizontal or vertically aligned and
then you did this plugins to to make it
behave the way you want it and bouncy
and whatnot and like i said i'll show
you an example in a little bit and how
do you use it it's pretty simple you
just feed a bunch of you know since or
markup that contains maybe images and
some context and then you sang she ate
the scrollview object and here you can
just tell okay so I want my flick even
to react at this minimum velocity or the
deceleration has to be this or you know
want to bounce this many pixels and
whatnot so again really highly
customizable you can really achieve
really good looking we hit like apps and
on behavior Sunday that mimic like
native which as web and to the example
okay so for the past couple of months or
so I mean working on this this is a new
yahoo local app that's going to be on
the app store soon it just something is
like a hyper-local up you can just find
deals and things going on around where
you are so when we initially represented
the marks and the specs you know that
you know everyone was a moment obviously
now we have to write all of this in
Objective C but then we as we start
going we start realizing that everything
which has been done using web on Yui and
not only that but when we decide to
launch this into Android will have to do
nothing you know just work I mean
granted the navigation its native but
you know does the only piece that will
have to write whenever we go to
android so for example this pull down to
refresh event that you know it's pretty
common in this mobile app out there we
being able to mimic using just web same
with this guy right here this is a
little scope oui je where you can just
swipe your fingers to see the different
movies going around your neighborhood
and we also using css3 plus 30 mins we
cannot leave this castle that looks like
iOS coverflow 20 side again you know
just using Yui 3 or web components
highly scalable so let me just show you
a demo day of the whole phone
by the way it's been it's been an
earthquake I guess so in California
centrica anyways so we have this weather
widget right here you know you see the
bounce all that is web using Yui same
with this guy right here that was
talking about earlier for the movies see
okay so you know all the issues using
web using scroll YY scroll view as well
as this guy right here and you know as
we swipe you know this thing changes and
all this just two inches a plan in css3
class to the element and using Yui flick
event so you know you get the idea you
don't really need to rely on a lot of
native staff you can just use web to
achieve and to get to this production
level quality apps does it pull down to
refresh 22 to create applications and
again this should just work on Android
so development time it's it's pretty
pretty fast so just dropping some
thoughts you know I know that why why
historically has all this a large amount
of widgets in the desktop and you know
maybe some of you are wondering okay
what happens to those with just one of
those which is going to be ported to to
mobile so the answer is that we're
working on a on a solution for that
right now we're trying to think how we
want to create or this skin you know the
skin for the widgets and and and you
know the level of skill so they're
agnostic intense of the device are you
running into the point into the the
different widgets so again we're working
on it we just want to make sure that we
get it right so keep an eye for 34
because we're going to bring a lot of
stuff for mobile we're going to be
bringing a lot of the
navigation controls are you so that I we
had to do natively we can produce this
after 34 ditches using Yui as well we're
going to bring widgets we're going to
bring data logs and overlays and things
like that so again and wireless so in
the meantime though if you are a Yui
user and you have built something really
cool that you like to contribute then go
to the gallery is that you know it's
open for everyone and the stone is going
to be dead place to where you will get
all your with you a demon core so again
please contribute to the gallery it's
free open for everyone and yeah that's
really that's all i have for you guys
and I hope you learn something and yeah