I'm so happy to be here I can't really
express my gratitude to Chris for
inviting me and for making this happen
and it was awesome to follow jid he's a
good friend and a good opener hopefully
hopefully you guys will laugh more
because he he's awesome and I don't have
to do as much work so anyway moving on
on a cue I don't I really didn't when I
saw the Jays conf last call it was like
a call to arms for me to come and
support Chris and Laura and everything
they've done and so I didn't know what
to talk about I haven't really written
that much javascript in a while even
though i did a talk at brooklyn j/s
recently it was about go cuz i'm
obviously an old person and so I I
didn't know exactly what to talk about I
realized I thought the first talk I gave
it a jazz conf was five years ago or a
little more than five years ago at jas
com 2010 and a lot in my life has
happened since then and I wanted to talk
about that because I think I learned
some things so I'm going to try to teach
all of you all the things that I learned
in five years in about 40 minutes are
you guys ready for that cool so first
let's start with the basics how to speak
at j s com 2010 so it all started Jed
was kind of mentioning this there was a
there was a nascent JavaScript community
in New York in 2009-2010 I was one of
the organizers of NYC j/s with a friend
Brian Mitchell who sadly isn't here
today but he's an awesome person and at
NYC j/s in some time in 2010 Chris
Williams spoke there are about seven
people there which was awesome because
that was the JavaScript community in New
York then and we after the after the
talk Chris did a little talk we went to
this bar as you do called ginger man and
we had some beers and I heard that
Jessica's coming up this is my first
time meeting Chris we went to this
little back room we start
talking I had some beers and I was at
that point I was working in JavaScript I
really wanted to talk to Jess comp I
hadn't gone to 2009 which was the first
year 2010 was a second I really really
really wanted to talk and so I was
telling you about my framework and the
things that I wanted to talk about and
he was like no you're not allowed to
talk about a JavaScript framework or
framework sucks you're full of
don't do that I was like well listen I
have other hobbies what if I talk about
baking or how I make bacon myself he's
like yes um he was like basically if
you'd give a talk about bacon I will
make you the keynote presentation and
this was like a couple of beers in I
don't know if he was serious I was like
okay cool let's do it and I was like in
mind make bacon on stage is that a thing
that we can do and he was a gay and
we'll figure it out with the hotel we
didn't actually get to make bacon on
stage but I did make a little video this
is me five years ago you can still watch
this video it's pretty funny Brian
Mitchell made it I look so young and
ambitious then what happened and yeah
I'm still making bacon this was from a
couple of couple months ago it's
delicious if you want to learn how to
make bacon watch that talk but thinking
is a gateway drug to many many other
things so I want to tell you how to cure
sausage is something I learned in the
past couple years securing bacon is
pretty simple you take your bacon you if
you want a more detail go watch the talk
you take a pork belly you take salt you
take the special curing salt and you
take time and you let it cure over
around time and then you add some smoke
and you have bacon and it's delicious
it's really really simple the
ingredients are so so small that really
anyone can do it at home the smoke part
is the only part that you might not be
able to do in a Brooklyn kitchen but
you're like me at that time I had like a
little kettle grill on a balcony and I
was able to do it and piss my neighbors
off and it was awesome so sausage isn't
that different I was always really
interested in the idea of sausage
because it's like the next level from
bacon so I'm like always trying to level
up how do you cure sausage so you are
it's not that different you can see
there's only a couple different things
there's pork and salt and seasonings and
then the big difference is is you have
these friendly bacteria and you have to
have a specific temperature and humidity
and then time is the same
so the friendly bacteria it's easy you
can order friendly bacteria on the
internet on amazon com you get them and
you add them to your sausage mix and
they basically friendly bacteria or the
bacteria that grow on the outside
especially by a sausage at a store it's
covered in white mold and you're like oh
that's gross it's white those white
molds are good they're good mold that's
keeping away the bad mold that's black
and green you see any black and green on
it don't eat it first rule of sausage
and so if you if you but in order to get
those bacteria to grow you need a
specific temperature and humidity when
you're occurring bacon who's put in the
fridge it doesn't matter top shelf
bottom shelf it doesn't matter with
sopressata which is one of my favorite
types of Italian sausage you need to
keep the humidity around eighty percent
or higher and you need to keep the
temperature in around 55 degrees because
that's where the friendly bacteria
thrive anything out of that and you
might get those green and black ones
which you don't like so how to make a
raspberry pi in nodejs monitored sausage
curing chamber so obviously as a
programmer that's the next thing that
comes to mind obviously right so you got
your sausage you got a little fridge
there's a raspberry pi on top some wires
dangling scarily into the into the into
the fridge and this is basically like a
layout of how it works you got your
sausage you have this thing called the
DHT 22 which is a temperature and
humidity thing you have a Raspberry Pi
that can run nodejs which is awesome
that sends these metrics to Heroku which
is a little a brownie on roku and those
metrics get sent to librado and if the
temperature goes too high or too low
then you send a text message to yourself
so you know to check your sausage I have
an app that's running unfortunately my
sausage fridge isn't running right now
so I don't have it running and I
realized it never took a screenshot of
it in action which is really really sad
but we you know this kind of follows a
theme of what we were talking about all
day this is the internet of tasty things
and it's something I'm really interested
in at one point I got really excited I
was like I'm going to add a camera in
there and this is what I can't wear my
sausage for it looks like
it didn't you could really do anything I
just got really excited about it I
actually I had to scrap that project but
of course once you get Sasha saying and
you realize that oh there's like some
cool stuff going on here you get more
into this whole idea of how do you
pickle things like what is that what
does that process look like and then you
have some parties where you have like
giant plates and Fickell's because your
entire freezer and fridge is filled with
pickles and not even joking i've had to
that sausage fringe has now become a
pickle for age because i ran out of room
in my fridge to store all my pic hose
and a pickling is actually what got me
into making bacon and this whole thing
but it's gotten a little further there
you have some pastrami and some coppa
and some sopressata and some duck
prosciutto which is amazing pickled corn
who hears had pickled corn it's so fine
it's amazing pickle yourself some corn
and the one thing I'll tell you this
fermentation you can get deep and I did
uh I highly recommend this book called
the fermentation Bible by Sandra cats
it's literally the size of a Bible and
it has everything you ever wanted to
know about it I just got this book um
that my wife is going to kill me it's
called the what's called how to preserve
the Japanese way of preserving and I'm
gonna start making me so why not fish
sauce is where my wife draws the line so
yeah but fermentation is everywhere so
you start getting these ideas in your
head about what fermentation is and what
it can do because look at this that
looks kind of familiar right you have
the same ingredients on the right side s
as bacon it's just the ingredients in
front of it are different you have flour
and water and flour and water plus time
you start the starter and you start
building it you build it and this
miracle of two things combined you have
bread you have this beautiful beautiful
bread and I've been obsessed with bread
for a long time I'm pissing off all the
gluten-free people and the vegans in the
audience but that's okay you got to do
it sometime so
then the you this bread was made was all
just those ingredients it's so simple
obviously there's some sesame seeds on
the left just so just for taste and so
you get this idea in your head that you
can take these two things and combine
them and basically let nature take its
course and this is a really beautiful
and I don't know to me it's almost like
moving like I'm really moved by
fermentation and buy bread because I
know that sounds crazy but it's like
it's the simplest thing and it's been
going on since almost the beginning of
time someone figured out that you
combine these two things and they make
something delicious but even with that
with those two things these simple
ingredients it takes years and years and
centuries of practice to get to what we
have today and something about that is
amazing right you take these very
organics base ingredients and turn them
into something special but that making
it something special as craft right and
I'm not saying I'm amazing at it I don't
have that centuries of experience yet
but I I'm trying to download everything
I can and learn how to do this so
they're easier ways to get into this
then the mastering the art of the
sourdough and that's Pizza Pizza is the
most basic form of fermentation if you
do it right it's the same thing you got
your flower you got your water you've
got your yeast you don't have to let you
add yeast to kick start it and you have
these beautiful balls of dough and pizza
is all this you add this extra thing
which is that people love pizza
and people love eating it and people
love sharing it it's just communal food
that gets people together and gets
people excited about being with each
other it's my homeboy mrb shoutout so
you get really into this thing of making
peace or her I get really into the
single making pizza over 10 years and
you make a lot a lot of pizzas and you
get really really good at it and it's
awesome everyone likes you because you
give them pizza how easy is that so from
there then you make so many pieces and
what do you do you have to write a book
about it obviously and how do you write
a book about pizza easy you make a lot
of pizza
so Mike and I have started on this
journey and we paired up with this
amazing designer named Steve berry and
we're making a book about making pizza
this isn't good my life of the past
month has been working on this book it's
beautiful here's a picture of it we're
raising money on Kickstarter we try to
raise twenty eight thousand dollars we
hit our goal in six days because people
love deep sorrow it's an easy easy thing
and so this is I'm bragging but I'm also
just super excited about this because
here is this little inkling of yeast and
fermentation and it turned into this
thing that people have paid us thirty
seven thousand dollars to do over the
next couple months which is just an
incredible thing so wait I got to go
back a little bit that's that's the
entire keynote effects for the entire
presentation you guys can all take a
breath because in 2010 there was a lot
of stuff other stuff going on and this
is the part where i talk a little about
javascript so how do you make a
client-side JavaScript framework in 2009
there wasn't a lot of things about how
to do that i created this thing called
sam ejs and it was awesome it was a
really fun project this is my initial
commit thursday march 19 2009 you can
see I am very verbose and I was actually
doing this at a conference I was hanging
out with my friend Blake in his rainy
and Blake miss grania is a creator of
Sinatra and I was like oh I'm doing a
lot of JavaScript these days what if I
take these ideas from Sinatra and
brought them to the client-side web and
built on the JavaScript little did I
know that that was like a thing that
people hadn't really done this idea of
single page apps people were kind of
playing with in touching at it but no
one had built a thing to a tool to build
them and I think Chris saw that and
didn't fully understand what I was
talking about when I thought said
jeaious framework he thought I was like
making another mood tools or something
like that but no I was really excited
about this idea that you could build
applications with this simple tool and
you could make something really simple
that people
we'll enjoy programming in and that was
my goal I really had fun and that took
off we a lot of people were using it and
then eventually other people like that
idea and client-side apps became like a
thing that everyone were was doing to
the point there were a thousand
frameworks to do it and that's exciting
I'm so on to my next thing so there's an
easy there's an easier answer to how to
eight open source make a framework um so
it turns out when you're starting out
with open source things are pretty
groovy these are all the gifs on the
including in the presentation to
jean-claude van damme dancing is just
too good so you uh you start out you're
making this thing people are really
excited about it people are contributing
and then you get a pull request or an
issue where the the entire body of the
issue basically is summarized by this
sucks you're an idiot leave leave the
earth and and how do you respond to that
okay one of them you're like okay no I
think I think I'm cool I'm staying here
cool thanks bye and then two of them and
then a hundred of them and then why
doesn't your thing do the thing that
backbone does why doesn't your saying do
the thing that angular does why doesn't
your thing you know you know marry me
and all these other things so you get
tired of it and it drink it's draining I
think remy is talking about this
tomorrow um I don't know if this ship is
going to play it's also just too good oh
yeah there we go umm so so open source
is awesome it's this amazing thing but I
got really burned out really quickly
because it's really hard to maintain a
group of positive contributors and I'm
sure there are some people were doing an
amazing job at this and I applaud them I
was not doing an amazing job and there
are reasons for that I was doing other
things at that time I was working at
this company called paperless post and I
was growing a team so people was post
was founded in 2009 and I started very
early on frivolous post also sponsored
Jase comp 2012 and scottsdale and did
these awesome photo
you can see here that's actually me on
the bottom but you can't tell without my
glasses that my eyes are super BD but
that's Mike on the right up and so in in
2015 this is what paperless post looks
like there are more than 1 million
receivers every week the revenues and
the tens of millions of dollars there
are more than 110 employees and 40 / 40
of those are developers and operations
and the offices across to you but
actually I wrote the slide a while ago
and it's actually almost three now
they're they're building on a third
floor but this is all just to say that
in 2009 when I started working with them
there were zero dollars zero receivers
for employees one full-time Deb
including myself and another consultants
and we were hanging out in this
windowless office akon seventeenth
Street that was also a women's lingerie
company where we just had floor cubicles
in the middle of it and then these
posters of women's lingerie all around
us and it was the weirdest office I've
ever worked at my entire life there were
no windows if it was raining I to text
Mike and be like is it raining which was
a lesson in and of itself so over the
six years of doing this I learned a lot
to say the least and I I wanted to share
some of those lessons with you and these
are have nothing to do with sausage so
ah this is hard because there's six
years of this stuff that I learned I'm
trying to condense it down it's like
four minutes so bear with me um one is
you can learn by teaching so learning by
teaching is an interesting idea but it's
not just about mentoring it's about
really pushing yourself and challenging
yourself to get as much information as
you can out of other people buy them
everything that you know and this is
like an oz mosis type process and being
a teacher teaches you how to learn it
doesn't isn't that weird it's a weird
thing and being a mentor makes you
better at learning new things and i
highly recommend doing it if you've
never done it before even if you're a a
junior developer you can mentor someone
on something this is probably one of the
most important things which I didn't
learn until after I
stopped being a manager which is seeking
clarity and not transparency when you're
a manager Anor you're in a part of a
team everybody wants to there's like
this there was at least a couple years
ago and still going on everyone's
transparency transparency we're a
transparent organization and
transparency means that information is
free basically like you can get any
information you want but information is
useless without context and when you're
seeking transparency what you're doing
is you're trying to open up lines of
communication but if you're not clear
about your intentions about that no
one's going to be motivated no one's
going to do anything so clarity and
understanding why you're doing what
you're doing is the most important and
that that goes into this too which is if
it doesn't really matter if you're
building in the new framework or you're
rewriting or doing whatever you're doing
it's the organization that you're
working with you don't understand why
you're doing the thing that you're doing
or your developers or your team doesn't
they'll never ever ever do the right
thing and that's simple I mean maybe
they will like monkeys in the typewriter
eventually do the right thing but it
it's much easier to give them the
context in the Y to get them to do the
thing you want them to do or to get you
to do the thing that they want you to do
this is one of my personal pet peeves
and pet projects is to get everyone on
board with this idea people are obsessed
with rewriting everything and burning
the world down and started from scratch
and I hate that it's like my number one
pet peeve because I really truly believe
that you can take any almost anything
and really do it in an incremental way
that benefits everyone because giant
ideas are amorphous they have no shape
people don't understand them and if you
can break something down into smaller
chunks that people can actually
understand maybe they'll get it maybe
they'll maybe they'll move forward and
finally the most important thing is
caring about people like software is
people like I don't know how many times
I've had to I've had to scream this to
the clouds but software is actually
about people like it
doesn't matter what language you write
in javascript is cool go as cool ruby is
cool PHP is awesome cool it's great it
doesn't matter what language you're
writing in if you can't communicate with
another human being and this doesn't
matter if you're a manager your employee
if you're a single person you're like I
don't have to care about people I'm just
writing code no you have to communicate
to your users who are people and so
everything that software touches is
about people so caring is hard though
and how to care is really hard people
are basically these walking blobs that
are just filled with emotions including
myself up here I'm actually brimming
with emotions right now so figuring out
how to how to deal with these emotional
sacks is really really really hard but
guess what like everything you do and
everything you learn like making sausage
or or writing code whatever it is
there's a books about it people have
been doing this for a long time and can
teach you so trying to reinvent the
wheel and being like oh we're going to
try this completely new management
strategy that I read about an ink
magazine cool that's great but also
people have studied this fuels for a
really long time and have some wisdom
maybe it's kind of some of its BS and
that's great but if you read a lot of it
and process it and form opinions about
it then you can apply it to your own
needs so there's this really great book
that was recommended to me once and it
sounds like everything about
that and you look at that book what are
you what do you see you see two point oh
there's a sticker on it that sideways
like you guys but it's a really
good book I highly recommend it forget
the two point oh it's just the revised
edition they just wanted to make it
sound cool but emotional intelligence is
this other field of study so people like
think of IQ as like your intelligence
about making rational decisions and
doing stuff like that and solving math
problems emotional attention i call EQ
and that's the other side of things
because people are like a complete sacks
of emotions and so doesn't matter how
smart you are what these p
gone to Harvard and done smart things
have have figured out is that people who
are actually emotionally intelligent and
can do these things and navigate complex
situations and people are actually way
more successful money wise career wise
family wise than anyone who doesn't like
you could be the smartest person in the
world but if you're a total dick you're
not you're not gonna you're not going to
succeed and Steve Jobs and you on mosque
and all these people who are praised for
their like being a DB basically I'm
gonna lie said dick and thence into said
DB but anyway um uh there there like
outliers right there are there people
who who like try to buck this and but
people like praised them and put them on
pedestals but really we should be
praising everyone else who's doing a
really good job and being successful so
you basically breaks down to this I can
do like a 90 hour talking about this but
I won't but there are four quadrants and
mainly the basic idea is being aware of
who you are in the world and being aware
of the people that are around you that's
what it all breaks down to and if you
will be aware of your own emotions and
how they affect other people and how
other people's emotions might affect you
then you're on the path to being
successful basically so like if you're
in a meeting and someone shoots down
your idea and literally fire start
shooting out of your ears you're not a
very emotionally intelligent person
basically as the bottom line people
understand that seeing that emotion
steaming off of you and know that you're
about to flip out at them and they might
be like oh okay or if you're walking on
an office and your boss just starts
yelling at people that person is not
very emotionally intelligent it's not
just about anger it's about repressing
feelings and everything like that Thun
but we read this book it's really good
you'll get a lot out of it it'll take
you about 25 minutes to read so you care
a lot you're doing this thing and then
how do you burn out well it's easy you
actually care about things when you care
about things a lot and you work really
hard you end up putting everything in
this basket of this golden thing that's
going to flow to the heaven
and be the savior of all mankind and in
fact actually when you do that you
risked a lot and when you risked a lot
you fail sometimes and so I got to this
place about September 2013 where I was
like oh this is not really something's
wrong with me I'm like not sleeping very
well I I can't really focus at work so I
was like okay well we need to like
rearrange the whole team and I did a
whole team reorg and that helped a
little bit at that point I was like
reviewing managing like 40 people and
that was hard and so I managed a couple
less people that helped a little bit but
it still wasn't perfect and in January
of 2014 I was like okay I got to make a
change and so I talked to my leaders the
other leaders of the paperless team it
was like look I gotta I gotta do
something else is not this is not
working anymore they were like okay well
stick around help us hire the next CTO
you'll do it and over the course of a
year and a half when I was helping out
in transition things just kind of got
worse and worse to the point where I was
like just not happy and kind of making a
mess of things and that wasn't it
burning out wasn't just about carrying
it was about a lot of other things so in
September 2013 I had a kid I'm not going
to go through the details of that whole
thing but here he is he was running
around earlier around a few saw him his
name is Magnus he's really cute that's
him in a chef's outfit with me in my
chef's outfit and in his first halloween
that team in our local farmers market
he's the king of the farmers market he
literally walked up to people and asks
for treats and give him treats at the
farmers market it's amazing um so having
kid is like this crazy thing that I
didn't I always wanted to be a dad but I
wasn't really prepared for it I think
emotionally so she because I was working
so hard it was crazy and because having
a kid is a lot of work and what I don't
realize is like how not only how much
work it was going to be but how how much
I wanted to invest in that little human
being and so your mission as a parent I
learned very quickly was you have this
human being and your job for as long as
possible is to make them believe
the world is an awesome place right
which is really really really hard right
it's it's really hard because the world
is not an awesome place oh well it can
be it can be but for the most part it's
it's not socially these days it's really
hard so I was putting you know in
September 2013 you might notice that
that might have a line when I started to
burn out because I had these 40 people
that I was managing and I kind of
thought of them as you know my children
and then I thought of my actual child I
was like wait I have to decide between
my children and this actual human being
that I actually care about because I was
a part of his birth and I am responsible
for him for the rest of my life at least
so making that choice sucks how many
people in this room have had to make
that choice between their child and
their work right I mean it's a horrible
heart-wrenching thing and I hope all of
you someday get a chance to do it
because it's heart-wrenching and it's
hard but it's also an a very important
thing at least for me so obviously if I
wanted to make things awesome what am I
going to do so I had to completely
rearranged my life so that they would
have a better life of me I grew up in
Brooklyn New York Brooklyn and sorry I
had to do that and I'm legally obligated
to do that as coming from brooklyn are
no feel free all you need that so my
parents worked really hard and I learned
working hard from them they worked every
hour I was raised by a nanny basically
and I didn't see them that off in and
now my my mom this is a picture of my
dad and I had this new world I'm
actually taking the magnets to Disney
World about monday whoo that's me scared
shitless of goofy so and my mom when
when my wife is pregnant with my son my
mom's favorite thing to do was to look
at her look at me look at her look at me
and say Aaron we did a really bad job
with you and you know she's a Jewish mom
she didn't intend to say it and that
that sounds really harmful what she
actually meant was that she wished that
I she was able to give me the life that
I am trying to give my son which is a
which is when you say it that way it
sounds much better so so we left the
city and we moved to this place called
Kingston New York and Kingston I'm
actually illegally obligated to say
Kingston like that too so Kingston New
York I'm not gonna talk that much about
it but Kingston New York is the first
cat was the first capital of New York
State it's one of the oldest towns in
America this historic reenactment
happened a couple months ago around the
corner from my house the best part about
this was this a red coat leaned against
a minivan and set off a car which I
thought was like the funniest thing ever
but there was an actual cannon rolling
down the street it's just celebrate the
his burning of Kingston my wife and I
which happened in October 1977 sanity
and and we came up we went to Kingston
just to visit and we saw this house and
this house is also known as a van kuren
house it's a pretty house it's old and
when we saw it it looked like this it
was actually basically staged like a
museum and it was on the market it had
been on the market for four years and
for some reason my love and I were like
yeah this is our house and so we bought
this house it was built in 1680 and I
the last renovation was in 1932 and
we're the third family to own this house
and I'm very proud of this and it's it's
cool because I could talk about this a
lot too but most of my personal family
history was destroyed between World War
to you and the programs in in Russia in
it late 1900s because I'm from Jewish
background Jews don't have a good good
you know I'm a good track record with
history so so we all my records of where
my family was from in Eastern Europe are
basically destroyed so I realized that I
could buy this house and buy a
erica by american history i am now a
part of American history and now i have
have this history unfortunately that
awesome portrait didn't come with the
house they sold all the things and we
spent like eight months renovating this
house but the whole point was to have
space and to have time so that could be
with my son and I'm happy to say that
that that for sure has happened my wife
hated it when he had voted in by those
hilarious he said data I'm working and I
thought that was where so I want to talk
about this I don't actually know the
story I don't actually know how to do
this except I feel like I'm on the right
track right so the first thing is any
career I enjoy for a child that's an
easy thing to do right no but really
this book hey what do you know emotional
intelligence and figuring out how to how
to be an emotional person and how to
share those emotions and read emotions
off of other people actually turns out
to be really interesting and proves very
valuable as a parent because being a
parent and a manager you know there
aren't that many differences developers
kind of act like children most of the
time and it's all about understanding
what emotions are and when you have a
child and a little little boy especially
I'm guessing I don't know what having a
little girl is like he just like
breathes emotions that's all he does
it's like he doesn't especially when he
was young he didn't know what he didn't
know how to talk all he could do was
like a moat at us and so learning how to
like balance our own emotions which I'm
not saying I'm like a hundred percent
good at this I still yell all the time
and get angry because as you can tell
I'm very passionate and emotional person
that I wave my hands a lot and sometimes
because I burn a pizza or because I do
something stupid like stubbing my toe
which Magnus actually thinks is the most
hilarious thing ever you know just
learning how to adapt and understand
other people's emotions is really
important and teaching him and trying to
teach him what I do and trying to be
present is my goal right I'm trying as
hard as I can to be present and that's a
really really hard in our world we're
surrounded by things that are trying to
have us be present for
then and our devices and everything as
opposed to the people around us it's
really really hard to be present and
this is him doing an impression of me
literally like he's like I'm working
just like death and he goes like this
and that's probably what I look like and
sometimes actually i have videos i
should have put it he's going like he's
like fat that but there's nothing on the
screen it's completely off but he knows
that that's what it looks like when dad
is working um anyway so but moving away
actually hurt some things too I have I
had some really good friends in New York
I had some people that I loved and
especially this this guy named Mike
Bernstein who's like my my best friend
and we would see each other almost every
week when we were in New York we worked
together for a couple years and it was
really hard to be away he actually moved
to DC to so were neither of us are in
Brooklyn so we couldn't figure out how
are we going to like be the same friends
and we came up with a solution which was
making a podcast this is the stupidest
solution to this problem ever but it
worked it's called beats Ryan types
we've done 40 episodes now and it's
about music food and programming when
it's the beats Ryan types and those are
our three interests and it was basically
just a gag for us to be able to talk at
least once a week for an hour and it's
turned to something that other people
actually like which is cool I don't know
why I guess where were we Diggle so much
that it's contagious i think is the idea
so out of that came the pizza book a
piece of books i was talking about
before is a project of beats right
intentions the two of us wanting to do
more things together we realized that
that the podcast was good but why can't
we just only work with each other and do
awesome things and do things that we
actually care about we're both
programmers we both like do programming
things are consulting or whatever it is
I do these days but we realize that
we're actually passionate as you can
tell about other things and so we wanted
to we wanted to share that passion and
the same thing this collaboration this
work with this other person it's about
people that's all
is but the pizza book is great it's a
great forum for this energy but all it
is is us wanting to be human beings
together and so out of that I got really
excited I was like how do i do more
human being things and I was like okay
I'm in the catskills I'm in this
beautiful place how do I want to run a
conference and I met some awesome people
who also had this idea to run a tech
conference in the middle of the woods
and so we got together and we did it and
how do you run a conference where it's
easy you just think what would Chris and
Laura Williams do and that's basically
how we did it we were like okay well
there should be booze there should be
music there should be non-alcoholic
drinks there should be really good food
there should be dancing if possible
whatever we can throw and crammed into
this weekend let's do it so we ran this
thing called Catskills humph it was in
October John re6 poke at it so we're
going to be successful and so but it was
awesome it was like we got this group of
like about 120 people together to forage
to do blacksmithing to make do you make
book binding to listen to some awesome
talks we got everyone to square dance
which is a pretty amazing feat I think
and we tried to run this thing without
any pretension just shove people into
the woods into this beautiful nature and
get them excited about the world around
and then the people around them and out
of this one I realize is that
collaboration in itself and working with
other people is actually a medium for
creativity like not the thing you create
but working with other people is a way
of being creative and that got me really
excited and how do you work with other
people how do you make it so that you
can how do you maximize the amount of
time that you can be creative and
collaborate because programming is
creative but it's also like it's created
in a certain way it's inherently
creative but in order to actually make
it truly creative you have to work a lot
at it and same thing with anything you
do I think so my mission right now which
I don't necessarily have the answer for
is how do you do the least amount of
things to make enough money to do all
the things you want and this I kind of
circumnavigated
site via and came back around to it
through my whole life because I never
really wanted to work 90 hours a week
but I really thought that that that was
going to land me in a position where I
would have enough money to do all the
things that I want turns out that
they're easier way is to get to that end
result like you don't have to work a
hundred hours a week to make exactly
enough money you want to do the things
you want maybe you work 20 hours a week
maybe you work 100 hours a week so many
weeks and not other weeks and obviously
I'm in a very lucky position to this and
I can't just say everyone just go out
and quit your jobs but all I'm saying is
to think about your choices when you're
going into this because the idea of a
start-up and the idea of this golden egg
at the end of this thing most of the
time it's not there it's just not and so
maximizing the amount of time you can
spend and doing the things that you
actually care about now instead of 60
years from now when you retire or
whatever it is like that's actually
probably what you want to be doing and
so that's been my focus is try to solve
this problem and I don't have the
solution i'm sorry but i know that if
you focus on the trajectory how you're
getting there as opposed to the money
the pile of money that you're going to
Scrooge McDuck into that that you can
actually do the things you want maybe
it's not a pile maybe it's just a
dusting of cash that you can kick around
with your feet and that's enough to get
you through the week you know maybe
that's all you need um and so my final
thoughts is that you can learn how to do
anything like I want everyone to walk
away with this feeling this like I
didn't know anything about making
sausage or bacon ten years ago and yeah
maybe that's not the hardest thing it's
not building a rocket but I bet if I
worked really hard maybe I can build a
rocket don't call me on that but there's
a lot of books out there about building
rockets right I'm sure I can figure it
out but there's a lot of stuff so please
you can learn how to do anything and
finally these things find awesome people
to do things with make things you
actually love and just everything
else because they don't matter right if
you
who can focus on these things and do it
you'll you'll be happy or maybe you will
hopefully you'll be happy i think i'm
focusing on this i'm trying and i think
i'm about 10x happier than i was in jazz
comp 2012 when I was kind of moping
around the pool kicking rocks like
peanuts so i think i can tell
you honestly that if you try and you
make things that are awesome and you use
the inherent creativity that is in all
of you and focus that energy into a beam
and shoot at something that something
will be awesome so thanks i'm erin quinn
here are some websites thank you