oh hang on a moment I got a tweet to get
one of those for your counts here
alright I hope you all have tweeted and
got in your accounts in and start a
stopwatch there we go so hello there I'm
Rachel neighbors and thank you for the
lovely introduction I used to be well I
guess technically I still am an
award-winning cartoonist I for many
years made a comic forks website called
girl calm and it was specifically for
teenage girls by teenage girls and this
little fellow here that's my alter ego
with the red hair known as Rachel too
great and the little fellow she's
holding that's tuna p cats and i dare
say he was more popular of the two and
if I'd kept staying in comics probably
would have had his own spin-off series
so I was making comics up until around
two thousand seven I want an award for
best new female talent in the industry
and it was everything was really cool
but then life struck and I had to get to
health insurance and you know get a real
job and all those things and I was sad
because one of my one of my dreams was
that one day my comics would be so
popular I would be able to have my own
cartoon based on them and I thought well
you know now that I'm in web development
one day maybe I'll learn flash and I'll
make that happen well they kept putting
off learning flash and learning flash
and and then I found out flash was not
the thing to learn anymore and said all
right I'll learn JavaScript I learn
JavaScript I was crazy about CSS always
been a big CSS nerd I know when people
think of front-end developers they tend
to think of JavaScript developers and
this makes it really hard to interview
for jobs by the way just really hard but
I was looking at the css3 spec one day
and I I noticed that there was this
property I could use to actually imitate
keyframes keyframe animation and that's
when the madness started and eventually
led to my quitting my job and traveling
around at conferences and just showing
this nifty thing
eventually I'll have to go get a real
job again but for now animation so let's
start with a couple of assumptions today
what you're going to be seeing we're
using chrome these animations will work
in all recent browsers including IE 10
ish and 11 IE tens animations can be a
little persnickety will be using
prefix-free so if you don't see prefixes
its spice lee because i'm using this
handy script by leave ooh what it does
is it goes into your what is it the text
what browser your visitors are using
goes into your stylesheet scans it for
everything that needs a prefix and then
injects new prefix code into the head
it's really nice but I don't recommend
it for production animation or
production development at all because
about once that of every 30 or 40
refreshes the whole thing is borked so
it's much better if you're going to use
prefixes to go ahead and use like
compass with sass and in that I have
actually made an extension called
animation studio which if you like the
techniques you see today this takes a
lot of the math out of them so first off
today I wanted to talk to you a little
bit about this is this talk is super
awesome because it's a compilation of
all of my best of from every other
workshop and talk i have given in the
past year and three months so this is
this is it you guys are going to get it
straight on i'm going to talk to you
about all the different cool things that
come directly from animation that i've
been using and we're going to start with
storyboards now this is a picture I took
and I'm sorry about the glare they had a
lot of LCDs in this room but this is
from the walt disney family museum in
california and this is an example of one
of the world's very first storyboards
storyboards are a recent invention back
in the olden days when disney was just
making little shorts that played before
movies they would have a couple of
animators that go off into their own
rooms and they work on their things
separately and then they come back
together and it's like I've got a gag
I've got a gag and they'd stitch them
together and then they play that before
a movie and that was all very well and
good until they cited to work on Snow
White you can have people wandering off
into their separate little coding holes
I'm sorry
animation tables and working on
individual projects and then coming
together because you know this dance
sequence isn't going to flow into that
dwarf sequence at all so they invented
storyboards which were just
illustrations like this pinned to cork
boards that they could lift up and haul
over to another studio plop down and let
new set of animators work on it so
anytime you needed to work with time and
talent it really helped I like to think
of it as prototyping with the fourth
dimension that is the dimension of time
so now these storyboards are used not
only in animation but they're used in
film they're using an interaction design
we use them in comics anything that
involves times and teams it's good idea
to bring our storyboard here's an
example of a storyboard I used for a
little music video which I use an
example all the time as you can see I've
got the loading page and exactly what
happens when it's all Illustrated I even
if you click on it have a little
description and image to let people know
exactly what goes where I was the only
person on this team but I still found it
very useful to have all of this
information at my fingertips and I'll
actually show you guys the music video
this is all by the way css3 animations
and html5 audio hang on
and it just loops like that forever I
know some people thank you guys so much
so that animation would not be possible
without that storyboard I showed you so
they save you time they help you figure
out timing and gives you a great
overview of a project so it's easy to
make changes and helps you break project
down to distribute among steam so you
notice the cat walking out I'm sorry to
say that I did not beat Raavan at being
the first person to show a cat today
which is so sad because it's all about
the cat but anyway let me show you how I
got tuning to walk across the screen
there this is something that in
animation we refer to as the walk cycle
and the walk cycle is oh darn it that's
not the right ah that's not the right
video I had this problem last night and
I thought i fixed it not being my friend
there it is sweet got it and so you see
if you can plane up at the computer long
enough it does what you want so walk
cycles are like the hello world of
animation when kids go to animation
school they spend like their first year
working on a walk cycle and you're
really proud and excited about it at
first I didn't go to animation school
but i watch the suckers who did and they
get really proud and excited about it
and then a two weeks in there like God
why am I still doing this it's insane is
like 24 frames just to get this to
happen this is a walk cycle and a stupid
escape button you ruin in it so this is
a walk cycle of the rather famous
character rogue from the x-men who
watches the x-men woo and or reads the
x-men yeah whatever alright so this is
from the series x-men evolution which is
a cartoon based on a comic see bleed
over comics tourney and cartoons dreams
crushed and she's a character rogue my
favorite character and she's designed by
this that walk cycle was done by master
animator and character designer Steven
Kate Gordon whose work you have seen
many many many times if you've ever
watched cartoons he's big fan of
rotoscoping oddly enough but
that is some of his work after you've
done one of these you you actually never
want to do one again and understand why
so much animation work is out sourced
it's simply not worth the amount of time
it takes a person in a first world
country to draw this so here is how I
made that happen that's tuna he's
walking it is strutting it yeah so what
is going on under the hood here as you
can see I just have a tuna dip up here
oh there's nothing nothing major special
going on there it's all down to the
animations and see if I can make this
just a bit prettier is that right that's
legible alright so we've got a key
frames block down here now how many of
you have at least used a key frames
block at least once raise your hands
okay I'm getting some depths for the
rest of you guys alright so CSS
animations work like this you define a
key frames block in this case we're
using uh we're calling it walk cycle and
inside that you define which properties
you want it to start with and which
properties who want it to end within
your zero percent in one hundred percent
locations could also label them start
and finish or start and end something
like that i use zero percent one hundred
percent because i like working with
numbers so in this case we're just using
a huge background sprite i showed you
yeah well we're only using this side of
the backgrounds right you can see that
he's got the sitting animation you saw
me using earlier you can stack these
animations so that you can have him go
from walking to sitting here I've got
one that goes between him running and an
actual running sprite over there which I
use in a different one which will
probably look at in a few so let's see
where'd I go here we go no that's not it
I'll show you that later guys so anyway
you define these basically what we're
doing is we're repositioning the
background sprite we're starting with it
at zero zero and then we're jumping all
the way down its length now the magic is
right here in this little time
function called steps usually when you
define a wat an animation it uses ease
in it's a and you get something like
that which is how very early animations
were done so so a little bit of
animation history there but when we use
steps what's happening is that the
timing function instead of just you know
starting point a and moving everything
to point B it chops up those properties
into in this case 12 different stops and
then it hops between them so you get
this lovely smooth interaction well it
looks smooth because I've designed it to
look smooth you could make it look
choppy I was just talking with Anna and
she turns out that if you look at some
of her examples she uses steps to help
add change sizes and add elements to her
cylinders at the same time if you use
something like linear it would look very
weird while she was doing that so check
out those and look for the steps and in
case you want to see how that works it's
basically a name oh I should have
probably shown you guys the duration too
yep so here's the name this is the
duration we want it to run for one
second and how many times we want it to
loop we could just say happened once and
it would do that that I like him to keep
walking forever get to you all right so
cutouts this is the best example of
cutouts I could find this is actually
from a demonstration of how flash
animation works but these are different
symbols or sprites that are being
layered to create a face that has eyes
and a nose and a mouth and you can
change the mouth to give the illusion of
speech and there's some blinking eyes
and such and you composite them and you
get this this face that changes so
instead of having to draw that same face
a bajillion different times like we had
to back in the olden days of Steamboat
Willie where Mickey Mouse was moving in
every panel that's because every panel
was a new drawing they weren't doing
anything very economically back in those
days it wasn't until the 1960s that
people started making things using a
technique called
doubts it was a pioneered by a company
called hanna-barbera and it was
originally developed I think in Japan
probably by osamu tezuka a grandfather
or God of all Japanese animation and i'm
going to show you an example of it I
want you to keep an eye on what parts of
these animations are moving and what
parts aren't we're going to skip ahead a
little bit this is Ben all right that's
a bit I think like and here's our chance
still nice transportation sounding
events with the invention of the four
engine jet hire one all right here comes
there's not much moving in a look at how
terrible and jolting others the only
part of that animation that's it smooth
is the movement of the mouth when they
had them actually turning and looking
you just see it the animators was like
oh it's just like drawing a walk cycle
why am i working here so anyway by just
moving the mouth you're seeing a lot of
other you're saving a lot of time there
and you'll notice that most characters
from that era have like a collar or
something that chops off their head and
separates it from the rest of their body
so you can have a person standing there
and only their head is moving but it
doesn't look weird it's you want to
learn more about that there's this
really cool video out from the escapist
called the importance of Yogi's collar
which goes into great depth and once you
see it you will never watch cartoons
from your childhood again quite the same
eyes so doing cutouts with CSS I'm going
to show you a sprite I blow it up so as
you can see this is the tuna from the
end of that music video these guys
little head sit on you cute face you
keep mouth right and down here you can
see he's got two slightly different
expressions where he's going to get
lower lids kind of go from this happy
open expression to kind of a grinning
yeah you know what I'm talking about
kind of expression
and these basically what I did was I put
a div over his face and then i use the
steps technique to flick over those
different states come on you there we go
I can show you exactly the code I used
to do that yeah you got the wiggly
eyebrows good kitty so it's just an
expression nested in here and I couldn't
help but this morning when we were
talking about shadow Dom elements I was
like yes I can finally clean up those
horrible horrible stringy divs inside my
animations just put a tuna on the page
and I can keep all that hidden and nice
and tidy I like that nobody will care
but I like that so anyway down here as
you can see it's the keyframe smirk and
the numbers for this one or just a
little bit less pretty than the ones you
saw before because it isn't your
regularly shaped sprite and I have to do
a little bit of finagling to jump
between it without getting strange
loopiness woot so scene transitions it's
got to be somebody who watches my little
ponies in here yeah there we go pinky
five all right so she is obviously
fighting what we refer to as an IRA
swipe in animations ah again you're
giving me the wrong video guy yeah it
will come back so anyway scene
transitions there you'll notice like we
you're watching a cartoon especially
they're used a lot in cartoons or in
feature length films especially poorly
directed ones scene transitions are
there to help patch over when you're
trying to move someone from one frame of
rye minor point of reference into a
different point of reference for
instance scene scene transitions usually
signify change and thought narrative
mood time or location and I just wanted
to show you a cute little example of one
hello
an original seat transition interesting
they can be really inventive that was
from edit and any which is I never
watched but it's no longer on TV still
pretty good though so I like to think of
them is like a full stop between spends
sentences or like the space between
paragraphs it's a way of saying i have
finished with this idea and i'm starting
a new one please disregard what came
before but keep it in mind let's just go
on to another thing now this is actually
something i would like to see taken into
account with more in UI development i
know we use a lot of fade in and fade
outs for user interfaces but if we
thought about it more like a director
thinks about using these transitions i
think we could come up with some more
powerful ways of dragging users out of
their current frame of rhyme which might
be like i'm editing a paper and into a
second frame of mind which is i'm
reading the paper to see if I got all my
edits incorrectly so instead of just
having like a I am typing in the word
processor save and then the page
completely blinks out to a new page
maybe it would be nice to fade out and
then fade in the new page like you're in
a different frame of mind now that's how
I would think about it so here's exam of
them I want you to spot how many you can
see oh oh no it's not big enough hang on
I've got to make it bigger oh yeah what
is oh no it won't let me login you're
supposed to be in the gigantic version
fine come here
so there were a couple of fade outs and
fade ins there we saw that there was the
iris wipe that zoomed in on her and then
we ended up switching over to somebody
else's point of view and then we faded
out so that we could come back to our
original character this is a project
called the black brick road which the
artist and inventor of is over here her
name is Sam egg she's Russian and she's
like she hasn't even graduated from high
school yet it's amazing I am still not
convinced that she's just not some 42
year-old animation troll out there
trying to pull everyone's leg but this
is number 11 of her installment and i
drew this to kind of look like her
because i thought she was super cute and
i wanted to match I made this part down
here but the the rest of her cartoons
are really cool she basically draws
comics and has little interactive bits
and she'd been doing the interactive
bits and flash and putting them on
deviantart com and I'd been following
her work and I was like hey would you
like to collaborate on something because
I see you're using a lot of flash and I
could make something that you know it
could actually read on an iPad this does
look pretty good on an iPad by the way
it's pretty fun and she came back to me
and she said yeah I would love to do
that um here I've got this gigantic
project you take care of it and I did
and I'm really excited that web apps are
becoming more and more widely adopted
kindle fire now accepts web apps on
their store which means you can look
forward to maybe being able to buy the
full version of this isn't as a kindle
fire app one day in the near future I
would like that get her some money for
her efforts so anyway enough showing off
other people's work it's my code it's
her art let's move on oh and basically
for that wormhole you might be wondering
how did I get that iris wipe I banged my
head against that one for a long time I
got really sick of it so basically what
it is is I made this huge image and I
started start with it scaled up so large
that the entire scene fits right in here
and then I just animate the background
scale on it to make it shrink to fit the
entire thing and this is all very
carefully done so that as it scales in
this positions exactly over her it's
fairly simple but not the
sort of thing you'd think about doing
unless you had this particular use case
so let's talk parallax parallax it's so
popular right now but I think it's kind
of overdone but that doesn't matter even
though i think it's overdone everyone
else is excited about it so i'm going to
tell you how it is this machine here is
called a what is it hang on him it a
multi-plane camera and it was invented
by uh it works who actually was the
original animator of Mickey Mouse vault
Disney actually did the studio's did a
lot of innovation for their time in fact
i would even say that the spirit of
animation back during the disney golden
years is not unlike the spirit we are
experiencing in front end development
today a lot of cool new things were made
one of the things they complained about
was when they were doing scenes of like
a sweeping landscape and they wanted to
zoom in on a house or something if there
was a sun or moon or a point of
reference in the distance as a zoomed-in
it got larger too in reality when we
look into the distance the sun doesn't
get bigger it stays the same so they
needed a way to imitate this they needed
a way for things in the foreground to
get bigger without things in the
background getting bigger too so they
could make those wonderful opening
scenes that you saw in in Bambi with and
when you're moving through the forest
and it actually looks like the forest is
moving around you or the the scene where
Peter Pan and Wendy are flying over
London it costs a small fortune to use
this basically what would happen is they
put the very very back background down
here and then they will put different
pains on top of it and each one of these
is a different sheet of glass that had
something painted on it and then they
would meticulously move each of these
there's a camera mounted up top and they
take a photo and they do this over and
over again of course you can do this in
flash no but no trouble at all these
days but back then this was pretty heavy
stuff and they did a great job of it and
then during a hard times they scraped
off all the paint from those glasses and
well very few of the backgrounds from
bambi exists to this day but the
interesting thing is that glass
discolors the paint so they had to use
very special paints that were
particularly keyed to be just bright
enough to offset that discoloration
pending on what what level of a glass
was on was very mathy work so anyway
let's have a look at this in action
because I've been talking about it but i
want to show you it's like I even got
this in German just for you guys it's
the last unicorn this is all parallax
you can feel the majesty
okay we'll put this on your website
don't you and now for some really
obvious examples you can tell them they
weren't quite ready to let go of the
parallax yeah
a few upsets a min disinvited so much
chillin item I know I've let me get site
brothers upstairs I lambast especially
believed I know if dr. D get dis new
Emir he does his dad actually I totally
lied I originally had used the German
version so people will pay more
attention to the parallax and they would
to the dialogue but anyway you could
tell that in the foreground things were
moving slower in the background they're
moving a lot faster that is to give the
illusion of depth and I don't know how
many of you have been to the mountains
or you've scenes like sweeping
mountainous vistas in your life ok it's
something you probably noticed from
taking a drive you'll notice like I was
raised in the Blue Ridge Mountains of
Virginia so I'm used to this scene where
you're driving in a car and the
mountains in the background are hardly
moving at all everything is racing past
around you and I did the same thing for
this particular animation I'll show you
the full the full version if I've got
the time oh I might not so anyway as you
can see cats walking up front and in the
background everything is moving at a
different rate this is simply you've got
a foreground here that's tuna I mean we
got the foreground of the grass running
in front of tuna we got the mid-ground
that contains tuna that's him in the
grass right behind him and then there's
the background and the background is all
those mountains and as you can see let's
see background the background is just a
pile of different mountains layered on
top of each other and they're different
lengths and their background positions
all move over the same period of time I
run this parallax PG keyframe over 40
seconds ad infinitum let me show you a
little diagram of how this works there
we go so as you can see the things in
the background they're shorter so they
take look they have less distance to go
they waddle along and the ones in the
front have to go faster to catch up
reminds you of a planet circling sons in
that regard some physics involved so
let's see you can also do this with 3d
transforms I'm not going to bother to
show you guys that article just yet
there's a really cool example of this
which I may show at the end but I
promised someone I was going to show my
version of Alice in Wonderland so let's
talk cushioning easing timing functions
you will hear these words thrown a lot
they are all exactly the same thing in
animation timing functions when we talk
about css3 animations and transitions we
often talk about timing functions or
easing well in animation and that's
always been called cushioning or I think
one time slowing as in slow in slow out
ease in ease out and here's an example
of well you can think of it this way
when you drop a ball it goes from slow
to fast as it increases its velocities
it falls towards the center of the earth
or whatever the center of gravity on
wherever you're running the experiment
is happening when you think about
rolling a ball across the surface it
slows down because of friction taking
away its momentum that is if you try to
do any of these animations using a I'll
show you here's an example of a bouncing
ball animation or where it doesn't start
right at all that's linear then you're
easing oh my god a little better
are you there that's that's some extreme
characterization there I'm going to
leave it on that cuz that's funny
alright so there's a really cool article
about applying that kind of science to
UI design and how you can come up with a
much more natural feeling interface by
keeping in mind that things move in a
certain way we're used to them moving in
a certain way and that kind of subtle
skeuomorphism it really does make a
difference and how well people relate to
a product and I'm going to give you a
little example of this this is just
using transitions to roll a ball as you
can see it's slowing down it's kind of
natural right but I want you to see how
much more unnatural this looks when I
change let's see ball ball ball come on
ball or did I put my transitions and
feel like an old man alright so that was
a nice timing function but if I change
it to linear which just starts the same
rate and ends at the same rate looks
very unnatural
and you can even roll your own using
this a there are many different kinds of
transitions but if you need a very
special kind you can roll your own using
cubic Bezier calm I have actually had to
use this from time to time alright so
before I show you show you my last still
set here so Wyatt kicks ass I've been
talking to you a lot about these things
well number one is familiar you already
have these tools you already know how to
animate things your front end developers
work with CSS all the time is nothing
stopping you from making things move and
shake into browser you don't need to
learn actionscript or anything like that
CSS is perfectly capable of most of the
things you're going to want to do and
what I've just shown you has helped
these techniques stick in your head
better than if I just showed you a bunch
of w3c specs which I'll be honest if I
hadn't been reading them it wouldn't
occurred to me to do that but I wouldn't
want everyone to have to read the full
spec to realize what steps exactly does
it's a lot of fun and and lastly I'd
like to think that content is so much
more than copy the browser is not just a
document reader right now we're doing
all sorts of things with web apps that
really stretch what browsers are capable
of and what they can be expected to do
this is why you really need to be paying
attention to the sorts of things that
you can animate and make move on the
screen it's not enough just to know
typography anymore you have to
understand motion design and interaction
you really do so with these kinds of
skills you can build all kinds of nifty
little things including I promised I was
going to show my version of Alison video
land I mean alison wonderland here it is
it's still in progress so you know
pardon if it looks weird it's just a
little something I'm working on
so you can see I I didn't bother to eat
I believe in showing the story instead
of telling the story Roz so as you can
see much superior or is a very busy
rabbit oh no where is that bunny going
parallax scrolling at AA a transition
and she's not in Kansas anymore so
anyway thank you guys for listening if
you'd like to know more about this i'm
giving a masterclass workshop on these
animations in october you can find out
all about this and read these slides at
share rachel neighbors calm / animation
power and i am available for and I hope
that I've inspired you to be doing more
with your user interfaces and spend more
time on perfecting those small
animations in the future
you