thank you for having you here today I am
really excited about CSS Kampf so I have
always been kind of stuck in the middle
because I'm not a very good designer but
I love CSS and so I spent a lot of time
doing JavaScript in html5 but really
there's so much to be learned about CSS
and there's so very few places for
people like us to go to learn about it
to share what we've learned with each
other so I'm excited to be here today
I'm excited to be with all of you my
name is Jeff Burt oft and I work for
Microsoft I'm an html5 evangelist which
means I get to go around and talk with
developers about html5 and how they
implement it and how it works it with
Internet Explorer in Windows 8 apps and
today specifically I wanted to talk
about flexbox so I have kind of a
love-hate relationship with flexbox
which I'm guessing that many of you do
as well but I want to start out with
kind of a definition of flexbox and this
is the definition I pulled from this
back it's quite boring and dry and it
says the children will flex container
can be laid out in any direction and can
flex their sizes either growing to fill
unused space and shrinking to avoid and
you get the idea you're probably bored
already
I like to describe it as this it's
parental control so we have an element
that has children inside of it and we
define rules on that element and the
children follow those rules do I have
any parents in the room does anyone wish
that they could have CSS flexbox for
their kids I mean I wish I could get my
kids to act like I want them to and to
followed the rules instead they end up
acting like me and I can't figure out
what I'm doing wrong but with CSS
flexbox we have parental control so we
can define how we want each of the
children of an element to behave and if
you start to think about the power in
that you realize what there is to get
excited
with flexbox I can have an element that
just by changing some CSS properties
some flex properties on that element can
you control and change the behaviorist
of as children depending on the
circumstances so we often think about
this for media queries and how important
it is when we have different sizes of
screens or different device orientations
and we want to lay out our content
differently we can do that with Flex box
you know also think about localization
you know we often think about how we
read and we go from left to right on a
screen but there's different languages
that have completely different set of
rules on how they read text and flexbox
actually gives us the power to be able
to change based on what we know about
the person who's reading it so we have
parental control
now here comes a bad part so flexbox
does have a sordid history so I'm going
to take you all the way back to 2009 the
original flexbox spec was quite exciting
introduced and then by 2010 it was
already implemented in a number of
WebKit browsers myself I was
specifically excited about seeing it
inside of webOS it was one of the main
controls for laying out your apps in
webOS so as a webOS developer at the
time I got real excited and dug into it
and really learned how flexbox worked in
the how to get the power out of it and
then I woke up one day and it was gone
the flexbox spec was just canceled they
had decided that it wasn't working out
it wasn't going to be interoperable it
wasn't going to translate a
cross-browser as well and that actually
turned out to be a good thing because in
2011 a new modern spec was developed
which actually had more power gave you
more flexibility and was a lot easier to
use so we'll talk about why this is
important in a minute but then in 2012
ie10 implemented the spec as it was and
then the spec
changed a little bit more so mostly it
was syntax changes you know we the way
that we we state those properties but it
also added a few new key features so
that was good as well but as developers
what that leaves us with is with
different browsers supporting different
versions of this same spec so we have
some older browsers that support the
2009 spec IE 10 is supporting the
earlier implementation of the modern
spec and release candidate in browser
versions going forward are going to
release the support the final spec so it
can be difficult for us to utilize but
I'm hoping by the end of this to
encourage you all to want to use flexbox
in the future for your applications so
there's a lot of good there's a lot of
bad now to really demonstrate how
flexbox works I tried to figure out kind
of some of my favorite things that I can
use to put a demo together so I thought
I love the Brady Bunch
and I love the animated gifs so what
could go wrong right let's go to flexbox
demo out of that so before I show you
this demo I want to tell you I had a
really hard time finally finding the
models for this demo so I do think I
ended up with some pretty attractive
models and at Microsoft we do have you
know availability to these high quality
models that maybe not all companies do
but I'm gonna start out and play the
demo for you
all right hopefully that's a little bit
more fun
a little bit more fun than just some
boring blocks on the screen now the key
to this is that I didn't change markup
for any of that I didn't change margins
I didn't change patents I didn't change
layouts the only thing that I changed
was flexbox properties and then display
so I could control which of those boxes
we're showing in which ones weren't so
just real quickly I'm going to show you
the code that went behind that it is
very simple
so all I had is a parent container which
is the screen area and then divs with
the animated gifts inside of them so
whenever we look at the CSS we're really
going to be looking at the CSS that we
apply to the screen area because
remember it is parental control that
we're looking at here so to start out
with mrs. braiding
what we actually did is let me stop for
a sec what I'm going to show you on the
the side of the screen here with the CSS
the top is going to be the MS prefix
that I'm using remember I talked about
the earlier version of the spec that was
implemented because that's what I use
for this demo writing ie ten and then
this bottom section is gonna be the
current spec okay so we're gonna kind of
focus on the current spec because that's
what ie
future versions of ie and browsers that
adopt flexbox in the future will use so
first of all we set the display property
to flex so that's how we know that we're
going to manage our children inside this
elem element as flex elements we then
are going to decide whether we're gonna
set it as a row or a column so we can
have our elements fall in a row which
means they're going to go from left to
right or in a column where they're gonna
go to top to bottom we also are going to
have the option to reverse that and
we'll show that in a minute
and then we're gonna decide that it's
gonna wrap or not wrap so what we've
done with Mrs Brady we've actually set a
justify to be the end which is basically
going to kind of cram all of the content
into the end of the Flex box so in this
case it keeps her on the right side of
the screen and also we're going to add
an alignment or to keep her centered so
we're going to keep her centered into
the light the right and so we apply that
to the parent element and it applies
those controls to the child next when we
add in the girls we have four boxes on
the screens that are different sizes and
it's important to remember that since
we're managing the parent not the
children it can be any element they can
be all divs that can be divs in images
they can be a mixture of whatever and
for this we have again our display set
to flex and then we're putting them in
columns because we
go from top to bottom and then we're
gonna center align it so it'll naturally
flow from one column to the next and
everyone will be centered aligned and
have equal spacing around each side so
when we introduce mr. Brady again we
have them set in a column and have him
centered but we have the justify set to
flex start so instead of kind of
bunching the elements to the end like we
had with a flex end for the justify work
on a bunch into the beginning and that's
gonna be the Flex start now adding the
boys was actually a little bit tricky
because what we wanted to do here is we
wanted to have one element in a column
of its own and then the other elements
in their own column so to do this we had
to add some additional CSS to each of
the child elements otherwise if we
applied it as the CSS is on the screen
now Peter or excuse me Greg the guy at
the top would be under mr. Brady because
he would want to flow in that column and
he wouldn't wrap onto the next column so
we added an element - or excuse me a
rule to mr. Brady where his order is a
different number than the rest of the
boys so we set him to be order of one
and by default all the boys are order of
zero which puts them into two different
groups so I talked about how powerful
flexbox is you can actually change the
order of your elements even though they
may be in a maybe out of a natural order
that they are in the Dom so in this case
we're going to group them by setting the
orders to one and zero and that means
that the groups are going to flow
together which makes mr. Brady in his
own column and all the boys flow
together in the second column now
centering is actually something that's
been difficult for us in CSS and
everything that we've done to try to get
something to Center on the
Paige has always been in my mind
borderline hackish to get it going but
flexbox actually has built into the spec
the ability to be able to Center
something top to bottom left to right
and in this case we want one column
centered in the middle of the screen
with Mrs Brady and mr. Brady together so
we have the Flex flow set to column the
alignment centered and then the space
the justified of the content to be
spaced around which just means it's
going to have equal space on both sides
so left and right is going to be the
same which puts it in the center of the
screen so whenever we add all of the
boxes on the screen together we're using
a wrap for the columns so it's going to
have three different columns on the
screen and they're all going to be
centered which is going to give them an
equal amount of spacing in between and
it's going to go from the first column
wrap to the second and wrap to the third
now when we think about outside of our
brady boxes the way that we can
implement this in real life we really
have some flexibility now what I have
here is the Bing sports app this is a
Windows 8 application that's written in
html5 and JavaScript okay that's one of
our platforms and while we're hearing
from our developers is that there's
actually more control and more
flexibility that they have when they use
CSS for their layout then when they use
manage code like sam'l so CSS is
actually producing more flexibility for
developers so our apps are Bing apps the
sports app our news app finance are all
written in HTML and use CSS for styling
and this is a beautiful edge to edge
layout that utilizes flexbox and
utilizes grids in a lot of new CSS
layout technologies to make these
beautiful pages and they're flexible as
well so here we have columns with fonts
and texts that are different and inter
woven pictures with the articles out
with CSS so flexbox is also great
because when you change the size of the
screen you can use your media queries to
determine how you want the layout to
change so if you have it in a wide
column it may look one way if you have
it in a full-screen it may look another
so point up one more example here so
mixing flex with media queries gives us
a lot of flexibility to change without
making any CSS alterations to those
elements so depending on the width of
the the screen here I choose the
direction of the layout whether it's
being from left to right or up to down
and also the order so I can set it to go
forward or reverse of that content so
the CSS flexbox still can be confusing
it can still be a lot to swallow and I'm
sure that you're not all going to be
flexbox experts from watching a few
minutes of a presentation here but I
hope what you do take away is that
there's power in this we have a lot of
control over how our page is going to
are going to layout and how each of our
users are going to see the content that
we want to provide for them
so I have a few resources here I'll make
sure that at the end I tweet out these
resources some of these are from Chris
Mills over at opera he's done a really
great job of explaining how to use
flexbox in today's world if you want to
support the legacy versions along with
the modern versions and then the
Microsoft implementation and of course
the the spec itself from the w3c so
that's the content I had for today I
hope that you walk away wanting to
implement flexbox in your applications
as well so question so I have a few
minutes for questions yes so the
question was are there any performance
concerns that you have to be considered
considerate of whenever you're using
flexbox so flexbox
being natively controlled
is actually going to perform very well
across browsers so if you are using
currently heavily nested CSS or even
JavaScript to control some your layouts
CSS in almost every case the Flex box is
going to perform better now it is
important to keep in mind that there is
not full support it's it's a this is a
fairly new spec that's been introduced
and being adopted so when you do use it
in a web environment you need to be
concerned about your legacy browsers and
either using polyfills or falling back
to a different layout for browsers that
don't support it yes so regions is a
great companion with flexbox the
question was have we used have we tried
adobe regions with the Flex box and a
lot of the layouts that I showed inside
of the Bing apps are using regions that
allow your content to flow from one
container to another so it gives you the
ability to be able to layout use the
high-level elements using flexbox and
then let regions control how much text
ends up in each of those boxes so it
becomes a very natural companion
together whenever you're trying to do
some creative layouts with text using
flexbox with regions again gives you a
lot of control over your content so the
question is whenever you change the
order of elements with CSS than they are
in the Dom are there accessibility
concerns I would say there are
accessibility opportunities because a
lot of times you layout your HTML in a
way that may be natural for markup and
generally natural for a screen reader
but if you want it to appear different
for the visual needs that you have then
you introduce flex box to change the
layout for that so if you are going to
if you're going to use flex box to
change the order of your Dom instead of
changing it you know in your markup
guess if you're doing it because you're
lazy then yes you need to be concerned
for accessibility but if you're doing it
because you actually need a difference
between what is being presented on the
page and what the visual users are
seeing then it's actually an opportunity