I'm Nikolai bachinsky I'm from Bulgaria
and I work as a meta engineer at
automatic we make wordpress com our
company has been investing more and more
in JavaScript a lot of our new projects
are our single page applications using
our REST API also last year we acquired
cloud up and share more the one of the
organizers of the conference actually
works with us I've been working with a
lot of single page applications lately
and honestly I have no idea if this
would if this is going to be the future
in the in the mid to long-term but
actually it's a pretty good way to
develop responsive and just engaging
applications now i'm really glad i was
able to come here because i have a
feeling that people in in Argentina are
are very similar to people in Bulgaria
in many many ways so I've been wanting
to visit for some time and I still
haven't seen much from the from the OCD
but ty will walk around on on Sunday and
Monday I've just blocked two days and
I'm really impressed with the conference
both both the speakers and in general
the organization has been great and
everybody has been incredibly nice which
I guess is something really common in
the JavaScript community these days I
think that technologies is another thing
which is another area where about Gary a
similar to Argentina we have a lot of IT
specialist there and
and it is growing really rapidly I can
see a lot of companies opening offices
and and especially with with a lot more
companies working remotely I see a lot
more friend friends of mine just staying
in Bulgaria instead of going to Western
Europe board or the US and this way it
is both good for for their growth and it
is really great for the country because
many many people from abroad get to
visit and in and all of those developers
get to spend their money in Bulgaria