so I actually went to Jess Cove 2012 I
attended it it was my first conference
ever as anything and i sat there totally
shy never talked to a person single
person so if you told me that this year
I'll be up on stage presenting then I
would be very surprised I sent this
tweet out this morning what if Jack Cara
Jane Austen James Joyce Richard Feynman
F Kendall Sammy Johnson mr. Ernest
Hemingway got in common and the reason I
sent that is because I hope song would
have a really clever answer for me so I
could say on stage but I got this which
is pretty good because they all work
office group right which which actually
as you'll see is not as far from the
truth as you might think
so this talk started way back August
2012 I was talking to a friend on IRC
and he asked what I was doing and I said
oh I just wrote a piece of JavaScript in
the style of of of Ernest Hemingway and
he was like great you should write blog
post and it was a and I'd actually
hadn't written a piece of JavaScript in
the style of Ernest Hemingway I was just
thinking about how that would work I
hadn't done it at all I thought oh crap
now I have to go and write it so I did
and it became a blog post and it became
a very successful post and on the front
of hakkon monthly and bunch of other
stuff so from that came this talk and
today I'm going to present I'm going to
have coeliac reviews from five authors
the five authors in that talk and plus
especially for this talk I promised to
write another five doing another
exercise I got seven in the end I
couldn't narrow it down so hopefully we
have time
so here are here's the mother of all
code reviews these authors sent me back
code sent me back from history the their
answers to two problems and we're going
to do a code review on them so exercise
one is Fibonacci numbers return the
Fibonacci sequence for the argument
given argument which is the number the
size of the sequence first up is Ernest
Hemmingway these are all quotes these
are all actual actual quotes actually
they really are I just changed
Ingle word each time sometimes they
didn't even change anything anything and
I think these quotes go a little bit
what a little bit of the way towards
explaining their approach to solving the
problem so let's look at Ernest attempt
that's a solving Fibonacci so those of
you know Hemingway he's very spare he he
he is very economical he only tells you
what you have to know there were no
comments because he was a proponent of
the iceburg theory which is that the
minimum possible amount is on the
surface the rest is for the reader to
discover hidden beneath the surface very
straightforward he names his variables
exactly as you would expect first second
not trying to be clever not trying to
use any terminology any technical
terminology it's a really nice solution
if the size is less than to Fibonacci
you know he could give you the answer
but he feels you were an idiot for
asking so that's what you're going to
get back next up is Shakespeare that is
an actual that's an actual quote from
Shakespeare
so he kind of drags this this one out as
only Shakespeare can calculation into
acts employing the humorous logic of
JavaScript and he introduces the
characters he has the dramatis personae
the main protagonists are the result
which is an array which is going to
return to you and a counter as he can so
we can count through the for loop and as
only Shakespeare would well not actually
as only Shakespeare but as Shakespeare
did he divided this into interact so I
want to see if this magic scrolling
works yes
so that one in which the zero is added
for initiation was just a long way of
saying he's assigning zero to the result
and by the way almost all of his comic
comments are in iambic pentameter which
is the way Shakespeare wrote thank you
which is ten syllables basically per
line stress every other syllable
hence pentameter five syllable stressed
he didn't always stick exactly to that
and he hasn't in the comments the point
is to emphasize certain words by by
switching the stress to those words so
let's go right on to Act two in which
every iteration the loop two numbers are
queried and summed and by divination he
sets a killing members as as he says and
it's it's pretty nice code I guess
there's a bit of of obvious Gatien going
on the reason he's doing result and math
max zero down there is that he doesn't
want zero or will want to be counted
there so that that's what he's doing
there and then finally he returns the
result to you and then the players exit
and that's the end now
who's heard of Andre Breton he was a mid
century French surrealist one of the
family members of the surrealist
movement and he believed dreams were
more interesting than he was reality so
all his prose have a very dreamlike
quality to them and he actually switches
nouns for any other word you can think
of so this is what we get so factorial
he renamed factorial took Colette which
I presume you first saw an old flame of
his but the amazing thing is and why I
really like his writing is there's a
certain elegance to it I mean he chooses
his nouns carefully and there's a
certain project logic to it you'll see
here staircase for the iterator the
thing that you do you think meant and I
think all in all he's done pretty nice
to hear it's a very nice answer next
onto the Chilean also Roberto bolaño
who's one of my personal favorites and
Bolano has a wonderful style he's
charming lean naive incredibly honest
and every aspect of human frailty is
included he'll tell you what he's
thinking the whole - the whole time the
most personal seemingly uninteresting
two thoughts he'll he'll he'll share
with you so you see his comments are
very much in that in that kind of stuff
also he loved the old poets and the old
rule writers any historical figure so
he's actually named his factorial after
a certain Leonardo Pisano
piccolo who was actually the person who
credited with identifying the Fibonacci
series so if L is less than zero L being
the size here if L is less than zero he
doesn't want to answer that because he
doesn't know how to answer although he
admits that several responses probably
not very nice responses occur to him and
then he just writes the code he doesn't
really care about the code if you meet
his books like the plot is almost a
sideline so he just he just writes the
code in short order and then says he
doesn't really understand what's going
on and then he looked he he lists a lot
of mathematicians which really interests
him and this is his kind of deal this is
how he works in it in his books he pays
homage to to these people and then he
returns the answer he said I didn't
really know what how many of this thing
worked but anyway here's the answer in
case you're interested and he's so damn
honest he's like he can't help looking a
bit further down the page even though
actually nothing happens and he just
points out that there was nothing
happening and he would rather not talk
about it even if it was this is a very
personal style of his so on - Charles
Child Dickens Charles Dickens I don't
really like his work that much he's very
superficial Henry James called him the
greatest of superficial novelists I
think he has a lack of substance at
heart he's very good at building
characters his great great characters
but he doesn't do anything with them to
my mind and there's a lack of honesty
and a lack of understanding I think
somewhere there so we can see what he
does here he is he ignores the principle
of the webinar series in fact adventure
that he doesn't really understand it but
he did notice that every number in the
series is almost exactly one point six
one eight zero three times the pre
his number in the series so again they
superficially he just used that to build
the series and there we have it so that
is that and now exercise two so those
are all those of all the five posts from
the previous blog that I wrote these now
are seven code reviews that have just
been sent to me for the next exercise so
I've no idea what's on these so I'll be
seeing it for the first first time to
exercise two is factorial so the given
argument n return the factorial and
let's start with Kerouac Jack Kerouac
now Kerouac had a very spontaneous
stream of conscious style and he didn't
think ahead so there isn't a function
here like he thank you so
it looks like he hasn't actually
prepared any other examples it would
only work for N equals 43 and he's put a
whole lot of comments in here too and
it's really hard to figure out what is
code and what is common but it actually
sort of works there's a kind of stream
there and then he's answering he
actually tells you the answer before he
gives it you so there we are that's Jack
correct so yeah I mean it's okay so here
is James Joyce this is a particularly
nice probably actually of his I don't
know how many you familiar with him with
those blighters of James Joyce but one
thing he liked to do a lot was make up
these portmanteau words which is like
two words combined and it looks like
he's actually taken that into his code
and he's using that in a lot of places
so this is a hack on the factorial
utility so he's calling it a hack toriel
and he wants you to pass a small integer
as the argument cuz the big integer it's
not it's just gonna blow the whole thing
up so that's why it's calling it an in
jet to hint strongly the small integers
should be passed he's returning a list
of holes he's here assigning it's not
sure why he's doing that actually
because it doesn't really help but
whatever that's that's the way he thinks
I guess he's got the resolution which is
like the the amalgam of resultant
computation now if you pass zero in no
one really understands to be honest the
way the factorial of zero is equal to
one it's just one of those things so
this is Behold the stranger asturian
it's like the strange and dangerous zero
that no one really understands and I'm
just going to hard-code that and then
calculate by multi capables I don't even
know way saying there
but I guess what he's doing is he's just
doing um straightforward for loop
counting down and multiplying up
everything that he finds and that's the
answer really but it looks like he's
done something else here what's he doing
oh okay he's yeah he's converting it to
shillings and pence which is the the
currency that was around at the time
Hewitt was actually writing now actually
when you think about this this makes
some sense because every factorial over
4 I think is divisible by 12 and there
are 12 shillings in 12 pennies in a
shilling so he realizes that shillings
is a pretty good way to express results
for factorial he's doing a lot of crazy
you see he doesn't actually use
functions in as functions declaration
uses a constructor he uses a function
constructor here god only knows why but
it seems it seems to work and and then
he and then he he passes all the non
alpha characters out of there and then
he gets the answer oh and he always
likes to throw in these super
portmanteaus right at the end which is
like whole bunch of stuff combined all
that Hickock lack of stuff that's just
heavy weights you know so there we have
some some examples there and it's
actually yeah it's ok it's ok and now we
have Richard Feynman who's not a
novelist or poet but a very interesting
guy I have a great respect for him
especially the way and this quote sums
it up and the things he's going to sum
up his approach the answer is he never
pays attention to anything by experts
programs everything himself and to that
end he used this approximation to
calculate factorial and hence he's
called it factorial or actually factor
whale because it doesn't just work for
in
teachers it works for fractions - I
think it's pretty damn clever very
scientific approach and so there we can
see we can see and that the only problem
is it's only an approximation so I'm
sure we've all kind of familiar with
this three is six point zero zero zero
five but now he can cleverly do
factorials of non integers - which is
really great now we have Arthur Conan
Doyle who the author of the Sherlock
Holmes stories and I think he's done
something a little bit odd here he's he
likes to solve problems he likes to work
backwards through the problems so
factorial doesn't interest him he once
give me the answers to factorial and I
will give you the unfucked oriole I will
work backwards to determine what was the
number that actually seeded this
factorial he uses a couple of things at
the beginning he just says well you
won't understand these first two so I'm
just gonna put them in a hard-coded hash
and then he gets to the real
I'm factorial function and he was a
humble guy basically well he like he was
humble here and and if the number one is
the argument then he doesn't know what
it could be because it could be 0 it
could be 1 so he says to Watson he's at
a loss and then second his second parts
whose methodology was to look for
logical president so we have had a case
like this go back through the case
history we ever had one like this before
because he's caching all of the old
answers he straightaway looks in the in
the case history and finds the old
solutions though and then he eliminates
the impossible
so actually any factorial over 4 which
is all we're left with now is divisible
by 24 so and this is if it if it's 0 or
not divisible by 24 then he says
charlatans
this is not the answer to of factorial
finally he knows it's a real factorial
and he will work backwards and deduce
the answer but even then if it doesn't
come up to a whole number or so if the
denominator numerator and denominators
do not match by continually dividing the
numerator by denominator then he knows
you're an impostor too and that wasn't a
real factorial and then he adds it to
the case history and then he returns the
answer that's very good okay now and
here's some examples for you now
cameo Johnson Samuel Johnson was a 17th
century writer if some of you may have
heard of him he composed a dictionary he
wrote the first diction or one of the
first first dictionaries back in 1700s
and he had a very famous quote when one
is tired of JavaScript one is tired of
life and the thing about Samuel Johnson
is he hung around in coffee shops a lot
he did always work in coffee shops and
also he he really did not like the
elaborate language his contemporaries
were using they tended to use elaborate
somewhat historical language and he
liked very clean very clipped kind of
language so coffee spirit was perfect
for him so he's used coffee spirit to
solve the problem the irony is he liked
very simple language when we look back
now on how he used to write it looks
kind of old-fashioned and and
interesting he's a bit sarcastic
ingenious sophistry to prove the
palpably of PS if the number is if one
is the argument then that's the answer
he also took her an entry from his
dictionary in the put in the comments so
recursion he defined that from his
dictionary and and you can see a little
bit of like slightly scathing wit there
towards recursion he's not totally sold
on it but
it's salsas problem so now Jane Austen
and the thing about Jane Austen was
because she was in a male-dominated
world
she felt she had to hide her cleverness
from the world but she she did it in a
very like this is almost a recursive
statement here because program is
perceived she has most misfortunate of
knowing anything should conceal it as
well as she can which is not really
saying that she's concealing the fact
that that she knows you shouldn't do
that and we can see it a lot in examples
and she parodies a lot she parodies the
conventions of the time and so you'll
see she parodies the pedantry of the
JavaScript community the fact that you
some people say you should use triple
equals for everything she's pretending
she thinks that's actually true she
knows perfectly well it's not and she
doesn't have to do that she even checks
to see where the argument is and that is
an actual number or not knowing that it
could not be a number yeah and so
there's a certain mr. Crockford who says
whenever we have a we have an ear for a
foreign look we should check for in case
it was inherited from the prototype so
she's pretending that she thinks she
should that's what you should do here
and then she carries on the cursing
until the answer comes up and it's a
very nice we just go back one as with
her writing it's very well it's very
well crafted she's used the self
invoking function took as a kind of
closure so even the caching and
everything is completely enclosed within
this it's a very tidy function and then
finally back to earnest can't keep him
out he wanted to send it again I didn't
actually ask him but he sent sent me
another response to this one so and
again Ernest Hemingway's very spare a
very economical that's how he did it
none of your other extra stuff he
doesn't care that it might be slightly
slower the because of solution he wants
it to be clean he wants it to be spare
and that's what we have and that's it
and here's some resources you might want
to look