hello and welcome to my very first talk
yeah it's named embrace a project
animation with concepts and yeah that's
me never see my face this big and maybe
I should stick to the microphone so I'm
care scene developer at some kuhmo here
in Hamburg and my twitter name is busier
Dave because I love Bezier curves and
yeah I'm a former character animator
I've been working as a freelancer for
about seven years and it's I'm sorry
body in character animation and other
things and now since ten years I'm a
front-end developer yeah so let's get
started and I hope you can see me is
pretty high here yeah I have a question
for all of you did you ever have one of
the following web experiences loss of
orientation increasing frustration or
maybe loss of trust I think you had so
how did it come to those feelings
think about it maybe your cognitive load
became too high could be so cognitive
load was it what is that
I've got a seat at well thank you I've
got a quote the total amount of mental
effort that is required to complete a
task involving processing of information
so animation can fill the gap between
viewing and understanding
that's what's happening if you have
overload there's a gap and you have to
fix it oh yeah I'm first hark so look at
this this animation on the left-hand
side you can see someone going from home
to contact hmm well pretty snappy where
are you on the side what about this here
wow I know where I am that's pretty cool
and look animation so maybe it's simple
as that huh
what do you want closing the gap how do
we do that we take animation so what do
we want to animate yes
so let's animate everything yeah let's
take some time let's animate tiles
let's any make some burger menus let's
animate some accordions looks like fun
okay let's do that so be brave and go
for it
I've got an example over here I didn't
do that that's my pretty cruel yeah so
where am I here well let's see I want to
go Oh what oh no no no no that was just
want to skip that okay I go there Oh
finally whoa so let's get some
information about that side oh oh now
where am I
where when am i I can reach to them
that's fine okay thanks whoa so where
was that start page I don't know I'm
lost I'm frustrated so how do I get back
to my I'm pretty lost okay here I am I
have sir okay just relax so wait what
what what just happened here hmm
overacting elements everywhere we've
been animating everything beyond so I
got a suggestion for you what about
animating with concept so but what you
need to know first is natural movements
give comfort they don't pop in okay and
they have weights
I had to do that so and there are 12
principles of animation
let me show them to you it's by Sarah
villains coma
Wow there are so many like easing I can
show you some easing it's like it's like
eating in and out what I just did was a
transform and transformation as was
going from the left side to the neck to
the right side from my side and yeah and
you need a minimum two poses and one
tween between is all the movement
between two poses
it's a tween so like this here or if I
do this unless opposes this but how did
I get there maybe like this or maybe
like that so I will represent to you the
animation superpowers they make context
clear they display hierarchies you can
see okay which element is the hero of
the day who's the sidekick and they make
the usage in in to it for me yeah I did
it okay
intuitive I say that every day from now
on so and they can make artificial
shortening of waiting time pretty good
for da jman maybe and yeah
and movement animation should be natural
predictable and comprehensive to our
users for a better user experience and
what else can you do you could maybe
create a mindmap
guess what you already have a lot of
them every one of you has several mind
maps so let's make an experiment and you
can close your eyes you can keep them
open as you like you can listen to my
soft voice think about your home think
about your favorite mug
where do you store it and how do you get
access to it so users need a mind map to
about your project and now I have to
drink something I really have it's not
joke and breathe okay so with a mind map
you have orientation for example and
next slide I have an example for you
from a project of mine I would like to
show it to you in the browser but
unfortunately it's not going live this
week maybe a Monday and so here we go
I had this from from the designer and
she said okay what you see above there
oh wait
spoiling
and what you see above there should be
the first state and what you see below
is the last date and I was like oh okay
when I press here this and this
disappears and what you have here these
two they go there okay
and this one goes to the X down there I
don't have an arrow I forgot that one so
oh no I'm just looking at my forward ok
I'd do it again I didn't it's not the
same as you see this I'm sorry for that
so okay this is the button I will press
here and this and this disappears okay
and goes down there now you get it okay
better you X now so and almost like okay
how do we get there they look they don't
look the same and so different so
different so let me tell you about my
story and the story it starts the secret
I have to share now with all of you yeah
I use pencils and paper
yeah great effect like if you got
shocked I had these cute animals so so
that's what I do I draw that's where I
come from drawing 2d and f10 3d and here
you can see my thoughts I had I was
drawing the first state and the last
date and I was thinking okay how do I
get from A to C hmm okay what do i what
do I have to think about and I can show
you the result it's like this and I'd
like to explain to you what I thought
why is the navigation up there going to
the right and not disappearing by by
opacity or something and yeah it's I
would love to go there but the mic is
here so it's that burger and magnifying
button which amplify that if you click
on it you see all the menu down there
and the menu is hidden in those
navigation items too you see it expands
if you click on it is it expands below
I'm sorry I don't have that in a picture
you have to imagine just like your house
and your cup and yeah for me logically
they have to move to the right into the
button because it's in there and then
it's it it expands down and yeah that's
why I could talk a little bit more about
that but now I'm too nervous about it so
I hope you got it
did you yeah thank you
so I breathe again and we go so what did
i do - good get there I did some
prototyping and this is how this is how
it looks at the beginning it wasn't
about being fancy or stylish or just
looking like
the designer said no I just wanted to
have a feeling is it right to make a
morphing the way I did it like this or
did it feel wrong and how does it feel
the timing when my navigation points are
moving what is right and when I finished
with that I couldn't resist anymore and
I took the project and I analyzed
everything every single component yes
and I thought okay which component needs
animation which doesn't and which
component needs what kind of animation
so which component needs some
transitions or a hover effect or a
movement from A to Z or who's the hero
here so I had some principles I found in
the internet by a surveillance camera
again and he says it's about micro
animation not the whole thing
it's micro just only a component
animating they have to be restrained and
narrator if they have to tell us sorry
that they have to be a reason why there
is animation and if you do so just do a
single movement don't do it all
everything together make pauses
sometimes and animation won't save you
if if you get a design where the gap is
too big between the first state and the
last state maybe just don't maybe just
talk to them we have something else
please and if you have some little
details they can be opportunities to
raise up the user experience and just
like I said I got really
interdisciplinary and I was talking to
designers concept oh yeah I see
who's on which side I'm on both sides
and maybe I just show you the little
piggies again okay so where happened
okay I talked to everybody and and was
like okay we're for example back end hey
when do the information come when does
the data come do we have to make an
artificial time thing so nobody realizes
that we are wasting time here or maybe
I've been asking they design it okay
this component it really doesn't fit
with animation and I'm a front-end
developer I developed it by myself but I
if I wouldn't do that I would go to the
front and a developer and say hey come
on how do we how do we the animator and
talking to everybody and I was asking
the real questions who's the hero here
not in my company but on paper in my
project on that side which element has
to be the hero who's the sidekick yeah
and that's what another example just
going through all the elements I had and
exciting how they have to behave and how
does that fit in the whole project
that's that's what a concept is about so
project benefits of animation concepts
yeah they give more structure because
every animation has a meaning they you
have a kind of usability testing by just
looking other hidden to bless others to
elements that look the same and note
that don't look the same but they do the
same thing they behave they behave
like twins but they are not if you look
at them
okay so just kick one of them but you
have to talk to everyone else before you
do that and everything gets more organic
you have a more organic feeling it feels
more naturally and it's a user-centered
way of development and you have more
interdisciplinary exchange that's great
so here are some developer pitfalls as
well because what great power you know
performance performance performance
performance think about performance so
here's the critical rendering path I
know I don't know if you heard of that
but if you animate you can't an image
all the properties because some are
rendered before they like here I have
that no didn't want to spoil it
I have to go there okay now that's app
animate I'm just for Meetup and here you
can see that's where we want to go we
want to animate things where the
properties here and the compositor
composite here not here not there not
there but you can check this out on code
pan yet there you have several
informations it's about performance
animation and so and if you wonder which
properties are these to animate here
there are I get another example for you
oh man it's falling again okay here we
go
so you can go there and just see okay
it's trying
translate X it's translates that scaling
[Music]
opacity rotation and translated Epsilon
and I got a little keyframe animation
for you here again there you go and
reset okay that's my presentation again
here we go so I've been spoiling this if
you have basic animation like one two or
maximum three elements you have to
coordinate with with each other just use
CSS if you go for more if you have to do
a complex animation like four five six I
don't know how many elements then I
would recommend you to use gzip they
whatever you animate with your keyframe
animations every change you have to do
in CSS might take you hours and on gzip
it takes you a few seconds so we can
talk about that later and yeah and you
also have some developer support what I
did when I started to take my project
and just go through every senior element
I was wondering okay um how do we get
from here to there so I took Adobe XD
and make some made some prototyping and
it's great if you want to know okay
where do I come when I click here and
where do I go next and yeah easy to
learn I think and then I started coding
on code pan my animations but I realized
that after why you go so deep into that
it becomes a big and you lose all that
time mm-hmm so how can I develop some
micro animations a bit faster then I had
principal and principal is program which
on which you can upload your sketch
files and then make some cool animations
they have timings and so on and yeah
there are some pitfalls if you're
interested we can talk about that later
how to handle principal and then I would
say go for it take your project look at
all your elements which should have
animations which not how does it feel to
be on your project hmm maybe it's all
snappy could be and then I'd say embrace
your project thank you
[Music]