hello my name is angel angel lopez I am
developer hard I developer for more than
30 years I draw programs in Java C sharp
COBOL and now in JavaScript my talk was
about Chavez keep an artificial
intelligence i am from buenos aires
argentina yes the idea was to present
sang algorithms and perspective about
javascript on artificial intelligence
artificial intelligence is a broad term
is bad I present some demos using
genetic algorithms neural networks an
evolutionary problems in JavaScript for
browser and fro for nausea yes why
javascript an artificial intelligence
because javascript is everywhere
artificial intelligence is racing again
with the big data with the internet of
things with a lot of widget that are
connected I interconnected we need more
knowledge representation we need more
frame language we need more expert
systems for example for home automation
are reacting to sensors that is I think
that JavaScript and evil intentions is a
good mix for this year's or she is calm
is great is the second she has comes in
a shin Tina I think that it's one of the
best conference we have here each year
why I started which our gift for the
browser but some years ago I started to
wrote for noche es noche es is really a
revival of JavaScript and you can write
food programs in osha yes for the server
you can still write JavaScript for