I'm going to be talking about useless
where useless where is I don't know if
it's a real term or not but it should be
and I'd like you guys to invest some
time and use the swear in the future
it's completely up to you so an
introduction to use the square what is
it useless where is probably exactly
what you want it to be but it's it's
taking yourself a little less seriously
it's having fun with code and it's it's
really just making something entirely
useless because you'd like to program
and you like to try new things out so uh
I like to set some ground rules and say
that it solves a problem that no one
wants solved it's usually funny it's
better when it's funny it doesn't have
to be a try to pick something that
you've never done before and and have a
lot of fun and and then pimp it on
Twitter afterwards and people retweet
the hell out of joke libraries and they
don't care about the stuff you actually
work on all day but it's important
because you can learn a lot and other
people can learn a lot it's a good way
to get into the space it's a good way to
learn how to even manage issues on
github even though they're joke messages
and all that kind of stuff so I'm
totally serious in that one of the best
things ever did was release a useless
where library and it kind of just bumped
me up into this group of people who was
committing code and taking contributors
even though it was all entirely false
but but above all useless where is all
about taking yourself not quite as
seriously we're writing code we're not
we're not necessarily a solving world
hunger I mean you can solve world hunger
via kosher but uh but we don't need to
get so heated all the time and we can
have some fun with our code so I'm going
to go through a brief history of some
useless where that I've seen the first
one being hello world pretty useless
program it's kind of a historical
example at first showed up in 1974 does
absolutely nothing you want it to do
it's not very funny but uh it's it's
educational it really helps you kind of
like it
that first step into grasping a language
or a or a framework or anything like
that and so that's kind of the whole
reason why useless where is is a good
idea because it gives you the same hello
world type advantage to whatever you're
trying to learn next one it's not
actually historical but it's hilarious
so I put the Shakespeare language I
don't know if you guys have ever seen
the Shakespeare language but it's a
Shakespeare style text that actually
parses out as a program so i'll switch
over to the hello world example and
shakespeare lang real fast let me full
screen on this not launch i-tunes either
or full screen itunes all right uh I
guess I'm out of order here's hello
world in Shakespeare lang Romeo a young
man with a remarkable patience so all of
this actually parses out and you run
that in the command line and it actually
prints out hello world so that's your
entirely useless but can you imagine if
you were the person like wouldn't it be
hilarious if we could get Shakespeare's
style text two parts into a language and
then you learn how to parse text you
learn how to do free contacts grammars
you learn how to write all all that kind
of stuff to make this work and be so I
mean you've got to have a lot of
tolerance in something like this so the
amount that these people probably
learned is immeasurable so I'll move up
that's not how that works three all
right other examples of that are Lowell
code if anyone's ever seen locos just hi
i can has a variable and then you set
the variable that way and there's like
python and so it's you add the like in
between like give me a variable it's
pretty good this actually i think got
bumped up but i might as well talk about
it since it's here I the
best part about useless where is the
joke websites you get to make along with
them the these are only kind of have
some useless wear on them and i'll show
some more in a little bit but i made a
part of html5 calm this is what is part
of html5 become it's just like a
sub-domain software and this is like
when everyone was like is such-and-such
part of html5 geolocation until like
here's your mom part of html5 right like
I encourage you want to do this because
it makes my day and I guess keep doing
so yeah check that out html5 rocks is a
good site to learn html5 from and then
of course like if anyone seen slides dot
html5 rocks so like html5 rocks is the
google google page so there's slides
html5 rocks it's like sweet thing
everybody's using these days and it
teaches you it the better slides html5
rocks with a zero slides additional
rocks
I don't have a large imagination also
there's html5 socks there's html5 other
words that rhyme with rocks too so some
examples of useless where lovers is
someone will get that in like 10 minutes
so so Adam Sontag's probably in the
audience somewhere he wait in the back
he he recently put out a beautiful
useless where library that I had already
said do this talk and I was I was very
happy put it out so a boilerplate
boilerplate is a boilerplate library for
making boiler plates so we can we can
look at the the source real fast of
boilerplate boilerplate if I can get
there here we go so he has a read meat
which is really the entire project
obviously you so square doesn't have to
be big i don't know if that was a thing
it just has to prove your point and
that's one of the best things about it
is that it you can actually prove some
really great points so how to use it you
forth the repository you edit the read
but you wouldn't want this in there you
substitute in your projects name do all
the work give Adam credit and preferably
use the word excellent get rid of
everything before here and then sub in
your projects name it's beautiful it's
it's a perfect example of useless where
and it actually gently kind of points
out the fact that maybe boiler plates
people shouldn't take them so seriously
hey this is a this is a good starting
point maybe and you shouldn't worry
about the things that you you hate and
then yell at Paul Irish for putting in a
script loader into the html5 boilerplate
like he doesn't care text-align Centaurs
I think one of my favorites in recent
time I I considered not putting this as
useless where because I totally already
use it on all my websites but it's
exactly what it sounds like quite to the
T text-align centaur you have a block of
text and then you can press the button
down here and it becomes the Centaur
very beautiful there's rubygems and
I think someone's working on an NPM
package for this as well so no worries
and the best part is you can go into the
code for this and let's see the scent
rjs file so that hears you like your
pattern matching hey that's kind of cool
if you ever need to do like JavaScript
like text pattern matching that's
actually kind of a nifty way to do it
and then it has this stuff and the best
part is he actually does a feature test
for text align centaur just in case it
ever shows up in the real spec which I
talked to Brandon and now that he has
anything do that spec go to jas is a
library this is how it cuz my foray into
useless where and it's exactly what it
sounds like it's go to in JavaScript
it's a joke but a lot of people didn't
get that was a joke because I kind of
used a lot of tongue-in-cheek it was
right when PHP was adding go to the
JavaScript so here's a simple example is
you just go back and forth from this
label to this loop and 292 times and
then it creates the URL this link which
stupid and then here's like this crazy
example of people like jumping all over
the place I think my favorite line in
here is a also a it's somewhere in here
it says oh yeah because there are no
variables pass into the function you
can't jump in and out of a function
because if you're real go to power user
you probably don't use functions anyways
which probably still hold by that
someone on Hacker News told me once I
wrote that when i put it up on hacker
news that they wish i would get hit by a
bus
uh so yeah malice follows you for your
useless where uh here's evil Jas and
evil CSS a library that I've had the
pleasure of committing to here's some
examples they change the native
JavaScript very extensible language so
let's change ceiling to always return 42
max returns min min returns infinity
power returns pow pow pow random I don't
even know from it returns a random
character based on a random member round
is obviously the square root pi is 3.2
that that one would get me I think I
actually added there's one in there too
that's if you if you have caps lock mode
or I guess to uppercase that's the the
function to uppercase I actually made it
emulate as if you held shift down
instead of actually doing uppercase some
numbers become symbols and like Colin's
are wrong and all that stuff's it's just
barely wrong I thought was good Thunder
hub was one that was like last week
Rezac put up Thunder hub and it's a
github repo that he has a another app
that will add anyone that you want as a
committer I don't know if you guys have
committed yet but like obviously the
first commit was like add more ascii
penises and then someone did it like
Isaac's like add it in like an NPM
module forward and everything right so
it's obviously that the like the gutter
of of everything that is like a terrible
and awesome about community engagements
but but it's awesome it's it's totally
useless it's just a fun thing that uh
that everyone did vapor j/s is a library
that Thomas Fuchs and I put out at JS
con tu and it's a zero byte micro
framework has a hundred percent test
coverage it's really really awesome I
encourage you to use it uses a lot of
the native stuff in JavaScript zero
lines of code it's one of the most
followed libraries on github
we've been working tirelessly on version
2 and one of the best things about it is
now any time someone tells me oh well
did you see dojos new selector is 310
micro nano seconds faster than J queries
and then I tell them that vapors
selector engine has never had an error
oh so so my challenge to you is to write
your own and do something fun it like
obviously like vapor Jas took us five
minutes to think of drunk and one minute
to push to github and a long time to
read the tweets so do something similar
have fun with it learn something new
like use some node library you never
have and put up a funny website for it
so we can all see it and then I have a
special announcement that actually we're
pushing a security update to vapor Jas
as of today it's a critical update that
you need to get we also have one hundred
percent code reduction size hundred
percent backwards compatibility hydrant
test coverage so grab that today if
you're using it in your sights and also
we have a new way to include vapor j/s
rather than put in the empty script tags
if you in line it you can actually with
html5 you can not even include the
script tag all together it's just
implied inclusion and that's also show
me tweet me your libraries or whatever
and maybe I'll put together some
canonical resource for useless wear and