well first of all thanks a lot for
having me here today it's a great honor
to speak here it's such a great
conference the talks the venue the
weather it's really really amazing so
who yesterday went on to a bull ride
perfect I think next year at the j scope
we should all try to you know bike on
such a bike to take to the next to the
next level we can see all that works I
don't know I would want to be that guy
up there but you never know so today I'm
going to talk about bike share and in
December we started video series i don't
know if you've seen it and we named it
the bike shed initiative my name is
Nicola aankhen non-code on twitter i
work at yoox ebu we used to do mobile
consultancy for a while and then last
year in October we decided to stop them
to entirely an only work on bike shed so
I'm going to talk and then show you a
little bit what bike shed is all about
so this is one of the logos we did for
the videos and before I show you real
demos in examples of what you can do
with bike I want to just go back a
little bit in in time and and explain
how we got where we are today so who
remembers the top I Toby Taylor to be a
Snider in 2010 here at the JS conf what
Gordon yeah I mean there was back then I
was completely blown away by the fact
that this is something you could do with
the JavaScript you know you could
interpret a swift file in real time in
the browser execute basically flash
content in the browser and this really
was kind of a step forward and to me to
see you know you can't really do stuff
which you wouldn't expect to be to be
able to do in the browser so last year
in 2011 in January we started continuing
working on Gordon with four people in
the company and brought it to the level
of support for flash 8 and extra script
too and then last year at the jas conf
in Berlin we all went to the conference
and rented an apartment and after the
conference we were sitting down and
thinking okay you know how can we take
Gordon and the flesh runtime running in
the browser doing everything in real
time to the next level so we can start
reusing content building our own flesh
like content building
games animations charts whatever you
whatever you think of and really really
quickly we came to the conclusion that
we should do this up until then
interpretation of the sweet files in the
browser we should do that on the server
side and convert flesh to JavaScript so
we can reuse components you know take
little Swift files and build our own
games and by that and that's how we got
to bike shed the next step was then okay
if we convert flesh to JavaScript we
need some type of API and that's going
to be inspired by the fish API and buy
extra script AP is and this is then
bike-share jas so before i get really
into bike shed and what you can do with
it i'm going to show you a quick video
of the video series we did in Christmas
for Christmas last year basically on
December first we were thinking okay we
need to do something for Christmas and
we have 24 days until Christmas so we
should do something every day release a
little bike shed demo every day and we
decided to make a video every day which
kind of was crazy because it was much
much more work than we ever thought it
would be in the area was really like
night shifts of creating videos and at
the same time we create created little
optical illusions using the first
versions of pike Sergius just as it is a
very very very simple use case of what
you could do with bike shed and I'm just
going to show you one of the videos we
did I hope the audio okay you have audio
oh yeah let's just take a look
we are crazy JavaScript scientists he
traveled to unexplored land to blow your
mind with the powers of JavaScript dr.
farmer dr. belham on its kind of
distorted today we discovered sector 30
the shed it's located at the exact
coordinates of we think will be useful
thank you that person in the world oh
darling so it was one of those videos
thanks and I think we should create a
video here from the jas confess well
something crazy okay so let's dive into
bikes edges the API a little bit i'm not
going to talk too much about the api
because in the end you can you know
check out the documentation and just
look at the API so I created a little
demo on the flight from amsterdam to
here and it's going to be I think it's
going to be a bit tricky to read the
read the code but it but it's just an
overview of some of the features you
have in bike shed so of course you can
create shapes many type of shape you can
think of paths stars circles squares we
have all kinds of helpers for color
manipulation lighter darker stuff like
that that's a nice picture a bitmap ap
is for sprites I'm animating Chris there
in the lower right you see this is our
kind of first version of a very simple
ide you see the documentation of what
you're doing right now I'm showing up in
real time then clipping and masking I'm
not using it in this example you should
see a little star coming up in a second
events multi-touch multi-touch is one
thing which is really really
useful you can get started writing a
game for the ipad right away and you've
event handlers filters sepia blur you
know you name it all types of different
filters it's the star there already
that's coming whooping of items no can
have different shapes group them animate
these shapes and these groups nest
groups if you're familiar with the flesh
API then you probably will recognize
whole bunch of stuff shape morphing so
you can take one shape morph it into
another shape I'm drawing a little text
bubble with movies and sub movies so you
can have I'm going to show later the
windmills away where the wings of the
wind will is one movie and then you know
you add that to another movie and rotate
the wings text phone support then we
have a timeline its frame based or so
you can you can access certain frames
and do certain things at certain frames
video support audio support as far as
it's possible on iOS for example and
this is kind of interesting and I'm
going to show you the more about this
later the architecture of bike shed is
you could name it a client-server
architecture so we have separated the
rendering from the movie execution and
that basically means that right now this
is using an SPG renderer the next thing
we're going to be working on is a canvas
vendor and hopefully in the future also
the WebGL vendor which is going to be
interesting so that's the rendering part
and then the movie execution runs either
you know in your brows in your window
threat or in an iframe or in a worker
them or you could also run it on node so
you can run the movie the bike shed
movie on node is going to stream or the
rendering data to the client
so Chris is swearing to JavaScript
as we have a really simple animation so
i want to show you four things today in
this talk and the first one is going to
be building a very simple nice turn
based game in bike shed and this is a
little story next to this the guy who
made the designs for this game he's
working noise from from Turkey and I
found him through dribble Elementary's
know if you know this side for designers
and we've built it's got this game
entirely using google translate he
doesn't speak English so he was pacing
his Turkish into google translate and
sending it through skype to me and there
was a lot of lot of great great laughs
for me at least in the end worked out so
i'm going to show you this game called
nine men's morris basically yeah it's a
turn based game you set stones and
whenever you have three stones in a row
horizontally or vertically you take the
stone from your opponent and whenever
one of the players has two stones left
that player lost so i have it running
here now on the ipad so you can drag
stones
that's pretty pretty simple now i have
three stones row i can steal one and so
on and so further so if we look at the
at the source hold on how how do i do it
in sublime that doesn't okay okay cool
perfect so here you see more okay that's
really slow haha its do it right let's
go back a little bit alright and so
basically you see here i'm including the
bike shed runtime you could you could
call it or the bike environment and
in this case it's the worker environment
and then i'm i'm just having the bike
shed player i'm telling the bike shop
player to you know run this game pass in
the frame rate the height and width and
then basically it's running and I see
here you know the game running now let's
see and get this running on node so I
built this simple node server and all I
need to do now is I changed the
environment too socket i/o in this case
and I need to do a little bit of setup
and so here I you know provided the the
address of the node server and now if I
launch the game restart I have it here
running on node and now I have it while
you you'll see how I do the moves moving
here I have it running on on the iPad
and now if I start doing this
and basically I didn't have to do
anything but just change the environment
there's one thing to it right now the
the protocol between the movie execution
in the render is not optimized so
there's some day there's a lot of
optimization we can do there switching
to a binary protocol or something if you
look at the rendering messages right now
there's quite some stuff being sent down
the wire right now but the idea really
is you know that that through the
separation it's much easier for you to
build games you know this is not at
least at this point is not going to work
for a real-time multiplayer shooter game
or something but for a game like this
it's really a perfect use case
turn-based kind of games and you can
build something like that really fast if
there's time at the end we can maybe try
everybody who has an ipad to just
connect to the server I never tried that
and maybe it's going to maybe it's going
to work so the next thing I want to want
to show you is how we can use existing
flash content and we use that in our own
you know game or our own bike shed
project so before I show you that I want
to have one short Paul who is used to
flash ID before ever that's quite some
people how many try to use it and failed
with the first tutorial of making a bird
fly well I did for me you know at least
in the beginning the whole concept of
the timeline and how it worked wasn't
very intuitive and it was kind of
complicated so you know I like to be
able to just take a flash acid convert
it to JavaScript and then use it in
JavaScript so what is it here is
basically and I was I was looking for
game as its online and I found this this
Swift file here was with it with a
couple of you know beautiful game as its
trees houses hearts and stuff like that
and I wants to convert that to two bike
shed so what I'm going to show you now
is our project called missionary its
mission is to convert
every existing flash content to
JavaScript so I took this the house here
and converted it to JavaScript oh and
created a little project so here you see
I'm just creating a windmill and I'm
look I'm loading a sub movie so what I
just did I had the house so that's going
to be a sub movie i'm going to replace
the content go back to missionary
convert the wings get the sauce pope
paste that into the wings Jas and here
you see stage load sub movie and the
wings and now if I look at the example
in the browser I all of a sudden have
these windmills running in JavaScript
and I can just reuse that they could
continue now writing a game just using
these assets so I have you know I've
taken the Swift file converted and now
i'm building a little game so i'm just
going to do one little thing just crazy
touch em windmills see what happens
let's do that all the time
so here we have our flash content
converted to JavaScript and now you can
do all kinds of stuff with this and it's
really easy to reuse these types of
content they don't really do that in the
netherlands two windmills by the way
alright so that's the second thing I
wanted to show you the third thing is
kind of related to the water was just
showing you before now it's how can I
take existing flash content and just
change it you know so i'm going to show
you an example of a of some some
advertisement I found online and you see
it's all in German so let's make it much
cooler convert it to JavaScript just so
you see it again here this is the flash
version and here i have the bike shed
version so I've the source copy it I
have it already in here so there we have
this means sales info I guess so we can
just look it up so you see it looks kind
of weird so I have two glyph positioning
here I'm just going to take that out and
the font family as well now it's a
little bit too big so maybe 3942 yeah
that looks good let's change the new to
know new to old
yeah I could not remove the glyph
positioning I'm just going to leave that
in at t-55 to es5 looks kind of weird
let's animate this coffee machine so I
have that here so we gotta one second
scale it up a little bit so maybe 1.5
now you should see it scale up yeah
little bit let's rotate again just
because rotation is fun oh I fell 10
more minutes left it's rotating and
let's do that all the time again this is
so much cooler than a was the boy okay
and so as the last one let's change the
text on their up so forth no let's look
for the four start it now change your
font size again yeah starting now so
this is an example how you can know
create like convert your Flash content
and we use it and create much nicer
animations than they used to be before
obviously one thing to note so we're
converting / 9 and 10 and actionscript 3
so right now you don't actually see any
action script this is just a few Liam
Swift acts we translate it into bike
shed but there's also actionscript three
possibilities and now that brings us to
the to the last thing I'm going to talk
about today and that's tools so we kind
of thinking thinking about you know how
can we create better tools to create
this type of content and like me
personally I'm running around with this
huge laptop right now and it's way too
big and I really would like to just be
able to work with an ipad I think and if
you imagine you have an iPad and you
have an IDE running on your iPad with a
keyboard and you create this type of
content you probably want to run it in
full screen you know if you preview your
animation or your game so the next kind
of thing thing to think about is I think
how can you use for example your mobile
device to then control that ide and
change for example bouncing behavior on
often animation just draw something on
your you know on your iPhone and it's
going to be reflected in real time in
the in the editor on the iPad or the
running animation so we have a very very
basic of version of an often I wouldn't
even call it an ID it's one editor the
nice thing is you see you know what
you're working on on the fly and i was
looking at this or a/c protocol who has
heard of OC so it's basically the the
next generation of midi
it's really used for controlling audio
software so we used to have all these
you know hardware controllers and
communicating with with software for
example using MIDI and now we have over
C and there's this really really nice
app called touch or see for the ipad and
for the iphone and I was just you know
playing around and trying to figure out
maybe we can use something like that to
control values of your IDE so I'm just
going to show that to you um it's very
very simple example I think I should
make sure the power is OOP just going to
plug in the power see okay um so I I'm
running this ocf here on the iphone and
you know this EF like these pads here
and faders and this is really made much
more for audio software so it doesn't
entirely make sense in the context i'm
going to be showing you here but i think
it might be just an inspiration of
thinking you know how can you build
tools to create content like this and
and how can you use for example your
iphone to then you know imagine i will
be running this animation and i just
want to change it it's the easiest to
just do it using the iphone so i'm just
going on two values here and now you
know it's just changing it
and really this would be changing in
real time as well it's just really the
first iteration of this but I can now
use my iPhone and control my editor and
you know maybe if you start thinking
about this you can come up with a whole
bunch of interesting scenarios so
Michael Jace is going to be open sourced
we unfortunately not release ready it's
going to take four more weeks roughly
and then we also will launch a public
conversion service where you can convert
your flash files and then we use them
it's going to be licensed under the MIT
yeah and i welcome you to check it out
and you can follow by CJ s44 release
info when it's going to be out there and
that's pretty much it for me today
another nice picture if the if the
previous bike wasn't was too much maybe
this one is a little bit easier maybe