[Applause]
Hey hello so I hope you're doing fine
my name is Velasco Raquel I work for a
company called Blackrock
and yeah it's a financial company but
also a software company because we are
selling our platform asset management
platform Aladin to other companies as
well so we have a nice office in
Budapest in a building called the white
house so you might say that I'm a
vice-president from the White House not
the president though and it's a not a
good joke nowadays so the bridge between
people and the underlying software
systems that the V developers build is
the user interface and it could be it
can can come in different variations
just think about the smart speakers that
are pretty popular today and most of the
applications have a visual interface now
you need really need to pay attention to
this visual interface because if you
break this link then it will make your
users lose trust in your business so
later in in the hands-on part of the
talk I'm going to show you how you can
use the tool called storybook to render
your components in isolation in your
angular project so I'm going to use
angular for this example and then I'm
going to show you how you can use a the
add-on called story shots to create
snapshots and then later how you can
automate this whole process to compare
the old snapshots with the new snapshots
as you're changing your code and running
the test again okay
so hands up if you have used this
software okay
okay I thought it would be a bit less
but but yeah so I think this is a really
great example of a well sold out user
interface it really made life easier
compared to copying files on the
personal computers in the 90s in fact
everybody pretty much had this had
norton commander on their PC it was the
first thing you installed or just copied
right and for those who don't know it
it's it has two panels side by side now
on this image I just only have one panel
open and the other is just showing the
information about this but could be two
panels with different locations on your
file system and you can easily copy
files from one panel to the other now
people don't believe this anymore do you
think why do you know why so I think the
reason is because people don't use
computers anymore you know what is the
personal computer anyway so instead what
they do is they watch movies they browse
the Internet they message each other and
if you're talking about design in the
software industry you pretty much have
to talk about Steve Jobs and his team at
Apple right because Apple had this
vision that computers will one day be
just a part of our everyday life as just
just tools and pretty much hiding the
underlining technology and it turned out
to be true and I think this is this
image really kind of represents apples
philosophy and although I have an iPad
here it was really around 2007 with the
introduction of the iPhone and then all
the other smartphones when things really
changed because this
new form factor required people to be
more creative and figure out new ways to
to do wijl interfaces and you know use
gestures and so on so now let's look at
some also I want to mention that a lot
of these changes that people figured out
on the smart phones were transferred
back to the desktop so let's see a
couple of examples of what changed okay
so this is a form that was previously a
registration form maybe it's pretty
static yeah you have some input fields
there but you get the error message once
you submitted the form and it was
rendered on the server side and sent
back with a new page yeah it's pretty
boring so now we have more sophisticated
form controls right they have different
states they have different ways to input
data as you type they show you whether
you have an error in the field or not
and yeah we can hopefully see in a
moment it you know it turns if you enter
a valid email and we have form controls
that even present you with a pop-up so
in one word they are more sophisticated
and of course it's more complex to
implement so luckily we have designed
systems widely available for example
Google's material design but also maybe
bootstrap however and you as a front-end
developer quino's can always just use
this but companies today are realizing
more and more that they actually have to
have their own branding their own design
system and inherently that means more
right because one design system wears
this many design systems you know it
cannot possibly be as good so let's now
take a look at one more example
previously this could have been a
banking application and a screen where
you transfer money from you know from
the image you can tell that it's packed
with features and you know what happens
if if the interface is slightly off well
you don't even notice it right you you
don't really dub that it will work now
today a startup company might offer you
an application in your smartphone so
this and they are using their own design
system right not using any native
components because they want to
distinguish themselves and so they come
up with a nice-looking application and
then they promise that it's gonna be the
easiest ever experience and the most
convenient and you start using it but
what happens if the developers screw up
and the user interface is slightly off
well in this case you quickly you lose
trust in the whole application and the
company because you know I mean it
should look professional but this
doesn't look professional and there are
some other things as well
that today make life harder for the
front-end developers so of course you
need to support multiple devices of
course you need to support multiple
locales and slow connections and you
need to think about accessibility so
user interfaces are more complex and
it's easier than ever to break them so
what do we do about that
well for one we are we do we create our
architecture in a way that supports
testing supports unit testing so as you
can see here there is a unit direct
shanell flow of the data along the
yellow arrows data flows from somewhere
the state through a container component
to a presentation component you can call
them smart or dumb components as well
and then if the user clicks something
then that action has an effect and that
along the purple arrows it flows back
ultimately into the state and from the
state the new data flows to the
presentation components right so of
course the presentation components can
have multiple layers depending on your
composition and we all will test these
components in isolation for their
functionality with unit tests I think
today probably everybody is familiar
with unit testing in angular but what
about visual testing wouldn't it be nice
if without the whole application you can
just test this component visually what
if you could render it in isolation so
that's what I'm going to show you now
and it's gonna be a live example so
fingers crossed and what I will do is I
will click quickly show you a sample
application that I created for this
purpose and then I will tell you how you
can add storybook it's really easy and
storybook will help you with just that
so you can render your visual components
in isolation it's also good for
documenting all your visual components
then I will show you how you can create
a simple story a story is the unit test
in storybook or the equivalent of the
unit test I will show you what you can
do with more complex components that
have downward dependencies and
ultimately how what you can do with a
container component that has maybe a
dependency on an asynchronous data
source so then we move on to capturing
images with the story shots Pauline
and storing those images for each
component and then later when we change
the code you can run it again and
compare the new snapshots with the old
snapshots so when ultimately you can
turn that into an automated visual
regression test okay change a bit okay
okay all right so is it running it's
running okay who likes Star Wars not so
many people well okay I'm gonna afford
those who lifestyle bores I'm gonna give
you a sneak peek into the new movie
that's coming in December of course I'm
joking right this has nothing to do with
a new movie which we're all eager to see
but instead it's just a silly game that
I developed now in this game some virus
spread over the galaxy and some
well-known Star Wars characters turned
into zombies and now your test will be
in the game to fight against the zombies
so all right here we have the zombies
the team zombies and then on the other
side we have the so-called renegades
there they are
people from both sides right and the
computer already chose me an opponent
from the zombies so let me choose
somebody well let me choose Bo and let's
fight okay so pong po1 it's by the way a
sophisticated machine learning algorithm
that calculates the winner based on
different properties okay okay so
another fight oh not looking good
so yeah as you can see unfortunately who
did I choose well anyway it turned into
a zombie so I only have two team
let's hope okay okay I'm doing good oh
nice so I might actually even this oh
yeah I defeated the zombies great so
that's the the application now okay so
let's let's take a look at this
application so you can kind of imagine
that maybe this is a component write a
low-level presentation component and
then the whole team is rendered with
another component there kind of has a
dependency on this component so let's
okay so let's take a look at the
structure quickly so I'm not going to go
into the details but I'm serving the the
backend for this application from my
local machine so I have a rest server
and on top of that I have a graph cure
server for another talk but for now I'm
going to just going to focus on the
clients part and in this clients I have
a couple of libraries and most
importantly I have the presentation
components right so in the presentation
components I have all the components
that are dumb components operate with
inputs and outputs okay so how can I
then take this component and render it
in isolation so for this I can install
storybook storybook I'm not going to
actually install it I cheated and I
already installed it but then I'm gonna
just stop the application and run
storybook and if I run storybook evil in
a second just building it's really quick
by the way compared to maybe compiling a
larger application
okay so by default I don't have any
stories right so let's create one story
which as I said is a unit test for
original digital company you can think
about a unit test like unit so I'm going
to go here make it larger
okay I'm gonna copy the name of this
component and then create a new file I'm
gonna name it dot stories dot yes okay
so it's an empty file so how do I create
a unit test here okay I'm writing
stories off and I'm obviously there can
be multiple test cases for this
component but this is going to bundle
the test cases here so I'm going to just
name it after the component okay and
then I'm going to I'm going to name this
test case and I'm going to name it
renegade view because I want to render a
renegade character there so okay I'm
adding the function that configures this
story and what I do just simply yes I'm
specifying the component so with that so
with that if I go back tada
storybook recognize my story and it
already rendered something now of course
this component has a couple of inputs
that I am not supplying here so it
doesn't look good right now but you can
see that on the left side I have the
collection of my stories just currently
just one okay so what do I do about it
well in this props property I can supply
some inputs to my
opponent so I can say I want this name
and I have an image URL as well and it's
if I did it right
no just one more zero all right sorry
as you can see I have I have worked with
this particular presentation component
without any other parts of the
application I supply the inputs and I
got it rendered on the screen very nice
but if you go into this component you
can see that there are some other inputs
here that I am missing already so what I
can do is just copy this part right and
I'm gonna name it
zombie view why not and then I'm going
to say zombie true and okay I have this
other story here so yeah
renegades Amba view I have some other
some other things here as well so I can
say selected I'm gonna say zombie true
and so at the - and I will name it some
selected okay and it's there but I have
one problem in the CSS there is some
negative margins there so what do I do
about it so you can get you get the idea
you can define these stories with
multiple combinations of the input
properties and storable storybook will
just pick up those and it will render
them so now I have this problem that
it's slightly off the screen okay so
what I can do about that is that I can
say instead of this part I can say
template template and I can just put an
HTML template there
just a second okay okay so here I have
the component and put it to some work
right
why doesn't it work well if I am
specifying the template I will I will
also have to add a decorator here and
what I'm doing with this really is
something very similar to an angular
module okay so I'm going to say
declarations I need to declare this
component and I can also do imports okay
so this is what I need for this
component right and if I go back well
it's there the only problem is whatever
the properties yeah that's not there so
what I can do here as well yes I'm just
going to maybe do the name property so I
can do something like this I can use the
regular way of data binding that you
have in angular and you can see it works
so you know this is what you can do with
just a simple component so now what I'm
going to do is I'm going to write all
the stories for all the components just
pretty quickly
just a second don't need this anymore
[Music]
and let's jump over to the master ban so
in the background story book runs and
picks up everything from the master ban
so you can see that I have this all all
kinds of you know visual tests for this
component now some of these components
for example the team view is a component
that depends on other components so
let's take a look at the HTML okay so
you can see that there is a ng4 here and
then in within the ng 4 I'm using the
character box so what happens here is
I'm using well first of all if I'm if
I'm doing multiple stories it's a good
idea right - to just create your
properties as constants so you can reuse
them and then in the stories when I'm
adding the decorator and the module
metadata
I'm just specifying both components here
right and in this case I'm using this
template but I could just use the
regular component version but what's
important here is that I am pretty much
mocking all the upwards dependencies but
I am NOT mocking the downwards
dependencies because they I need them to
render this component so this is how I
do it and then finally let's take a look
at the container component so by the way
as you can see I can I can use this pipe
to to put my stories into different
categories right here I have the
presentation component and then I have
the container components so this is a
container component that depends on some
asynchronous data if you if you go
look at the cold air right here you can
see that it has observable data bindings
from a service well so what do you do
about this well actually it's no
surprise it's just like other unit tests
you need to mock them so you just create
a more class and then in the module
metadata you just use it you know as as
the class to provide the real service so
that's all right okay so now very
quickly what can you do to store the
images of these components well so there
is this plugin called story shots for
story book that you can install I'm not
going to go into the installation
because it's a bit more complicated but
ultimately what's important here is that
I have created a separate library just
for the story shots test file it's just
one one test file right and the
important part in this file is this
well I'm where I'm initializing the
story shots plug-in so I just tell that
it's the angular framework I give it
some configuration now the configuration
you don't need to understand it too much
but it does just point to the stories
files and then I am also specifying that
I want to compare newer and older
versions of this component with images I
could also do an HTML template compare
but I want to do the images part okay so
if I
run this just like a unit test by the
way you need to use jest so it's part of
the configuration if you're not using
just in your angular project you need to
come to your just to run the story shots
plug-in well yeah that's life yeah
and so when I run it it will create
these image snapshots the reason it's it
is a bit slow it's because I configured
the plug-in to wait one second before
taking the screen shot because I'm
loading images and although I'm loading
them from my local machine well just to
be sure I configure it for one second
now the result of the oh by the way so
you know as you can see everything is
green right when you run it the first
time it will just create the snapshots
like that and you can for example take a
look at it so this is the image created
from my component from my you know my
visual unit test that I made in
storybook okay so now what can you do
with this why is it useful well you can
go into the CSS variables for example
and you know you're wondering what would
happen what would be the effect of
changing this well let's run the visual
regression test right it takes some time
and here because storybook is watching
all the files you can actually see if it
found something because it will just
reload all the files when a new file is
written and I hope people to demonstrate
I'm saying come on
spits low yes one failed okay
one failed and I can go here to my image
snapshots and I can see a diff and well
okay I hope you can see so there is the
old version there is the new version and
in the middle you can see the difference
now this algorithm works by subtracting
the two images and so when you're
configuring this whole thing you can
specify a threshold in percent
percentage because sometimes there's
slight changes between you know the
images that you don't want to actually
treat as an error yeah so that's it and
so back to this slide
okay so right so so we took a quick look
at how you know that the sample
application how to add the new story
which is the visual unit test equivalent
in storybook what you can do with more
complex components how you can then
create image snapshots store them and
compare them to newer versions and well
automated vision regression test is just
as easy as running this process in your
continuous integration as part of your
continuous integration okay
so visual testing is here
don't use your losers trust and there is
really no excuse not to do it because
it's so easy thank you