uh my name is jet Schmidt I'm Schmidt
I've one of you it's cool we can friends
um and I i gave a talk here last year
had an awesome time and and so I want to
come back and talk again but this time
it's gonna be a little less brain and a
little more heart I guess I'm gonna
really to you guys basically the only
way the only way that I know how through
HTTP headers so uh I'm okay you know not
maybe not as tall as most of you but I
came here from Tokyo which is actually
where I live and enjoy ramen a lot I
don't quite understand all these headers
so I'm just gonna go fly right through
that but do you have any HTTP you guys
want to talk to me out I'd really yeah
so but i'm generally friendly but for a
living I actually don't program my
translate japanese and so for me
programming is a hobby and i love
programming in JavaScript so we're gonna
talk a little bit about that um also
love jas confi you this is a great great
time seriously line it up line it up
organizers possible crowd food excellent
food as some of the best eggs I don't
think I've had in a long time yesterday
um awesome venue
and really all the sponsors that made it
possible seriously thanks to those guys
one here that's actually near and dear
to my heart is actually google because
i'm staying here in Prenzlauer Berg
right down the street from their
headquarters it's like a total
coincidence um no I'm just kidding I
know that Google Huff is not the google
headquarters I know that it is a German
pastime
it's cool let's go we won't judge you
let's go um but we're gonna talk about
golf uh and so if anyone here plays golf
you might be familiar with these rules
uh what's the point of golf well it's
pretty simple well the fewer strokes
wings okay and so today we're going to
talk about code golf which is very
similar except it's the fewest
keystrokes um and so specifically here's
how everything started in terms of
keystrokes um Thomas Fuchs a friend of
mine too did this thing hey little
helper is a tweet sighs JavaScript
templating engine and I saw the code
there you can see at the bottom and I
was like well that's cool but dude it's
like kind of bloated right i mean you
could totally hacked like it but carry
the one like like nine bites out of that
and so that's that's that's the
beginning of the end right there and
that's when I started code golfing so
this back in May and so that was the
birth of 140 bites um and so basically
it is a tweet sighs fork to play
community curated collection of
JavaScript tweet sighs and that every
piece of code has a fin to tweet this
via 140 bites I know tweets are 140
characters is 140 bites purists only
asking for it to play and then all you
do is show up at github on our master
just fork it enter the code that you
think is cool and then we will all
curate it through comments and golf the
code down as small as we can and so we
end up with this collection of
javascript is pretty cool and we have a
site that showcases it we have now
hundreds of entries which is kind of
cool and i'll show you a few of those
today but basically how this all started
in terms of the history of javascript
code golf i think it started with a 10k
apart contest where you had to build an
entire web working web app in 10 K which
after seeing the next level of that
jayus 1k looks 10k looks quaint I mean
that 10 came foods they give you jquery
for free which is like weight and so so
Jase 1k was a fantastic contest in like
oh I learned so much about JavaScript
from not only
from you know from peter van der Zee
organizing it but from all these awesome
entries in it and so we thought well
okay let's take it down another notch so
that at least we can have all of these
significant powers represented and i'm
pretty sure that we're not gonna be
undercut because it's really hard to
golf 10 bytes of code because you can't
even declare function so I think we're
safe so basically here are the rules it
has to be a valid JavaScript session
okay it can't be more than 140 bytes
which looks like this so after a
function boilerplate you have 128 left
okay and the point is to maximize
utility and minimize waste the point is
not the smallest code possible the point
is to pack as much punch as you possibly
can into 140 bites okay so if you go
bang per byte hmm you know kind of
climbs then it peaks and it kind of
falls and so right at that peak is a
hundred forty bytes so um that's what
we're looking for if you go slightly
over its cool right but the whole point
is go slightly over so that the rest of
us can help you golf it down and we've
actually golf down some pretty cool
stuff especially in the past week which
I'll share with you okay so no global
leakage this is something that J&K
doesn't enforce the whole point is these
small little snippets I want to actually
would be cool if we create like an
actual collectible click usable library
of code you can just like drop in and so
if these things are all overriding I or
J it's not gonna work so no global
leakage also the license has to be the
WTF PL who here is familiar with this
license okay if you're not you have like
five seconds to do that
yeah it's it's pretty simple in the guy
index is at zero hardcore okay and have
fun that is really important is the
point is that you know this is not it's
kind of easy to get lost and once you
start golfing and you know get too
serious about it but the point is at the
end of the day this is a fun activity so
how do you play you go to the site you
fork the master gist you replace it with
your code you teach by annotation every
entry must have an annotation okay so
instead of like having it's like all the
opposite of what you would do in
production right instead of having a you
know regular code and then unifying it
you basically have unified code and you
expand it by annotating it right so each
line should have a comment you'll see
what that looks like and then you tell 1
40 bytes so that we can tweet it up to
the world but why would you do this it's
simple because small code means really
fast downloads that's not true um if
you're doing this for that reason I'm
gonna come and I'm gonna hurt you
seriously no the point is to learn okay
and the point is not only to learn
because you guys can learn java stir any
where the point is to learn the last
twenty percent of JavaScript okay I'm
not talking about you know for typical
inheritance and like any of that stuff
I'm talking about literally the dark
corners the language so if you guys are
familiar with the good parts he you'd is
the bad parts oh wow really applause for
Crawford with Morris sweet crowd I'm
gonna put to check marks nikla hoon
listen um but as my favorite other
favorite um programmer would probably
call it not the not the bad parts but
the no sea bass but this is actually I'm
sorry this is an old picture I think I
might have something more there we go
more recently
um so some examples okay and we're gonna
fly through these here um yeah so that
was it ladies gentlemen thank you okay
okay I'm gonna go a little bit slower
we're gonna go like maybe like movie
credits so since May we have accumulated
uh yeah 200 and change entries I think
we're the most forked gist on github and
there's people have been doing all sorts
of really cool stuff from the totally
trivial what does that pay per day yes
yes actually you really have to check
out that one because it's not what you
think it's like it loads of a purge is
from somewhere else it's like this we
filled 140 bites of just like the most
useless code anywhere and that was
actually written by Malta so you should
definitely compliment him on his style
all right so I'm gonna show you the mifi
favorites like this is just completely
subjective this is what I really like um
this one's actually pretty cool konami
code so you put this code on your site
and then up up down down left right left
right ba will fire your callback right
that's pretty cool it's a fun little
entry but it's not just games there's
stuff it's a little bit you know more
useful this is felix is it felix i think
is here homburg oh you're right there
hey Felix shout out this guy is amazing
this is a loading spinner and this code
is fantastic it basically creates eight
elements each with that little dot and
then it you know rotates them so you get
this loading spinner actually if I can
maybe to show you guys what that looks
like there it is right there
oh hey what's up what's going on in the
kitchen where we are ok uh and if you
like his spinning technology you're
gonna love spin Jade yes check it out
that was repelled number three a 140
bike par slur by sub Z this is a guy
I've never met him he's from Russia and
he's incredible at like parsing and so
this parse is this code that you see
right here with all those alighted
elements in an array parses Roman
numerals into numbers an incredible um
second game of life by Martin is Martin
here there is oh yeah that's Humber goal
no that's good so check this out guys is
the game of life you'd know what it is I
think it's like the most miss named game
in history cuz not actually game but um
it's a cool thing you can watch right so
that whole thing 140 but it's just
amazing so good job on that and then
finally and most recently this is
something that actually was only
submitted last week an entire su doku
sovereign hun 40 bytes
right alright so that's us that kinda
stuff you can build I'm gonna show you
the 10 tricks that we learned from
golfing over the past few months okay
but first I want to say two things
people who maybe might take this too
seriously I want you to know the point
of the code is not to be readable okay
the point of the code is to be small if
you want readable code read a dan brown
book you know you have to understand for
me this code is very reasonable because
if you look at the script that I look at
all day for work it's this okay so
honestly not gonna complain bout before
dates and also I want you to treat this
as kind of like it's like kind of a
warning like you shouldn't use this at
home right this isn't this is you know I
wouldn't put a lot of this code in
production right so but this is just to
educate you about JavaScript so think of
it as like Grand Theft Auto j/s where
instead of acting out your minification
fantasies in production you do it in a
safety with your friends um because if
you put a lot of this code in you know
like working stuff I'm gonna like
totally find you on the internet like
control all your comments well I don't
someone will anyway Terry the tricks
we're gonna take the tricks they're
going to sort them we're actually gonna
sort them by level WTF where to reverse
that and slice it in it okay good lesson
okay so 10 spaces no spaces spaces are
not your friend so you know that space
right there you actually don't need it
right you can actually put anything
that's not going to be an identifier
right up against return or even type of
things like that I was one trick I
learned 9 semicolons no try to get rid
of semicolons I mean I don't actually
use semicolons anyway unless I have to
but there's actually places where you
can make your code its smaller by
writing it so you don't need semicolons
it's almost like giving your coat a
semicolon osku p
oh there it is found it
by the way by the way don't ever make a
presentation where you have to google
sim like colonoscopy seriously at like
eight in the morning all right all right
so take this code all right so how we've
got that semicolon in there how can we
get rid of it can anyone tell me how
without actually changing what would
actually happen with this code how would
actually get rid of time going get rid
of who all right you're behind Susie is
fantastic thank you here's how I did it
okay so make that function a declaration
cuz declarations don't need and
semicolons after them right I didn't
know that uh here's one with document
open then write hello and then closed
okay so now we have well this is
actually a comma could be I guess but um
all right so we actually can make that
shorter but the only reason we could
have minified I could make a sort of
necessarily the only reason we can make
a service because we know how this code
works and what we actually do is move
close over here and then get rid of that
right that's another that's another
trick you'll see a lot of eight loops we
can totally golf loops down here's some
code so what is this cody ok we have
Naren we have I equals 0 and 4b
envisages the global object in this case
set that index of the array to that key
so we're getting this was basically
object keys that works for everything
right so we're gonna get all the keys
we're gonna put in this right okay but
we can actually golf this down and this
is again something I learned only after
starting these contests we can actually
switch these things so actually the
thing that's like in like something in
something that thing can just be
anything that can be assigned right and
so this thing we're actually it'll sign
it for us which means we don't need that
anymore right and as long as you lead
that well we don't even need that body
anymore he's replace it with semicolon
right and we're not done yet cuz the
trick we just learned we can actually
move that in over right so which Gulf
that down I that was four bites through
keeping track at home represent
you use numbers like this quadrillion
well you can actually make that shorter
you can golf one character off love that
15 0 SI using math.pow but actually four
decimal we have a notation for that
that's very short so you see that used a
lot the decimal notation dennery
notation colors too you know it's
shorter decimals actually even shorter
if you use an operator to create that
number okay uh here's one infinity right
to use infinity here in code well guess
what I just saved you like one two three
four five bytes and not only do you get
five bytes for free but you also get
free internet points as which he is
playing so I hadn't claimed mine yet by
assume he's good for his word cuz he
seems like a nice guy I'm number 6
recurse recursion right oh it's so much
your code can be so much cleaner like
for example if you want to get all the
dominoes in a document that's gonna be
recursive right we got a tree okay so we
can write iterative code we're lucky to
get well we have X that's gonna be the
next thing we've see which is the first
child now we've of this list we're gonna
cumulate while see we're gonna push to
this ray and then we're gonna like
traverse down if there's nothing down
and we go over and then for something
over we go up and then we finally hit
the last thing so we're done and so we
return the new list okay well we can
actually do that by just having a
recursive function that says okay well
if the node this wasn't there create it
and then right basically we're curse ok
that's a group is a function so I'm do
you guys do you guys like writing
recursively yeah i know someone who's
excellent at writing recursively you
guys want to see one second sorry she's
right over there
ladies gentlemen recursive writing sorry
that was a super super cheesy joke um
but seriously uh oops hey let's see this
again that was fun Ruth at guys hey
remember we told the Gulf that down
those one this is the hardest working
person that Jay is cough so I stick over
the applause is fantastic
awesome work and she's like like 10
hours straight without taking mini break
so super super props um all right hmm so
next thing we can do we can outsource so
if we want to escape HTML right so you
want to like escape something like that
so it doesn't get injector our code we
want to look like that well we could do
it the way that backbone does it right
they use all these regex is right but if
we know that we're in the browser we can
actually do it a little bit smarter than
that um we can actually create create an
element create text node appendage wat
the techno to the element right its node
value and then read the inner HTML from
its parent right so that's a you know
completely Dom based way of escaping
HTML 4 units for free and you don't have
to worry about whatever those red x's
are because if your browser can't do it
right then you're in trouble anyway it's
actually going to be even shorter and
this is this is like I discovered like
like three years ago that some forget if
think it was Eli did this but there's
the option constructor that'll create an
option element and whatever its argument
is will actually put the HTML like what
I did that with that so you can actually
that actually doesn't work in IE
something I don't care personally but
but yes so so yeah that was actually
kind of a fun surprise or if you want to
parse URL you know this is from a URL
library and node and so you know this
code is good because it's written by
Isaac and it's long it's really long are
forcing your words like super hard it's
like you know like 6k okay but we
already have a browser so it's actually
pretty easy all you have to do is create
an element and instead its href and then
you can read any property of it cuz it
just like the location object will parse
that for you right so that's like a cool
way to save code number for introspect
okay i'm gonna get all bro Graham Ronnie
right there with my favorite bro
amer is that so uh you know you got the
red bull it's rectal in twenty-four
seven uh and so let's uh let's grok it
let's see what it's got take the string
prototype get the own property names
since you we got oh look at this list I
know these things out man slice totally
use at all time care at totally value of
oh my god awesome search yet a search it
totally wait what huh what's this what's
a home this stuff at the bottom we suck
I'm sorry I'm sorry yo sup but note is
your homie cuz uh it'll say sup yo go
Matt the brow
yes there are all of these like relics
from the 90s that lurk on the string
prototype so you sub sub you can beg you
can small you can bold you canít Alex
you can strike you can font color you
can font size and any size I guess and
you can anchor and actually you can link
and I've used this there is a 140 by
century that will turn a tweet into
valid HTML it'll take any link any
mention or any hashtag and put any
channel for you we use that function do
it that was actually very helpful and
then come on you could not you could do
with that blank like what blink were you
guys thinking it's crazy yeah it's the
most fascinating relic from the 90s I've
seen in a long time since the hit single
Chumbawamba tub-thumping from 1997 I
believe okay so and programming thank
you there were three coerce uh so if you
want to get a uuid you know these things
look like here's twenty of them for free
feel free to use that in your code
that's a freebie if you want more talk
to me later this is version 4 ok so you
ideas all these specifications and they
have to do special stuff a version for
says basically almost all these things
are just random numbers so if you just
have random numbers it's okay except for
a few places a few exceptions so I was
like okay I wrote this code and I was
like 000 blah blah blah and I'm just
replace all the zeros of random numbers
using this ring place function but then
this guy subzi came along and he's like
no do you check it out look what I can
do change all has changed the first zero
to one each one of those things all
right fine that same length okay now how
to string and then take a number right
all right so it's longer now what are
you doing okay well alright okay so now
he's using the dinner invitation that's
cool and you're starting with a string
so everything gets coerced into a string
there's likely cool now we can do a
hyphen and then a thousand alright cool
but you actually can turn a thousand
back to the 123 but then with the Chi
Fionn it doesn't even need to be hyphen
you can coerce a negative number and
they'll get the hyphen for free
it's crazy this guy's crazy it's awesome
and you just keep doing that oops sorry
and you got that thing all the way down
that is just kind of tiny anyway so that
was very very surprising number two you
have to exploit um so here are all the
operators in Java Script love some of
these guys you're gonna have to really
just exploit the heck out of these guys
they will do a lot of work for you
because they're tiny you want them in
your code so can anyone tell me who can
guess my favorite operator up there huh
not comma I'm sorry it's the tilde hey
seriously the tilde is the smoothest of
the operators well I'm glad she had hits
here too because I was worried about
that um it means it's a bitwise not okay
and if you know what that means you are
way ahead of me because I didn't it
inverts the bits of its operand all
right whatever here's what it does okay
in layman's terms gonna do uh it turns
anything into a number it's like a plus
sign will have na n if it's not an
actual number this thing will number
anything right I'll turn it into a zero
if it's not a number okay then it'll add
one and then it will negate it right
it's so like why is that useful well
actually we can do some cool things with
that by kind of abusing it so here's
basically what it looks like right so
till the 0 negative 1 you can see the
pattern here right but this is the
coolest property is that if you put it
undefined I'll actually it'll be
negative one so you can use that to
floor instead of using mass floor you
can use a double dildo and I'm sure Alex
exum has a cute word for that operator I
should ask him about that um that one
gets used a lot you can also use 0 bar
which is cool but also the one you see a
lot in in 140 bites introduces the
ghetto operator which is right there
sorry too ghetto iterator it's right
there this thing is crazy because it
does not care that your variable has not
been assigned yet it does not care and
so it'll just keep adding one so
basically it like okay but the number is
zero it'll turn it into a negative one
but I'll negate it it starts at one so
basically the first time you do this
it'll set to one
time you execute this thing here it'll
up one right on them so we actually use
this in the JSON p code for 1 40 bytes
okay check this out this is crazy okay
so you have a function with
document.body.appendchild create an
element script fine set the source equal
to a which is the original URL + C which
we you know which we are setting to D
which was script so we can name it plus
and here's the crazy part ETA equals
negative tilde a okay so he is the
function that actually we're rewriting
right now and a is some random property
that we never ever signed so this thing
never knows if it's if it's the first
time it's been called or not right and
saves the state and so this way we don't
care just like call this thing as many
times if you want each time it'll do
it'll set the callback with this JSON
PETA script one script to script
threescore 45 those can easily but
here's the number-one dirtiest tack and
this was last week and this is actually
Felix also in back all right
so this is the su doku solver this
solves your Sudokus for you so you can
stop sitting on the train or whatever in
doing them just you know fire this up in
your browser all right can anyone tell
me what is funky about this code oh come
on not you yeah you'll get yours later
anyone all right here's the thing see
that you on the second line at the end
what is that we haven't defined that so
what happens when you try to accessing
you haven't defined right well you
should fire up node you type units like
reference area you was not to find okay
so here's we're doing we're actually
putting that you there because you get a
reference ever to stop the iterations
for cursive iteration rights recursive
and so we didn't have enough characters
like a hundred thirty eight characters
we'd enough to actually stop so we just
throw so like you actually to use this
to no clue solver you have to wrap it in
try catch
Felix back there nice what Felix um
lumberg represent and so so you can
throw in one bite was kind of cool but
what if you're worried that like the use
this function elsewhere what if you is
already defined then what then it's not
gonna throw well if anyone can solve
this problem it's you guys cuz I have to
do that moon loud let's do exactly yes
probably the the chances are there's a
variable with that e is probably not
very high so um so that's that's that's
140 x to the top 10 stupid tricks for 1
40 bytes that we learned so we have the
site that has all these things and you
can actually see them you can reuse them
if you want and we have a leaderboard
that shows you all these people many of
whom are here who contributed to this
project what's really cool about this
that I like though is that it's
completely dog fruited right so thanks
to that guy over there Alex cloths can I
just get a random puzzle lumsden
wouldn't do that but their days we
actually reuse a lot of these entries to
build the site itself so the site itself
is a single page app that's made up of a
lot of those entries which is really
cool um and you can tell in the source
code it's pretty obvious
when you get to the bottom um but yeah
that's that's kind of cool and so what
we've done is we've taken all of his
golfing advice every time we discover a
new nugget we put it in the wiki let me
actually show what that looks like so
Eva waked page um that game of life
still running that's crazy um yeah so
like all these things all these tricks
so you can actually check those out it's
kind of cool and then if we have a wish
list so if you want to check out you're
gonna add something like I think someone
could do this and they'll try it let me
do this with a lot of es five ish
polyfills disclaimer ish polyfills uh
and we actually we golfed base64
encoding down what to like like sub 100
territory um that was right pretty cool
and so now what how much time do I have
is it written somewhere three minutes oh
sweet all right uh well so basically I
guess I'm out of time which would a
shame I've no slides left but there's a
few things I'm working on that I thought
was kind of cool you should check out
the first is kibbe this is something I
intended to launch your rent at a time
but kibbe is ajs 1k web framework does
everything you need is templating json p
and a router and escaping and all that
stuff and so you can create a very tiny
web app with that and it's completely
self loathing which is pretty cool I
also wrote name-drop which is an
incredibly crazy thing that basically
it's of one function that's a hundred
bites and you give it anything and it
will iterate through all the keys and
it'll basically scrunch them down to two
bites of JavaScript valid JavaScript
identifier and then you can use that to
not ever mention so if you have like
create document fragment you just give
document to this function and it'll
actually hash that down two bytes so
it's accessible by two bytes I'm not
sure whether this actually saves you buy
some long run if you're gossiping but
it's kind of a cool experiment that I'm
gonna continue another thing you should
definitely check out his jazz crush a
Jess crush this is poor man's gzip it's
fantastic it basically it almost it look
it's like it's basically a very similar
algorithm that just basically takes your
code and just totally squashes it it
doesn't actually do it a JavaScript
level does it the string level so it's
actually very very it gets your job
they'll save you like 500 bites on the
jace one pan for
and so you'll see a lot of these days
one kind of entries actually use that
which is cool and finally my favorite
before you crush you gotta uglify and
then together you can ugly crush and so
above is the library and below is you
know is Marines awesome thing that he's
hosting that lets you do it in line and
so that's it thank you guys for
listening
any questions oh no oh no Jed where does
your fascination with small things come
from I live in Japan dude this is like
it's so nice cuz like it's finally I
don't have to be the tallest guy at the
Congress anymore yeah and I get the
enjoyment of having to pee up into the
urinal just kind of new thing for me but
that needs your question okay any other
questions awesome thank you guys very
much psych bitwise not what's up are you
looking at 140 bites the characters can
I do like a full bite you're a UDF
character so I guess you got here late
now I'm sorry um it's a we're keeping it
pure we're keeping it keeping the pipes
because uh yeah we're trying to solve a
problem think the thing about Jason 1k
it's really cool but like if the thing
is if everyone starts everyone basically
what I mean it doesn't make sense not to
low Jays crush before whereas the 140
bite is a really cool level to not have
any of that infrastructure you can
actually use me as death it's not gonna
come in handy because by the time you
have this function that squashes your
stuff you only have 40 bytes left and so
want to keep it super small and I think
it's actually a good sweet spot for just
like straight up code that's not
pretreated at all but yeah so it's bites
anything else final answer all right
guys