hi everyone my name is tobias funke lips
time and I'm working for a company
called uke Cebu and what we are doing
we're developing mobile applications
with the open web technologies and i
will show you today what we did the last
year and i want to show you an
application that we pushed to several
devices and as you can see here on this
picture already we have a simple
application that we push to the all
these devices there you have for example
a blackberry device you have a Windows
Mobile you have and this is a vodafone
device and also palm pre and all others
and i will show you our experience we
had with developing for all these
different platforms and yes version 1 is
mobile sorry windows mobile it's worse
than 6.5 so yeah all other versions
before you don't want to support yeah so
but before I really start into
explaining how we did that i want to
show you more the landscape of the
mobile world and its really really
blurry at the moment and here for
example you see there is a weapon you
can't with the URL but this is a website
that is listing all the app stores that
are available and in july two thousand
nine there were 14 stores where you can
place your weapon and in September 2009
it already were 23 stores and I looked
it up yesterday and we already are we
already have
for stores where we can or where we have
to push our apps too if we want to reach
all the devices so when you want to
write applications for all these devices
it's really hard to do that if you do it
natively so here for example for the
iphone you have to learn objective-c for
the nokia devices you have to learn
symbian c and this is going on and it's
really a pain if you have to use all
this programming language just to build
one in the same app so in this going on
but there's HTML and it's yeah it's the
engine of the web and why we've chosen
HTML was mainly because yeah there are
so many depths out there and it's there
the potential to write applications for
mobile devices with this open technology
is really there are so many people doing
that then it's also really easy to write
yeah it's common easy to test will have
all the test tools already there with
file back and all everything and we have
a standard for that and yeah widely
spread so when did all that stuff
started with with the airpipe I think it
started with the iphone and what the
iphone already came out with wasn't
really impressive browser and where you
can do really impressive things and this
is a comment by tony allen is a mobile
analyst and he's saying that seventy one
percent of all phones have a more modern
XHTML web browser what is meaning by
that is that there are also some
browsers out there that just support the
wa p standard but at least seventy one
percent that's really huge huge amount
of mobile phones that support or have a
good browser so yeah here's the comment
it so and one other interesting thing
we've seen is there's a company who is
building apps that have that aren't
allowed to get into the app store
because of their topic they want to
present and they really have an interest
in concept how they get around the App
Store so basically it's just that you go
through a URL and what they are showing
is really like an animated gif showing
okay here press the plus sign and add it
to your home screen and when you add it
to your own home screen it these this
application really feels like like like
a native application there's no
difference anymore what they also did of
course is here in that case they
implement their own payment system so it
was just a pop-up way and your credit
card information and then it's
installing an app for you but it's all
based on HTML CSS and JavaScript nothing
natively so once again here HTML works
really everywhere and it's really it's a
low-hanging fruit to support all to use
HTML to write applications with that so
you I think you wonder about the the
topic of that talk about what is what is
an html5 app and I will try to explain
all the different standards out there
and what I mean by calling apps that run
on html5 or HTML or coined that that
term so what we did to ride event ninja
this this was our first website and we
wanted to have a spot where we show all
events we are attending the next time
and we thought yeah it would be a good
idea to just place it on a mobile device
and have it available there of course
you can say yeah you can just link it to
a website but then it's not
easy accessible as you went as you place
it in an app store so the question is
how we did that so there are different
types of apps that that can be on a
device they can be pre-installed they
can be native apps that we're pushed in
an app store you can have a website
where you have your application running
but of course when you have it on a
website the capabilities to access
native functionalities on the phone are
really limited so it just can access for
example geolocation on the iphone and
the S or no you can't get the estimator
but it's really not as much as you want
or you can do more with that and there
are html5 apps and the XS for for the
furthermore of all the device specific
features are of course depending on the
run time I think you all heard about
phonegap and it's allowing access to
more functionalities on the phone and i
will show you some other things that
also enable of access to some Native
functionalities so I go into detail so
here's the device what we have there
it's really it's basically you have in
something like an index.html you have a
simple style a style sheet and then you
have any I ex-library out there and you
have a database that is feeding these
events and what you then do is you sip
it up you see all the files up and what
you then place in is in configuration
file a config xml and you add an icon
and this is what you get out of there
it's a w3c widget it's standardized so
it standardized how you can pack HTML
CSS JavaScript together and deploy it on
several devices
and you can really just pick that w3c
this zip file you created and put it
into opera and test it there if you want
to because they have a native runtime
for w3c witches so then you're ready for
that and can use it so can you really
use the w3c widget already on any phone
phone so yeah you can there are some
devices that have these native
capabilities to run w3c with widgets so
one is this is a Vodafone device that is
that already has that functionality on
board so you just can send a widget w3c
widget to that device and you can run it
there so yeah and of course you have
HTML native support on the palm pre but
the packaging there is completely
different so I will go into that later
so yeah you have these native
capabilities but palm really is not the
not supporting the w3c widget yet I
don't know what their plan is to support
that then you have native support on
Android nokia with the Opera runtime
there's a w3c widget runtime from opera
and you just have to install or you can
install it on nuclear several nokia
devices and also an android and
meanwhile i think also on windows mobile
so here you see these are all devices
that already support w3c widgets and
interesting is that Microsoft started to
support w3c widgets since windows mobile
6.5 so you also just have to pick your
widget file and place it on a device and
you can also place it in any app store
and the same is for the blackberry
device since blackberry operating system
five-point oh you can also place w3c
which it's there
so yeah and of course the iphone and
palm tree and i really have the best
HTML support yeah and if you use that
technology to write a w3c widget what
you get really for free is a Facebook
widget if you want to write that
dashboard widget website widget TV
widget opera for example are I've seen
it at the mwc conference they showed an
opera runtime that is running on a TV or
wec runtime and its really really
interesting just to get just HTML CSS
JavaScript on every device that is out
there that it has a screen so yeah here
this is a widget runtime on the bottom
and also here on our website we're using
that we use it on a DOTA campus side and
here it's running on an iphone so but
also what i mentioned before about
native functionalities a phone is also
like it's a camera you have a camera on
on nearly every device you have
compassed sometimes you have a calendar
that you use and a lot more native
functionalities you want to use when you
want to when you write your app so there
are really multiple ways to get that
native functionalities into your w3c
widget or any other packaging solution
that is out there so there's there's
free i would say competing specs out
there there's a consortium called Jill
that are defining aspect how to or they
they have written a spec how to access
native functionalities from JavaScript
and also there's another consortium they
also started to implement that it's
funny to see that and and I don't
understand why they don't really
work together and they're also defining
a standard for that and there's
meanwhile a w3c group that is trying to
go and get all that api's out there and
bring it together to a good standard and
what we also have is of course phonegap
they have their own standard how they
access functionalities from from there
on time so these are all and also nokia
wrt polym webos they all defined their
own api for the same thing it's not it's
always just about I want to get access
to the camera I want to see what the
estimator is and all these things and
I've written down below there's also
Google Chrome OS I think they also will
have something like native
functionalities they want to use and may
I hope so that they they use any
standard standard that is already
existing and as you can see it's really
getting complex if you want to right now
an application even if its HTML in HTML
application and that is using just
making a picture with your app so I hope
in the future we will collaborate more
together and find a way or a good API
for accessing native functionalities so
when you really look at that which
platforms or phones support the
different standards as you can see w3c
spec is supported by a nokia runtime
then of course nokyo wrt they have that
standards in several years it's also
running on a nokia s60 device then
there's appcelerator they support
currently iphone android I don't know
how far they are with blackberry but I
think soon they will have something like
that then of course yeah phonegap
bonilla be supporting a lot of devices
and maybe it's the right way to
to program applications now and use
their existing API because they already
support so many devices and I don't know
what phonegap is doing to work together
with one night or jill but i think we
will see that in the future so but what
is interesting about phone game is that
their goal is that they are not existent
so this is what we really should aim for
that we just can access that api or this
packaging that it's phonegap is doing
and that it's easily working and less
complex as is now so but yeah you you
see a table I think it's half a year ago
they already supported all the features
on the iphone they wanted to support and
here for the Android the context support
was missing and since yeah it's open
source you see the blackberry the
BlackBerry device is now better
supported and you can get an HTML html5
app also on blackberry with the phonegap
wrapper so and here are more there's a
table what they also support for native
capabilities and this will all will
change more in the future and we will
see which devices will support which
feature so what also is interesting to
see how big such an application is and
we took our event ninja application and
in total the file that we place in the
app store was a 300 kilobyte and our
JavaScript HTML and CSS was 120 k and if
you subtract that you really just have a
footprint of 200 to 40k for phonegap so
it's really really small so you can
imagine that you can install a lot of
phone web applications on an iPhone or
an Android device so now I will talk a
little bit about the our application
event ninja and just to show you how we
that and what the focus focus law was so
once again the w3c widget standard and
we have an external database and our
external database there we saved our
events that we show in our application
and here you see it's really just
basically a google calendar that we've
chosen with we said we don't want to
write a calendar again and just picked
up a google calendar and filled our
dates in there and and then we really
just packaged it up and brought it on
the different devices so here this is a
nokia device with a different look and
feel then this is running on windows
mobile with an iphone look and this is
palm OS with a different layout and it
really just was too yeah mainly fixing
browser box between all these different
devices and of course we used a lot of
CSS features to make the skinning
different for each device and here for
example blackberry device then on
android and on the iphone so and then
what we then want to accomplish to see
where we could push these apps too and
here you see a list of all the app
stores we pushed our app to and for
example here you see also here devices
that are supported or where we tested
event ninja on and it's really a lot of
effort to send the application on the
device tested then you find on a problem
and do that again it's it's really a lot
of work and here you can see also that
getting into all the app stores it was a
manual task it wasn't like there's no
automation out there where you just
place your application to and then it
sends it to all the app stores and also
it was a large expense to get into all
these eps tours like I
everyone knows for the ex store you have
to pay ninety nine dollars each year to
get your apps into the app store then
the funniest thing i think was windows
mobile there you charge your account
with 50 euros and every time you push
your app to their quality assurance you
have to pay or it 15 euros are
subtracted from your account so after
three submissions you have to do it
again and sometimes you you get feedback
like it's not working then you say okay
why is that working and it's really
ridiculous and you see again this charge
from this demo which app stores so we
pushed our rap too and I think it's not
so difficult to get into more app stores
but really it's not worth the money to
to get into all of those so what really
felt was was hard with developing for
all these different devices and we're
not just talking about high-end devices
like iphone and android we're also
talking about blackberry and windows
mobile and nokia devices they don't have
so much power so what really was the
pain was supporting all these different
browsers it's not true that we just have
WebKit if we have WebKit we have a lot
of different webkinz the android webkit
is completely different to an iphone web
kit and the palm WebKit is different and
then we also have the browser of rim the
blackberry from the BlackBerry device
then we have fennec maybe in the future
I don't know how many devices will ship
fennec in the future then I think large
is also opera and opera mini opera mini
for example also has widget runtime so
but the difference here for opera mini
is that javascript is executed on the
server so what just is possible with
opera mini is that you can can write
code that is using click events or mouse
down Eva and something like that so then
you can write apps for that
but if you want to have more like
animations and dynamic staff that
doesn't work and also bold it's
something similar like opera mini they
also have a widget runtime oh and I
forgot ie there's also I windows mobile
and they have a widget runtime and it's
also funny they brought out windows
mobile 6.5 about half a year ago and
they have a strange mixture in the
browser they have a rendering engine of
ie6 and a JavaScript runtime of IE eight
so it's really hard to distinguish what
is then used and what I've heard the new
windows mobile seven will have an IE
seven so at least a little bit better
but I don't know what they will do but
at least the Opera runtime is always
running on on windows mobile so you can
just place an overrun time there and be
happy so yeah there's also not much more
pain we're in the mobile space we have
to handle touching key events that we
don't have to care about so much on the
desktop browser and yeah this is a big
big pain that we have to support several
different screen sizes if you now look
at the ipad you really have large screen
sizes and I think it's not just
sufficient to pump up or to zoom into
that application I think you also have
to give a different experience on every
device that has a different screen size
so we have to think about what we will
how we will handle that so and as you've
seen the packaging and deployment to all
these different app stores it's really
complex and I it's a lot of work do that
so it could be really painful and
performance is a big big issue and you
really have to be careful what
JavaScript functionality you use
to write your application and Costa code
size really matters if you deploy your
html5 app on earn one on web server it's
really dependent all you have to
download and how much is cached like for
example the iphone browser is caching
25k uncompressed so if used geez if it
it doesn't help it's really like the
pure JavaScript code uncompressed that
can be catched so you have to care it's
like a vampire now that was only true
way back and I really yeah okay that's
good news so what but they're also a
different device like the nokia device
they handle it all so different and i
think we still have to support all the
devices and also older operate our older
browser environments so because people
don't just upgrade their system all the
time so and also what is really hard
testing on all those devices and i think
not everyone has all these devices at
home they cost a lot of money and it's
there need a solution for that that you
can access all these devices there's for
example what an interesting service
called perfecto mobile they really have
x there you have access to all the lot
of mobile phones and you pay a monthly
fee and what they then do you have a
camera and look on to a device and they
put it into like a holder and place
there and then you can place your
application there and test it it's
really maybe it's a good tool to do that
and a lot cheaper than buying all these
devices but yeah there's there's a lot
of relief I think using all the existing
JavaScript frameworks also is a big
relief but it's they help you a lot but
you're not completely there i would say
ninety percent there's ten percent
missing and as i know john you're
writing currently also writing at
it's getting more mobile support into
jquery i'm doing that you're doing a
business mobile devices yeah I'm getting
it this reverses yeah and i hope i hope
so that more frameworks will do that and
that all the frameworks can be used on
in the mobile space without explicitly
testing every little tiny bit and
checking if something is not working but
i think there's still a lot of work to
do to support all those devices that
devices so and also there's mu touch
jqtouch I you I for solving at least the
problem to write applications now for
the iphone or that they look like an
iPhone but there will be I think more
look and feel different look and fields
for different platforms then there's xui
the JavaScript framework or phonegap
it's also interesting because they
really care about fire sighs and about
features within their JavaScript
framework so it's a good start if you
have want to ride in simple application
you can use xui so and what also really
helps a lot is using CSS transitions or
media queries to support we have to get
the speed the performance on the device
and also supporting the different screen
sizes so of course yeah then jazz
packers just to keep the file size small
and all the existing debuggers that are
out there like firebug and you can just
test it in the browser and have the same
tools as you would normally write web
applications so this just a small thing
a position fixed is a problem on iphone
and android you can just do it and so
next week there will be a real release
by david l radio he's written a touch
scroll epic javascript library or a
helper that helps with scrolling like
pains and it was really worked on at for
three months and tested it all on the
different
Isis and we'll be out next week and we
were also currently working on a dojo
mobile and you will also hear something
about in the next weeks so what are the
conclusion of all that is all these
different packaging systems that are out
there absolutely phonegap and so on I
would be happy if we're not talking
about specific platforms like Palm webOS
or just phonegap I would be really happy
if we coined that term html5 apps and
that everyone can use that term it's not
technically completely correct but I
think it's easier to sell that to
someone who is not into our business and
so this is my conclusion of html5 apps