I'm gonna be talking about responsive
talking about typography techniques like
slick just said and it's actually been a
really fun day so far I mean CSS
confident pretty cool for a first time
around don't you think thanks so much
for you guys for having me it's been
really awesome and like it's a big honor
to be at the first time of a conference
that's really really cool I also
appreciate all of you guys letting me
talk about typography cuz I don't have
you notice so we've been talking about a
lot of like pretty crazy stuff I'm
pretty serious stuff and I'm like let's
talk about type yay so yeah at least one
other person so a couple things that I
do um I am the managing editor of
creative Jay Austin basically we collect
up a bunch of cool tutorials and
articles and things about fun stuff
people are doing with JavaScript and we
also teach some workshops I teach one of
those workshops obviously the coolest of
all the workshops that's the creative
jazz for designers because designer to
the coolest obviously we also run web
design day which is the day kind of like
this except in Pittsburgh so we don't
have any ocean or Sun so anyways um but
we do talk about web design in a lot I'm
so very running that for a while also I
think just like last week I released or
five simple steps released my book the
pocket guide to CSS animations it has
exactly nothing to do with what I'm
talking about today like literally
nothing at all there will be no talk of
animations but if you're into those you
might want to check it out so um I just
realized one thing that is missing and
I'm not sure if I can get it back sorry
that's how you can tell I'm Canadian I
just apologized for fixing my screen oh
you guys do get any do you pay there's
gonna be better jokes not okay so we've
just been talking about things like
viewport sizes and checkboxes and all
this stuff and I figured that maybe you
know to get everyone thinking about type
and to get in like a typography kind of
mood we could play a little game maybe
up for it okay good you guys are a
little bit of laughs so um the game I
want to play is called font or fish
basically oops well we already ought to
the first question I put a name up on
the screen you tell me if you think it's
a font or a fish so this one fish yay oh
and don't you love these like keynote
transitions amazing all right how about
this one
yes you guys are a little too you gonna
shut away these harder this one i
stumped you on one but this is fun isn't
it um how about this one yes it's a fish
isn't it cute last one yes awesome
all right so everyone's about set to
start talking about typography right
yeah yeah I'm so glad you guys play my
game that's really cool um all right so
a couple things we have in this talk
will list of exactly four actually we're
gonna talk about or I'm going to show
you some three approaches for awesomely
readable body text in responsive design
I'm gonna hopefully prove to you that
even just the smallest bit of attention
to your type can give you huge awesome
results for your designs
um there's only one very sad cat I'm
sorry and any number of terrible jokes
might be sorry about that too but really
the main thing is there's no one way to
do any of this stuff I'm sharing what
works for me and what seems to work for
some other people I hang out with as
well um but I find that responsive
design has really changed my process a
lot and it's very much involving so this
is the stuff I'm doing now maybe I'll
come up with a better idea tomorrow
maybe you guys will come up with a
better idea tomorrow and that's kind of
the fun part about sharing so oh well
let's start with some science that
typography probably never killed anyone
um I put probably in just in case
there's any like lawyers or
fact-checking people in the world maybe
it has happened but chances are it
hasn't happened very
um so you know there's also been the
worst thing that could probably happen
with bad typography is you can look a
little bad maybe you can look a little
bit like out of style a little bit
awkward a little bit ugly but it's not
really gonna hurt anything you know
worst thing you might look a little
below average but they're not gonna be
like painfully hurting anyone there's
been some scientific studies even just
particularly this one the aesthetics of
reading it's great Ani on the screen but
whatever one of the things they proved
is that it actually doesn't make a
difference if you're reading good
typography or bad typography you still
retain the same information you still
read the same speed so like about
typography doesn't slow you down good
typography doesn't make your job of
reading easier
so you're kind of like alright well
that's sort of weird um but this thing
study also proved that or found that
good typography induces a good mood and
that's probably something you've heard
quoted before a lot of a lot of tight
people like to bring it up but what they
found which i think is really cool is
they gave people something to read and
they had like their one section of
people read something that was set in
bad typography but they gave them like a
present first they're like here you go
here's a present go read this bad
typography and at the end those people
were in just as good of a mood or the
same good mood as the people who were
given no present but got to read good
typography so the obvious conclusion is
good typography is like giving your
users are present right but I mean maybe
not that literal but it's actually true
having good typography puts people in a
good mood makes you look better and you
know having people in a good mood having
people more you know thinking more
highly of you is a pretty good thing to
gain by good typography and of course a
little bit of time on typography will
give you really really great results if
you spend even just a few minutes at any
point in time in your process or any
point in your process you'll get some
really good results and it's not
something that you even need to be you
know a type typography expert for just
by paying attention to a few the things
I'll list out you're gonna be so much
more awesomer at typography and that's
awesome ur is totally a word but
responsive web design has totally
changed the way we think about web
typography um you know suddenly we were
doing this thing where we're setting
type that's what you call it you and if
it's CSS and stuff studying type because
we were serious type people as web
designers now even though one day we
weren't now we
um not that I'm scarred by that or
anything so we're suddenly putting type
in these containers that can change any
size at any time and we're basically
like making our sites and containers do
this all the time and we're gonna throw
type in there and we're doing it on
purpose so we used to set up our tower
style rules for type just once right we
just set them once to be like we're done
it's a fixed container it's good and if
we do that now you know we just set our
styles for text once the same styles
that give us this which maybe isn't so
bad it's some small text in a small
little container maybe it's like some
sort of mobile eview or something but
the same styles that give us that give
us this
on larger screens when it becomes
responsive um and this is not okay this
is completely horrible and no one would
ever want to read it like it's
impossible to read even if it wasn't so
small just having line lengths that long
no one would ever want to read it and
sadly with responsive design we've been
subjecting to people reading our sites
to things very similar to this way more
than we should not saying anyone this
room has done it yeah you've seen it
you've gone decides to spin like what is
going on um and and so we need to stop
this on the internet because in fact
when you put line lengths this long on
the internet and makes the cat's behind
the internet cry and we really can't do
that so if not if nothing else cats are
on the internet and long line lengths
make them cry all right on a roll so now
we've established that everyone wants to
keep their line lengths in check
obviously um responsive web design or
typography for responsive web design my
titles are getting so long you know what
kind of goals might that have you know
if things have changed we've got these
flexible containers what goals are we
going for now I would suggest that we
kind of have two goals to be consistent
in some way shape or form like visually
hopefully somewhat consistent to help
project a consistent message or some
crazy idea like that
um and also to be easily readable no
matter what size or what sort of
situation you're being viewed in it
sounds like a couple pretty good goals
so let's look at how to meet them
because clearly that's where I'm going
with a list like this so what can we do
to bring more more consistency to our
type in responsive web design the very
first thing the main thing we can do is
to set a scale because consistency makes
you look good
and the first thing everyone says when I
talk about a typographic scale is that
Robert bring her said you should use one
right of course totally heard that and
he did see it's right there
he totally did say that but here about
this book originally like a gajillion
years ago in internet time why should we
listen to this now so I have an even
better reason and that's the consistency
factor the idea of keeping a consistent
look to your type really makes you look
way more professional looks things more
planned out and more composed and that
consistency helps carry a similar feel
across the board of any server size of
that your types being viewed at and it's
not like people reading your site are
going to be like hmm looking at this on
my phablet I've noticed that the ratio
between the h2 and h3 is exactly the
same as it was on my desktop but they're
never gonna say that because that sounds
ridiculous but in their minds people
recognize that and that consistency is
totally gonna do you some favors and
then there's also the idea of
consistency being having a consistent
base having something that already looks
good is gonna be a hundred million times
easier maybe not a hundred million but
at least a hundred times easier for you
to adjust as you go I tend to exaggerate
numbers anyway it's a scale equals
consistency and that is really really
awesome so has anyone has anyone here
worked with typographic scales before a
few just a little bit okay we're talking
about some math for a second so
typographic scale is really just a ratio
and this one is the golden ratio which I
don't know if you've noticed but a lot
of times on the internet we find out it
exists in little dotted lines and
triangles and all the logos of all of
the worlds and that may not actually be
true I think that gets added later it's
a bad design joke anyways um it's
basically a ratio where you take a
certain you know you multiply the
different sizes in your type so if you
start at like 12 you multiply to get the
next size IP multiplied by one point six
eight and you keep going until you get a
list of numbers like this and maybe this
would be in pixels if I was using that
scale I rounded them because decimals
and pixels make me feel weird
you could also do the same thing with
thumbs and it might look like that
decimals and M's are totally okay and
you would get these numbers from
someplace well you could just make them
up yourself by doing a little
multiplication but I like to get them
from modular scale comm which is a tool
that Tim Brown put together
then you can just enter in a couple
numbers hit go and I'll do all this
multiplication for you it'll give you
sizes and pixels M's based sixteen M's
and percent of thirteen first three are
pretty useful I'm not really sure
percent of thirteen is and these scales
that have as much meaning or as little
meaning as you want you've probably read
some articles sometimes are people are
like oh and I picked this scale because
it was like based off a major fifth
and this font was designed by Beethoven
or something I made that up and it was
horrible but you know that they had
these crazy stories about why they
picked his scale and that those are
great stories but that's not an
important part of picking a scale if you
pick a typographic scale and you want to
use it because you like it and it looks
good and it fits what you're trying to
do that's enough reason for me you don't
have to have you can make up a story
like that if you want but you don't have
to have have a story like that and one
other thing about scales is that scales
or not gospel basically you get this
list of numbers and you can use those to
assign your different type sizes you
know pick your size pure H to use your H
ones and everything else but you know if
you're if you're looking at a scale like
Oh apparently have to go through this
way if you're looking at a scale like
this and you decide like oh you know I
decided my h2s we're gonna be 25 pixels
in size but I'd really like them to be
just a little bit smaller don't throw
out your scale just set it to like 22
and be fine with it because you as a
human with eyes and a brain are smarter
than straight-up math anytime when it
comes to what looks right and what looks
more balanced so you can always fudge
them a little for the human factor all
right so that's what we can do for
consistency and scales if you haven't
used them or typographic scales despite
them sounding may be a little bit weird
are pretty darn awesome to use for that
um so what can we do to typeset well in
our containers are flexing all over the
darn place so um there's three main
things we need to consider when it comes
to balancing readable type or keeping
type readable and if I was like an
infomercial right now I would have like
well actually already did have flash
bulbs and little explosions didn't I
well I have more of those and I probably
tell you like I could sell you for $9.99
the three secrets to like setting type
and well three secrets to setting
readable type but I'm not gonna get that
crazy with it because that's sort of
silly but there's three things that are
kind of considered the I guess macro
typography or something like that the
three things you will need to have
imbalance to keep type readable
- sighs second is letting and the third
is measure those are the super
typographic names for them in CSS they
are font size line height and width yay
so those three things looking at just
those three things you can get stuff
looking amazingly readable very easily
when a body of text is hard to read one
of these three things is out of whack so
they all are kind of related do do and
as you kind of adjust them with their
fancy little faders you can pretend
that's what we're really doing if you're
just any one of them or change any one
of them especially drastically if you
need to adjust the other two to make
something that's still more balanced and
the relationship isn't like a linear
mathematical thing it's not like well if
you increase measure by two pixels you
must increase letting by half a pixel
it's nothing that literal and that
linear it's more just by you know when
you adjust one you have to get your
balance back and the goal isn't really
like black and white rules of like this
is better it's more of just a goal of
creating something that's in good taste
and we all have pretty good taste I mean
we're here right so we can do that so
also according to Robert burgers the
optimal length or the most optimal
length for a comfortable measure of
reading is 45 to 75 characters I
probably heard that sometimes too it
comes up kind of a lot that's considered
a comfortable measure for reading line
length on the Internet I've noticed that
we've kind of changed just a little bit
sort of interesting so I know a lot of
you guys probably read sites and then
totally go and count the characters per
line but if you did because you know if
you haven't already I mean we tend to go
up to around 100 pretty easily and those
things are actually still pretty easy to
read so 45 ish to 100 or 45 to 75 up to
100 main point is that it's arranged and
we're really dealing with ranges here
there's no I mean kind of like what Mike
was just saying earlier it's like
there's kind of no absolutes right like
pixels are about this close to becoming
meaningless right now for web design so
everything is ranges and things that
look good within a certain range
characters per line of what's readable
is also a range so it kind of fits with
that a little bit
all right so what can we do with its
information and actually maybe get to
some code because you know there has to
be code in this talk so one approach I
like to use for keeping line lengths in
check is something that I like to call a
typed weak points I'm pretty sure I
didn't invent that name but it sounds
cool
and basically it's approach number one
for keeping or my first approach for
keeping text comfortably readable no
matter what you're containing size might
be um and tweet points that's a pretty
cool term that I first heard from the
spark box guys out of Ohio and I really
like the idea of them cuz it's the idea
of like it's not like your design is
broken it's just like there's these
points where things just need a little
bit of help that's yeah that's kind of
more what's going on so these are
actually creating a set of media queries
or a set of breakpoints or tweet points
whatever you want to call them better
type-specific I actually make a whole
set just for the type um and I find them
this is crazy
by checking and and like actually
reading things and checking them on
various devices and sizes for the
examples I'm going to show you today I
have a super simple like stripped down
just type example so we can look at the
styles that will actually affect that
it's definitely not the most practical
and we're just gonna look at it by
resizing our browser but obviously in
the real world we'd actually look at
this on you know actual device things
and that sort of thing oh and I should
also point out actually no I'll point
that out later so two points what what
we do to kind of do this of this
approach start with using a scale using
relative units like ends or rooms I'm
actually going to use I mean I'm gonna
be using rounds because I've kind of
noticed they've got some decent for
these days that's kind of cool
but em to be pretty much the same
situation um when line likes gets you
long according to our 45 to 75
characters ish we had a media query
which I have conveniently shortened to
MQ not sure why just for fun and we
adjust the base font size based on that
new width and then evaluate the font
size and line height from there just to
make sure we have some balance so that's
kind of the trick to it oh and adjust
more if needed of course there might
always be more to adjust so let's take a
look at what that looks like
so here's my super simple example it's a
super simple type centric I keep
fretting there's a screen over there to
both play
this simple example and we were just
thought to text it's conveniently from
Goldilocks cuz you know we're looking
for like a nice medium range of things
that's good right okay maybe it's not so
good and so it's the breakfast drama of
Goldilocks and the three bears
so I usually start out with something
kind of Moberly sighs something that's
gonna look good on the smallest size
kind of phone size here on the screen
looks a little tiny but on the phones it
looks kind of not it looks pretty good
so I was pretty happy with that as a
starting point and for my starting point
I had my base font size as it turns out
set to 75% I'm in the night signs all my
you know I'm in here my H ones I have
this like leading paragraph and then my
body text that was all set off the scale
that I used the same numbers from the
previous example from the previous scale
list sorry so I had my bought by
original fonts our base phone so I set
to 75% and the one thing I point out is
that the line height was set to one
point four which is a unitless
measurement and while we can't do things
really in CSS like set a min line height
and Max lines light this is kind of a
close second so unitless is pretty
awesome for these it'll kind of scale
with a font size as I'm sure you knew
and then as in my lead-in paragraph I
set that font size to 1.618 so you might
remember from our fancy scale golden
ratio yeah that means it'll be amazing
bottom margin set from the scale as well
and a line height that's just a little
bit smaller because generally bigger
text little less line height is a good
idea and that's gonna usually look a
little more balanced and then I had some
stuff set for my h1 as well but I want
to get through all these to then usually
what I would do is throw in some lorem
ipsum some nice lorem ipsum with a
couple little asterisks in there one at
45 characters and and one at 75
characters in because I really hate
counting so this is a really good visual
way to do it and it's actually an idea I
stole from Trent Walt with you it
probably also does not like counting so
I think that's why I think he's cool um
that might be the only yeah cuz that's
one reason to read people I also don't
like counting yeah so we have those in
there and then we basically just start
seeing what happens when our containing
when our page gets bigger and our main
texts container or it gets bigger and
bigger so eventually we hit a point
where we have those two Asterix on one
line or like
yeah this is probably getting a bit too
long to read yep I mean you'll see
notice on the body copy we have that
both on one line it's getting a bit feel
on to read our lead in paragraph that's
super huge and dynamic or dramatic
rather it's still doing okay but our
body copy needs some help so this point
I put in one of the typed weak points
which is basically setting a media query
ID approximately six 15 pixels and
bumping up the font size to 100 then I
should probably point out as I meant to
you before but then I stopped myself is
you know this code is definitely not the
kind of code you'd be like copy and
paste and use it in your in your own
projects write media queries however you
would like
you know you sass all that cool stuff
but this is just an easy way to
demonstrate it here on our super simple
example so um as we keep going we would
make some other changes maybe decide to
add another one in around 850 for this
one
a bumped up the font size and then that
font so I started looking a little bit
big so I made the line height a little
bit smaller as well and these sorts of
things there you can get a whole list of
rules of like when line height should be
smaller or bigger usually like larger
text you want a smaller line height
text that has lots of space within the
letters you want more line height but
really the easiest way to do it is to
find where things look a little broken
find where your line lengths look a
little bit too long and then start
adjusting things and see what looks
better to you because we're we're all
really good judges of what's easy to
read it's just a matter of taking the
time to look at it and adjust things and
if your first adjust that makes it look
worse try going the other way I think
that's the easiest way to learn this
stuff and you really get a feel for it
so we kept going and then in the very
end I ended up setting one for 1200
pixels and basically you know we would
end up with something that might look a
little like this oops
no we wouldn't that's the next place so
biggest question is you know for
something simple like this is where do
you stop and in real-life situations
when you're not just walking up a page
about Goldilocks you're gonna run into
something other than your attacks
needing to stop getting bigger maybe you
know you you don't want to be in a
situation where your text is this big
and you have like this little video or
this little image like something else in
your design will generally stop you and
have you have to put in a max width
somewhere and when that happens then
you're good to go but for this
particular one it was just kind of an
arbitrary one Bryce
my max width of my container at about
like 900 pixels or something like that
and these these tweet points that you
put in for the type don't just have to
be adjusting your font size on your line
height I think those are the first two
things you should look at to balance out
your reading but you can do more
interesting things as well for example
then you a list a part redesign they
actually switch out to Georgia Pro
condensed on their smaller viewport more
Moberly ish views and you can go tiss
looking at these little carefully
because they're very close the
characters in the left and one on the
mobile view one or the smallest one take
up less space than the ones that when
they get bigger so what they've done is
switch to a font that's a little more
condensed they can get more characters
in on these tiny or thin viewports
but still be able to keep the text
bigger because a lot of the time
depending on the font you pick you'll
notice when you get down to these
smaller viewport sizes to get a readable
length you start having a really small
font size and then it's like well is
that really more comfortable if it's a
good you know comfortable measure but
it's so tiny I'm like squinting at my
phone that's not comfortable anymore so
your font choices affect this as well I
think that's a pretty good trick and you
could even maybe do it bigger on the
other side you know a lot of web type
comes as display faces so you could do
something when it gets really big to put
in one of the display weights so that
our anything will look something like
this I'm just gonna go through it kind
of quick because we have two more so it
starts out small expands and gets bigger
we hit our various type tweet points and
then eventually it stops our container
stops getting bigger and we allow our
margins to get bigger instead so let's
type of graphic tweak points which is
the terrible name I've given this
approach that definitely is not
something I invented but something
that's get you gets used quite a bit so
we start with our scale using relative
units that's the biggest most important
thing and then we can adjust our base
font size to get our scale basically to
scale ha and we sent a cutoff point
based on some other factor usually then
our type and my own media queries ended
up looking like this so you might have
noticed that I switched from pixels to M
based media queries usually since it's
pretty easy to get something to tell you
how many pixels wide your browser is not
so easy get something to tell how many
Emmas wide it is I start with pixels and
then convert them over
I like the M based media queries a lot
better because it kind of makes you more
resolution independent
like if somebody is viewing is it kind
of doesn't matter how many pixels are
anymore ms which are essentially roughly
based on the 16 pixel increments
you know if they get bigger because
someone zooms in or something you have
fewer MS and then you might hit one of
your other media queries as well so it
really takes you away from pixels and
takes you away from that you know makes
you more resolution independent pretty
cool way to do it in cloud 4 has there
probably even though it's a little more
than a year old probably the best reason
of why you should move towards those on
their blog as well so to get these
particular numbers I just ended up
dividing by 16 but when it comes to the
M based stuff you kind of end up playing
things by ear a little bit more you know
relying less on actual numbers and
actual pixel pixels and just find those
good ranges so one problem with this
approach though is that M still equal ms
anymore you know if I have increased my
based font size my M's vertically yes I
screwed that up sometimes it's very
embarrassing when vertically have
actually gotten bigger they're not
approximately 16 pixels anymore right
but my M base needed queries going
horizontally are still based off the 16
pixel ratio they don't get bigger when I
increase my base font size um some
people have a really big problem with
this I'm actually kind of ok with it I
don't know if that makes me weird but I
tend to work in really small teams or
it's like making a developer or like me
and three other people and there's
probably only like two of us ever
touching the CSS so we can keep this
straight bigger teams maybe that's more
of a problem and really lately I've been
finding myself playing by ear more when
it comes to setting these typographic
tweak points of like where I actually
change things and relying less on
exactly how wide my browser window is
and just more on how things look and
maybe I should make a change here or
there so one other approach besides out
that we can do Emma five things that's
okay that was supposed to be funny title
it's alright but title wasn't funny
enough for you I totally have some
terrible puns in this subtitle so if
changing good yeah you guys are still
awake
you're like type makes me sleepy yeah um
if changing your base font size is a
problem which is often can be you know
if that making your M's not matches a
problem or other reasons is a problem
for you there's other ways to do this as
well and obviously by keeping things
constant by keeping your base font size
constant your M's will always be
approximate
based off 16 ish pixels like how all the
math we're doing now for responsive
design it's like approximately kinda
sorta it's like we have numbers and the
economy and stuff but the kind of dough
it's pretty cool it's great when you
like to make up numbers so to kind of
take this approach you want to measure
your column widths and ends and this is
maybe the main thing stopping
make-it-or-break-it point of people not
everyone likes to measure their wits and
and these people have grids that work in
percentages and all that kind of thing
and they don't want to get away from
that it's ok you don't have to do it
this way but if you do this is a good
way to do it um
you keep your base five pace font size
constant and then you can use keep your
containers fluid when they're smaller
and then when you get to a point a
certain point which we'll talk about one
second you stop letting anything get
bigger and you just let your margins get
bigger and you base that on an M value
because generally kind of sort of with
our fuzzy math some more there's any
like super math people in the house
they're probably starting to feel like
um but 1m is approximately like one of
them at least typographically is based
off of a capital M which is
approximately 2 ish characters for most
fonts so if we say 75 characters is our
maximum comfortable reading measure and
we divide that approximately by 2
somewhere in around 32 M should be the
max size of our of our main text
container and if it never goes over 32 M
s we'll never have more than 75
characters and we will always be at a
comfortable readable length yeah math um
so we would end up with something like
this when it's very small we keep it
nice and flexible oops sorry
that when we get to more more medium
length we're still a little flexible but
at some point in that sort of medium
range we hit our maximum 32 MS and then
when we do that things get a little bit
bigger but only our margins get bigger
and as we get bigger and bigger and
margins gets huger and huger if this
were a real project and not Goldilocks
and the three bears we might you know
kick up to two columns or something like
that but in this case it just hangs out
there in the center all bias lonely self
and our font sizes never actually change
so that's another approach to keeping
your line length in a comfortable way
but without having to make removable I
guess making fewer tweaks so
wits and everything in M's
keeps you nice and
resolution-independent that is pretty
awesome there's still an option to make
adjustments here there you know you can
make more adjustments if you want to and
make those little tweak points in
addition to doing this one and it
doesn't work well with all grid making
approaches I know some people who are
like the idea of making setting up their
grids and Emmas and they just kind of
like freak out and don't wanna talk to
me anymore
so it's okay I mean I'll get over it
I'll just do the other version instead I
end up having to work with a lot of
different teams so yeah I'm used to
adapting so one more approach since we
said we do three and I realized I have
no idea how I'm doing on time because my
counter didn't start so I'm sorry about
that one other approach that I've been
playing with a little bit and haven't
really gotten to use for real yet is V H
and V W B H is my favorite obviously get
it bow head VA okay like that's awesome
I have a unit named after me um either
get it knees don't really have enough
support to use anywhere real just yet
but they're really interesting um 100 V
W equals all of the you port width
essentially so one is like one percent
and you can set up something that will
constantly change the font size and even
like your margins and line height and
everything you want in all directions
based on your viewport and it just
changes all the time well except most
browsers make you refresh before it
updates but once they fix that all the
time
squishy it's great but it's kind of
drastic for example these two are both
set to 2 V W for font size this one
you're never gonna be able to read even
if that was on a real phone not gonna
happen
it's way too tiny so it kind of scales
to any proportion at all and when it
gets really big you know kind of looks
okay but it doesn't handle small size as
well but I do like what it's doing to my
heading I mean that's kind of cool a
little small and a small end to you but
it's maybe a little bit more of a
headings thing so these guys are
definitely fun because squishing things
in all directions and making your
margins change and your font size change
is really fun to do but it still needs
limits somewhere probably especially on
the low end because that text was so
tiny I don't even know if like a
magnifying glass would help you out
without it was pretty bad um and it's
pretty kick-ass for titles and display
copy I think that's the kind of place
these are really going to come in hand
places where you might have used
something like fit text and use
JavaScript to make sure it always made
your text size big enough to fill your
whole window you might be able to use
these instead
kind of nice okay so responsive design
strangely enough is more than just
making your boxes all flexi so
typography for responsive design is also
more than just fitting them into flexi
containers so I wanted to talk a little
bit about what we can do to make what we
can do with our type to make it I guess
basically more aware that we're under
different conditions not just in flexi
boxes but I realize I've been doing this
like all day like yeah this is my new
dance anyways so things we can do a type
that consider devices at least just a
little because we don't have any real
reliable way still to really find out
like what someone's connection speed or
anything is but we can kind of make some
assumptions and I'll go with the
assumptions for now until we have
something better so loading web fonts
can take a while it can take a really
long while you especially notice it on
mobile situations where you generally
speaking your connection might be a bit
slower for lack of a better way to
measure and you know you're gonna know
you're gonna see that you'll actually
notice this loading thing happens so
there's a couple things we can do to
make this happen more gracefully we can
use font stacks till I know things like
services like Typekit and font ACK and
everything they give you the CSS sample
it's usually like your awesome web type
and then like serif there should always
be something between your awesome web
type and Sara always you know just don't
just copy and paste that because
sometimes this is a little sad and
terrible sometimes your web fonts won't
load at all don't want to scare anyone
but it's true I mean not just in mobile
situations there's actually like um you
know ad blockers and stuff that will
block things like Typekit and then
suddenly you're on your fallback fault
so they better be awesome this is a
chart that is scary but true and it goes
to try to show you what font exists on
all mobile platforms none good luck with
that so basically at some point no
matter what on some devices you're gonna
be stuck with your basic serif or sans
serif um it's also possible to hide web
fonts from mobile situations if you want
to if you're okay with basing thin
viewport means probably mobile maybe not
really good connection speed and we can
do things like actually by not calling
our awesome
thought it won't get loaded but that's
only if you actually load in your web
font through pure CSS a little trickier
if you're using javascript but you know
JavaScript can handle that whole like if
this then that stuff too
I've heard of people taking some
approaches of creating like a light type
kit and have a type type type kit
one with fewer faults one with more
serving the lighter one to mobile and
this is a great article since I don't
have any time to get into it but CSS
tricks did some great things and
examples about preventing the
performance head of custom fonts they're
also web phone events that we can that
we can look into you and they are
seriously awesome
google has put these together and you
can actually use the Google web font
loader to get events of the situation
every web font web fonts loading with
any service or situation for loading web
fonts that you want it comes built-in to
type kit but you can set up this Google
one even if you're rolling your own at
font face setup the way it works to get
some classes one for when your web fonts
are loading called WF loading the naming
structure is amazing obviously when
they're in active means they have it
loaded at all and when they're active
and you can set some different styles
based on that and this comes in handy
especially for titles or really
important text like tag lines or
something like that where you want to
really handle every detail of how it's
going to get swapped out but from its
default font or the fallback font but
then what it gets one swapped out with
once your web fonts load so you can
control every step of the way on this
and make sure that like when it's just
set to plain old Sarah it still fits in
the same box it's gonna fit in when
you're using your good prximo Nova or
whatever else so those are pretty handy
whoo I've been going through a whole lot
of stuff so the very last part that I
want to talk about cuz I'm assuming I
only have a couple minutes left is uhm
responsive typography for the future I
mean there's a lot more we can do with
width type and fonts than just spitting
them into flexi boxes and trying to
figure out if we have a good connection
speed or not to load our stuff and
handling that loading function um one
thing that's really interesting and I
didn't talk about it too much is this
the idea that um on Retina displays your
fonts look different we've all seen it
we've got you know high resolution
phones or high density phones or
everyone to call them Retina display
phones and then regular old monitors
and on ready display as your type is
going to appear lighter even though it's
not lighter basically because it's
higher resolution so the folks over who
make I a writer have actually done some
things I've done some experimenting with
graded fonts and basically these fonts
are aware of you know what your
resolution that you're dealing with is
and they actually would serve up a
slightly bolder version to Retina
displays so that it ends up looking
exactly the same as the coarser lower
resolution version so it's like a font
that knows what resolution it's being
displayed at and adjusts itself
accordingly that would be pretty cool to
play with I think so that's one way that
things could be getting pretty
interesting another way thanks maybe
part getting pretty interesting is
there's I believe this is a series
actually
but that Nick has been writing on a list
apart but he's suggesting that you know
all fonts have some hinting included
with them and that's basically
instructions of how to make their
awesome smooth curves translate to
coarse harsh pixels and how that's gonna
happen and hinting tells them how to do
that but he suggested it maybe hinting
could do more than that like what if the
hinting instructions of your font could
tell it hey skinny uh viewport maybe
condense your characters a little bit
give me a like a condensed version or
like hey a really really big viewport
why don't we go with the more wide
version um so that kind of things those
kinds of things could be actually
embedded within our fonts and our fonts
could be smart enough you know we
wouldn't have to swap them out ourselves
they could actually no I think that's
kind of cool the idea of like pulling up
a web font and loading it up and having
it know like the resolution and
adjusting for that knowing what kind of
viewport size are dealing with smart
fonts sound pretty awesome so the whole
idea of responsive and typography I
think is heading to some pretty
interesting directions and I'm kind of
excited about all this stuff and
hopefully maybe you guys are a little
bit too so that wraps up our journey of
typography for responsive design a lot
to cover in like 30 minutes so thanks
for for following along thanks for
having me and talking about responsive
typography for a little while um I know
that we're having a party on the beach
later and there's probably nothing more
fun than talking about typography on the
beach right
so if you guys want to chat later bunny
type stuff let me know if you want to
chat on the internet that's where to