thank you very much for coming inside
today and giving me your attention like
they said my name is ray Daley I'm going
to be talking about javascript
journalism the new profession and if you
want to follow along and examples that
are in the latter half of the
presentation go to jay s journalism com
I just tweeted it if someone would
retweet it so let's start with what is
news to different people news as
different things but most people
consider news this text you often hear
the people say just give me the facts
everything else is fluff all I want is
the facts we see the same thing in web
development people will say content is
king we don't need no stinking UX we
don't need other stuff just give me the
facts on the page in fact this attitude
about news is just text was prevalent at
the Wall Street Journal into the mid 80s
they did not publish photos regularly
until that time they did not consider
anything but text to be news the same
attitude affected the launch of USA
Today they'll at that point many people
considered us a day USA today is not a
serious news publication because of all
the color photos the flash the
interactive graphics in color but now
it's generally accepted even the Wall
Street Journal has photos on the front
page everyone accepts that news is
photos as well as text and you can go
back on more than a century to look at
these looking at these historic photos
to realize that photos are also news
even the most gifted writer could not
write a story to compete with this photo
entire books have been written about
this photo there's an emotional hook the
photos that you just don't get in a text
story we have an expression for this
that a picture is worth a thousand words
and photographs are regularly on the
front page of any news publication
whether it be printer or on the web or a
news app but news is also JavaScript
more and more on websites you see
JavaScript being used to help enhance
the storytelling in fact I will contend
from the day javascript was released
every website became a nap just the
people didn't take advantage of the
capability so how do I show you in hard
numbers that javascript is important to
news organizations is important to tell
journalistic stories so I decided to
look at how much text is on leading news
organizations websites versus how much
javascript is there so this is how much
a graph of how much text is there I know
you cannot read that in the back but the
largest site has just under 80 thousand
characters of text they average about
50,000 characters a text now you all
know that that jQuery is on most
websites so you've got jQuery how much
other javascript is there what do you
think it's 10 times 5 times 3 times how
much more drought how much drop more
JavaScript is there than text
as you can see by that chart
substantially more you can barely see in
blue at the very bottom of these charts
the amount of text and characters versus
the amount of JavaScript now I wrote a
source program it's well I made it open
source it's on github to create these
charts or get the numbers for these
charts it doesn't after actually create
it and these are the hard numbers that
produced the ratio is generally 30 times
more JavaScript than text I don't think
anyone would have expected that I
certainly didn't even in my job at the
Washington Post expected there was that
much more on all these sites and New
York Times it's 91 times The Wall Street
Journal has 1.8 million characters a
JavaScript on their site so as i said i
put the program that created these
numbers that pull these numbers from the
sites in github and github is becoming
the new footnote in javascript
journalism instead of just referencing
something you go to the actual code that
helped produce the story or helped
interpret the data that made this story
so you look at those numbers about how
much javascript is on these sites and
you start wondering does that really
prove that javascript is being used to
tell stories well just the numbers don't
but the numbers are important to tell
you that javascript is important
delivering the news so let's look at
some examples how javascript is being
used in news stories
the first example I'm going to I can't
actually show is the oldest example it
was Chicago crime this was done over 10
years ago where a mash-up was done doing
excuse me wasn't 10 over 10 years ago
but it was done a long time ago to prove
that the amount of crime in Chicago
varied by neighborhoods so they plotted
out with google maps where crime was you
could see the trends and that story live
for a long time it just wasn't a one-day
story and lived for a long time so that
was called mashup journalism a similar
one this is an app by slightly off the
screen let me see if we can fix that
there we go this is the forest fire
forecaster from NPR using maps to
present a story that could not be told
just in text and I could go over and
over different maps maps are very common
way to tell stories in JavaScript
another way you see is the use of
slideshows or sliders in news
organizations websites they love
photographs everyone accepts that
photography is now journalism they don't
all except the javascript is but they
accept that photography is and they have
lots of photos so you see sliders or
galleries of photos and everything just
like I showed you at the beginning so
maybe that's like show journalism I
don't know the Seattle Times use
JavaScript as a navigation aid to get
people to the right story depending on
the congressional district they used so
the story was told in a unique way
because the JavaScript lots of examples
of if it being used in navigation
and it's not just in the United States
that it's being used this is a from
LeMond in France and they're using here
a timeline and as you scroll through the
timeline of course it won't work right
now here we go you can get different
stories about the timeline for the
election and I think timelines are an
underutilized aspect that JavaScript
journalism another way is what some
people are calling Geo journalism using
the geolocation in devices to figure out
where you are and deliver you a story
there because of your location one I
worked on at the Washington Post was
based on if you were attending a
Nationals baseball game you got unique
stories and unique information about
what was going on at the park that no
one else got here's another example that
I think is a very interesting this is I
don't know if anyone's heard of this
study this study's been out for a little
while but it was just recently updated
these are words that are last these are
words that have used in many
civilizations civilizations many
different languages over thousands of
years over hundreds of years and these
are the languages and these are the
words and you can actually play the
words and you can tell a story with
audio that you could never do in paper
because you want to hear what those work
how closely those sound those words
sound alike in the different languages
now now that everybody in your packet
got this little box are you ready for
sensor journalism this is a story from
WNYC in New York called the cicada
tracker now if you don't know what
cicadas are you part may not live on the
east coast but cicadas are the 17 year
locust that return so they come out of
the ground when the temperature is above
65 degrees so they created a project on
here and you can go and look at this
project and maybe even build it tomorrow
measure when the temperature is over 65
degrees and it will get back into the
story incorporated in the story that
cicadas are likely to come out in the g
equal in near where you live so there
you have appt journalists sensor
journalism now I don't think JavaScript
journalism is limited only to newspapers
and news organizations I think anyone
can create a story that is compelling
journalistic story and I think this one
from google which is a google doodle
let's go I don't know how many people
have seen this one but this was several
months ago it showed it was done on the
anniversary of a Zamboni and it told you
about the Zamboni by interacting with it
you figured out hey it's not so easy to
drive a Zamboni as it may appear and why
the invention was such a big deal
let's go a little more detail here this
is the balance of power chart this was
for the last presidential election this
was showing the as the votes were called
by state the electoral votes here in the
United States who who was winning and
there was a bar in the center to
indicate that when you reached tipped
over that bar you'd won the election and
this is what we put up on the Washington
Post on the mobile site and it was all
done using an API and CSS so maybe this
is API journalism but it was all
JavaScript reading the JSON from the API
and producing this balance of power
chart was all CSS the other thing we had
to do was how do we deliver in a dynamic
way new charts or new maps showing which
states had gone to which candidate so we
created a no Jas program that read The
Associated Press API parse that figured
out who would one what which states and
it went to a series of editors who then
called whether a state or not and gone
to that candidate and to give you an
idea how important JavaScript
journalists were at the Washington Post
on election night they sat in the table
right next to all of the editors who
were calling which states were being
called they were the most important
people for the editors they have contact
with and so this created a JSON file
that then created an SVG file that then
got converted to PNG file so those are
what we served to the mobile users
instead of having to put all that burden
of creating those on this mobile site so
in javascript journalism the new way to
proofread is code reviews so I don't
expect you to necessarily read this
exactly but you know what a JSON
statement looks like and this is just
JSON and the top line is for the
presidential election and it indicates
either
an uppercase R or lowercase are just
typical proofreading things do we do you
have the case right but in this case the
values after the upper case of their
lower case had a significant difference
in how the news was reported about how
the election was going so when I made
this proposal of this talk i said i
would talk a little about the academics
behind this and this will be the only
slide on that i don't want to completely
bore you but one of the reasons
javascript journalism is not recognized
as necessarily new medium over the
profession it is is because the content
of new media is always old Mia this is
the media theory that Marshall McLuhan
was famous for creating the medium is
the massage or the message and the
content of this JavaScript journalism is
often text and videos and photos which
are people are used to seeing and
they're just saying oh it's just the
standard stuff we're used to sing and
not recognizing it really is a new
medium it's really is a new way of
telling stories okay so I think you can
all see that using javascript you can
tell probably intuitive to most of you
that you can tell stories that you can't
tell with just text or photos in the
standard newspaper online you can tell
stories that are different then you can
tell with the paper and as you recognize
this there's got to be credit to this
photography photographers always get
their credit newspaper reporters get
there by lines the JavaScript
journalists are going to start getting
their credit for this but something else
also happened in the last six months
since i made this proposal we now have
long form javascript journalism and
these are substantial stories not what
anybody can say are just get gadgets or
gimmicks or anything else
these are stories that certainly could
only be told with JavaScript so the
first one I want to point out to you is
leading up the 601 and if you go to Jess
journalism com you can link to this on
your own device and take a look at this
this is the story of the last 32 hours
of Martin Luther King's life as we know
the information now when he was
assassinated not all the information was
known a lot was buried in behind Freedom
of Information request in the FBI and
other places this is a very interactive
story done by the Memphis Tennessee
newspaper and they have interviews with
people are still live great photos from
the time a lot of information
this one's from the Washington Post this
is the profits of oakridge these three
people are peace activists activists
ones and none they want to demonstrate
that our nuclear facilities are not as
safe as everyone says and they pose a
grave danger to the United States and so
they broke in to oakridge spray-painted
messages about peace on a wall and stood
there and waited for the guards to come
and arrest them this is a very
substantial story fifteen different
parts to the story
so I don't know if you know about this
story this is not only in the standard
newspapers this is an ESPN this is the
long strange trip of doc Ellis so if you
want a very entertaining story take a
look at this one and you can see that
this story again makes use of things
that we see a lot in our profession
being applied to news stories now this
is an early one from the wall street I'm
seen sorry the New York Times this was
the bribery aisle how Walmart was
bribing officials in Mexico to get
favorable treatment to get into
locations it was in the news for quite a
bit quite a long time but this was one
of their first efforts of going that
good just on time here so I want to
really point out to what I think are the
most significant stories that I've seen
so far there may be other ones out there
this is cycling Road forward it was done
at the washington post a few months ago
it is again a long piece and tells the
story of a new writer in his training
and how he's trying to break into the
sport that has had so many problems and
I'm taking it right to stage four
because the cohort mine at the coworker
mine at the Washington Post worked on
this piece here that I think is one of
the best examples I've seen so this is
decoding the ride so this is taking the
raw data out of the cycling equipment
that he was writing on in Nice France
and showing the map in a very engaging
way and there's also as you can see on
an audio clip that you can actually hear
him talk so you can play that audio clip
and here is the actual data from those
devices and you can look at his heart
rate and see how it varies based on the
training is going at you can see as you
would expect the speed the change
dramatically
look at his cadence how consistently as
cadence was that's what the trainers
were looking for so this was the typical
job of a reporter go out gather
information turn it into a form that's
usable and entertaining that can be
presented to the public and make it
understandable so I think this is just a
great piece and this is wilson Andrews
who did the pic all the JavaScript work
on the piece and there's a story called
making cycling Road making of cycling
Road forward so if you want to read
about the details behind the coding of
it it's all there now let me go to the
what I think is the most significant
piece we've seen to date and that is
snowfall if many people seen this
article yet it was published last
December and I don't know if you can see
in the monitor here but the snow is
coming across the screen in this video
they've incorporated and as you scroll
up you can read the story and you can
see the video remembrance of one of the
people who survived this Avalanche and
there's where this Avalanche occurred in
these mountains
obviously more photos and then a video
here the skier coming right at you and
this continues on for page after page in
the first week I believe they had six
million let me get the exact number I
don't want to misquote it here in the
first weeks for six days they had 3.5
million viewers of this article a story
that just does not relate the same way
if you try to tell it in text or on
paper so again there's articles on the
making of this if you want to go read
about exactly how the JavaScript was
being used now one of the more
interesting things I found was this blog
about one of the by one of the designers
of the story he did this presentation
talking about why design manners matters
in telling these stories and I'm sure
you've all read the New York Times and
other stories and you can see that he
translated that story into the standard
New York Times template here and what
you can see on the screen it would have
taken 41 pages in the standard template
to tell that story and I don't think
many people of those millions of people
would have gotten beyond page three was
in the standard template you could only
tell the story by using javascript
so like I said a lot has changed in the
six months since I proposed this talk
and one thing is we're now seeing some
news organizations advertised for what I
would call a javascript journalist this
is a help wanted ad or from New York
Times for it from May seventh for in an
interactive story designer now they
could have called it a JavaScript
journalist but they use this title and
the bold is mine expertise with web
development especially using javascript
HTML and CSS is required and experience
with video audio photography and game
mechanics is a plus sounds like a
JavaScript developer to me with
journalistic experience now what any
journalist aims for the highest honor
you can get as a journalist is the
Pulitzer Prize that's what this is the
Pulitzer Prize and so as I said a lot
has changed in six months when I said
initially that there was no respect for
JavaScript journalists or not as much
respect for JavaScript journalists as
there was for photojournalist but that's
changed so in 2013 John branch who wrote
snowfall won the Pulitzer Prize for
feature writing so it was to me the
first JavaScript journalist art to first
drop JavaScript journalists to win a
Pulitzer Prize it says awarded John
branch the new york times 4 is evocative
narrative about skiers killed in an
avalanche and the science that explains
such disasters a project enhanced by
steph integration of multimedia elements
so that's quite an accomplishment we've
come quite a ways in this new profession
of JavaScript journalism in a short time
but I think they made a mistake in this
presentation
I think what they should have said by
the deft integration of JavaScript not
multimedia elements so that is my talk I
hope you now appreciate that there
really is a new profession of JavaScript
journalism and I hope to see other
JavaScript journalists attend feature
Jaya sconce I'm just learning I consider
myself to be a mediocre JavaScript
programmer and just a beginner in
becoming a journalist thank you very
much