bye
okay so sorry about that often I do
without the speaker notes to this fine
yeah as I said I'm not an expert by any
means one of my goals is basically not
to become grumpy developer who runs away
from the new JavaScript frameworks I
want to sort of embrace this change and
I think like the more time I spend at
this that the grumpy grumpy or someone
can become and I've definitely worked
with some folks who have become so
grumpy nyan they've moved off to do
other things or moved up in management
or move to different roles and they just
gotten frustrated with the change so
like a part of that is to address this
like how can we approach this how can we
change our attitudes so my talk is
simple it's broken up into a few pieces
the first one is constant change as a
factor in Java and JavaScript and in
philosophy and maybe we can learn
something by it sort of comparing the
two and you know take a look take the
lessons from one and apply them to the
other that's sort of my goal so yeah the
second one is sort of changing your
attitude to deal with that change and
then the third one is sort of advice to
my younger self and so I think it's easy
for this to become super preachy and
yeah yeah saying like oh I know
everything now I'm going to frame this
as a sort of a humble you know advice to
younger me but also its kind of advice
to my current self because I'm still in
the progress in process of becoming
better a better human being better
developer so the first one constant
change it turns out to be like a super
important recurring theme in philosophy
for today we're kind of going to focus
on older philosophies the first one sort
of from the Western perspective is
Heraclitus who famous famously said you
cannot step twice into the same stream
everything changes nothing remains still
interestingly a contemporary of
Heraclitus is someone you may have heard
of Buddha nothing changes nothing
remains without change that these are so
similar to each other is kind of
interesting not so much paradox but it's
sort of
like suspicious like someone copied the
other person you know it's too
coincidental there must have been some
wisdom being transferred along the trade
route but you know both cultures we
think of them is so separate like East
and West but they turn out to both care
about this this recurring thing that
there's just constant change in the
world and how do we deal with it you
know it stresses us out and this is the
foundation for Buddhist philosophy
change sort of leads to suffering and
suffering is one of the things we try to
get away from in the world we have to
sort of transcend it and recognize the
impermanence of the world and so maybe
in small ways we can apply that to sort
art every day developer lives you know
constant framework churn just dealing
with that situation this is something
from more than a millennia later but I
thought it was interesting because it
was very similar to Heraclitus as well
it's a Japanese story the current of the
flowing river does not cease thing I
think the water is not the same water as
before very similar so sort of pulling
this back to just little old me and so
thinking back to sort of start of my
career JavaScript career I sort of
jumped into a job started using whatever
they were using there probably was the
latest framework so you I'm just going
to call it framework X for now and it's
the way of the future it's the way of
the future you know this is the latest
and greatest thing this must be what the
future looks like you know it's not
going to change much from here this is
what we're set on right everything
before it's just total crap we don't
need to worry about that this is the way
of the future it's all framework X huh
and you start writing blog posts and
maybe you give some talks you go to meet
ups and okay you've reached expert level
okay and and you're becoming kind of
entitled at this point probably an
arrogant as we have want to do you know
I know everything about this that you
should listen to me I know I know what
it's all about everything is well and
dandy for a little while and you think
of yourself maybe as uber developers
maybe or not maybe I kind of self to see
but then this happens new JavaScript
framework appears on the horizon okay
people start using it and maybe you
think oh this is just the latest trend
you think you know this is a flash in
the pan that is going to go away you
know framework X is so much better in
all these ways you know I don't have to
pay attention to this but people you
know pick it up more and more and sort
of start adopting it and writing posts
about it and this is where all the
excitement is happening like nowadays it
seems to be like in the direction of
react next year probably something else
but you know basically yeah it's sort of
this situation you've probably seen this
before sort of like oh yeah backbone
it's the new thing yeah it's the new
hotness Oh angular yeah yeah react yeah
and it's just this it's like a fashion
trend it's like man is it is this actual
progress or is it just changes in
fashion and people jump in on bandwagons
and you know this is kind of like
frustrating because like you know you
start at one of these years in the past
year and you've seen this all in your
kind of like okay I've been through this
before like why am I even learning this
new framework and you kind of get pissed
off and that's where the grumpy
developer sort of comes in you want to
avoid that so yeah this is part of my
perspective this is like okay how can I
sort of change my attitude to not be
like that to sort of be receptive to
this to be able to keep up with it this
is her cleitus putting on his developer
hat in this case this JavaScript head
technology is constantly changing cannot
step twice into the same stat tech stack
which is exactly the case it's
constantly changing people are
constantly changing even the libraries
themselves are changing over time we saw
that with angular 1 2 angular 2 and now
people got all frustrated and you is
everything changed like why don't I
don't just move to react down you know
you know people get frustrated with that
this is a something you probably saw Ben
nato's blog about angularjs in
particular and it's kind of like a
optimistic perspective this angular JS
one it's optimistic because there's
still upward trend it's sort of like
your feelings get better about the
framework over time you're sort of like
you start out with nothing at x 0 you go
on your like
is pretty cool and then you're like you
get frustrated with pieces of it and you
dip down into a valley and then you go
up again you plateau and then you're
like this is really crappy why did they
do this you know but you're you feel
like you're making progress because
you're getting more comfortable with
that framework you know this is this is
a good thing right you're making
progress but the reality is we change
out framework so often especially in the
front end world and the JavaScript world
that it feels to me like more like this
like you start out from time zero with
nothing you go up to a certain level you
learn this framework and then this is
like over the course of years maybe your
whole career or something and then you
plateau and then you hit a valley again
because you basically have to discard a
bunch of your knowledge and you have to
be happy well not you don't have to be
happy with that you have to be okay with
that to be able to continue being a
developer so i would say fifty percent
at least maybe greater of your knowledge
that you worked so hard to acquire is
just chucked out the window and you have
to you have to be okay with that
impermanence and that's a hard thing to
do so you're later career becomes okay
maybe i'm not an expert in anything
really i'm just going to keep my head
down at my job and you know hopefully
they don't notice you know i'll be
proficient but you know I'm not like
uber developer obviously and then later
on obviously you switch to programming
and go move to Florida as judge Smith
said and this leads into this constant
changes is recognized I think we all
agree in philosophy and in JavaScript
and in the world in our everyday lives
content change is just a fact of life so
the second part is our attitude towards
that so we can't control the constant
change but can we change our attitudes
towards that I think it's easier that we
can we can change our attitudes but it
might be difficult so I'm doing this by
way of analogy I have two analogies that
maybe we can use our knowledge of one
thing sort of apply it to JavaScript so
how we approach one thing and apply it
to another thing so the first one is
Swiss are
my knives so I'm going to say JavaScript
libraries are Swiss Army knives their
tools there means to an end you pick up
the Swiss Army knife you might not have
a fancy one but you know you use it as
means to an end it's not an end in
itself you know it's not the goal to
just have the light how did the library
or the knife and just say well this is
this is what it's all about now you use
that you'd apply that use it as a tool
for other things a hammer is another
good analogy but like Swiss Army knife
because it has some tools on there that
you use and some other things that you
probably don't use and you might not
even know what they are but that's okay
you know and then the new library comes
out it's got more features it's got
different features it's got a magnifying
glass that's pretty cool it's got like a
little hook thing that you don't even
know what that is for really is it for
fish Eden I don't know oh you got a
corkscrew still but it's it's basically
still a tool it's like your old tool but
it's slightly different you got some
scissors on there but you know it still
means to an end and these are these are
like libraries because they're kind of
smaller and everything and then you
might have this monstrosity this is like
the uber Swiss Army knife that's totally
impractical can you even take this
hiking or anything it has like like
clippers like nail clippers on it i like
how do you even use that you put it on
the desk or something and then I don't
know you have to get assistance for that
yeah frameworks are kind of more bloated
and it's got stuff on there you probably
don't really need but hey there it is
anyway but in any case all these things
are related they're all tools they're
all means to an end so we should be
thinking about the end in itself the
product that we're making so we can plug
and play all these different tools
basically swap them out but our focus
should be on the tools themselves it
should be on on the product and the
users don't really care they won't
really notice most the time so that's
the takeaway from this and it's
interesting because the javascript
library is a means to an end to building
the product the product itself is a
means to an end for the user the user
isn't using the product just because
they really like using the product
they're use it because they get
satisfaction from it that you
is it because they need to book a flight
like they're not going to just be
obsessed about that product well maybe
sometimes so in essentially the law the
driver script library becomes the means
to a means to an end it's not even like
the most essential thing in the whole
chain that we should be focused on
another analogy things you might have
heard of sand mandalas and I kind of
adapted this or stole this a little bit
from John rice eggs eulogy to why why
the lucky stiff from the Ruby community
basically this is sort of approaching
JavaScript libraries and recognizing
that they're impermanent and being okay
with that so Sandman dollars are these
things that have bitten monks basically
put together some days this is all made
of sand it's really delicate and they've
got these special tools that they're
sort of grinding and the sand is coming
out and you can check it out on video
you can look up like San Mandela just
your construction and destruction
destruction is is the second point and
that's sort of the more interesting part
of this right after they finish building
it they they destroy it like okay what's
the point then you know like it's so
it's so ephemeral it only lasts for a
few days and now it's gone like you know
we have a tendency to want to preserve
it like you know I think in the Western
world we would say oh you should put
some like glass over that or put some
glue over that's where the sand doesn't
shift around or we have a tendency to
want to hold on to things and we're not
okay with sort of like letting things go
we have a tendency to swear when I
accumulate preserve it hanging on the
wall you know and you got this whole
massive fortune that you've built up
over time and that sort of your goal of
life is preserve all those things you
come in contact with but this philosophy
is quite different from that it's sort
of like hey you know life is impermanent
you know you got to you got to come to
terms with that sometime so this is an
exercise in impermanence and being
comfortable with that and that it
exactly turns out to be the life of the
developer because they construct this
framework and you may be like an author
on that library but you have to
recognize that thing is going to be
around for forever
you know it's it's like a few years I
don't know a decade if you're lucky you
know I have not even a decade really but
you have to be okay with that and I
think we can get help from a soak
philosopher if it epictetus on this
point of all things are in our power of
things somewhere in our power and others
are not of a harsh appearance if a harsh
appearance relates to anything which is
not in our power be ready to say there's
that is not concern you I don't know
what concern it looks like that but
anyway you get the point so there's
things that are in our control some
things that are not in our control if we
should be worried about one or the other
we should be worried about things so we
can control because we can fix it and we
can make it better so we can't control
the turn of JavaScript frameworks and
libraries so we put on the developer hat
we do not have control over JavaScript
frameworks changing but we have control
of our attitudes towards them changing
and that's the key thing now this is
obviously easier said than done we can
say oh yeah I'm in control my attitude
but this turns out to be super hard and
this actually is like the starting point
of all of the stoic philosophy endeavor
is recognizing this point and then
trying to address it trying to control
your attitude towards it so the both of
these Sigmund allergies sort of give us
these points they embrace the constant
chains and impermanence that's the sand
mandalas and control our attitudes
towards that change that's what the
stoic started for them basically so now
we're come into the last part of the
talk so it's a short talk advice to my
younger self keep it in mind this isn't
just to my younger self actually don't
get too attached to your favorite
JavaScript framework it's not going to
be around forever but become proficient
in it and be able to use it it's a tool
that you have to employ it to as a means
to an end so get comfortable with it but
be ready to let it go when the next
thing comes along something that's been
said over and over again focus on
vanilla JavaScript
basically because it changes less than
the job is your frame works although
javascript is changing a lot very
recently but it does change at a slower
pace than those frameworks and that's
sort of built into the core library if
javascript is language you're using
should get comfortable with sort of
framework list javascript and in general
get comfortable languages in general
because maybe you're not going to use
JavaScript tomorrow maybe again is
something else so that sort of is an
extension of that philosophy don't
despair over the JavaScript landscape
constantly changing actually it's kind
of an exciting thing you knew what
you're getting into when you got into
this career because everyone sort of
said I changes too much you know I can't
deal with it you know but people said
well this is part of what's what's the
excitement about you know being a
front-end developer it's like you're
constantly learning constantly learning
new things you never get bored with it
but when you and you're in Europe you're
okay with that you sign up for that and
when you actually experience that you're
like this kind of sucks you know like
you have to ditch like fifty percent of
my knowledge like every year or a couple
years or so that kind of like actually
experiencing that is kind of a pain but
so but don't despair over it as much as
you can try not to despair like I said
easier said than done but yeah I'd be
ready throw away large chunks of
knowledge as I said be more humble
you're not goober developer unless
you're special maybe you are uber
developer but I'm not so I think just
over time with more experience you kind
of become more humble naturally I see
this happen with developers a lot over
time like and they they're younger they
start out it's kind of bull it's
exciting it's new and they get become
very confident which is ok you know like
and then you learn like man I don't know
as much as I thought I knew and that is
like yeah that's very true or philosophy
in general to sort of you start with
like a sophomoric view of the world and
then you learn crap I don't know nothing
no grammar be selective about applying
old knowledge so yeah we have to ditch a
lot of old knowledge but we do get to
keep some of it like
the principles and things like that that
can be applied generally we have that
experience and we're not throwing away
all our knowledge when new stuff comes
out but we have to be selective so this
happens a lot when you come into a new
job and you're like I want to use
everything I used to use at my old job
so it's like you know but we're not even
using the same framework or library you
know and like you have to be really
selective it you're going to piss off
your co-workers too you're like well at
my old job you know we use you know mood
tools and this function is essentially
the same as that but you know move tools
was a little faster and no one wants to
hear that it's just annoying so you have
to sort of be selective with that
there's still useful stuff that you know
obviously but not all of that is going
to be useful not all of your experience
is still useful so think twice before
you you give advice with it and this is
something that came out from a talk
yesterday from Aaron Quint stock which
was awesome by the way if you didn't get
a chance to see it watch it online when
they post it it's definitely worth
seeing and it's very similar to the
sakai thing but he does a very good job
with a bill cool things with blank
choose your tool and just build build
the thing be concerned with the thing
itself like that the end not the means
to an end so just pick up the hammer or
the Swiss Army knife start building
stuff and put it down put it down at the
end of the day be proud of you know what
you've made basically and then yeah this
is kind of what i was implying before
this isn't actually a advice to my
younger self this advice my current self
to you so so I haven't really perfected
how to get to these points I've
convinced myself of these things but I
don't necessarily know how to get to
them so hopefully maybe that helps you
too but I'm not I don't know the way to
get to feel all these things like I can
convince myself okay I need to have this
kind of attitude like that but like
actually doing it and actually having
the experience of doing that as a
different thing so maybe that's you know
for everyone else to work out I think
the good thing that came out of this is
actually I realized you know actually as
you get that experience your life
competent see kind of goes up where
sort of like the the JavaScript
competency level kind of was a sine wave
over time and it felt like you weren't
really making general progress which is
kind of pessimistic crappy of you
looking at things but it's kind of how I
feel a lot of the time actually you get
better at life you get better being a
human being over time and actually
that's the thing that it turns out to
matter i think because you could use
your life experience in other things
other than programming and life is more
about programming obviously so if you
just spaced out or whatever that's cool
I'm cool with that but like is it too
long didn't watch I could too long
didn't read change is constant it's
uncontrollable because it's
uncontrollable I need to shape my
attitude to accept things and that
better attitude can make me a better
human and I think better humans make
better developers just by virtue of the
fact at least that they're better
co-workers I want to work with good
human well-rounded human beings so I
think that working on ourself and our
attitudes can make us better co-workers
and in that sense make us better
developers if that's what we want to
become I think that's an essential piece
maybe it's not sufficient but its
necessary for that and I just do this in
that at the end of thing hellos other
browsers there's nothing really to do
with anything but this is from PP k's
blog PPK his old time JavaScript
developer if you haven't read his blog
so he obsessively tracks you know all
the differences between browsers I think
he still does and mobile browsers more
nowadays but I thought was funny so yeah
if you want to check out the sides or
reach me on twitter yeah thanks for