I think we should think more outside of
the box
my name is Phillip in racing on Twitter
you found me a spikey on github you
found yes poltergeist yeah we think we
use our technologies like each day the
same way like totally the same way we
should reconsider basically like do it
differently let's take for example
we right get commit messages like each
day this could be a journal basically
how we write them right so like a blog
isn't it so wait this is actually pretty
awesome so let's say I prepared
something which I call like good luck or
good journal basically so I have
different commit messages basically the
ones which I don't want to show my blog
is basically that's - - exclude and this
is how I recognize them so you see
basically good luck has basically
already two different styles like short
here like one is the very big version
the other one is very condensed so I've
had like a little or a couple of NPM
scripts which basically do create like a
different were which creates a custom
format for get locks and I write the
this to like in index markdown file and
yeah this is basically to add a nice
seam on github and then I deploy this to
get her pages so let's create a message
so basically let's make a bookmark so
JSON Kampf is there's an awesome
conference you know and this might be
the link for the next awesome.js
uncomf-- which might mean next year so
let's put this like yeah right then we
credit commit or credit to commit and
then yeah we basically just run em run
build and this pushes to you well
basically this builds our spirit then it
pushes it to my
posit re and let's see this my screen
okay yeah oh let's see awesome there's
already what I've created out of my
divots that were out of my commit
messages so how far how far is this for
me blogging I don't know but it
definitely helps me was my get work flow
since I use crazy but where I have like
a similar get alias was a different
format which I usually run against
origin/master when before I created PR
and then I commit a copy this and paste
this at my commitment whereas my PR
message since I'm usually very verbal
and microwaved messages about how to how
you can test it and what I changed
actually so I push this onto my PRS and
nobody a because sometimes people don't
look at your commit messages like in
detail so this helps me in my daily
workflow and I just made it up then
where I just found this out by doing
something crazy
so sometimes we should come out of our
silos and look at stuff which we don't
usually do or even look at our stuff
with with a different set of eyes by
thinking outside of the box thank you
[Applause]