ah
as Chris said I'm a co-founder of 280
north my two co-founders are also here
Ross and Tom is somewhere we are
primarily responsible for a framework
called cappuccino we just really started
latest version 0.8 point 1 I will talk
about that a little bit later in the
presentation but as Chris said I kind of
wanted to do something a little bit
differently and kind of talk about what
was this kind of passion / side project
for us for the past couple of months and
has now increasingly become more
important as we start preparing for kind
of cappuccino one point oh and that is
documentation so I think it goes without
saying that documentation is really
important and I think most documentation
of most open source projects kind of
sucks ours included and I kind of want
to start this with kind of the funny
story behind cappuccino documentation so
if you go today to keva chino
documentation this is kind of what it
looks like it's it's your generic open
source documentation which is you know
we figured out how to use the tool that
spits out the method names and that's
more or less it there are some places we
were able to have some good descriptions
generally it's not that great we lucked
out however because since cappuccino was
based on an existing framework you know
we were basically implementing aspect
that already exists kind of the open
secret in the cappuccino community is
that you should never go to our Docs and
instead just go to developer apple com
and if you want to find out about CP
view you just read about NS view and the
documentation applies a hundred percent
not only that but if those aren't good
enough you can just hit the canoe staff
documentation which is also pretty darn
good and again applies one hundred
percent and if that's not good enough
then you can hit like all the different
cocoa blogs and books and stuff and you
know we even today recommend a cup of
cocoa books to our users so it we kind
of lucked out in this regard but we're
trying to change that for one point oh
the way I look at it is that we got
eighty percent for free like most open
source projects you know day one have
zero documentation
we had like seventy to eighty percent
good documentation the problem is
achieving that last twenty percent is
impossible with this model of oh just
disco ask Apple how to do it obviously
we can't change their dogs we can't add
anything new so we'd really like to do
for cappuccino 1 point 0 is have truly
world-class documentation and that's
kind of a problem because documentation
is hard and I think it's particularly
hard for any new project especially open
source and the reason I'm talking about
this here today and the reason Kris
asked me to talk about this is that i
think our community is at a place where
we could really benefit a lot from kind
of a revolution and documentation you
know we're at a place right now where
we're trying to really sell JavaScript
to a lot of people being able to do a
lot more than it could before you know
we're even taking the step of saying you
know you should be able to write your
servers in JavaScript and to be able to
do that to be able to convince people
upon kind of an already sketchy idea
they need to be able to know how to use
this stuff and again the problem with
most open source projects is that
they're really cool they're really
advanced but the documentation is kind
of terrible on day one and with these
kind of programming problems that have
nothing to do with code I think there's
a tendency to kind of look at in two
different ways one of them is to think
it's a cultural problem and this is kind
of what the testing community has done
right they've said well testing was a
cultural problem we have the right tools
for testing what we need to do is to
build a culture of testing and it's
worked out pretty well an example I
guess the flip side to that is to say
take technological problem and I usually
tend to side with that I happen to think
that most problems have technical
reasons and technical solutions and a
good example of that is version control
right I think most people are using
version control incorrectly not because
we had the wrong culture but we had the
wrong tools you know when get came out I
think all of us started using version
control completely differently we all
became much better and much more like
tightly knit community thanks to that
and it was all thanks to just a tool
that actually did its job correctly and
when I'm proposing today is that I think
that we do documentation completely
wrong and that's objectively like oh I
don't like it
but like mathematically provably wrong
and I think the main cause of this is
documentation and comments that's my
thesis for you I'll trying to make it
clever and save it to the end but you
know when you make your slides a day
before that you can't afford to do that
so I think that this is the root cause
of bad documentation in the JavaScript
community in the open source community
in most communities in general and so
before i get into exactly why that is i
want to give you guys a glimpse of how
your users for using your products
interact with your documentation what
the problems are so this is obvious
right day one you have no documentation
I think that's okay I think you'll never
solve that problem day one you should
have no documentation the problem is
that day two three four five months
later you still have really poor
documentation and we get into this place
eventually if you're I think a good open
source project where you have either
incomplete or incorrect documentation in
seconds for a lot of reasons right open
source projects iterate very quickly so
it's hard to keep the documentation up
to date and also when the source changes
your documentation becomes incorrect
right you fix a bug and the
documentation no longer matches etc etc
so for a whole number of reasons it's
really hard to keep your documentation
up to date with whatever tool you're
selling to users and what this means is
that your users are the second your
documentation is good enough they're
going to start looking at blogs we're
going to start looking at other places
and eventually they'll end up here your
IRC room otherwise known as purgatory
this is the worst place on earth on the
internet like I hate this so you go into
the IRC room you're like oh I'm using
this new tool and I'm naive and I want
to know how it works and your general
response is why are you trying to do
that idiot like come on like just take
my word for it there's a reason I'm
trying to call these functions just tell
me how they work and then you have to go
through the slow grueling process of
they have the information you don't so
you have to be nice to them all they get
to be a dick to you and
it's terrible it's absolutely so like
this is a cultural problem this is not
going to know IRC tool in the world will
make people not be jerks IRC but um so
kind of a corollary or you know a side
goal of Socratic is to make sure your
normal users never end up on your IRC
room we try really hard to keep our IRC
room very civil in fact if 280 north
goes out of business if no one if
everyone stops using cappuccino I will
still say you know this company was a
success because we were pretty good in
our IRC room so again we try to keep
people out of here you know for your own
benefit we're trying to keep people out
of your eye or serum so the other
problem with documentation for your
users is that it's generally not rich
right it's generally just a bunch of
text when a lot of times a movie or a
picture would be a lot better for them
and both these problems see to this that
I kind of alluded to which is at the end
of the day your documentation ends up
all over the place right it's really
exciting when you have a new project
when people start blogging about it but
blog posts are the worst forms of
documentation because they never get
updated like you're a ton of projects
were like the way you theme is described
in a blog post that came out you know a
year ago and that's the number one hit
on Google and it's not the way you theme
anymore until you go and you tried and
it's wrong and then go into the IRC room
good doesn't work let me back to square
one so I think that ideally most people
would have to hit your main docs
obviously you want to have a community
that like talks about your project and
everything but ideally you want your
website for your project to be the
central place where people get
information because the other problem is
that users like it seems really
intuitive to us like oh yeah there was a
blog post for years ago that describes
how to do this why didn't you check that
well it's really hard for users to know
that's right they go to your main site
if they don't find it they're kind of
stuck this is another huge problem right
like all this applies sevenfold's for
like a 100 falls for japanese or
whatever like we have for documentation
English no documentation in the other
language right and obviously that's
really bad because most people don't
speak English so if you want your
project to be successful it should be
really easy to localize your
documentation and this is the absolute
worst problem this is the problem we're
trying to face which is all this other
stuff is kind of okay and expected like
you have got documentation whatever
that's okay as long as it's capable of
getting better but because of the way
most of our documentation systems are
set up we make it so difficult for
people to contribute back documentation
so what we learned is that people who
want to document cappuccino are
generally not our core contributors you
know our core contributors want to write
code it's generally people who are
writing actual apps that want to write
our documentation and they're actually
the best suited for this right they just
spent all this time going through the
hell that you created to learn how to
use your framework now they want to give
that back well now you've got new hoops
for them to jump through right well your
main users are probably not using
version control right they're using your
nightly builds or whatever so step one
is they might have to learn gate or svn
or whatever to get your code just to be
able to document it right so that may be
a challenge for them step 2 they need to
learn how to build your product or
whatever great because you can't to make
code that you haven't built step 3 is
you have to learn how to use kind of an
obtuse documentation tool we used oxygen
it's not the easiest thing to install
and learn and finally they have to learn
your whole you know your culture of
patches or whatever they have to make a
patch they have to send it to you you
might send you know come back with them
with like you're using tabs instead of
spaces or whatever and at the end of the
day it's just really really hard for
them to make any sort of real
contribution and if they really hard
trying to real contribution then you can
imagine no one's ever going to take the
time to do all this to like fix
capitalization or whatever in your code
right and in your comp and your
documentation so now I want to talk
about the problems for us like the
maintainer of projects now there's some
dispute over this this is my opinion I
think documentation in text is
incredibly annoying I don't like having
to scroll pages in between methods I
don't like seeing a bunch of stuff
that's designed for other people to
learn I especially don't like seeing
HTML in my comments I've already
programming one language I don't want to
see whatever crazy language you invented
to like few documentation in my comments
all green right again there's this
problem how do you localize like
documentation and comments are you gonna
have like 50 languages all in the
content of course I and you know
documentation and text in comments is
annoying to me imagine to someone who
doesn't speak your language where
there's all this foreign language that
old like in some funky color but they
don't understand what it means i've used
japanese source code this sucks i hate
it not japanese source code just
effective you it's in that i'm sorry
just got cut off but it says it requires
specialized tools you know that may not
exist for your language and then the
other thing was our framework so the
problem with this is that the problem
with this is that there's kind of this
is kind of a spectrum right like on one
extreme you have us we kind of almost
invented a new language right we added
to javascript so day one we had a
problem where no documentation tool
existed to handle our language and
that's you know pretty terrible and i
think we're going to see more more than
that right we're starting to see in the
JavaScript world more people creating
kind of dsl's or you know a brand new
languages on top of JavaScript you know
like coffee script and you know deck
today which is ours and you know right
off the bat you don't have a tool that
can properly look wise I mean properly
document that so what we actually had to
do was use an existing tool called
doxygen and I said oh it should be easy
it's plug-in based I can you know create
a new parser for my language well you
have to write the plugins in C++ and I
didn't get into the web to write C++
again so that was out so what we
actually ended up doing is someone in
our community took the time to write a
converter from objective J the
objective-c just we can feed it into
doxygen just so I can get the shitty
documentation that we have now so that's
pretty bad and it's also a problem like
in other languages obviously any new
language is going to have this problem
and also in a very dynamic languages are
going to have this to such as Ruby and
JavaScript where you're kind of almost
creating dsl's right like your
documentation tool probably doesn't know
that class dog create means you're
creating a class it can't pick up on
that automatically right and yes i know
i misspelled language
here's here's the other bad part which
is uh it's really hard to include rich
media right and this gets back to the
whole languages within you know your
comments it's bad enough I have to read
this this documentation that's not meant
to me meant for me in the comments
without all of a sudden there's like a
video tag in there or random link or
stuff like that and on top of that you
know there's a question where you put
this stuff right well if the images and
the videos end up in your source repo
then all of a sudden you know it takes a
long time to download my source code is
because they're a bunch of stupid movies
in there right what you should have but
not in your source rebuild and
ultimately just like it's hard for the
people using your stuff to contribute
comments I mean documentation it sucks
for you to have to actually review it I
can tell you that when i get a commit or
like a pull request which is entirely
documentation the temptation to ignore
forever or you know allow immediately
without review is super high and that
should not be the case so we're working
on this new tool close to product we're
not done we're specifically announcing
it to ask for help from you guys and
it's kind of a new take on documentation
you kind of our idea is if you want to
have really great documentation for 10
we want a building system that allows us
to quickly build up documentation um in
there and we've tried to address all the
different problems and the first one was
the parser problem right every time you
start your documentation tool kind of
step one is you know a not so fun
programming task of building a parser
and what some people have done is create
like little pseudo languages or whatever
to create easier parsers that are you
know mainly for documentation but again
you have to learn how to use this etc
etc so we are really really good I
piggybacking off of other people's
success I think it's one of our best
qualities and so what we've done is Oh
first let me say this is the guy was
actually making this is our intern what
he looks like in case you're a visual
learner that's as a Twitter he's
actually doing all the work I just sat
down and pontificated over the phone to
him and you know he said okay I'll
mented but anyways what we're doing is
using existing technologies and textmate
already has a huge storage of language
definitions so basically what Socratic
is capable of doing is if you already
have a text mate bundle for your
language socratic knows how to parse and
create documentation for it and if
you're brand new language and you don't
have a text may bundle well at least
it's two birds with one stone right
because not only are you creating the
documentation parser but you're also
getting you know the plug-in for the
most used text editor for free and so if
you're not familiar with the way
textmate handles source code it's really
quite cool I personally think that text
made is one of the ugliest programs ever
created that's why I don't use it
however internally it is quite beautiful
and this is what it does it actually
creates these things called scopes so
basically you know right here that's
some objective J code that's the class
name and as you can see it knows it's in
the objective J source and it knows it's
within a class implementation so as it's
parsing it kind of creates like a tree
of your source code like live right and
so here I have a method with in table
view and as you can see once again it
knows working the source code that
subjective J which is no kind of like
JavaScript it knows that if we're in a
you know implementation of a class and
love a blind it even knows that where my
cursor was right here when I was doing
this it even knows that I'm in the
argument types and what kind of type it
is so textmate is incredibly smart it
knows exactly what's going on in all
your source code and there's already a
librarian Ruby called text cow which
uses this information to syntax
highlight and you should check it out
it's very cool and we took this idea a
little bit further and what we actually
do when you run socratic on your source
code is we build up the Dom of your
source this is kind of how you can
imagine it being that that's that little
snippet if you're familiar with HTML
then this should be very familiar to you
we're basically taking all those corpse
and scopes and building the tag soup out
of them and the really cool thing about
that is that that allows us to create
queries right so all of a sudden you
don't have to write parsers for your
language or your DSL or you know
your framework anymore you can just do
queries and this is a very very powerful
thing so this is just like an example if
you imagine docks at Kempton org slash
classes / CP table column you do
something just like jQuery where you say
well give me all the implementations
where the name of the class is CP table
column you can do many more powerful
things too like and cappuccino there is
a convention that all methods that start
with an underscore our private so you
could actually say give me all the
methods in the class ap table column
which do not start with an underscore
and that's really easy to do with this
query language so when you build your
templates it's really really easy to do
things like will give me all the strings
within the function class talk create
and i'm going to say those are my
classes so it's really a powerful
templating language the second thing is
i think pretty obvious from what i was
talking about earlier if you're not
putting your documentation in the source
code then it's a wiki and it's a media
wiki so people can put movies and
whatever they want the other interesting
part is that it's a wiki based on get
this is actually one of the places where
I'm very curious if people have other
ideas the idea here is that we're trying
to make it really easy to keep your
documentation up to date with your
source code so what commonly happens is
you have a lot of people running off
trunk but your source code represents
the stable branch and no one wants to
update the stable branch like source
code that's public because well then you
know would represent stuff that's not
shipping so what we actually do is since
it's a good base wiki it matches the
branches of your source code so if you
tag a release a 0.6 or whatever when
people hate your source code they can
actually say well show me the
documentation as it was during 0.6 or
show me what the documentation for this
new feature branches or show me blah
blah blah so it matches all the branches
and creates a pretty powerful way of you
know managing the different
documentation few different versions of
your source code secondly we built in
support for date of issues so at some
point we're going to you know make it
generic and let you do whatever right
now we're just trying to ship something
so this tries to solve that original
problem of they go to your documentation
it's
have to go somewhere else etc what we're
trying to do is you hit the
documentation and you see the
description of the method and right
under it you see all the bugs following
that method right so if you know the
method says you know should return six
and there's a bug filed on it that says
returns five you know immediately
there's a problem you don't need to go
try it think that maybe it's your fault
end up in the IRC room or whatever and
the next step to this is we would also
really like to include the tests right
next to it so I think would be cool if
you know you have the method description
here are all the bugs and hear all the
tests so if you see that a test is
failing it's almost like an automatic
bug right so we haven't worked on that
part at all yet but the github issues
thing is working pretty well so yeah so
so kind of the sum of what socratic is
doing it's it's using text me bundles to
automatically generate a wiki for your
documentation you know that sits on
topic did so I can you know
automatically track the different
branches and stuff of your revo it will
automatically synchronize with your bugs
and tests and the other thing we've done
is just building out of the box support
for github and the idea is you just type
socratic and then you get URL and you
have a server that's running that's your
your documentation so it should be a
really really easy in the day you took
your code to have really great
documentation for it and of course it's
built entirely on top of common Jas and
this is important for two reasons one
because I think we really need this
right now because you know again we're
kind of a new community for building
lots of new stuff we can really document
it well and the other thing is I think
this could be a really powerful coup for
us because documentation again I believe
to be like a space that's not really
paid attention to a lot and I think if
we create like the gold standard of a
documentation tool we can get a lot of
people to be running how much Jes
servers serving this step up and you
know that will introduce them to kind of
you know JavaScript on the server etc so
I'm pretty excited about that um so what
I'm going to show you now is not the
actual documentation tool it's not done
i'm going to show you kind of the tool
that we use to analyze what's going on
in the background
you'll understand the second so this is
here I'll show you what happens right
now so again when you load this up the
first time so again the idea is that you
would not do this in a you I you know
you running off your server but again
it's set up right now to automatically
piggyback off of any existing repo so
I've already have the one set up for
cappuccino and the way the the queries
are working right now is that they are
file based but again you could turn this
around so right now again all it does is
this is this is being automatically
generated from our queries so there's no
there's no fancy parsing taking taking
place we're just saying you know give me
everything that looks like a method
within everything that looks like a
class etc so your dough if you look at
individual methods and again we have the
capability of here are all the bugs and
you can link the bug to the issue and
now those in the system are you know
considered tied together or whatever so
again this is kind of the tool we've
been using to test out these
technologies this is not the way we
think the documentation will look
obviously so yeah we're really excited
about this project again we'd like it to
be ready for one point o before then so
we can actually have dr. really good
documentation we really interested in
your guys's ideas ultimately we want
this to be you know a really great
documentation tool for everyone if you
have any ideas kind of like the things
that have always bugged you about
documentation feel free to talk to us if
you want to start writing code for this
feel free to talk to us there really
isn't a one repo for this yet because
again our interns partially working on
it and we are when the coming weeks
we'll release kind of one place where
all this stuff is together yeah so that
is Socratic defense or presentation
alright so that was again saccadic and
now I want to talk about cappuccino just
for a little bit about our new release
the coolest part about the new release
is that and it is built entirely on top
of common Jas which means if you're
already running Narwhal or any other
common gas distribution you can now
install cappuccino with the JavaScript
you know package manager notice tusk
tusk and sell cappuccino and you will
have it the other cool thing is that our
entire system is on top of GX which
means we don't build with Ruby anymore
we don't require you know our users to
you know install some crazy jam or
anything you know we use build tools
that are built with JavaScript we know
who's you know JavaScript across the
board all the tools we provide the
custom ones are built in public comes
yes so I'm really excited about this
this was actually one of our main
complaints I really don't understand why
like Ruby comes installed on Mac OS 10 I
never understood why people find this to
be hard but whatever you know the users
wanted they don't need to know Ruby
anymore the one I think valid complaint
was that if people wanted to fix bugs in
our build tools or whatever if they
didn't know Ruby then yeah of course it
was going to be hard for them so now
that's not an issue anymore it's one
language across the entire system we I
think are now at a point where we can
have parity with other languages like
Python and Ruby or that's the case so
it's pretty exciting the other really
cool addition is CP table view this is
one of the classes that was most
obviously missing when we shipped Kevin
G no it's one of the most used classes
in cocoa it's really really important on
the web and on the desktop and this was
created entirely by outside contributors
which is pretty exciting to us mainly
because that means I don't have to know
at all how it works and that's always
good and it's very performant that's
very beautiful and I not only think that
we have like all the coolest-looking and
performing table views but it's also one
of the easiest to make because we
shipped 08 with nib to sip support for
table view modes like to show you that
now so if you're not familiar with a
cappuccino we have kind of two main ways
that people make kind of you is for a
framework
one is with our tool called atlas and
the other one is using Apple's existing
interface builder tool which were
capable of converting into web
interfaces and ever since we released
new to civ this is kind of the main way
that people make you eyes with kevin t
know now because i think it's way easier
so i'll go ahead and show you how you
make a table view in epigenome so here's
this this zip file which if you've ever
done anything on mac OS 10 this is kind
of how you make interfaces in OS 10 so
this is kind of like the main window of
my application and if i want a table
view I just bring it up here
and you know we can add columns and give
it alternating road colors and that sort
of thing
so that's kind of all it takes to
actually make the table view and then to
get the data you just need to give it a
data source so we use this technology
called connections so I just connect the
table view to my app controller which
will be providing the data for the table
view and then I save it and
we go that will convert the file
so this is the table view we just
created and it's got 5 million rows and
as you can see was pretty darn good of
course we're just providing dummy data
but still pretty impressive for went
away they're just so that's how you make
table views in cavaquinho really heavy
with this feature I'd like to try some
more features from table view but I'm
going to take the chance to kind of show
you two features together so something
we released recently with 08 is this new
cap record tool and basically what this
lets you do is record interactions and
basically the idea is you know your
users can kind of record what they're
doing if they have a bug that can send
it to you and then you can see what's
going on so I'll go ahead and hit record
here I'll reload the app so these are
kind of the different kind of table view
styles which is like a list style you
can sort these rows I guess you can sort
the Rose I'm sorry very good so you can
drag and drop and we've got like
different kind of drag and drop and
stuff and if i get stopped one this will
actually save it on the server and then
you know wherever the servers running
so some apps
so
we go to actually we play again
everything we just did as again really
cool because people can send you you
know where they're experiencing bugs and
stuff and then you can profile on your
machine or you know do the whatever
debugging you want and what we actually
found which we didn't expect was that
this tool was actually really useful for
this device over here the iPad because
as is generally the case with the web we
take one step forward in like a thousand
map so the ipad is really great web wise
because you know it's it only runs web
kids we can you know rely on all these
fancy features which were usually afraid
to use or whatever but it's really bad
because it's kind of jettisoned us back
to 2000 where we didn't have any sort of
tools at all there is basically no way
to debug any sort of web stuff on this
device there's a little debug console
built into Safari it sucks I can say
that because I wrote it and it's
terrible like it basically tells you the
errors you're having but it cuts off the
strings so your goodness you're running
I can see an error it doesn't fit so
your best option is to turn it sideways
and then you can see a little bit more
of the error because you have a little
bit more room so that's that's a basic
that's basically the extent of debugging
on the iPad so what we've done and I'm
just going to load this up here okay so
i guess the other question is well why
can't i just a bug in safari they're
both WebKit right well that is true for
the most part but if you have bugs that
happen due to like touch events and
stuff you can't because you know Safari
does it have touch events on this
machine and you can take the time to
like manually recreate the events
yourself but that's a real pain so this
tool is really great because you can
actually let me so take a second to load
here you can actually do whatever
interactions you want on the iPad let it
crash and then you can run it back here
and then profile it or you know catch
the errors or break on the air and see
exactly what's going on because you know
we can translate all the events and
everything so I me do some stuff here
again I'm sorry that I'm not showing you
this live we wanted to hook it up but as
it turns out this thing does not export
video by default like your app has to
support that feature and we thought it
was silly to write a native app to wrap
the WebKit to show how cool web apps are
on the iPad so hopefully I can now show
you this here
so take a second load up Cyrus our
servers pretty slow
when I just made
here you go so as you can see that's me
doing all the touch events and stuff and
you know getting all the wonderful CSS
redraw errors as you can see so this
allows you to go in there to bug see
what's going on yeah so I think that's
pretty cool we've been using this tool
to write a kind of an iPad app that we
are going to open source soon it's
called scrapbook I'll show you that very
briefly this is this this we're going to
open sources completely and we're also
going to release it and basically lets
you create scrapbooks um so come here
you know you can choose a template this
is pretty cool it actually grabs the
images straight from your facebook
account this is using a new plug-in for
cappuccino called Facebook kit that we
released recently so as you can see
you've got like different templates and
stuff and you know you can you have the
images and drag them in and do touchy
kind of things so yeah so that's pretty
cool again we're going to be open
sourcing this the other cool thing is
we're going to be releasing this and
we're going to have a print button so
will actually send you your scrapbook
printed out in paper so you can show it
to your grandma who does not have any
ipad or apparently those are built for
her so maybe it'll be for you so one of
the cool things about the way we built
this app is that we used atlas to do it
so Atlas is this other tool was talking
about like we have nib to save which is
completely open source so you don't have
to pay us or anything to use it and
Atlas is kind of our version of this
Apple tool and the really cool thing
about it is we recently added this
plugins feature where you can write your
own custom UI plugins for Atlas so if I
open this out this is the project and
what we did was write a plug-in for kind
of our scrapbook pages so we're actually
able to give our designer just Atlas and
this plug-in and he doesn't need to send
us Photoshop files that we need to cut
up or anything he can actually just
build these templates himself so show
you that
so it's all the little template pages
you saw running on the iPad there are
actually created right here so this is
how we lays them out and again doesn't
need to know any code or anything and
you know these things have their own
little custom inspectors so it comes
here and you can say well this is
actually a cover back color or page
whatever and and this is really cool
because you can write your own custom
ones of these so if you're using Atlas
and you have a new UI element you can
write your own inspectors and you know a
lot of people to use it yeah and you can
actually do this interface builder too
so if you want to write your own IP
plugins again in the open source world
without having to deal with us you can
do that and finally the last thing I
wanted to show that we're actually
announcing today this is not part of 0.8
is an improvement to nip to sip and we
thought it was a good we've actually had
this kind of under wraps for a while but
we thought it was a good time to talk
about this feature given all the stuff
that's going on with you know what
languages you're allowed to use on you
know iPad and not and I always thought
it was not a very interesting question
of you know how to get more stuff into
the ipad i think you know if Apple wants
to you know have the lock and key to
this device that's fine to me much more
interesting question is how do you get
stuff that's already on the iPad out so
as I've already said like we have this
technology called nip to see which is
capable of transforming Mac os10 desktop
apps into html5 web apps well we've
actually extended you to save to allow
the same kind of thing to happen with
iphone app so I'll show you that very
quickly right here just like before i'm
going to open up apples tools this is if
you've never built an iphone app this is
kind of how you do it these are like
their visual tools you can come in here
and you know
set everything up so I'm obviously
building something very simple here and
if I hit run this launches the iPhone
simulator well this isn't my bug this is
apple stuff Oh hurt all right there um
so you know since I'm very obviously a
very simple out right so what we do is
if we save this now I can go here and
just like before i can run new cusub
oh sorry
there we go I think Lou the the family
area so now what the app that started
off as an iphone / ipad app or whatever
will show up on the web and it's
completely converted and this will run
on android or on palm OS or whatever and
again we've started off with just like
three or four classes just like when we
originally wrote a new to sit for the
desktop that we're adding more and more
classes and just like right now in it to
save is a very very complete tool if
you're going from desktop to web
hopefully in a little while this will be
a very complete tool to go from iphone
to the web so we're pretty excited about
that and i guess i'm running out of time
so i was going to show you a few apps
running on a late but since i'm at a
time i will just end it there and say
yes this enforces the urls to get to all
this stuff again do you want to contact
us to about this documentation stuff for
anything else you saw feel free to do so
we're happy to hear all your comments