ah
my name is had a more i work at yahoo i
work in a Yui team and I was going to
talk about something that's been going
on for the last about two or three weeks
Dave glass many of you probably familiar
with him he he's an engineer on the Yui
team and he's been experimenting with
running Yui on the server side
specifically Yui 3 and really he made a
lot of progress in a short amount of
time in fact if you think and I'm
talking about events today I changed in
the last minute because because this was
a lot more interesting a lot more
topical for today so we chose nodejs I
think everyone knows what it is you saw
Ryan's presentation yesterday it was it
was basically it's fast and it's
JavaScript server-side process we're not
looking at nodejs as being the only
thing we're going to try this on but but
this is what we've done so far so we
wanted we wanted to try this because we
think it is time to to basically take
advantage of all the code that we've
been writing on the client the AP is
that we have in Yui people are writing
more complicated applications that that
can't be translated to the server and
hopefully we can do some really cool
things and one of the things I want to
talk about in particular is progressive
enhancement what it means to be able to
take the same code that we're currently
generating controls with on a client and
moving it to the server as part of our
progressive enhancement strategy so why
do I three it's pretty new some of you
might be familiar with Yui to one of the
fundamental differences is that it's
very modular it has a as a module format
that's similar to the common jayus
module format
it the the strategy for loading Yui is a
is a small seed file 7k Steve file which
knows how to bootstrap the Yui loader
and and complete itself whatever
dependency those dependencies that you
need and one thing about the core of the
library it's not just about manipulating
DOM and that's important because when we
talk about nodejs we're talking about a
JavaScript runtime we're not talking
about a full browser implementation so
so what can we do with just the core we
can do I oh we have we do data
communication we have we have an
abstraction for managing our data sets
and and communicated communicating with
remote resources and getting that data
in JSON format or other ways we have a
custom event system and custom attribute
system if you look over at nodejs
there's module there's a modules
directory that has a lot of these these
sorts of things on that sit on top of
node.js today but you know these are
different API Z may be good we already
have code that's written with all this
stuff that that we can actually use it
today on the server side with the way
that node with Yui the way that Yui
works on node today we also have a
lightweight template template engine
it's kind of related to last talk if you
were if you were here the idea is that
the same thing that we might we might
used to generate strings can be used on
client server situationally so just a
little bit about how we made it work
first of all as of Yui 3 10 we we are
exporting the Yui object where we're
basically complying with the specs so
that any implementation that's going
against common J's bakit it should just
work at least the core part of the
library the rest of our modules are used
are marginal
module format Yui knows how to load
those modules but we don't have explicit
exports for each one of those modules so
once we did it pretty much worked but we
didn't really know what it was doing so
what we what we did is we configured Yui
to use a no GS way of actually
outputting whatever log messages that
are coming out of the Yui system Yui has
a bit built in log or that will do the
will log to the browser console but it
but in this case we can pass this this
configuration attribute to make its
biggest so that we can see what it's
doing and we can do a simple program I
know it's boring but this is how this is
how we get why you I running there's a
project called node node J s hyphen Yui
3 and that that projects available on
github under Dave glasses account and by
the way you can both nodejs and Yui 3
can support SHANY so you can chain it if
you like that kind of thing that first
line is is actually not required just
makes it simple more simple to execute
the program so this program can be
written in one line but then it works
does what you expect it to if we execute
it and and so that's cool but it doesn't
really do anything with the rest of the
library so the next part was to get the
loader to work and so the way that
loader works in a browser is it goes out
fetches remote well it calculates the
dependencies Fitch's remote resources
and and insert script nodes into the
document and then sets everything up so
all we had to do is replace the
transport that Yui normally uses to
something that is more that that uses a
nodes either remote
HTTP requests or local file reads to get
these resources instead of trying to
answer script notes that point
everything our system that that relies
on script note inserts just work so
loading these resources also things like
JSON p where we're using where we're
fetching remote data and and processing
that data so we can test that out this
was the first little simple test that
says okay we're going to get why you I
we're going to have it fetch the custom
event system and all the dependencies
that are required we're going to test
out the the custom event system and now
we see basically this is the output of
it it analyzes the dependencies it gets
the loader it it fetches all the
individual components this in this case
on the local file system it could get it
remotely as well hooks everything up and
then finally execute that custom event
so it works fine and that's cool
something more more sophisticated so why
you i knows how to load itself but it
also knows how to load Yui 3 gallery r
mod gallery modules and if you don't
know about the gallery basically you're
you can submit your code you know onto
our gallery and request to have it on
the CDN if you if you you have to it has
to be released under the same license
that Yui is and all this but we will put
it on the Yahoo CDN and then interest
intrinsically Yui 3 knows how to load
that and so in this case I'm actually
going to request a Yui 3 gallery module
for white YQL and JSON so it's going to
go out it's going to get yql from the
gallery so from the yahoo CDN analyze
its dependencies along with the JSON
dependencies do another combo URL to get
all those or get actually in this case I
think I'm getting them I'm configured to
get it locally yet and then finally I
can do
ql query i should get you know the
results on this expected in this case
I'm I'm Quarian my github user data and
I cut out all the all the boilerplate
but if I ran this look like this
so it goes out it's going to fetch it's
going to go and do all that dependency
processing like I was talking about
finally execute that query so on my
machine right here running nodejs I've
gotten remote data local data for the
library put it all together executed YQL
query which in turn use the new script
transport that I replaced and execute
that query I got everything back and it
works fine so pretty pleased with that
but that's but that's a good that's a
good start got some other ideas why you
want like I said why do I knows how it
will itself so why not have Yui load
itself from the server so now let's talk
about putting Yui behind a web server or
are actually exposing it as a web server
and and using the built-in loader have
it emit script and for Yui so in this
case what I've got here is a is a loader
service that actually will provide combo
handling locally all i'm doing is i'm
configuring yui to look for the
resources in a different location which
in this case this is a working a web
server on Dave glasses test machine so
and it should still be working
so I execute that code looks like this I
pointed out his combo server this is
drag and drop it works if we look at the
head of the document you can maybe see
if I can fit it that this is actually
one combo URL or combo handled script
that was served from his machine so
that's cool taking a step further
because Yui knows about the dependencies
that are requires we can take it one
step further and say when I request that
Yui script tag I can also fill in the
dependency trees i know i need upfront
so in this case i'm saying i'm passing
in module names that are Yui module
names drag and drop in I oh and it's
it's on the server side is going to
analyze all the dependencies give you
one combo URL for everything and now I
can immediately access that there'll be
no further HTTP requests if I'm not if I
if I don't need anything else one step
further quick Yui is a little extra
service on top of it says okay well
let's make it as easy as possible to use
Yui with this combo service so I need
these components I'll go ahead and get
all these components combo handle them
deliver them and also create a global y
variable create that instance for you
now you can get rid of that boilerplate
code that wraps the actual application
trying to reduce the barrier entry 2 by
2 to get in your application running so
all that works you know great it's
working right now
so it's same deal by the way why do I
that loader service is still on this on
the client side here so if i once i do
that the initial request and get that
payload i can always add more stuff that
isn't already on the page and the same
syntax you used to set up your instance
can be used later in this case i can ask
for slider the syntax for Yui use is
okay here's here's the component give me
give me a function to execute at the end
of it so whether or not i already have
the component available or i have to
fetch it so it's asynchronous my code
can run right then and it's all it's all
good by the way we can also combine
custom resources depending on your
configuration there's a there are a lot
of configurations for you to serve your
own components from your server or like
I was talking about with the gallery if
you submit it to gallery get it on CDN
and trinsic lee it will know how to pull
those resources let me back up a second
I know that there's I've heard that
there's a few people that prefer jquery
so i thought i'd try to see what happens
this morning if to get a jquery in here
so i ran this so i put this together
so this is actually how you can
configure those external resources is
one way and i'm just saying that i have
a jquery module that that's located here
then i can use it and it will pull it
and then try to execute that code and
you know it's actually run that it fails
it fails it's not surprising it's
looking for a window why you i would
have failed that way at one point in
time as well before I i mentioned that
Yui isn't all about the Dom but it but
it is a lot about the Dom so those
jquery and other these other libraries
and so the next step after all this is
like how cool would it be if we could we
can have some kind of Dom so on the
server side along with the nodejs if and
and and be able to use more components
from our library so Dave got on the case
I think that that was after the first
two days of everything I did hear the
next two days I think he got I got he
got the rest of it done but he put
together a couple of projects that are
out there j/s Dom both of these are
available on github jay is done he
worked with the with the author that one
to get it to work the way he needed to
work and HTML parser he he kind of
hacked that fork didn't acted a little
bit we needed it for inner HTML the Jazz
dump provides fooled on level one
support and these are generic JavaScript
implementations for developing a fake
Tom and and it works all of our Dom
related components can run under this
thing's like selector API that are no
wrapper around the around HTML elements
Dom creation manipulation styles all
these things actually work
are our test suites pass it looks a
little bit like this you know that
basically each this server that we we
have now this HTML service can actually
create individual requests with their
own document and we can start working
with the Dom after we have all that
boilerplate set up and it's running
right now on that test server you can
take a look calendar control not that
interesting by itself but this is this
this is a this is a control that is in
Yui too so first of all we're pulling
the that combo loader is also pulling in
Yui Yui to resources via the two and
three project that that we put up a rep
with 3.1 oh so this is rendering the
HTML for this calendar control exactly
the same HTML that would be rendered if
you ran this code on the client but the
difference is is now each time I do
something here from clicking pieces of
the calendar control each time it is
going back to the server and in fact if
you look at the source we're not
delivering any script at all it's all
just HTML and CSS well what's cool about
this is is that this can be a part of
our strategy for progressive enhancement
you know a progressive enhancement is
basically your content should be
available to everybody all device's
browser new browser old browser assisted
to assistive technology devices and we
can use CSS if we have it to make it
pretty and jazz to make it work more
fancy if we want but the core thing is
that everybody can get that content and
this what what we just saw was that this
calendar control is the exact code that
that almost rendered from the server as
we would render on the client that
calendar
can also render itself from pre-existing
markup in order to support progressive
enhancement so basically that can that
that calendar control has all the
engineering you need in it to get
progressive enhancement out of the box
you don't have to build you don't have
to build a server-side application that
generates markup in PHP or whatever it
is for the for the for the core markup
that's going to be enhanced by that
JavaScript code it's the same JavaScript
code on both sides so here's another
example it's a not very pretty but it
actually illustrates another aspect of
that that's cool so this is a this is a
template system we have say we have a
multi pain view that we want to that we
want to render well first thing that we
might do is is you know pulled out that
entire HTML content down but subsequent
requests we don't need all the chrome
around and we don't need anything but
the new content generated so we can
situationally say okay I just want that
that content area or in another
situation we might not need any HTML
rendering on a server at all we maybe we
just want the data and we can get that
with the same code and just a little bit
of a switch in there we can have that
same code output three different outputs
and what does that get us well in this
third situation this is where I say okay
I have a client component that knows how
to render itself this is the the
enhanced experience each click is going
to ask for the JSON data so i can
rebuild the the the page on the client i
can generate the HTML but what if I have
you know I want to deliver it to to a
mobile device having all that script on
that client is expensive Val time
execution time maybe I just want to
deliver a small JavaScript piece that
that knows how to ask for
just a Content area each time and then
of course that first example this one
here when it renders the entire HTML
piece is is the degraded experience it's
it's the one that's available to anyone
so three different responses the same
code a bunch of tools in their built-in
already engineered for you two to help
you do progressive enhancement without
without extra engineering costs and
that's a big deal if you watch the
presentation Gems presentation yesterday
see all the sites that don't that don't
do progressive enhancement at all
because it's not easy but it's but you
need to do it so that's that's why I
think this is cool there's other things
you might do with this you can you can
to have the Dom available we can maybe
do some fast testing along with my build
it's not it's not a replacement for a
browser testing but but you can actually
do a lot with the utility layer that
doesn't actually do any Dom manipulation
and I could even smoke test a Dom you
know Dom manipulation because we do have
a complete Dom we can do a lot of stuff
there we could we could hack it we can
provide any kind of document who wants
so we could actually like try to emulate
things we know that are broken in IE
just to smoke test it before we do the
full before we do the full browser
testing also validation code is an
obvious one we have to we have to
validate form fields on a client-server
writing that code once is better and so
Yui 3 it got working under node really
pretty easily we're excited about you
know being able to run some of the code
that we have already have running on the
client on the server just like
presentation before and I've heard many
times were a little bit lazy we don't
want to have to write same thing twice
in different languages and and the and
the Dom work that's gone on so far is
has really
actually surprising to have its performs
pretty well even though it's rendered it
in it's rendered in script rather than
in C space but there's other people that
are working on projects where they might
they might build the same sort of
functionality and live xml or Xerces or
maybe even try to get a WebKit
implementation hooked up to the to it to
make it faster but today it works really
well and if you're interested in this
stuff at all I talked about the gallery
I mean try it out submitted to the
gallery be part of that community help
us out it's it's there will serve it
will serve it from our CDN for free and
that's all i have are they any questions
that might reduce d movies what's that
pleasure yes it's PSD all right thank