my name is John David Dalton and I've
been working on a framework for about
two years now at night in my spare time
and today I'm going to be talking about
some of the innovative solutions I've
done to address common problems with
JavaScript libraries and I'll get into
that but before I do I want some crowd
participation if you're familiar with
jas comp there's a big pirate theme I
want you guys if you see something cool
I want to hear an offer and if you if
you don't like something don't say
something yeah so to help with that I'm
going to go through a series of slides
and if you see something cool I want to
hear it all I'm allowed all and so let's
uh let's do this all right favorite jas
right there so here we go so there's an
ice cream cone it's spilt there's a flat
tire no one no one likes that right no
one likes that but what about bacon all
right so then there's some wilted
flowers nothing right a shoe with a
ghetto lace you don't you don't want
that oh but what's this
alright so let's try it again at a chew
toy yeah a diluted addy saturated sunset
there's nothing good about that or what
about fuchsia is spelled with bacon oh
oh what what what about plus beer okay
alright so now I'm going to get into
some of some of the innovative things
that I've done so so here we go there's
the yaar alright so I've been working on
this framework for two years now in my
spare time at night in dark rooms and
yeah and in over those two years I've
come up with let's see I've come up with
two features that I want to talk about
today just to two features all right but
maybe maybe it's a little bit more than
that maybe it's maybe it's 50 plus
features that I'm going to talk about
today all right and that gets a what
your 50 plus features all right about
not so much there alright so one of the
first things I addressed is a script
synchronous script injection i forked
from prototype js2 years ago and I've
been moving it forward since then as few
cas and so one one issue I've addressed
is synchronous script injection and what
I do there is whenever you insert a
script via like the update method where
you use inner HTML or HTML and you
include script tags and your code you
want them to execute as you insert them
which is how jquery does this and and
some other libraries and so I came up
with a way to insert script elements
into the dome and when you when you do
this you have to feed your test and so
there's various feature testings that
you have to do like for example IE will
allow you to set the source of a script
element over and over again and continue
to update the code and then firefox may
not allow you to do
that but it will allow you to remove it
from the script and then insert it back
in and so there's all these variations
and I have it to where now you can
insert script elements directly into the
code and they'll execute as you insert
them and on top of that something that
jQuery doesn't address or prototype is
that it actually leaves the script
element in the source so as you're
updating HTML um it doesn't magically
strip that away you can actually access
the script element just like any other
element a lot of libraries remove that
because of how hard it is to get be able
to track whenever it's been written to
and whenever it's been set but I handle
all of that so that's script injection I
have solved global a vowel with fused
run and what's neat if you use jQuery
you know they've got like a global eval
solution they tie it into their Ajax
methods and things like that prototype
has a Val scripts method and I'm sure
Domo tools has something similar but
what's unique about this and I take it a
step further than jQuery or prototype is
that you're able to execute code and get
the result back so it's just like a
normal eval but it sits on the global
the global scope so the window and
what's also cool is you can send a
second parameter of an iframe and
execute global code in the iframe and
it's it's awesome because then you're
also able to capture that result to
which is something you haven't been able
to do in jQuery or or prototype or
mootools and I guess I should explain
when I mentioned jquery prototype remove
tools fuse j/s is a collection of the
good parts of these existing frameworks
it's a fuse of their techniques and
ideas and so what I've done is I've
looked at these various frameworks and
looked at how they solve these solutions
are these problems and try to pick and
choose the best parts of them and come
up with a better a better solution so
there's global eval something I do is I
work across context like like I frames
so you don't have to have the framework
loaded into the iframe
be able to manipulate Dom elements in
that iframe you're able to pass a
context into like the fuse method which
is the same as like a dollar sign method
and then you're able to work with
iframes in foreign documents without
having to have the framework actually
loaded in that other document so you're
able to pass contexts I do feature
detection for XHTML supports which means
i don't use inner HTML if i don't have
to i check to see if it's supported by
running various tests and some of those
tests are actually going to be donated
to Peter Higgins has j s which is a he's
trying to standardize a feature
detection javascript low-level
javascript that frameworks can share and
use so we're not all running over the
same feature test because jquery does
feature tests i do feature test fuse jss
feature tests and yui probably does some
feature tests and so instead of us keep
repeating things we want to share that
stuff and so I support testing inner
HTML and XHTML support something else
I've done is the methods / tag and this
is a really unique feature that you know
prototype has this too and it's
something that jQuery doesn't doesn't
have for being dom centric and that's
being able to give specific elements
methods so you can have an image element
and give it a refresh method or you can
have an input element and give it a
validate method on the element but
because I don't extend the native Dom
elements i use wrappers i'm able to
simulate the the Dom object structure so
for example I have fuse Dom node element
dot HTML element dot HTML div element
and so on it just keeps going and going
and going and you're able to assign
specific methods to various tags so I've
got that
the methods except fragments and text
nodes this is something i think jquery
has started to do in prototype lacks at
the moment but you're able to actually
pass dom fragments and text nodes into
like the update method and as you know
working with fragments allows you to
increase your speed of injection and and
and managing nodes all at once because
instead of doing individual opinions you
can just append one fragment with all of
your your nodes in there and then the
fragment is able to be reused and
recycled so I accept fragments and text
notes I do event delegation with event
bubbling if you've used jquery you know
that you're able to bubble in on events
that normally don't work cross browser
like submit reset and change and so i
found a way to do this also with blur
and a focus and i found a way to do this
that doesn't require all the work that
jquery does basically when jquery does
event delegation with bubbling they try
to guess what you're doing they say well
did you do key up did you press enter
does this really change and it tries to
compare the last value and the logic is
just really thick and very complex and
it's it's it's not a stable because it's
trying to guess something instead of
just knowing something actually happened
and so how what I do is I break it down
into a different technique and this is
I'm going to try to explain this with
hand gestures so it's a lot easier than
like code because it's crazy what you do
is you you have a parent element when
you're delegating does everyone know
about event delegation no yes are ok ok
ok good so you know you have a parent
element and the but the event bubbles up
to the parent element from the child
element all right well what I do is I
attach a watch here a watcher on the
parent element and basically it's it's
two types of events one is for IE and
one is for modern browsers well I guess
ie9 but and so what this does is on IE
it uses an event called on before
activate
which fires before any other event and
for the other browsers I use focus with
a capture face so it's it's triggered
before the other bubbling events and
what I do there is I inspect the event
target so the element that you're just
about to interact with our that you've
just interacted with either clicking on
it or about to change something or
submit something and when you do that it
goes and it says hey is this element a
problem element does this element have
events that need to bubble but don't
bubble and it goes yes and so what I do
is I then flag the event system and tell
it to manually bubble whenever that
event is triggered and I if that element
if that target doesn't have a dispatcher
on it or a mechanism to trigger those
events I add one listener to it and then
whenever it's triggered it knows to
manually bubble afterwards so it's not
guessing that something happened it
actually responds to the real event that
happened and then just tells the event
system to simulate bubbling so it fixes
the bubbling issue without having to do
a lot of guessing and so you get a lot
smaller code and it works it just works
without all these complex conditions and
like race conditions about click and
change and all of that so that's event
delegation with bubble I support on what
is this I support clone with more robust
options so mootools jQuery prototype all
do element cloning and what cloning
allows you to do is take an element and
basically clone it and copy all of its
children if you want you can use it's
called a deep clone but then on top of
that there's cross browser issues with
like ie which copies over the events too
and you don't want that necessarily so
what jQuery does is they allow you to
say well no don't copy the events or do
copy the events but I take it a step
further and I say that you can copy the
events you can copy the data which is
the data per element if you've used the
jQuery data method you know you can
store data per element so you can clone
the data but then you can also tell it
to exclude certain attributes so let's
say your cloning a chunk of elements but
you don't want to clone their IDs
because IDs are unique and so if you're
about to inject those and
to another chunk of your HTML you don't
want to have duplicate IDs you can tell
it to exclude specific IDs and that's
taken from mootools so I've combined the
mootools approach with the jQuery
approach to get a better more robust
option there so that's element climbing
ok and I have what's if you'll notice
this is fused object dot clone instead
of window object clone and that's
because I use what's called sandbox
natives I gave a little talk about this
at j s conf in april i also have slides
up that i'll be linking to at the end of
the presentation so you can get like
screencast about sandbox natives and how
they work but basically what it allows
me to do is have multiple instances of
native constructors on a page so i can
extend those native constructors without
dealing with the window object or window
array or window dot string or date or
math or you know or all of these things
and so it for the in this example i'm
actually extending the another instance
of the object constructed there and
giving it a clone method but what's nice
about this is that it also clones other
objects like arrays and dates and reg
axes which some of them some other
frameworks don't do that and so I've
gone and taken it a step further and
given at that also I address issues with
for in and cross browser issues with
that IE has issues where it may not
iterate over shadowed properties of the
of the better exists on the prototype so
like if you if you have a two-string
method on your object whenever you do a
four in it's not going to see that so I
address cross browser issues with that
because there's also bugs with Safari
and other issues there so I I handle all
of that for you so you can do a very
accurate each in that which goes over
each and every own property of a object
so if it's if it's their own property it
will literate over that in the for in
loop all right I also do I took a little
bit of stuff from mootools here and I
have
class mix-ins basically they're like
plugins or extending the prototype
except they don't add in the super sugar
and they're able to be passed around
from class to class and mixing them in
for example I use class a class mixing
for events for classes so your your
class sugar can have and observe and
stop observing on your your your
constructs for like your factory method
or your your your widget that you have
in your page you can you can trigger
events for them for your classes so
that's mix-ins I also do which leads
into class events and then here's
something that's that's really neat
debug mode with that allows errors
without halting the event handler loops
crockford talked about the event loop
and one of his slides and I noticed it
was that he said that you can have a
chunk of code fail and it won't stop the
rest of your stuff from from executing
and that's true in a in a browser
whenever you have event handlers if one
air is it will still execute the next
one in line and so frameworks that kind
of man handle this and take over this
this the the event execution will
actually go through there in a for loop
and if it errors it will actually fail
instantly and so you lose that
relationship jquery does this mootools
does this um it's some people say well
if it errors you know I it's best that I
know about it but if you're picky I've
put in a mode a debug mode so if you put
fuse underscore debug in the URL and
there's also a variation in the source
tag it will run in debug mode and that
means that that gives me the potential
to later give you errors and error
messages and things like that in the
code but what it also does is it allows
me to run a switch modes in my event
handler loops and actually use script
injection to create a different context
so I can actually execute these handlers
in a for loop and if it fails it doesn't
stop the for loop from going on and it
gives you accurate line numbers for your
error messages so that's that's really
really
cool i geeked out over that one all
right all Ajax ready states are
guaranteed to be hit if you if you run
through some of the documentation on
these frameworks they'll say that you
know like some some of the earlier ready
states in an AJAX request may or may not
be hit what I've done is I've taken over
that and basically ensure that if if
ready state like three was hit then you
know one and two would also be so you'll
it's guaranteed to hit every single
ready state in an AJAX request it also
observed because I have because my Ajax
calls are a wrapper around this stuff
it's it's using the the class sugar and
because it uses the class sugar i use
the event mix-ins and so the event
mix-ins allow me to have ajax event
observers for the Ajax requests if you
see something that's marked with a
asterisk that means that it's King X
approved I don't know how many people
know King X from Twitter how about an R
for that all right so it's khang x
approved i gave him a preview of this
and if you like something you went ahead
and put a little notch there so ajax on
timeout I believe jquery allows you to
do this basically if your Ajax requests
times out you can put a call back and it
will trigger that so you're able to do
something so I like that about jQuery
and so I decided to take that also i do
on the board and i have an abort method
so if you want to cancel your Ajax call
you can do that and it will respond as
well I am try to ensure that the CSS is
loaded before the dawn load fires I
don't know if y'all follow jquery issues
but there was an issue where depending
on how you loaded your style sheets if
you loaded your style sheets after your
javascript it would cause an issue where
sometimes download would fire before
your CSS was finished loading and so
then you would be able you would be
trying to evaluate styles on elements
and it wouldn't it wouldn't give you the
right results because the CSS hadn't
finished loading so I make my best
attempt to ensure that the CSS is loaded
before the Dom load event triggers and
because I'm I manage the events in the
event handlers I'm able to actually also
say that Dom load is a simulated event
in IE so there's a potential that
depending on on how things are done that
it may end up having some handlers that
are called sometimes after a window load
issue and so what I do is I actually
ensure that window load will not fire
until everything is wrapped up in the
Dom load I add more traversal methods
like a first and a last and with first
and last you can also say give me the
first three and that's the first three
elements give me the last three give me
the last three elements you can say give
me the last three that match this query
and then the selector and so it would be
three and then a selector you can also
say give me the first that returns true
to this function call so you can put a
function and a condition and if it
returns true you'll get the first that
returns true for that so that's some
more sugar for traversing I've gone and
taken the jQuery approach and done
things like a pinch I'll prepend child
and then I'm really big into naming
consistency so there's prepend siblings
a pinch I'll to prepend child 2 and so
on and they just make managing and
handling your elements that much easier
and I noticed some some libraries don't
have that jQuery did and I thought that
was a really good addition so props to
jQuery for that another nice thing is
that there's the mark again that you can
create elements just like jQuery that
really easy fantastic syntax of just
fuse and then your HTML there and then
you could then go like a pin to body or
whatever and then it would upend it it
would upend it to the
body all right now this is this is a
really a really cool one I support
jQuery style with a node list and this
node list is basically another array
constructor on fuse Dom node list so
it's separate from shoes array and
separate from window array so I'm able
to add dome centric Dom centric methods
to the query result and so this actually
works with the dot hide in the dot show
but it's not an array-like object it's a
real array with an internal class of
array so you can use it in methods that
require it to be an array and that means
the length works and everything so if
that's that's really cool in fact I want
our for that all right I put it there
just for you guys all right all of my
methods conform to the es five spec
which means and that's not just array
that's also a string number any kind of
method that I add to it I try to ensure
that it works with the spec and so that
also means that it works with sparse
arrays it also is this generic so you
can pass it array like objects a common
pattern with that is if you have the
arguments object and you want to convert
it to an array you do slice well you do
a ray prototype sliced call and you slap
the arguments object in there and it
converts it to an array but a lot of
frameworks when they when they add their
array methods they don't make it this
generic so you can't do that with their
methods so I went ahead and made sure
that all of my stuff follows es5 and
that's that's taking it up a notch there
my event wrappers are optimized for
execution so going along with this thing
of fixing the issues of extending
natives and extending the Dom part of
that is using wrappers i use dom
wrappers I don't extend natives on the
window and I also use event rappers but
something that a lot of libraries do is
up front every time you pass an event it
populates every single property even if
you're ever accessing that property and
so it's doing all these calculations
that don't need to be done and like if
you're using a mouse move sometimes
they're they slow it down so much that
they have to do something like debounce
the balancing
something it's where you where you where
you call it every other time and try to
try to delay it because your stuff is
slow this allows it to actually be
optimized so you don't have to worry
about that one moment Oh better so
basically what i do is instead of
properties i have methods that you call
so you can say get target get current
target get related target and all of
these things and it's doing something
super cool here it's actually lazy
defining so it's it's actually not
forking based on features until it's not
working based on features until you call
it the first time and then if you call
it and then it actually stores the
result on the instance of the event
wrapper and this allows it to not have
to be doing those calculations every
time you call that function so it
actually stores the results afterwards
which creates a highly optimized ivette
wrapper which is great for like mouse
move and other things when you need it
to just work and you need it to work
fast so that's cool my element rappers
have caching built in and this is
important for backwards compatibility
when I'm trying to run as prototype and
you'll see there when I explain it this
means that whenever you create a new
instance like with jquery you can create
a jquery instance boom and then you do
it again identical it returns the exact
same instance so it's not a different
instance and so this will actually be
true and this is great because I meant
what does this look like if you do a
dollar sign there instead of fuse that
looks like prototype or mootools and so
this is this will work just like that
but it's using wrappers instead so it's
a familiar syntax something else cool as
I use advanced character encoding and
what that means is that some some escape
HTML method
and unescape will well actually only
convert like three characters the
greater than less than an ampersand and
I actually go through and i use the the
doctype and the inner HTML to actually
encode all of these supported entities
and so you can you can really get fancy
with with your stuff there and it works
to its feature tested for like Safari
2.00 crazy old browser and then crazy
new browser too so it has you covered I
added a bit of sugar on top of the
function bind and this is very handy
whenever you get into a lazy defining
methods which is great whenever your
feature detecting and you don't have
like say the body element available or
something like that until you need it
you can actually pass it an array and I
kept this the the argument signature
identical to spec so even if you know
later on something happens it's still
the same i'm not going to crazy off spec
and adding an extra argument you can
pass it an array and then it will it
will use the the object and the method
to be executed during the bind instead
of just the method reference so you can
actually define that at a later time it
would still work in your bond which is
great i have class defaults so whenever
you instantiate a class or a constructor
with sugar you're able to have options
that are that are there by default so
you can set things like default color or
default name or you know any of your
properties they will support defaults a
big one is there's no expand owes on IE
and and a now on firefox and this is
cool because if you'll notice there's
there's jquery issues and there's
prototype issues of some elements don't
allow expand those like 4am and applet
or object and this also avoids redraw
issues and i don't it's it's a it allows
me to have a rapper that doesn't touch
an element it leaves it completely
unchanged and unmodified which is
fantastic
and so that works for IE which is great
because I E has the problems and then
now firefox has a Dom level 3 method
called get user data and set user data
and you can use that to set IDs on that
as well which then is used to look back
for it's it's a data storage so that's
that's pretty cool a big one that that
seems to buy every framework and you'll
see the the j s nerds go crazy for this
and that's proper attribute handling
jQuery confuses properties attributes
mootools does dojo every framework does
because at the time whenever they were
creating them the difference is really
hard to determine because the spec uses
the same words for different meanings
one is an interface one is a one is an
attribute and they'll say an attribute
in it'll say the interface has
attributes which actually means
properties it's crazy so I have handled
it in a way that's where I don't confuse
what an attribute is and what a property
is for example an attribute is like
what's in there in the HTML source
source when the page loads and then a
property would be like the live value so
like on input the attribute would be
whatever was there in the beginning the
property is there what's there right now
after you've changed it so that's
attributes and properties and my methods
handle them correctly and this actually
bleeds into things like proper query
selectors on your selector engines if
they can handle things like attributes
and properties correctly and so that
that is what I do there fragment caching
a John Resig did a lot of testing with
this I was doing some testing about the
same time fragments are awesome they
help speed up things in the Dom I've run
some tests where like just a little a
minor league complex insert can cause IE
to freeze for like 60 seconds like ie6
to freeze for 60 seconds which is crazy
slow but with caching it was like down
to one second so I'm
that's that's still bad but not as bad
in 60 seconds so caching is really good
it really helps out whenever you do
iterations over your selectors over your
your query results it actually will sit
there and say if you pass it an HTML
string it'll create that element and
then as it's going over the items in
your collection it actually instead of
creating that element over and over
again it just clones it but unlike
jQuery which persists that cash I just
discarded after that iteration and the
reason is is because if you have single
page apps and you're continually caching
elements that cash just grows and grows
and grows and grows and it's a pseudo
page leak and so you don't want that and
so I cash fragments correctly I also do
this for I mentioned before where I
support the iframe context and foreign
documents and things it creates specific
fragments for those as well because you
can't use foreign fragments on your
pages fragments on a foreign document so
it caches that too all right my methods
support I'm literals and objects and
this is because sandbox natives are
objects if they were primitives they
would be primitives of the window and
not prim and not of the fused array or
dot fuse Dom node list and so my methods
because I have to support both actually
support you know this and this which is
unique and if you're ever wondering why
that's that's because I have to support
them for sandbox natives and regular
natives I have consistent naming of
functions um so if J queries API is WTF
and some of prototypes is the same way
mootools is very good about naming
consistency and so I've kind of taken
the lead from them and done things where
if I've return a boolean value I prefix
it with is or has because it's returning
a boolean value and if it's getting
something it's get blah or set blah so
there's no ambiguous meaning of what's
attr you know or
or what CSS mean oh is it a style
property or instead of CSS value of is
it's it's very consistent naming honor
yeah in fact did that have an asterisk
it sure did so feature testing 0 browse
our sniffing and this is a big deal
because with ie9 coming out we're
getting to see again what happens when
you browser sniff there's some nice
frameworks out there that are breaking
now in ie9 um because they browser sniff
they basically said is IE let's assume
all these features exist and now with
ie9 they don't and so we use feature
testing for everything so there's no
browser sniffing I actually have a
feature registry so you test once it
caches the results and then if you query
that that feature again it automatically
has the result there for you so you're
able to look that up it's fused a and v4
environment dot test the the string and
so I have that and that's part of what
I'll be donating to has Jas will support
custom builds like mootools does where
you can basically select the pieces you
want and this is because the pieces i
use don't depend on other pieces in the
other modules in the scripts and its
uses a lot of vanilla j/s and so you're
able to get really fine grained control
over what you want to include in your
library or in the build of fuse jas i'm
also working on supporting being able to
load things via like a seed file like
yui does where you can have load one
file and then add in the pieces as you
go and jquery i know is working on that
too so that's that's going to be really
cool kind of a random note i resolve the
scroll element which could either be
body or document element depending on
the quirks mode browser all kinds of
jazz i do that if you needed it you'll
appreciate it if you don't you probably
have no idea so that's that's all right
method generics this is some
that Firefox supports I don't know if
any other browser does but I supported
on mine as well so any array or any
method on any namespace has a generic on
its constructor so arrays elements
anything it's there's always a generic
there that you can pass a values to I
support eight selector engines which
means i support basically any of the
ones that are in existence and that have
mildly been used i support them i'm very
open to supporting any others i don't
like to recreate the wheel believe it or
not i like to use components that exists
so i'm all for like has j s or if there
was a ECMA five shim i totally adopt
that in a heartbeat because i don't want
to have to keep doing that so I support
eight selector engines including sizzle
and the most awesome NW matter which is
totally the best css3 compliance
selector ancient out there and also the
fastest engine as well a big thing is I
support emulation which is brand-new in
jas frameworks you can run as prototype
and actually delete prototype j/s drop
few JSN and then your api won't know the
difference that's the goal with
innovation and what's cool is that
you'll be able to get the browser
support the added speed and added
features but not have to relearn an API
and so eventually we're also gearing up
to support jquery so you'll be able to
use jquery plugins and everything and
it'll still be awesome I support special
Dom events like setting up and tear down
so I can support things like Mao Center
and mouse leave cross browser I'm
speeding up now because I'm sensing it's
time to wrap it up I support firing Dom
events and that also includes bubbling
and other nifty features I similar to
jQuery even if you lazy load the
framework it'll still trigger some
events I know there's some discussion
about whether that should be moved into
like a ready method and I'm open for
discussion there were
we're about ready to start making some
solid decisions there minification
support I'm really big on minification
I'm it's frustrating to see some
frameworks on Google CDN not support
magnification or not provide a min ified
version because minified can give you a
gain of like 18 plus kilobytes which is
awesome for mobile so minification
support is big I will eventually be
supporting JSON p it's something I don't
do yet but since its mapping to jquery i
want to do that i do also want to add no
Jas and comedy is compliance so for like
the module system be able to load that
and an export thing on the exports
object names based events is something
that jQuery uses a Yui calls it like
label event labels or something I'm
totally butchering that but I want to be
able to do that that's handy for widgets
and custom events something else is
really cool is all of our developers
have signed what is it see la's clas and
and whenever we release we will be
submitting our stuff to the dojo
foundation I like following and in
committing to really good open-source
practices and we're going to go that
extra mile and join the dojo foundation
we offer crazy browser support which is
great for the mobile market because they
use kind of crappy browsers and we do a
lot of feature testing so even if you're
like I'll never use that browser you
might we support it later on we'll be
able to add custom builds based on
features because we have a feature
registry and so you can profile certain
environments and then create a build
specific to that environment so that's
awesome and that will be added once I
get help we are very active I try to do
commits every week if I don't just
assume I'm actually doing them on my
side and there's going to be a massive
commit any time now so I try to do that
every day it's I work on this project in
my spare time I work on it from like ten
o'clock the 3am and it's a passion
of mine and so I've been very active for
two years now haven't slowed down so
i'll keep being active i fix a ton of
bug fixes I even go into other
frameworks bug repositories and take
their bugs and fix them and then put
that in my change log that I've been
able to address that bug as well so if
you go to the change log which is like
mile and a half long you'll see every
bug I fixed in other other frameworks
that I've applied to my framework and
then I've also included all the credits
to anyone that's helped during the bug
fix process and then thanks I'm not done
yet I have a special presentation for
Peter Higgins I need him to come up to
the front where is he at I need him need
him to come up here say where's yet he's
got a coffee someone go out there and
grab them all right Peter Higgins has
gave me a pretty hard time about being
vaporware so I've got a special
presentation for him it's very urgent
for you you got to come up here I'm
giving I'm presenting something to you
yeah why don't you stand right over
there well that's it it's you have no
idea we are cooperating and it's awesome
what well I don't know um here you go
I've got a little card for you
then I've got something else for you
here you go yeah you basically pop it
Chuck the whole thing while you put
anything yeah there you go you can't
block it you have to do it right now
yeah he's getting bro ice by the way so
yeah oh I actually had one of my pocket
too and you have to do it today that
adds to the humiliation do it it's look
warm too
thank you for you guys I've also
launched the website now so no longer
has that annoying like seizure-inducing
green or the orange and yellow thing
there we have a full website up it's
still work in progress but if you go to
fuchsia is calm it's up now and here are
some other links that you might find
interesting I've got to Jay Dalton my
email my aim my why my skype fuse Jes my
repos I've got some other things they're
all you can lead calm is my blog don't
type it all you can feet it's not the
same and all you can lead and that's it
thank you guys