[Music]
my name is Deanna and I want to talk
today about Hell meant to tell and
whatnot but I will not tell you
something that you don't know already
but I just wanted to more share my story
because I figure maybe if I share my
story maybe I can help somebody before
they come to the point that I was so I
wanted to speak mostly about health
because about two years ago I started to
have pain in my arm and I ignore it for
like about a year and then a year after
suddenly like there were like days that
I have this freakin pain in my arm even
when I was in coding like over the
weekend doing other stuff and I was like
what's wrong what I guess I never even
heard from other people or even myself
even when I work in the industry now
almost for 10 years never read so much
about it now and I went to a doctor on a
Saturday to the emergency because it was
really terrible and then they told me I
think you have to donate is probably you
need to go on Monday - I know specialist
just to give you the accurate analysis
of that but the doctor in the emergency
room told me that then I wonder and they
told me yes
you actually have tennis elbow
I believe it's calling Yurman and then
they told me I was in a point where they
told me you need to take a break at
least for a month and do Frankham
gymnastic which is the therapy and
massage for the arm and I did that and I
remember I was very shocked because I
never thought this kind of stuff would
happen to me
as well because I'm very passionate
about the stuff that I do and I do spend
time in the computer even outside work
experimenting with stuff so for me to
tell me for a month to sit in the
computer or even use the telephone
because they told me that as well not
only the computer but the fact that you
spend time probably in your telephone so
I pin the tendons get tired of that and
everybody's different now - every person
can happen and anyway after that
happened to me I started to take care of
myself I got myself birdy called Mouse
and I started to take more breaks and
watch out in my free time not spending
too much time in the computer doing
stuff more active and it came it became
better after a year actually taking care
of that I stopped having the pain of my
arm but I guess when it got better I
again thought okay now I'm good so it
doesn't matter I can still like push it
again and then half a year later earlier
this year I started to have really
really a lot of pain now in my back so
then I am back to the doctor and they
told me out let's go onto an MRI so to
see if there's actually something
particular in there and then it turns
out that actually yes I started to
off one of my discs in my lower back now
it the gel that we have in our spine in
the lower back if somebody had ever had
this it starting to get out of or expand
it's cold and I'm really lucky the
doctor told me that it's not so much
that is going out at the moment that he
told me I don't need any medicine or
surgery because some people if this gel
that we have in our spine gets out
usually you might need surgery or
cortisone and
yeah more therapy but he just
recommended me to do more exercise and
to what more heat on me if you don't
like to do sports just go out and don't
fit too long if you go back home as well
sometimes sitting in the sofa is way too
much so I started to do that again and
taking care of myself going out trying
to take a walk in the winter I find it
always very hard in here in this country
I'm from Mexico so then every time I
have to go out I'm like please no so
that probably why I develop the problem
during the winter and and that's it I
just wanted to share my story because
before you get into this point always
listen to the signals so that's it
[Applause]