my name is Brendan Eich and I come from
California where I live and I am the
person who created javascript in 1995
and helped found mils of org in 1998 and
I had a long run with Mozilla helping
launch Firefox future of JavaScript is
it's still being used more and more it's
being adopted by more programmers being
used in more programming domains it was
always in the browser because it got out
first when I was at Netscape before
Microsoft could make vbscript be that
thing the one and then it got into the
server side several times but the one
that really succeeded was node.js
nodejs is used all over now and Java
scripts also being used in the internet
of things as well like the tehsil system
on a chip in and of things controller
this was great really top-notch speakers
gear Mo's exceptional and puts and show
this crew did a great job I liked the
venue quite a bit too I wish I could
stay longer I flew in this morning and
some knots in the paper I'll be