[Applause]
well hips all right
so yes I work on web standards at Adobe
I am co-chair of the CSS working group
but last week it was my other co-chair
who managed to get riding modes resolved
to go to propose recommendations so I
don't get to claim much for that one I'm
going to talk to you today about how all
of you can help getting browser bugs
fast I'm going to start with a little
bit of audience participation everybody
here does some kind of web development
how many people here raise your hand if
you have run into a browser bug so many
bugs all right of all you people which
is almost everybody who has run into a
browser bug how many people have
actually reported the bug that you found
that's about what I usually see maybe
10% yeah I'm hoping by the time I end
this presentation more people will feel
empowered to log browser bugs help them
nudge them along the way to being fixed
and I'm gonna tell you about the things
that I've found have been effective at
getting browser developers to actually
do something for you so why should you
care you run into a browser bug you find
a solution and you go along your merry
way if you're anything like me you find
the bug you figure out a solution you go
along and sometime later months years
maybe even weeks you run into the same
bug again and you've forgotten what the
solution was and you have to go through
the effort of solving some of the else's
problem
again so yes you managed to get a
browser bug fixed that means there's one
less thing that you have to do you're
helping future you but it's not just
yourself you're also helping hundreds or
thousands and developers around the
world who will also run into this bug
maybe some other people in this room
will run into the same bug that you do
and if you all can manage to get the bug
fixed that's one less thing for other
developers to worry about but also a
more bug free web helps users of the web
a better environment for browsing is
better for everybody and the less bugs
there are the more that web developers
like yourselves can do things for your
users and getting a browser bug fixed
means that billions of people around the
world have a better time in their
browsers and I apologize I don't maybe I
need to shave my beard for presentations
the microphone always seems to rustle a
little bit and I'm sorry about that so
what can you do to fix about well
browsers are open source so your
developers you could go fix the bug
yourself it is possible I worked at a
team on Adobe that did this very thing
we fix bugs in lots of browsers we added
features to lots of browsers but it's
not really what I expect anybody to do
we no longer do it ourselves it wasn't
really a cost-effective thing we
couldn't really justify the expense of
having a team fixing bugs in browsers
because there are people where it's
their job to fix bugs
there are browser engineers funded in
some cases by companies that have lots
of money so they really should do their
job and
there are ways in which we as users of
the platform we as developers can help
them to nudge them along to fixing the
bugs that are the worst things in our
development life so what I'm going to
talk to you today about is how to
influence browser developers how to
nudge them along things that I found
effective both in my own life and in
what I hear from other people and
getting browser browser developers to
fix the bugs that are important the one
basic if nothing else just do this one
thing it's just make sure the bug is
reported there are a number of search
engines this is one of them that will
search through all of the bug bases for
all of the browser's all placed all the
major browsers and let you know whether
a bug has already been reported so at
the very least you can go and see
whether something needs to be done about
this rug if you find the bug that is
causing you trouble the easiest most
cost-effective thing you can do is just
a vote for it you might not think that
this would make much of a difference but
it actually does I've been in meetings
with browser developers talking about a
particular bug sometimes about that they
know has been around for a long time but
they've told me point-blank I can't get
anybody to fix this bug because it only
has ten votes and these other bugs over
here have 200 votes and so these are the
ones that I'm gonna actually spend some
time fixing so if you can find a bug
please and it's kind of causing you pain
please vote for it there's like a plus
one a favorite a follow in these bug
systems
that gives the browser developers some
sense of priority on what actually needs
to be fixed element platforms and it's
not just bugs new features are all
listed in these bug in these but
repositories has bugs so if say you were
interested in having paintwork let's be
implemented in more browsers you can go
to the browsers that don't implement
them and find a bug that says implement
paint worklet and vote for that bug and
that will help the browser engineers get
around to implementing pig worklets and
making them something that you can use
all over the web you can also put new
information in bug comments if you came
at the bug from a slightly different
direction putting new steps in is a
really good thing to do the only thing
that you should not do in a bug comment
is actually just do a plus one because
the voting mechanisms are there for that
and if you can't find the bug just write
it up it can be a very quick thing or it
can be a very involved thing depending
on how much effort you want to put into
it
and don't worry about adding a duplicate
bug to these systems if you've made a
good-faith effort to find the bug and
you haven't found it
riding a bug and letting some browser
engineer do some triaging and say oh no
it's actually this mug over here is
perfectly fine and that just means that
the next person that goes and tries to
find the that bug with the search terms
that you used they'll find your
duplicate it'll link to the actual bug
and so in some cases like this
duplicates are a fine and good thing
so you've gone and logged a bug or you
found the bug and you voted on it so
you're done right all bugs get fixed or
sometimes they just hang out forever and
get closed as one fixed after 20 years
of being around so there are some things
that you can do to improve your chances
of getting a bug fixed and they're
mainly just writing a good bug making
sure that the steps to the bug are the
smallest number of steps that can
possibly be quite a few bugs that
browser developers get from outside
their projects or load this URL and
things don't look good that's not much
to go on
so if you can reduce the thing that is
going wrong to just a few lines of code
and say here's what needs to be fixed to
make things better for me it's much more
likely that a browser engineer is going
to actually do something about it
you can add examples to a bug you can
show what the repercussions of the bug
are that will give the browser developer
more to go on when they go and have to
fight for spending time to fix a
particular bug and finally the most
effective thing that you can do is to is
to add a test case the browser developer
when they fix the bug they're going to
have to go add a test case or a set of
test cases themselves so you can do a
little bit of work to help the browser
developer and that'll make it more
likely that they'll actually get around
to fixing the bug for you
so I'm going to talk to you a little bit
about test cases ten years ago before I
got started in this web platform stuff
all of the browser's had their own test
sets that only ran on their own browser
and there was no sharing of tests and
over the last 10 years there's been this
thing that is now called the web
platform tests project that is a
repository of cross cross browser tests
that the browser's are now all sharing
and so if browser developer on Firefox
writes a cross browser test they can
upload it to web platform tests and that
test gets synced to all of the other
browsers that are sharing and so it's a
multiplier effect and somebody who
doesn't work on a browser can add a bug
to this repository and it will get moved
out to all of the browsers testing
environments and be tested in perpetuity
using some shared infrastructure that
they have been working on together and
the set of tests are run independently
and reported on every test there are
millions of these tests every test gets
run four times a day on all the major
browsers and the results get recorded
and so it's a second indicator for the
browser developer that something is
going wrong in their browser and it's a
second nudge towards fixing the thing
it's not only a failure in their own
test system it's a failure in this
external test system that they have to
look at and triage and decide whether or
not
bugs that have tests in this
cross-browser
test repository are much more likely to
be fixed especially over the last couple
years they've shown how the trajectory
of tests that run and pass in more than
one browser or in all browsers has been
increasing and the the velocity of these
tests working in more than one browser
has increased as this web platform tests
project has been going on so there is a
bunch of documentation at web platform
tests about how to contribute how to
write tests and there are a few formats
that they talk about and the two I want
to mention are test harness digest tests
they're basically unit tests and so if
you know any sort of unit testing
framework this is just a test in
JavaScript with assertions much like any
other unit testing framework if you
don't know what unit tests are go find
out they are one of the best things that
you can add to your own development but
I think most people know about them so
I'm not going to mention much about of
this except that this is one way that
you can add a test to web platform tests
the second one that I'm going to talk
about is ref tests which are a kind of
visual comparison test but they're
different from regular snapshot tests
that are actually just testing against
say an image that you've taken a
snapshot of a test result they're set up
a little differently and they're set up
such that
they can run across all browsers across
all environments across all say font
setups graphics setups and there's no
picture of the test result that you have
to maintain they're actually the only
snap choice tests that are actually
worth anything if you look at this
documentation there's a bunch of other
tests test formats that they mentioned
but you should ignore all of them
they're mainly just test formats that
the browser's used in their legacy
systems and nobody should ever write
them again test harness dot J's tests
and rec tests are the only way to go so
a little bit more about ref tests here's
how they're set out you have two files
that get rendered in a browser one file
has what they expect the tests to render
as and it doesn't use the feature under
test at all in a lot of cases it's just
a green box of our certain dimension and
then you have another file that actually
uses the thing that you're testing that
produces exactly the same rendering as
the reference and that can be a little
tricky to set up but sometimes it's
actually pretty easy and you have the
browser in a particular environment with
a particular font setup and all of this
rendered both files and then compare the
two against each other so there's
nothing to maintain
you're just rendering stuff doing the
pixel comparison and if the pixels match
the test is good so I want to show you a
simple ref test that I recently added to
web platform tests
the situation was there's a typography
slack I'm on
and one of the people there mentioned a
bug they were seeing in Firefox they had
a they had a JavaScript file that was
comparing the widths of various bits of
text and then doing fitted so he would
make the text bigger to fit a wider
thing or make the text smaller to fit a
smaller thing so you could measure in
JavaScript and get the text to fit the
environments you wanted it in and
Firefox was just giving bad nets for a
particular set of features first letter
and text transfer so I went and found
the bug for this it's about 10 years old
Firefox knows about the bug it's not
that important to fix so it's never
gotten fixed but I voted for it and got
my friend on slack to vote for it as
well and then since I had a talk to
prepare about testing I decided right a
ret test for it and let's see let me
show you
the test so here is the reference it's
got a green box it's got some text that
describes what you should see on the
screen that there should be no red
that's not actually necessary but it's a
style that people use for rep tests that
I kind of like and it's not using any of
the features that I want to test it's
not using first letter it's not using
text transfer and then I have the start
of the test that in season first letter
and is using text transform and
measuring the width in a visual way by
adding a background color and here is
the text reference in Firefox and the
test start in Firefox which on first
rendering does it that you can see
there's the extra bit in the red part
who knows why that width is actually
there so I'm going to be a coward and
not do any live coding I'm just going to
show you the complete test which is
adding a couple things I had those two
spans that were in line walks and I've
just said that their position happen
absolute so they will overlap and
actually I need to redo this because it
is only on first rendering that the bug
shows up
so the two things are overlapping and
I've made the text transparent because
the actual text rendering isn't part of
this bug it's just the width that we're
concerned about and on Chrome everything
looks great
there's no red because those two things
the test and control spans are exactly
the same width and in Firefox the red
pokes out so this is going to be a
failure for Firefox and so that's
basically it
- a rough test you have two files and
they have the same rendering and if you
were looking very very closely it's
probably hard to see the rendering is
actually different between browsers the
green box and Firefox is a little white
is a little taller and that just happens
to be because I have a default font that
is a little bit taller than the default
font that's used in Chrome but this
doesn't matter because we're comparing
chrome rendering to chrome rendering and
Firefox rendering to Firefox rendering
so I put this into web platform tests
and it's now being run four times a day
and you can see that the latest Firefox
that was tested is showing a failure so
there's now a test result that is
showing up four times a day for two
basically shame the Firefox engineers
into eventually fixing this bug
and hopefully they will get around to it
all right
so adding a test case is really the best
way to get some attention to the bug and
adding a test case to web platform tests
is a way of getting more people to look
at the problem and hopefully get
somebody to actually commit to the VIX
but another thing that you can do is
just to tell people about the problem
that you're running into my friend on
slack told everybody in the slack
Channel about this problem and I happen
to read it and do some extra work to
make it slightly more likely that this
bug is going to be fixed mentioned
people that you're updating or voting on
a bug maybe you'll get more people to
vote on it in solidarity and you can
show people the test case I showed the
test case to some people that I work
with in the CSS working group and they
showed me a few things to fix in it to
make it a little bit more bulletproof
the test that's actually in web platform
tests is a little bit more complicated
but I only got those improvements
because I told people about it and Here
I am today telling you about this bug
perhaps some of you will go take a look
at it and vote for yourselves
letting people know the problems that
you're running into letting people know
what it is that you've done to try to
fix the problem you can get better
solutions two things you can get people
talking about the problem and you can
get browser developers to notice
something's going wrong this is an
example from about a year ago there was
a developer who had a site that was
written great in all of the browsers and
he tested on Chrome Canary which is an
excellent thing to do you should take a
look at all the developer versions of
browsers and see how your site is
working in them to get some idea of what
is going to happen for your users in the
upcoming weeks and months and he found
that his site in Chrome Canary regular
chrome is fine but in Chrome Canary just
broke and so he wrote a bug saying you
know here's my code here's what's going
wrong why did you change this you're
making the web worse and he didn't have
to wait 20 years to have his bug closed
this won't fix almost immediately the
browser developer went and closed it as
won't fix because the spec said it was
supposed to be this the spec had changed
and so the chrome engineer was being
diligent and changed chrome to match the
spec so this guy of the developer said
no this is not good enough he looked at
the spec and found the email addresses
of the spec authors and said why did you
change the spec and it turns out the
spec change was bad they hadn't
considered this case and because of this
guy's diligence he fix the spec and
fixed Chrome Canary before the bug or
the spec conformance actually shipped in
the browser
here's another example from just a few
months ago this guy said you know hey
I'm running into this problem anybody
knows why this is going on and he got a
browser developer to reply saying well
it works for me what are you talking
about and they went back and forth for a
while came up with a jsfiddle that
actually demonstrated the problem and it
was an actual problem and just recently
this got fixed and it's going to be
fixed in mainline Firefox next month so
telling people about things letting
people know the problems that you're
running into on Twitter in a blog post
in a conference talk in a lightning talk
grousing to your fellow employees all of
these things can be a good way of moving
the platform along making it better for
everybody so
I hope I've convinced a few of you that
there are little things that you can do
low effort and medium effort things that
you can do to try to get browser bugs
fixed when you run into them so
hopefully the next time you run into a
browser bug you can go find the bug and
vote on it or log the bug if you can't
find it if it's a bug that is really
holding you back consider spending some
time looking in to writing a cross
browser test so that you're saving time
for the browser developer they can more
easily justify spending time fixing it
and tell other people about the problem
maybe you can crowdsource a bit of help
and getting some of these things done so
that your bug can get fixed so please go
out and improve the web platform for
future you your fellow web developers
and everyone else in the world thank you