thank you very much and sorry about that
setup I have like the least technical
presentation today so of course I had
the most technical problems getting my
computer working so you know I tried to
make it nice and easy but you just you
know technology I love it and I also
hate it so yeah so alright I have this
thing
it makes the slides go big secret so
yeah so my name is Laker and I'm gonna
be talking to you about some of the work
that I do with young developers on our
platform but really I think that it
extends to all development and really to
pretty much almost any industry if you
really really think about it
my magical button things don't work and
so I'll just be over here and so just to
give you kind of a little roadmap of
what we're gonna do today I'm just gonna
give you a little bit of a who is this
guy
gonna talk about some of our developers
talk about some of our experiences
working with them and then last I'm
gonna wrap it up and kind of talk about
you know maybe what you can do with your
community and some people that you know
so to start off my name is Laker
I am always hesitant to give out my
title as we saw the manager of
information experience no one knows that
what that means that's okay my title
changes all the time basically the gist
of it is that I teach kids how to make
games that's really the long and short
of it I started as a full-stack engineer
but then realized you know I'd rather
teach people how to code than to do it
myself all the time love coding but only
in small pieces or rather teach people
how to do it and the company I work for
is called roblox
maybe you've heard of it maybe you
haven't the trick is if you have someone
young in your life like a nephew niece
son daughter chances are they might have
heard of this yeah we're a gaming
platform it's primarily aimed at kids
although we like to think that we're for
all ages and the beauty of our platform
is that we try to take all the heavy
work out of doing making games I'm not
sure how familiar all of you are with
game development there's a lot of things
are just a real pain in the butt
things like networking physics you know
just managing servers so much of that
just gets in the way of starting up a
new game starting up a new project and
we just realized you know what why don't
we just do
all that work for people so that they
can just focus on the gameplay focus on
the experience and what's really nice
about that is that because we take all
those little technical aspects that you
usually need lots years and years of
experience doing we've just cut all that
out and it leaves a really nice simple
shell that people can work with and it
really aligns nicely with kids because
they don't have to do all these fancy
things they can just hit the ground
running within like five minutes if you
want to see this in action we actually
have a workshop tomorrow where we're
going to literally do that with kids
they'll just have games up and running
really quick and technically full
disclosure we aren't actually JavaScript
so I appreciate you all welcomed me
welcoming me to your tier community we
do do Lua which is also scripting but
not quite the same it has its own fun
little quirks anyway
I didn't really want to talk too much
about robots specifically I did want to
talk about our developers because
they're a pretty unique Bunch they're
like a lot of people you probably know
they're very passionate very talented
very driven but they're also very young
because we're a platform that's
primarily aimed at kids are the games on
our platforms are played by kids you
know 9 10 11 and they suddenly get this
kind of realization moment usually when
they're kind of like in middle school
there get a little more tech-savvy
they're playing all these games on the
platform they realize oh these games
were also made by kids maybe I could do
that too and so they often start off
being like okay well let's just dive
into this and again we try to make it
very simple for people to get started
you don't have to learn you don't have
to learn about you know a big fancy game
engine you can just get a project going
on day one and so they'll just
experiment they'll just try things a lot
of these kids are self-motivated
self-learn they try to just recreate
games that they see or just recreate
little mechanics or they'll
reverse-engineer you know it's something
that they've seen and so they're a very
interesting bunch and I really like
working with them for lots of reasons
and that's mainly what I'm going to talk
about throughout this talk and I want to
start off by just giving you a little
case study just to kind of paint you a
picture of
kind of one of our one of our typical
users so this is Brandon LaRouche he
started very young with roblox I think
he was probably about like 10 or 11 he
played with his brother his twin brother
actually it's weird I knew a lot of
twins on roblox it's weirdest thing and
they all come in pairs like they don't
do it individually they all do it
together yeah he started with his
brother and again it's this classic
story that I told you he just started
kind of playing games and then he
realized oh there's these really easy
development tools I guess I could
probably do that he didn't start off
fancy he didn't try to make Skyrim or
anything like that he just you know made
little little platformer games or just
made little tiny game mechanics again
just try to recreate little things of
what he saw and from that he actually
realized like oh I really like software
development I really like coding and it
really could just jump started his
career again I want to emphasize very
very early so he took that and he went
beyond roblox although he's come back to
roblox since but he explored all kinds
of software development because of this
initial spark he explored baking mobile
apps he explored making websites he even
wrote books and again I want to I can't
emphasize this enough young he wrote two
books by the time he was fifteen I don't
know what I was doing when I was fifteen
I don't know what you were doing is when
you were fifteen I'm gonna guess that
you weren't writing books and this guy
published - which just blows my mind
it's it's amazing and also like his apps
like he's made apps that have like
650,000 downloads like again that's not
something I did when I was 1516 but
there he is and yeah and really what's
kind of neat about Brandon is that I was
fortunate enough to work with him he
actually came for an internship at our
company and then we liked him so much
that we just hired him pretty much on
the spot I mean we have to wait for him
to finish school but he's so talented
from again just kind of jump-starting
really really early he didn't wait to
finish high school or college to you
know develop his skills we're you know
when he's joining a company he's not
going
a junior level because he's basically
the technical lead on our development
website he started that up and he's an
intern and we contracted him after it's
soft and so amazingly talented person
and what's really cool about what I'm
talking about today is that there are
lots of brandon's out in the world just
kind of wanted to paint you a picture of
one of them there lots of them that we
work with and so to kind of segue from
that I want to talk about some of the
programs that we do and again this is
sort of gives the context of how we work
with these developers so we have two
programs that we run on-site in our
offices down in San Mateo by the way yes
I'm from California and I'm really glad
that it's not smoky up here so really
refreshing change yeah so we run two
programs in our offices and they're both
essentially mentorship programs we have
what are called our incubators and
accelerators difference isn't too
important basically we bring these kids
on-site to give us some direct platform
feedback because their domain experts on
our platform so we want to make sure
they can talk with engineers and say hey
you know it'd be nice if we could fix
this would be nice we had this feature
but the other really big part of these
programs and whoa Kisan here is that we
give them mentorship and guidance
because really the theme of what i want
to talk about today is that there's lots
of these young developers out there who
are really gifted and talented but
they're lacking in some just kind of
real world expertise a lot of them again
our self-taught self-motivated you know
they you know watch videos on YouTube
they read tutorials they just kind of
try things out a lot of times they'll
come to us as sort of lone wolves
they're like yeah I've dabbled with
everything I've learned a lot but then
they don't really know how to take that
to the next level they don't know how to
achieve like their vision of creating a
game or making an app in our case is
pretty much exclusively games but again
it this applies to pretty much anything
and so yeah when they come to us we
really just kind of kickstart them
through development of their games you
know we sit them down they make sure
that they have a plan make sure that
they assemble teams make sure that
they're prototyping again just all these
things that maybe not may not be super
obvious to a developer
who's just starting out but something
that we as industry experts can kind of
impart upon them and it's kind of kind
of shows you some of the things that
came out of this
there's just three titles that happen in
we are a platform and just to give you
some context across these three titles
there's more than two billion game plays
across all three of them it's just again
just blows my mind the success of some
of these young devs have these are all
people like half my age and it's just
it's I don't know I just get flex I
can't talk about them because they're
just so amazing so yeah again so we work
with these kids on site and so now I'll
just talk about you know some of the
learnings that we have and like how we
how we work with them and how we guide
them in how we mentor them and again
giving the context that they're all
really really young so kind of one of
the first lessons we learned very early
on was not trying to tell them what to
do in terms of like make this game
implement this thing do it this way use
this tech we definitely tried that early
on we were like hey you know let's let's
try to have you make this game we had a
very heavy-handed approach in all
aspects of their development from the
design to the implementation and you
know we we we met a lot of resistance I
think that if you if they even work with
kids or work with almost anyone really
no one really likes to be forced to do
what to do we don't want to be told what
to do they don't to be forced rather
they you want to be guiding people and
so that's kind of what we shifted
towards was instead of telling them hey
here's the games that you should make we
instead try to just inspire and guide
them one of the classic stories I like
to actually tell about this in terms of
not forcing is that one of our early
early folks in fact the person who made
that game on the far left in each city
he came in he pitched a game to us he's
like oh we're gonna make this game
you're gonna just socialize or hang out
with your friends there might be some
mini games it might make a house but
really it's just kind of this social
hangout thing and a whole bunch of
veteran gaming people looked at him or
just like that
never going to work do something else
make this other
game he did it it was okay and then he
came back and made me city and again
this is the game that we said hey don't
you know this game probably is not gonna
work but then it did it's super super
popular as one of our top games of the
platform and it has been for like over a
year so again kind of lesson we got from
that was you know the people that were
working with these young developers they
have a dream they have a vision and they
also really understand these new
audiences as well and so really what
we're looking to do with them is again
not tell them what to do but just help
them reach their goals so in terms of
inspiring you know really what we do is
we try to help them refine their ideas
so kind of the example I like to use for
that is one of the very first things
we'll do with kids when they come join
these programs we talk about their game
pitches I don't know if you're familiar
with this but quite often you'll hear
there's a term called an elevator pitch
where you have to try to exploit boil
your game down so that if you're talking
with someone in like two minutes you
could convey what it is and they could
kind of buy into that and we took that a
step further than we're saying okay
typically I usually hear like say it's
like do this in two minutes we tell them
okay you've got 15 seconds to sell me on
your game and you know it's a tough
challenge they don't they can't do that
right away they have to work on really
boiling down and distilling their game's
mechanics to the real core of what
they're trying to do it's a big
challenge but it really helps them think
critically about what they're trying to
do because well quite often if you just
sort of let these young developers loose
they have a million ideas that go in a
million different directions and they
just spaghetti all over the place and by
kind of just saying hey take a step back
just think correctly about what you're
doing it really helps them focus it and
get started on the right foot and we
kind of carry all carry that through the
whole process so that goes to you know
thinking about their game mechanics you
know don't try to do a billion things
try to really hone in a couple really
core nice things you can execute well on
and it applies to all areas of their
design to you know their interface their
environment design just their just their
game mechanics
because really once they do that then
they can arrive at a really nice clean
idea and execute on it and then another
thing that we try to help them do again
as I said a lot of these kids will come
to us just again having done this all on
their own they you know just you know
we're in their bedroom and they just
were hacking away and that's great they
learned a lot but I think as you all
know any project of any kind of
significant size even even smaller
projects you really need to have a team
you can't do it alone
and that's a thing that a lot of these
young developers don't always
necessarily understand you know
sometimes they'll be working with their
friends and whatnot but by and large the
pattern that I've seen is that they're
they're trying they think that they can
do it all and they try to do it all and
I definitely encourage people to touch
all different areas of development I
mean that's what I did on my journey I
was a full-stack engineer and learned
very quickly about the areas of
development that I didn't like so I
definitely like people exploring but I
do want people to kind of understand you
know what are the areas that I'm really
passionate about because when you have
that sort of intrinsic motivation when
you love what you're doing it makes it
that much more easy to be successful and
you know you make your projects work and
so the things that we'll do with these
teams is we'll help them understand ok
you know what are the things that you're
good at where are the things that you
enjoy doing and the things that you
either you know don't enjoy doing or
don't think you have the time for you
know let's help you figure out how to
form a team around that how can you you
know hire artists how can you
collaborate with other coders you know a
lot of these kids haven't worked with
any kind of you know source control or
version or anything like that
so collaboration is a really big
learning for a lot of these young devs
and then you know just even things in
terms of leadership and just the soft
skills involved with working with other
people it's not all just tech you know
you have to get along with the people
you're working with or if you don't get
along you have to figure out how to not
work with them and you know I I'm glad
that I don't have to do this but some of
the other people who work with these
kids who are a little bit more closely
involved the program you know they're
dealing with just drama in situations
because you know they're just dealing
with humans these are things that you
have to learn and fortunately for these
developers they're learning it
early and the other thing that I kind of
want to make sure that you sort of take
away from this because this is a big
thing that we also want to that we also
had to learn so somewhat the hard way is
you know thinking about diversity in
term in your for your developers and the
kind of people that you're looking to
attract again I'm not saying suggesting
that all of you go out and start a
mentorship program and recruit 50 devs
to work for you you know this can go you
know be as large or as small as you want
but you know when you're working with
anyone who you think has kind of that
fire that sparked that vision that
person who could really be encouraged to
grow into a developer you know there's
some times I've noticed in the industry
I mean this is true for gaming so I
don't know if how widely it extends by
imagine it's pretty true for software
there's this kind of celebrity persona
of like a hotshot developer or like a
rock star and you know when you've set
up programs to attract people like yeah
let's get the best of the best of the
best you know well advertise like that
we're like we are looking for the next
new stars looking for hotshots and you
know the truth of the matter is you know
there's two things wrong with that one
you know a lot of people just don't
self-identify that way you know when
you're asking about that you're asking
for sort of like a personality type
rather than a skill set and you know
just a lot of people that you know I've
worked with through this program they
don't think of themselves as like
celebrities in the programming world you
know they just want to work they just
want to learn skills they want to do a
certain project and you know that's
something that we had to learn and we
had to to work to diversify our teams
was to say like okay you know let's not
focus on like trying to get the best of
the best of the best
let's try to get a big range of people
because they're gonna give us you know
not they're gonna give us a really good
wealth of feedback to because they're
coming from so many different areas of
expertise and so you know we look for
people that not necessarily are like top
of their field but we try to find people
who really have dry
and have passion and look like they're
really gonna stick with something so not
someone who so will definitely accept
people into our programs who aren't you
know mate maybe they have a lot to learn
in terms of like technical skills but
they've shown that they're like yeah you
know I've you've got a lot to learn
learn but I've worked on this game for
three years it's my passion project
we're like that's really cool we want to
help you overcome whatever things are
stopping you from from making it and so
you know by focusing on you know the
passion and the drive you know you help
out these people because you're setting
also setting them up for expectations of
you know we're gonna focus on not you
know boosting your ego and making you
feel really cool but we're gonna help
you do really cool things and that's so
it's gonna help you get a bigger range
of people to just the talent pool is
much wider if you you know think about
just you know you know passion and drive
I think and so you know where what what
to do with this again as I said I'm not
really fully expecting anyone here to
you know set up big programs I think
that this can work at scale at pretty
much any level you know so if you do
work with some kind of like developer
relations team like I do you can
probably you know do some sorts of
mentorships you know either in person or
virtually you know a large scale but it
can also just work with one person you
know if there's someone in your
community someone your family a friend
that you know you know I think that
these sorts of lessons about you know
just teaching them how to realize their
dreams instead of just saying you know
hey you want to be a software engineer
just do this project this project this
project you're done you know really help
them explore the ideas that they want to
do and help them think through the
problems that they're going to encounter
facing that because you know really
there's so many people in so many
different ideas that we're not gonna be
able to help them we're you know they're
just gonna come up with all kinds of
things that will never think of and the
things that we can do as industry
experts and as veterans as we can
you know help them just understand what
the stumbling blocks will be help them
understand you know what what challenges
will will get in their way
and so you know that's that's very good
for like a one-on-one mentorship thing
and then you know also there's never
been a better time for people to just
get started as well you know sometimes
you know I was saying you know don't do
like I have you handed do this project
do this prior to this project that's
true although I do think you know when
you're very very very green and new is
nice to have sort of project-based
learning to kind of help you get started
and there's lots of great resources for
that the power of code is a really
really big thing now you know a lot and
there's a huge wealth of camps programs
and stuff that you know particularly
kids can get involved with to get
started but again I definitely want to
make sure that you know if you're you
know if you're if you again have like a
young person in your life you're like
okay there's this cool camp that you can
go to there's this cool class that you
can take well make sure that you know
you help them think about again just the
things that they're trying to make and
not just say hey you should go to this
camp because learning programming is
good you know we're going to the Future
everyone's going to need to know some
kind of programming which i think is
true but you know help them understand
why that's important especially if they
do you know play games or if they do
like like some app on their phone or if
they do like some website they're like
man it'll be really cool you know I can
maybe make that help them understand yes
you actually can make these things you
know these things were made by people
just like you and you can get there and
all you need to do is just give them the
tools and caps or the guidance to make
that happen
so and yeah I'm got a little bit of time
left but yeah pretty much out of slides
but thank you very much everyone it's