hello so first of all I'm really happy
that so many people are interested in a
clean architecture or coding clean
components in the front-end code quality
or clean code is something that I really
am passionate about and I think that
learning some tricks can actually help
you to significantly improve your code
and make it a lot more testable and yeah
I kind of repurposed my initial idea of
using snake to convey some of these
ideas because I was inspired by a talk
yesterday about clean architecture
looking at it a bit from a higher level
and I just felt that that was exactly
what I wanted to share too so first of
all a bit about me my name is Peter and
I'm a developer at small improvements in
Berlin I'm a big fan of many things but
among these things are functional
programming clean code keeping things
simple regardless of what it is and
perhaps a bit random air quality I'm
quite obsessed about measuring particles
and stuff odd things about me okay and
yeah so even if a snake is not like main
thing now but I still have a lot of
snake stuff and it might be helpful for
you to see an example of how it looks
just so that the code examples are a bit
clearer
so let me embarrass myself by losing a
snake quickly so this is the a game that
I built and we will use that as an
example but I will also go beyond just
snake and show you some example
that are perhaps more in line with what
you might I died that are a bit more in
line with what you might be be coding on
a day-to-day basis but I think snake is
a great example because it's yeah you
couldn't see it has a component with
quite a lot of interaction so a quick
outline first we'll look a bit at
presentation versus model or present or
view versus logic whatever you call it
but I'm trying to distinguish between
these two different things and then dive
a bit deeper into what a model is how it
can look like and then proceed with
views because they are pretty useful and
some testing on top of that and finally
I will summarize learnings so what you
can take with you so let's start with
kind of a quiz or just yeah engaging you
as the audience so if you look at the
first one a checkout flow what would you
categorize that as is that a
presentation thing or is it like more
model logic any opinions ideas sorry
yeah it's good I will also share my
opinions after
and generating components what would you
treat at us very good and the setting
game over if you hit the wall very nice
and yeah the first one a bit tricky in
my opinion fingers both and you have to
remember here that we are looking at
focusing on the front end a bit so what
what our model is in the front end can
be a bit different from what you would
see it as in the back end for example I
think some frameworks call it also view
model for example which is kind of
speaking to that but yeah I would say
check out flow as it needs both both
sides generating components presentation
ideally of a model and setting game over
if you hit the wall and this is in snake
then I would treat as a model concern so
what can a model look like here's an
example of check out model I made up so
you have a step because this is a
stepwise stepwise process and the first
step could for example be entering your
contact details which consists of a
bunch of fields and then perhaps yeah
perhaps based on the country you select
you offer different payment methods or
something so you need this for multiple
purposes both to influence how you
render the view later on and to have
this logic in the system so in Iceland
you can pay with cookies but in Sweden
maybe pay with blueberries or something
another model would be snake my favorite
model so in snake it's yeah you saw me
playing it before and I was listing or
showing the status
if it's game over or the game is running
the score and then you have a bunch of
details that you need to keep track of
to be able to like ya decide what
happens next
can I press up what happens when the
time goes on will I move up if I eat an
apple what happens then and where are
actually the apples so let's do an
experiment because we didn't introduce
views yet
really so how would it look if you would
just play with a model
and we will go into this disc out a bit
later so don't have to care too much
about it so in a very easy way to play
with our model is to just use
console.log
and it's it becomes a bit trickier think
yeah already game over now that
challenge is kind of not eating the
apples but staying alive yeah so that's
how it look and it shows that the model
is kind of enough in a sense it's what
you need to be running whatever you do
and the check out example exam for
example you could also technically work
with the model you see the step and you
you're on your own say that I so now I
need to fill in the contact details but
it's really boring to play with this
model directly so we need views and what
is a view yeah you can see it is
something that you just connect to your
model kind of a mapping of your model
into something else so you take the
model transform it for example you
already seen how I did it into the
browser using under the hood react
components you also seen one of Darwin
here console.log that I used it's in a
sense of view and then I could also
implement a terminal view which I
actually did but what is a view at a bit
of a higher level so in essence if we
look at the snake example you present
the model and then yeah I'm kind of
combining also what you would if you
know MVC for example you typically treat
this as the controller bit but in react
world it's very common to group these
together in the component which I also
do but so a view in react world is about
present presenting what you have so we
need to draw the status in some way so
this is the conceptual idea and we draw
the apples we draw the snake we draw the
walls and we repeat and we need to move
the game forward by
the stick which moves it moves it
forward in time and then we have a bunch
of things that allow us to manipulate
this view and as I said the snake is
just an example because it's fun to work
with but actually this is how I think
you should be coding in your normal
day-to-day coding for example with the
checkout flow you could have something
like this
so we render the contact details which
is some kind of form and this form has
some handlers that allow you to
manipulate the model so this set name
will give in a model and a new name
give you back your new model which has
this name set and then you rerender it
so it's yeah it's not limited to snake
but you can apply it for anything
basically in the front end and let's
have a quick look at how this actually
looks in real code that's also
so can can everyone see the coat is it
large enough cool
so this conceptual yeah there is some
boilerplate here because this model is
running in the terminal but you can see
these drawn methods here draw snake draw
apples and then yeah a bit
boilerplate getting the initialize
initialization but here is the loop that
you saw in this conceptual idea where we
draw the different parts and manipulate
in the model and one observation is that
it's pretty simple in there are not many
like if statement conditionals and stuff
and let's also have a look at react one
cool yeah and by the way I'm using some
typescript but to such an extent so it
you don't really need to know it or care
about it so it looks a bit different
because I'm using react here and have to
adapt to react but the principle is
still the same so up here I have these
mappings that allow me to control the
model and yeah need to do it a bit
differently because I don't want to
rerender all the time
and here is the game loop and because in
react you given the state update you
render the state so so I don't do draw
walls and stuff here but I rather do
that here that you might recognize and
again something to observe is that this
is pretty simple code there's not much
that tells you about the game for
example you can't really say even what
happens if I eat an apple all of this is
not not existing here but everything is
just about putting the pixels on the in
the browser basically so let's jump back
to presentation yeah
testing so actually I wonder if I
yeah I've been running for it pretty
quick but testing is there an
interesting topic so let's try to spend
some time there so test one problem that
I often see and if you look at what
actually we will see it when we look at
the test so a problem with tests that I
often sees that they are very very
detailed it's like for example in a
snake game a test could be a set
movement vector should set the movement
vector and you assert on that and I mean
that's an extreme example but you will
see often a huge amount of tests that
are at a very detailed level and I want
to show you how I think tests should
look like and how these principles when
you put them all together makes it
really easy to accomplish that
so these are my tests for the snake
model yeah first start with a bunch of
simple tests that that you would
probably normally see also but then I
test confirmed that very important
properties of the snake model works for
example different seats so this is
another point that allowed me to do
testing well that yeah I don't rely my
model is pure as well maybe that's
something worth mentioning that the
model execution of the model will always
give the same result and one key aspect
of that is that it's pure so I'm using a
seat that initializes our random
generator that allows me to still get
randomness in it while keeping it pure I
can show you that soon but here I just
confirm the property but the more
interesting tests are here where I'm
pretty much playing the game so going
into the top wall leads to game over and
check the order walls as well eating an
apple increases the score by 1 and what
do I do
well I just create a game instance and
play until I eat an apple and thanks to
using this seat for the random
generation I know that the apple will
always be at the same place even if a
user would perceive it as random of
course when you play the game I just use
a random seed every time that makes sure
that you can't memorize where the apples
are and stuff like that yeah but I
managed to test like pretty much the
whole game here snake is growing snake
crushing into itself leads to game over
and all of this is done with tests that
basically could be as the usage of the
code
and yeah what enables this simple
testing yeah a pure model the random
generation something very importance is
simple construction of the object let me
show you so to create a snake game and
this is actually something you typically
don't fully can control because
sometimes you just need a lot of data
but based on my experience yeah
from whenever I started being
professional software developer one of
the biggest obstacles are that it's hard
to test and it makes people skip it so
is a construction rich model with very
meaningful modifiers so I'm a big fan of
DDD domain-driven design and this is
something I brought with me from that so
rather than having a set movement vector
method on my model that I looked at a
lot of snake implementations and most of
them were dealing with updating the dxdy
to to make things yeah to change the
movement but I just call it move up and
that's what I use in my tests so I try
to make the model very deep in a sense
so there is of course a lot involved in
moving up I have to check if it's
possible and stuff like that but the
model on the exposes simple move up
yeah or we have to move down example
here and complete separation of model
and view I think that's the most
essential things and it boils down to
separation of concerns what we discussed
in the beginning with what is what is
presentation what is model this is
really the key to to code cleaner
components because as you've seen
examples the view layers just be are
trivial basically and all the logic
lives in the model and the model itself
is also trivial or at least you can make
it it's a bit of a different small scale
challenge how you code it but as long as
the interface from it is nice then you
have something really nice to work with
that will kind of translate into a
simple view simple react components yeah
nothing it's important that in your
day-to-day work you need to remove
obstacles you need to make it really
simple to make people test more because
this is I often heard these arguments
like is testing really worth it it's
such a big maintenance burdens it just
takes a lot of time but I think if you
showed tests where an application where
all tests looks kind of like this then
this would partly disappear and this is
what happened at my work for example we
we started to write way simpler tests
and it makes a lot of people write more
tests that I you can just see that that
when you extract out the logic from the
components then it's so easy so there is
no excuse and the tests are really
meaningful as well so you you kind of
can motivate for yourself why they are
valuable so what are the biggest
learnings well I would say that I have a
lot of learnings in one way but there
are only two things
that are really important to like if you
would start to do this I think you would
produce better code that's my belief
that if you kick up kick out the model
from your component to really be strict
about separating it go back to the old
MVC wrote I'm sure you done it at some
point then yeah separate it out and for
example at work I am really happy every
time I see a folder which has the
component we often put it in indexed ojs
and next to it sits a model jeaious and
this is a really small model that or
well the size doesn't matter but it's a
model where all the logic has been
extracted which ensures that the
component itself is super pure super
nice super easy to read and the model is
trivial to test super quick to tests and
as I showed you the tests are not really
limited to a set movement vector or
stuff like that but you can actually
test the whole logic such as playing a
game of snake or whatever you are doing
our checkout flow yeah I think we can go
to if there are any questions everything
crystal yeah you in the back
that's correct and that was an example
of like kind of one of the points of you
normally you don't care about that you
don't need to run your model in
different places but this is a free
benefit you get and it's a clear example
of how separation of concerns help you
so if we look at my snake model so so
the snake model it really doesn't know
anything about where it's running we are
creating the model that I showed and I'm
using some interesting concepts but not
so important but then we have these move
up move down and let's look at exported
things and at each method get the score
so it doesn't matter where it runs and
that's why I could run it in the
terminal and browser actually I might
also so in the terminal I also did
I did build an interface so you can
actually play it as a real snake as well
and like abuse you can have as many
views as you want by separating the
model out like this any other questions
or do you want to see details of any
specific part
okay so maybe a final question from me
did you learn anything do you feel that
will you separate out your models a tiny
bit more after my talk at least I see
nodding heads very nice
it's truly it it truly has a very big
impact on your code and for me these the
principles from clean architecture that
I read the book and I often apply it in
the back end and I also read Dedede book
which I really love there which
emphasizes separating out the business
logic which in this case would be the
snake model and this this theory can
really help you to produce the cleaner
code that is just easier to maintain
more fun to work with yeah so if there
are no questions or anything you want to
see yeah this is what you would have
seen in my FB talk but maybe next time
but very nice in my opinion okay that's
it then thank you very much and please
[Music]