hello everybody I'm Nicholas Carr 7
Monta I'm the guy behind the JavaScript
in for his tool kit and today I'm going
to be talking about creating interactive
data visualizations for the web so there
are too many topics related to the
project one is data visualization itself
the other one is JavaScript since I'm
going to be describing more what the
toolkit does I'm going to focus more on
data visualization but you can ask me
any JavaScript weird question so the
JavaScript them for this toolkit its
purpose is to create web based
interactive data visualizations it
supports charts and multiple graph and
three layouts it's a modular extensible
and composable and its web standards
based so by modularity what I mean is
that you can go to the to the page and
you can actually make your own build of
the toolkit so you can keep the code of
the visualizations you will use and keep
all the code of the visualizations you
won't be using internally actually the
toolkit has many independent small
modules of functionality that you can
add or remove those are kind of generic
modules for example you can add total
support or event system with you know
event delegation or most movement
tracking or you can add remove
navigation panning and zooming or graph
operations and dissolve work the same
for visualization so you can add or
remove those this is interesting because
you know for the loading time of the
page then
it is extensible in a way of know the
mathematical definition of a graph is
that you have a set of notes and set of
relations between notes and there is not
much a more concrete description of what
a node is awarding edges and so I try to
keep that kind of abstraction to let you
you know customize the nodes and edges
just as you want so basically in this
example we can see different node types
these are built-in types and you can
change different properties like size
color or any canvas style same goes for
the edges you know like line with color
etc or you can hack your own note
rendering functions or edge rendering
functions by augmenting the node types
object and so you could you know use
draw image from canvas or pester video
inside of the canvas or you know etc and
following this idea of extensibility I
thought that it would be quite elegant
for the toolkit to be able to compose
visualizations from other visualizations
so you could add visualizations as node
and edge rendering functions to other
visa actually but you can do it and most
important of all web standards based so
I'm basically using html5 canvas but I'm
also using SVG CSS and JavaScript ie six
to eight is supported via Explorer
canvas or flash canvas which is you know
flash a JavaScript API for canvas in
flash all our browsers are supported
natively there's also a mobile support
for Android and iPhone I'm supporting
touch events and also for example some
versions of iphone do not have
very good Phil text function for the
canvas so you can fall back and just add
HTML and svgs labels for the note the
future visualizations are stacked charts
like ariel bar and pie charts you have
space filling visualizations which i'll
be describing later and also know to
link visualizations you have stacked
aria charts everything is you know very
dynamic you can filter and restore your
filters and you can upload the data
alive also by sending another json
object jason data same principle for the
bar charts you can change the
orientation of the bars can also update
the data live sm goes with pie charts
this is kind of a more complex
representation of a pie chart in which
you know each pie slice has different
heights and you are dealing with many
different layers of information which
are aggregated on each file but you
could also just make up I a simple pie
charts
so not much to say about charts then you
have space filling visualizations so
watching what our space filling
visualizations so if you take a standard
3 layout and you want to render it on a
constraint space you will find out that
there are two main problems actually the
first problem is that there's a lot of a
new space actually the entire white
square behind the tree is a lot of a new
space and the other problem is that if
you add a level to the standard tree it
won't feed anymore so researchers
thought about changing you know the
visual metaphor of parent-child
relationships in just something that
would make a visualization that could
fit in a constraint space and so b is a
child of a they thought it could be a
child of a B is contained in a and so by
changing this metaphor they made a
visualization which solved the true
problems actually it fits in the entire
rectangle and if you add add levels in
indefinitely it will still fit and so
this is the tree map visualization there
are many different types of trim up
tiling algorithms each one has different
characteristics so for example if you
were to find an element alphabetically
you could use a slice and dice layout
because it lays nodes ordered but for
example for what you use a trim app on a
mobile device with it with a touch
device would be better to use those
qualified layout because notes are more
like square fish and so is it's it's
easier to tap on a node from a score if
I trim up than nearest to tap on another
no slice and dice trim up which as you
can see notes are quite thinner and so
you can
you know make mistakes easier and so
these are freely out there are many
along layouts actually but I implemented
free of them this is actually a tree map
of the music I listen to so there's a
band Incubus if you drill down the tree
map you can see the album's very smooth
animations for everything same here this
is clarified layout and you can change
the layout also on the Flyers animations
for that too so this is a strip layout
of the tree map this is a slice and dice
as you can see notes have a higher
aspect ratio they are not very squared
as you can see but they can be sorted
which is kind of nice in some cases and
so following the idea of space fading
visualizations you have like radial
layouts of space filling visualizations
for example the sunburst visualization
which is generally used well is used on
many different things but generally it's
used on file system visualizations so
for example this is the code this is the
source of the of the project itself
mapped on the visualization the
uncompressed source of course so when
you click on a node you have you know
the last commit on github it's file size
and what it was last modified and you
can focus on an old
now you can extend this visualization
for four graphs so not just trees in
this case I'm using something called
hyper lines to connect nodes it behaves
just the same then you have the Icicle
space-filling visualization in which you
know a parents children are actually on
the right or at the bottom of its parent
this also used for filesystem
visualizations generally but you can use
it for whatever you like for your keys
as you can see can handle a good amount
of nodes this visualization was house
was actually contributed by
visualizations like the one that you're
seeing are like more intuitive it's
easier to understand another link vs
ation it's easier to see what's the
topology of a tree with a node link
visualization and also what you can do
is you know add extra information on the
edges like coloring the edges or adding
a line width etc something that you
can't do with space filling
visualizations at least when I showed
you see there there are no edges or the
visualizations in this ones you have so
the first one is a radio layout of a
graph which is kind of simple to make
but researchers made a lot of research
about how to make intuitive or non
confusing animations for this and I'm
going to and so they arrived to the
conclusion that by changing free things
you could make you know more
understandable animations with a radial
layout and so I'll be describing these
three things
so this is a rare layout of a more
general graph so if I were to click on
node 9c the top left nodes which are on
the on the Outer Ring they will remain
on the same outer rain on the new
position but during the animation they
will get all cluttered in the middle and
this will make the animation quite
confusing see they get all in the middle
that's because they use some linear you
know the shortest path to do the
animation from the starting to the
ending position by changing a
rectangular to polar interpolation you
will see that during the animation notes
will remain on the same outer concentric
ring which is kind of more
understandable for the animation itself
same goes for another case say for
example you have a central node and lots
of notes on the on the first ring if you
click on white if you click on this node
you will see that the notes jump on the
outer ring but they also rotate a lot so
it's kind of complicated to understand
word notes are now and to actually
follow each node properly but if you add
this constraint you'll see that the
notes just jump out and they remain on
the same relative angle so this makes
the the visualization more you know
understandable and these are the kind of
things that in focus researchers work on
and I kind of implement these things on
a toolkit so then you have a hyperbolic
to visualization and this is what it's
called a focus best context technique it
has sort of like a magnifying glass
effect in which the sensor node has a
lot of detail and then there is
the tree is kind of distorted to fit
into a disk and in order to make this
effect what you use is another type of
geometry which is called a hyperbolic
geometry which is actually the same
geometry s-curl I don't know if you know
him uses to make his heart so I'm going
to show a couple of examples of this
he's a very simple transmission as you
can see the center node gets bigger and
the other nodes remain on the constraint
space what you can also do is add graph
operations on the tree so say for
example you'd like to remove the bottom
right subtree you can do it with
animation say you want to remove some
edges you can also do it the top left
edges with an animation and will
recalculate the position automatically
you can add a graph or transform a graph
into another graph by adding and
removing notes so this is just a generic
model that works on abstract graphs and
you can implement it on any
visualization you want then there's this
pastry this is like a more intuitive
layout of a tree with the addition of
the fact that you collapsed sub trees
which aren't in the path between the
clicked node and the root node and when
you collapse these sub trees you do an
animation and you also add some type of
visual encoding to you know inform the
user that what is the topology of the
tree like is that a big surgery there or
how number of know how many number of
notes that it does it have etcetera so
this is a very simple example this all
on the demos page of the of the homepage
of the toolkit see if you click on a
node it makes all those animations of
contracting and expanding subtrees you
can change the tree orientation also and
besides selecting a node what you can
also do is you know
set a notice route that will change the
topology of the tree itself now you have
another tree with another route then you
have the force directed graph so first
affected is a physical system simulation
in which all nodes have a repulsive
force and notes which are connected to
each other have also an attractive force
and you run this for a couple of times
and then you make a layout and what's
interesting about this layout is that
symmetries are preserved so you can see
the symmetries of our graph by doing
this layout and also it makes
aesthetically pleasing layouts it's very
useful for general graphs generally you
know this is just not a tree anymore
this example is also interesting because
it is like a small graph editing tool in
which you can add panning and zooming
and you can drag and drop nodes and you
can click on a node and select it and
you can delete notes and cetera at those
so this is a very simple example you
have the code here and you can access
and so this might be quite useful to
some some people okay some examples so
this is a trimmer visualization I made
of Doctor Who's valence so each villain
is a is a rectangle or it's represented
by a rectangle and the size of the
rectangle is proportional to the number
of episodes the villain appears on so
you can kind of drill down and have more
information on demand like the stories
of your own appears on and then what you
can do is kind of have a dynamic
filtering on the tree map so here on the
right I have the name of all the actors
who played doctor who from 1963 to 2010
and so you can filter the villain
is through this bar so you click here
and just your dynamic filtering which is
kind of interesting
then you have an old example of artists
and relationships but I don't know if
you know it it's kind of like a six
degrees of separation to Kevin Bacon so
you have a band which is centered and
all the members of the band on the on
the first level and then you have other
bands related to those members on the
second level and so when you click on an
artist it will fetch the information via
Ajax and morph the graph into the new
graph of relations and so what's
interesting about this is that you can
browse up which has lots of you know
collaborators and it works pretty well
and this is actually done with the one
dot 0 version so not that many of the
optimizations in the code then then I
was surprised to find this article from
google wave developer blog in which a
person was you know mapping the shape of
a wave into a visualization so I found
this dis article which was quite
interesting surface are unavailable
Mozilla also used it used actually the
hyperbolic trivialization to make a
community map so they styled it with and
then you have other examples the
Guardians embedded a tree map inside of
a data block page and that work sorry ah
I don't know if I have the link but you
made it right oh well I don't know if I
have
was it like for this yeah that's it
right yeah I don't know where but you
have also fourth grade so what's next
I've just merged a branch in which i
implemented WebGL on the toolkit I'm
working on trying to you know map what's
to the canvas on to some primitives on
3d so as to be able to scale to a lot of
notes by using you know the GPU also
working on Howard acceleration for by
using CSS free you know one emotions and
stuff like that and working on 3d
layouts I have a small example of this
on a nightly so we can crash it's a very
simple example so this is actually a
force directed graph render it on WebGL
with the API of the javascript in forest
okay what you can also do is just add
notes dynamically it will recalculate
the layout
and so that's it if you have any
questions about the implementation yes
okay so actually the entire toolkit has
a nice namespace which is a dollar jet
and so you can if you don't have a
toolkit that also has dollar jit as
namespace you could put it with it with
another library tools place with with
variables and it works fine so it just
just 11 global element dollar jit and
then torch it dot whatever to create
your visualizations no defense
whatsoever no that's why you can create
your own build because you know if you
put all the visualizations together even
if you're not using them it's not very
practical because you are adding lots of
code that you won't be using but it's
interesting to see that there's actually
a builder and so you can just select
yeah I want the our graph and hyper tree
and you use either closure compiler or
no no compression and no compression you
have the entire documentation inside of
the code so it's good for testing and
just understanding what this stuff does
yes
so what's to protiv is compare it to
proud of is I think that I'm not sure
because i haven't used it a lot but i
think that they have a good amount of
layouts different layouts and charts and
said ran for charts is very you can you
can really customize a lot what you can
do with the toolkit for charts
specifically which was the last thing
thing added there's a very simple api
and so it's easy to use for for easy
things but perhaps more complex things
can take a you know hacking more code
but i think that the the adventure is
the advantage is that you also have like
smooth animations for everything and
generally when you are you know drilling
down a tree map its kind of useful to
have the animations because understand
better the zooming part and etc and also
i think that you know being able to be
working with WebGL right now is that the
fact that i'm guaranteeing that by the
end of the year you will have if you
have a WebGL spec which is final you
will have a toolkit that works with it
and you will be able to scale 200
thousands of nodes easily so i think
that these are kind of the differences
any other question