[Music]
yeah hello I'm glad you're interested in
that weird topic my name is Anna I like
to talk about computer games
role-playing games and theoretical
computer science so just one topic was
fitting for the conference so I went
with theoretical computer science I'm
here today to talk to you about one of
my secret passions which is complexity
theory and I'm going to give you a short
introduction to computational complexity
so I'm not going to talk about time or
space complexity if you already have an
idea what this is I will use a very
made-up real-world example to help you
understand what I'm talking about
so let's go picture this for a moment
you are volunteering at an animal
shelter the shelter has cats dogs
turtles you and your weird manager the
manager is weird because she sets up
arbitrary rules for you and other people
to follow you are in charge of the
petting process over viewing the petting
process so visitors come to your shelter
and want to have pet animals and you
have to make sure they follow the
petting rules
each rule is different every day so on
your first day the rule is the visitors
cannot pet two cats or two dogs in a row
they're not allowed to touch the turtles
just for completion but this is through
so visitors come in may go pet the
animals they come to you and say well I
pet it a cat a dog a cat and a cat and
you have to decide for example if there
was a valid petting sequence or not if
they're good visitors or bad visitors
you know stuff you have to do you're an
engineering you're just volunteering
there so after 20 visitors you think
like ah a machine could do this and so
you build one you start thinking about
the process so
the visitor comes in and wants to pet an
animal and they can either decide to pet
a cat or a dog
if after petting a cat
they pet another kid there are the bad
visitors and I'm not allowed to come
back same with the dog petting a dog
after dog but they're good if they pet
another animal this is a very simple
machine that can handle your daily tasks
to see if the visitors alternate in
petting animals this machine has a name
in theoretical computer science at the
computer science it's called finite
state automaton so the pictures were the
hand and the animals are so-called
States the arrows between them are
so-called transitions between those
states this is a very simplified version
of what that is so if you never seen
anything like this because you don't
have a computer science education that's
basically the rough idea that you just
need to follow so you think you're good
and you're good for a couple of days but
then your manager changes the rule and
they say well the visitors first must
pet a specific number of cats and then
the same number of dogs
thank you again you sit there you want
to work but also you want to have time
to pet the animals yourself so you think
well maybe I can just adjust my machine
to do that work of checking the petting
sequences for me and you think about
that so you can start work petting
something if you pet a dog in the
beginning you're out that visitor but if
you pet a cat you can pet a lot of cats
and then you can switch to a dog and pet
a lot of dogs and if you're in the dog
stays if you cannot pet a cat again and
you think yeah that's that's nice fish I
mean I know now that I can only pet care
before dogs and not alternating between
them but it's not giving me a check for
whether I pet the same number of animals
and you think of it and think maybe the
machine I'm using is just not powerful
enough to handle this constraint that
the manager gave me so we're introducing
a new part to our machine and it's
called the stack the stack is really
like a stack of books you can put stuff
on top of it and you can put you can
take stuff from the top that's all it
can do so you cannot grab something from
the middle or from the bottom because it
will collapse and will not work I think
okay maybe that's already enough so we
go back to our machine which is not
working and we introduce the stack to it
so whenever we pet a cat we put a cat
token on the stack and whenever we put a
dog we remove a dog a cat token from the
sec so if this the cats and the dogs are
the same number the stack will be empty
in the end that we're good it was a good
visit or if there is a cat left it's bad
visitor if we want to take away a cat
and there's no cat there although we
have pet at a talk and it's also an
envelop petting sequence and the visitor
is a bad visitor this machine is called
a pushdown automaton so the push down is
just pushing stuff on the stack and the
stack is endless is like it's a deep
cellar with no end that doesn't matter
to you how deep it is it's just you can
use as much assist of you want if you as
much of it as you want remember that
this is just a theoretical models are
like no computers having infinite space
and again you're good for a couple of
days but then there's another rule the
rule change again changes again so again
we have to pet the same number of cats
as dogs but now introducing the Turtles
we weren't allowed to touch before and
then thinking again well how are we
going to
this with our stick you know it's now
not just two types of animals but three
so it just cannot take stuff from the
top and put stuff on the top we somehow
have to take into account the turtles
now so we need a new formalism a new
mechanism so we did just the stack and
introduced the tape a tape is the number
of cells and every cell can be accessed
and modified so in the beginning we have
the stack and we couldn't take stuff out
of the middle we can do this now we can
read each cell we can modify itself
the only restriction we have now saying
okay the lengths of the tape is just the
number of animals petted nothing more
that's it about these are the bounds
let's see if we can work with that
this tape is a so-called restricted tape
so our our input will again be in number
of family Mel's two cats two dogs two
turtles I spare you the state transition
diagram because it will get confusing
starting with this machine but the idea
is the following so whenever you see a
cat you walk on the tape until to the
right until you find a dog and then
until you find the turtle and then you
stop again go back to the beginning of
the tape and look for the first kid and
go on so if at the end of the cat's
their only access on the tape it's a
good visit or if there are any moles
left then it's not a good visitor
they're out this machine is called a
linear restricted Turing machine a
Turing machine is a linear restricted
Turing machine is the closest we can get
to a real computer because we have some
restrictions but a lot of power already
the Turing machine is named after Alan
Turing was a British meta machine met
the message math guy
he helped solve a crack the Enigma was
treated really bad by his government
unfortunately but he laid the basis for
the modern computer all this so that's
also white formal models are named after
him because they were basically his
ideas so now you'd a new rule and the
manager is not happy about the process
of retrospectively approving the padding
process she tells you know you have to
check beforehand now if they're going to
put nice on it but the rules simple you
know like you know what as long as they
stop petting after petting 2,000 animals
we're good you know okay weird manager
let's see yes but you know you have to
check beforehand if they're going to
stop at 2,000 animals so your day starts
like this
welcome to the animal shelter how are
you going to pet today the first visitor
says like I'm going to pay at 9999 cats
and one dog and you think about what you
do yes that sounds about right
just petting under 2,000 animals you're
good the next one comes like I'll pit
twice as many pets in this step then in
the step before and I'll start with one
cat and you're already thinking about
autumn izing this but now you cannot
just check sequences of petting but you
have to check you know descriptions of
petting processes and that can can get
really complicated and the programs are
not just like the the descriptions are
not limited in any way they can be
everything if you think well you have to
believe me that restrictor tape won't do
anymore
I might need more space I don't need I
don't know how many space I want it
maybe it's twice as much maybe it's a
lot of orders of magnitude higher than
that so we now go to infinity and beyond
and we introduce an unrestricted tape
and this is the point where it's really
just a mental model anymore
again we have a tape we have
read/write head where we can access and
modify every cell but our tape is
infinite has an infinite amount of sales
to both sides and we can do a lot with
it like really a lot there's beyond that
there's basically basically just I
cannot solve this problem anymore
type of problems some fur does a now
what's the German word it's like a big
hammer to solve your problems even if
you just have a tiny tiny nail and it's
called an unrestricted Turing machine
the description how you access the cells
is it's not super complicated but a bit
too much for that talk but you can ask
me about it later if you want so that
was the basic introduction of
computational complexity so let's recap
a bit during our process at the animal
shelter
I work there we build four machines in
our head mostly the first one was was
the finit stayed at someone won the
pushdown automaton the linear restricted
Turing machine and the unrestricted
Turing machine these types of machines
helped so-called help to solve so-called
decision problems for languages so what
is a decision problem in English it
would be decide whether an input is
valid against the given set of rules or
not it's still in English but like a
little more computer science he is
decide whether a word is part of a
language so if you if you don't have a
formal computer science education you
might wonder like what we what do you
mean by what is the language what is the
language I mean it speak English like
French and these are languages but in
computer science a language is just a
set of words the set can be fin it can
be infinite and some sets are described
by rules and some are not so some
languages would be for example every
sentence in the English language it's a
set of strings it's a set of words
others would be the set of all valid
phone numbers
the set of all polynomial in tin hello
world so you can see that some of the
sets are no they are all infinite as a
matter of fact but just you know the set
with the word hello is already a
language in a way and these machines
help us to classify those languages
there are formalisms
to help us understand how you know how
complex the language is in the
computational sense there are some names
for those languages for example the
first type of language we we set with a
finite state automaton it's called a
regular language so you might have heard
of regular expressions and they're like
really really deeply connected to that
the pushdown automata describe
context-free languages most of the human
languages are context-free languages and
can be computed with those machines the
next type of languages would be context
sensitive languages they are human
languages who fall into that category
and another one which you're probably
not going to touch anytime soon are
recursively enumerable languages there
are a lot of other words for those
groups but this is these are some of
them and if you want to look close into
that you just google for Chomsky
hierarchy Noam Chomsky was or is he used
to work as a linguist at least and he
laid the basis for a lot of formal
formal syntax and formal grammar and
it's a really interesting read because
it was one of the first people to look
at languages in a mathematical way and
they also laid the basis for this type
of theoretical computer science so now
you're wondering like why would I need
to know that and maybe you don't you
know if your job is just increasing
conversion by coloring buttons that's
totally fine and you're probably not
going to touch this part of of computer
science but it can be useful for
validation purposes
as I told you like a decision problem is
to see whether an input follows a
specific set of rules and phone number
validation or address validation you
might have touched this and now present
you would like to groups of problems at
this point so we have the set of valid
phone numbers and the valid street
addresses and in this second group we
has correctly matched parentheses and
valid SPG so why would you check for
correctly matched parentheses you
probably wouldn't but if you write a
text editor for programmers for example
that's an interesting thing to know like
do you inform your user that they're
missing prevent parenthesis and I told
you how regular languages are deeply
tied to regular expressions and for a
lot of problems and sets we have regular
expressions are totally fine but for the
second group they're not for example
because the second group the language is
in the second group are more complex
than the one in the first group and they
need a different type of machine a
different type of formalism to be
evaluated and checked against so you
can't really write any regular
expressions for SVG or HTML for example
because you have the opening and closing
parentheses now I know that there are
people here will probably say yeah but
there are regular expressions that you
can use to do that and in a way that
their implementations that make it
possible on a strictly theoretical base
it's not another thing that you might
leverage but that another knowledge that
you might leverage is the so-called
expressive power
so all formulations or machines have a
power of what they can describe and one
thing this hierarchy has is that the
machine in order higher can always be
used to describe and solve problems that
are lower than it and a lot of machines
formalisms actually do the same so we
have many tools for one job available I
mentioned that if unit state automata
regular expressions and regular grammars
are basically the same they're not just
very very that's not just a very strong
connections they're so called Aquila
equivalent so you can always transform
such an automaton into a grandma or red
X and the other way around that's the
important thing
so if at one point you think well array
X would not help me here it would be
very hard to write we very hard to
maintain you can up for in other
implementation of the same formalism and
still have the same power attached to it
and there are other other tools that are
basically formalisms for formal language
just like XML schema or JSON schema or
tree automata that you might find useful
so for example you wouldn't you know
implement a finite state automaton by
hand but but knowing like well JSON
schema is is more expressive than that
and I like working with JSON schema you
can use JSON schema to to handle the
task of the finished state automaton
some people say well you should always
use the machine the most easiest the
easiest machine for the job but it's not
really worth losing sleep over how to
implement the most the best machine if
your curl machine is doing the job so
you're not really using losing too much
performance or anything if you do it
right and another thing that's really
really helpful if you know that is
avoiding pork so I'll show you again the
rule our manager put last pairing stops
after 2000 animals and other rules now
you know what as long as they stop
petting at any point we're good
and remember you have to decide
beforehand or not if they're going to
stop or not and we have the example that
they're just going to increase the
number of pet animals every step and
just imagining that humans can pet for
infinite amount of time it would be
really hard to check if they were going
to step to stop at any point or not and
that's what the machine says well like
that's not compute I can you know I can
decide I can say so if the petting stops
at any point if it does but if it does
not I'm not sure because it could step
stop in the next step or in the step
after that so if you're able to
correctly identify which is the problems
if they're solvable or not it can help
you avoid some work you know and then
you can just say no ie I couldn't find
an efficient algorithm or an algorithm
at all that solves that problem but I
could those famous people in my yeah in
my surroundings or in history at all so
this is what's computational complexity
about there are different formalisms
that describe different sets of
languages and some formalisms are more
powerful than others
and knowing how they connect and how
they relate to each other can help you
make your life a bit easier as a
developer so thank you very much that
was it
[Applause]