as I talk to you this afternoon I want
you to think about something that you're
passionate about and that you're willing
to share with other people that's
unrelated to programming here's my
example I'm Brian Brennan and I'm really
passionate about music in fact Alex kind
of embarrassed me because that last
track was my band over the past 10 years
I've learned that playing music is is
something that's really important to my
well-being
I play into bands and all of my free
time that's not dedicated to programming
community building I dedicate to
practicing and playing gigs so I want to
tell you a story about my first jazz
comp I it was 2011 it was Portland I
showed up I was traveling alone I had
just started Mozilla and I didn't really
know anyone so I was just going by
myself
and I was really shy and I was anxious
because I was just super intimidated by
all the awesome people that were there
like I there were people that I followed
on Twitter there were people who's like
videos I had seen giving talks at
previous jazz comps and I was I was just
super intimidating it was intimidating
for me because I didn't know how I was
gonna fit in I hadn't thought of myself
as having done anything particularly
noteworthy noteworthy so I just didn't
know I didn't know if I really belonged
so I was walking around the edge of the
room trying to be invisible and Paul
Irish spotted me and somehow recognized
me from the internet and he introduced
himself and invited me into his
conversation and I was just I just felt
very welcome
and I asked Paul if I could share that
just really small tiny story and he
barely remembered it because for him it
wasn't a big deal at all
but for me it was such an act of warmth
and kindness at a time when I needed it
it made me feel welcome when I was
anxious about having a place to fit in
one thing kindness matters that's one of
the reasons I wanted to share that story
small actions matter in the right
context even the smallest kindness can
be deeply meaningful to someone in ways
that are unpredictable Paul didn't know
I was gonna be telling that story here I
asked him like a week ago it was just
for him a throwaway action but for me
something that really stuck with me also
congratulations on your wedding Paul
wherever you are the other reason I
wanted to share that is because I want
us to start thinking about how we
welcome people into our communities a
lot of people approach communities in
the same way that I walked into that
conference shy and worried about fitting
in and anxious most new people go in and
they try to stay invisible they follow
us on Twitter they join our mailing list
they hang out in IRC channels but they
don't interact with us and we have a
word for that it's called lurking and
it's a great strategy I've lurked on the
edges of all of the communities that
I've joined before deciding that that's
a place where I could see myself fitting
in and I think we all have a job to
convert these workers into contributors
eventually we hope that we can conscient
turn them into contributors
collaborators and possibly even friends
and to do that we need to remember to be
patient and kind when the lurkers of our
community the people standing around the
outside try to make that first step we
were all novices once and we need to
remember what it was like when we were
new and when we needed help and that can
be an incredibly hard thing to do
because when you think about the same
thing all the time on a regular basis
when you're so entrenched in your own
community it can be really easy to
forget that people aren't also thinking
about that same thing all the time
something a colleague of mine Selena
Declan once said is
the best thing we can do as experts in
our field is make it safer for novices
to experiment and I think this is
absolutely true and more of us should
spend time on that if you want to get
better at this I recommend that you
volunteer your time as a teacher or a
mentor and preferably do it in person
because guiding someone through learning
face-to-face helps you remember that you
are dealing with a real person with
their own unique background rather than
some abstract online identity that's in
need of your time and energy other
people are people too and that's another
thing we need to get better at
recognizing that other people are people
too even online we are all individual
human beings with our own individual
needs and values and feelings and we
need to respect that last year there was
a post on the Linux kernel developer
mailing list where Linus tears into
another developer tells him to shut the
up in all caps and then rips him
apart for the way he handled some
situation and some of the developer
response I saw that really bummed me out
I saw people saying you need to have
thicker skin if you want to be a
programmer or gettin'
development if you want to be coddled
and that's some really defeatist
language it's saying we have a culture
of abuse that tears people down and it's
your job to change and get used to that
rather than our responsibility to start
treating people better a command just
Cheryl sharp who's a developer on the
kernel and she put herself out there
saying that they really shouldn't stand
for that abuse in their community and
Highness replied to Sarah and his
response left me even more despondent
than the original post and I want to
read part of it to you I do it partly
because it's Who I am and partly because
honestly I despise being subtle or nice
I simply don't believe in being polite
or politically correct political
correctness I want to say a quick word
about that before I move on
I see that term thrown a lot around in
arguments on the internet and every time
I see it brought up it's by the people
who are resisting change and it's used
as a way to shut down conversations by
appealing to people's fears people here
politically correct and they think that
all the life of their culture will be
extinguished if that's the path we go
down that's why people throw it into
arguments they want other people to back
them up and say oh no we can't go down
that slippery slope I'm not gonna start
wearing a tie to work so when you see
this come up in an argument I want you
to remember it's a loaded term and that
you should rarely take it at face value
that doesn't mean you have to reject
everything the person saying but it
means you should think about it
just realize that political correctness
is is not it's a loaded term anyway
being nice is not about being
politically correct at all being nice is
about respecting another human being as
individual with their own feelings needs
and values last year I saw Isaac
Schluter give a talk called building
compassionate communities in tech it's
excellent you should absolutely watch it
online you can just go type building
compassionate communities to Ask Jeeves
and you'll find it it's the first result
and in in his talk he recommends this
book called nonviolent communication and
after he recommended that I read it and
I was actually really excited to see and
Gen Turner's talk two days ago
lessons and emotional safety she also
recommended that book so this is the
third time so read it but I want to I
want to read you a quote from that book
that has stuck with me we all pay dearly
when people respond to our values and
needs not out of a desire to give from
the heart but out of fear guilt or shame
sooner or later we will experience the
consequences of diminished goodwill on
the part of those who comply with our
values out of a sense of either external
or internal coercion they to pay
emotionally for they are likely to feel
resentment and decreased selfish
deme when they respond to us out of fear
of guilt or shame furthermore each time
others associate us in their minds with
any of those feelings the likelihood of
their responding compassionately to our
needs and values in the future decreases
using guilt and public embarrassment and
fear to motivate people may get things
done in the short term but it comes at a
huge human cost and this is not me
saying you can't give criticism we need
criticism as software developers that's
how we build better software being nice
means realizing that you are dealing
with another human being and that how
you give that criticism matters we have
a stereotype as programmers that were
unemotional and cold and that we operate
on pure logic and the stereotype is
destroying us we are human beings we
have emotions and we feel it when we're
on the receiving end of negativity but
so many of us have internalized an
unrealistic standard of how we're
supposed to date so we avoid talking
about it we don't talk about how we feel
we don't talk about our emotions we
learn to ignore them and we learn to
bottle them up and then we wonder why so
many of us burnout I want to tell a
story that's gonna seem unrelated but
I'm gonna bring it back around so just
hang with me I'm Hispanic and most of my
life I've struggled with my racial
identity my mother is from Panama that's
a small country in Central America for
those of you who are unaware we have a
canal so my mother moved here when she
was 18
a few later a few years later she had me
and my mom knew that the trouble the
English as a second language students
get into in early developmental
education especially where I was growing
up and when I was growing up I've
actually heard stories of some personal
friends who are
english-as-a-second-language Stephenson
they were held back because their
teachers thought they were mentally
retarded because they couldn't speak
English and so my mother made the
decision
to raise us in an english-only speaking
household so I never learned to speak
Spanish and that turned out to be a big
deal for me because the other Hispanic
kids all spoke Spanish and I didn't fit
in with them and they held it against me
because I couldn't speak Spanish
they made me or I was I made myself feel
like I didn't have the right to call
myself a real Hispanic years later I'm
living with a guy who's a friend of a
friend and he would sometimes start
complaining about Hispanic people not to
other people like to me to my face I I
didn't mention this before but he also
collected guns and I was quite
intimidated but after a couple of times
I get up the courage to say to him dude
you know I'm Hispanic right and he goes
like without missing a beat he's like oh
well no no no you're not really Hispanic
you're different I was different I
didn't fit into his mental model his
stereotype of what a Hispanic person was
so I couldn't possibly be one and the
worst part is that at the time I thought
he was right when he said that to me it
brought up all of my issues about how I
thought about myself and I thought yeah
maybe he's right maybe I'm not a real
Hispanic real programmer how many times
have you guys heard that term thank you
I run a user group in New York with my
pal judge Schmitt called Brooklyn Jas we
use the Jas comp code of conduct and we
talk about every meeting we created
Brooklyn Jas because we want a safe
place for people to come and learn from
each other but more importantly to meet
each other and see each other as real
human beings a couple of meetups ago a
guy went up to one of our attendees a
woman who's also a good friend of mine
and said you can't be a real programmer
you're too hot this guy didn't even
realize that he went up to someone and
said the equivalent of up you don't look
like how I think you should so you don't
belong
I was so so mad and ashamed that this
happened at my Meetup and I'm still
trying to think of ways just beyond the
code of conduct to make sure this
doesn't happen again but in the meantime
I want all of you to do something for me
think really hard and try to make all of
your all of your unconscious stereotypes
that you might have about programmers
conscious think about them what we look
like the types of things we're supposed
to be interested in how we're supposed
to think and feel I want you to think
about those things and I want you to
remind yourself that all those things
are I want you to
remember that we are all different and
the one guaranteed thing we have in
common is that we write software and
that's it other than that we're all
individuals with our own identities our
own needs and our own values it's our
responsibility as members of the
community and leaders of the community
and members of various communities to
build and maintain a culture where it's
safe to express our different needs and
values where it's safe to just exist
without emotional or physical fear think
about the people lurking on the edges
and what kind of example you want to set
for them think about the effects your
words have on other people
Adam Braille gave a powerful talk at
Jay's coffee you last year called people
first and many of the things that he's
said in that talk has have stuck with me
but I want to share one particular quote
no matter your title it is your job to
make the people around you feel cared
about empowered and encouraged and
humanized as much as the internet
connects us is incredibly dehumanizing
need to recognize and embrace our
responsibility for taking care of each
other
we need to recognize and acknowledge the
positive influence we have on each
other's lives it shouldn't need to be a
special occasion to let a friend to know
how much they mean to you if you see
someone who's under attack stand up for
them and if you see someone who's
hurting reach out to them and if you
yourself are hurting
talk to someone don't ignore it about
eight years ago I lived through my worst
period of depression I was in college at
the time and I stopped going to class I
failed out of school I stopped going to
work I dropped all of my hobbies my
computer broke and I didn't even care I
didn't bother to get it fixed I don't
know what other people's Depression
looks like but for me it's a profound
deep emptiness but I never talked about
it with anyone I didn't want to burden
people and frankly I was ashamed with
myself how couldn't I control this I
don't have a lot of memories from that
period but I do remember the day I
decided to get help I was driving on a
freeway and a car was coming in the
opposite direction and as it was about
to pass me I had a thought that almost
turned into an action I could swerve
into this car right now and it wouldn't
matter and it was a thought so strong I
could feel it in my hands physically
that I really wanted to do it and at the
last moment I didn't I thought about
what I'd almost done and I thought about
my mom and I thought about my brother
and I pulled over and I started crying
and it took that moment and coming that
close for me to realize that I couldn't
handle it on my own and this is
something that I couldn't change in
myself or by myself and I know that
story makes a lot of you feel awkward so
I apologize if it's any consolation I'm
pretty sure I feel more awkward about it
so but if I was talking to you about
breaking my wrist or getting malaria
that would have been an easy story to
tell but we have a social stigma around
mental health so it's not something we
talk about and so so many of us suffer
quietly and alone a shame that we have
this problem in ourselves that we can't
fix and I think it might be worse for
programmers because not only do we have
that additional stereotype of being
unemotional but because we are supposed
to be able to fix things kind of what we
do so we need to take care of each other
let people know that you're there for
them so when I was telling some of my
friends I was gonna give this talk
the most common advice was oh just be
funny
just use a lot of animating
gifts so I'm pretty sure I nailed it but
for real
I I know this has been some sustained
real talk and I want to thank you for
giving me your attention
I actually feel incredibly positive
about our future more than I have in the
past I see us starting to have open hard
conversations about a lot of this stuff
where we wouldn't have dared talked
about it before I see more people
starting to recognize that there is
humanity behind what we do and seeing
that we need to learn how to deal with
that just as much as we need to learn
how to deal with anything else in our
field I've met and I continue to meet so
many awesome people through programming
and made friendships they even if I quit
programming tomorrow I'd want to
maintain in the beginning I asked you to
think about some of the things are
passionate about that aren't programming
and as we wrap this up and go into our
last evening of celebration I want you
to remember those things and when you
talk to each other don't just talk about
what you do or where you work but in
your entire self to the conversation you
are so much more than just your opinion
on ember or promises remember that being
awesome to each other starts with being
awesome to ourselves thank you very much