so how's the ER the Wi-Fi holding up
here good awesome because my my
presentation uses none of its ah so
how's that for an introduction question
so anyway so it's it's actually a very
important question because I've gone to
a lot of conferences lately where where
the the Internet is suspect at best and
what you're finding is people have their
Dropbox active everything else active
and it's in its causes your your
complete system to go down so how would
you like I instead to be able to create
an app that shares data with everybody
else without requiring all of the the
cell phone and/or Wi-Fi infrastructure
and not only that but I just want to
kind of change the way we think about
the web and especially the pier web who
reads the user end user agreements when
you actually install some software Wow
one person all right do you realize how
much data you're giving away a personal
data you're giving away okay she
realizes firstborn and all of that
beautiful and you know especially when
it comes to to the topics of the pier
web you know people think about data
loss they think about data theft and
they think about things like Edward
Snowden in terms of how much data people
are really collecting so as was stated I
am indeed a principal sde at this
aforementioned company and I'd like to
think that I'm bringing a little bit
more metal to the company so most people
recognize me mostly for this particular
project and so I'm starting to to kind
of get more away from this and on to
other things but what's very fascinating
about this project is the fact that now
Google and Netflix are the biggest
contributors to its who would have
guessed that Google and Netflix and
Microsoft would be working on
same project all at one time so really
this is about starting conversations and
back in 2011-2012 timeframe you know we
we had this this great idea Chris
Williams and I have you know how do we
change the world how do we as software
developers fundamentally change change
how how we interoperate with the world
and everyone was welcome whether they
drank alcohol or not it was just a
convenient name since we happen to meet
at a bar when we started that but that
ended up turning into robots comp which
I think a lot of people I've seen a lot
of swag around so that's really kind of
cool that a lot of people who came here
also supported us there but going back
to Cascadia j/s 2012 Chris Williams came
up with this talk to basically
challenged us all and to say what are we
doing as developers are we creating the
next flappy bird to you know create a
few moments of joy or are we
fundamentally doing something to for
betterment of society as developers are
we helping grow new developers are we
helping in areas of hard science those
kinds of questions and so that's really
kind of a mantle that I picked up and
ran with so let's just talk a little bit
about the Internet of Things you know it
really is about the things and how
they're they're connected to each other
whether it's a the your nest that you
have at home or a raspberry pi you know
quite honestly a lot of that's very
interesting I mean I have literally a
stack of these these boards at home I
have no idea what to do with them all
but I am a collector and I'm a maker of
basically just about anything but what's
what's really kind of interesting about
this is to see a lot of people building
a lot of really really fascinating
things but yet leaving the the door wide
open on
purity which really really troubles me
but I think when it comes to the
Internet of Things I think the most
important piece that you're that you're
missing is this your phone your phone is
largely who you are nowadays in terms of
its your central access point for pretty
much anything whether it's paying for
something whether it's controlling your
house whether it's opening doors etc
your phone is usually where it's at and
so that's why I really wanted to focus
on on the phone as being that that's
that piece that really changes what I OT
is so taking that that idea from Chris
and really let's let's take on some big
challenges here so for example could we
reinvent manufacturing as we do as we
think of it today and the answer is
absolutely I for example these factories
have millions of thousands of machines
that are all trying are all
interconnected and all need to transmit
data so how do you actually wire those
things up and save these companies a lot
of money millions upon millions of
dollars because these companies you know
keep each piece of their hardware for
years you know 20 years or more how do
you allow them to modernize without
costing them a fortune here's another
one how do we improve the lives of
communication of everybody regardless of
economic status whether you are the
whether you're in the the lower economic
brackets or the upper economic brackets
you should have the same access to
communication everybody else does that's
fundamentally important to me is that
everybody should have access to to
information and regardless of whether a
nation state decides that you should
have internet access or not so that's
more of a political issue but I think
it's still fundamentally fundamentally
interesting especially some of the
research that's going on now around
radio white space and allowing the
internet to pre pretty much anywhere
but I think also helping in times of
crisis IOT has a huge huge role to play
in in helping in times of crisis from
because what happens the first thing
that happens is that your right is the
cell phone infrastructure completely
fails your communication infrastructure
completely fails how do you fix that
here's the answer IOT and the phone and
that so not only it will help first
responders be able to find who is in
need of who is in need of assistance but
also help people find and connect with
their loved ones to make sure that
they're not panicking and they know
exactly what's going on and indeed going
even further saving lives because as
people such as our reporters without
borders go into hostile zones what
happens well they leave behind all sorts
of interesting tracing data about
themselves why because your phone of
course is emitting any number of pieces
of information but if you use it
specifically only as a peer device that
doesn't happen and that's why I think
it's very important now most of all I
believe when we're developing these
these kinds of applications especially
as we're building things internet of
things we believe especially I believe
that you as a user have a bill of rights
and that we as ethical developers must
abide by them so i will i will just coin
it as the devices Bill of Rights now as
part of this we're working with with
Bluetooth Bluetooth Low Energy and in
Wi-Fi direct per job to provide that
local discovery mechanism the ability to
do to discover who's around you I is is
is both fascinating but yet terrifying
at the same point so i'll try to i'll
try to enumerate exactly those kinds of
Rights that you should have as we're
developing these these Apple
Asians and I'll and I'll refer to Kim
Cameron who is a computer scientist who
works on identity issues so that that
you have a basic understanding of what
we are trying to go for so the so
Cameron's laws of identity the first law
is that the position the solution
discloses the least amount of
information and the best limits its use
of the for its stable long-term use so
what that really means is that the the
users information does not go out on the
air unless they specifically say so and
then users also must be prominently
notified when exactly it is going out
there you know discovery is different
than any type of other services because
it has imminent dangers along with it
why because for example stalking
harassment and so forth when you're
you're when you're broadcasting this
information you're opening yourself up
to that so users must be able to of
course disable this this kind of feature
and they must specify constraints on
that such as if I'm leaving work I don't
want to be not notified anymore so
that's where it's really key is to is to
to help people keep boundaries because
if someone's being harassed especially
over these these kinds of programs what
kind of recourse do they have well
turning it off isn't exactly the right
answer but certainly limiting access to
to the harasser certainly does now
that's that is a total key part of of
limiting harassment but it's also about
limiting people's access to to getting
people's locations as well so the second
law is pretty you know pretty
self-explanatory I and so you have this
and then you have the digital identity
systems must be designed so disclose
identify is limited and only justify a
justifiable place given a relationship
now these to the previous law in this
law kind of work together thats the
users data only must be exposed in the
smallest amounts of the smallest number
of devices within the users desire
that's it now number four is a really
huge kind of law and I don't expect
everyone to read all of this but
basically the users ID of the users ID
that you're giving out must not
necessarily be their true name but just
something that represents who they are
for immediate purpose only not to keep
it out there in perpetuity and then of
course you also must keep it open that
other people can use other providers for
your particular application now the
sixth law is once again rather long but
what this really means is that it has to
be understandable to humans well I don't
think that's very possible so we'll just
keep on moving the seventh law is is
that we will use our technology to
enable itself and the community to use
the identities that will be separate
from all other identities so hopefully
basically will convince others that we
are we are providing an identity system
that other people will start to to to
buy into so you might ask yourself you
know is this all this privacy a bunch of
nonsense am i full of crap up here
possibly i but there are a lot of people
that still say if you've gotten nothing
to HOD nothing to hide then you've got
nothing to fear that's one of the most
ridiculous statements I've ever heard is
because why don't you just give me your
email password your slack github and and
everything else and i'll just post it to
your employer to your to your insurers
and everyone else still have nothing to
hide
I don't think so but you also might say
well our phones themselves broadcast a
lot of information what are they
broadcast well they broadcast not only a
self cell phone number but also the
equipment ID that it has and your
subscriber number based upon who you're
using so how do you actually minimize a
lot of that well when we're talking in
privacy terms we're saying first do no
harm make them more no more vulnerable
than they already were so it's my belief
that a lot of these addresses that we
have right now are kind of you know
permanent but I think that they can be
random in the future and there's no
reason why they shouldn't be now when it
comes to owning your own data I think
it's really really key is the fact that
now we have a way of of talking to one
another that we own our own data we are
not sending it to Facebook we're not
sending it to Twitter we can send it
back and forth and keep the ownership of
our of the data by ourselves what kind
of implications does that have well for
example if you have something like this
around your house where each of the your
things are emitting data well you can
start to collect it on your phone and
then you can decide whether you send
that data off to somebody else so what
we came up with was called the tally
project and that was these to serve as
the basis of what we're building here
and that's it and it's a Indian and
nepalese term and it's basically four
plates and usually what the it's a plate
of various different things such as as
holding six flavors of sweet salter
bitter astringent and spicy now we feel
that the ideas behind all of that become
very very interesting especially as as
we start to think about privacy I access
control and so forth each of those are
little dishes in the big thing so let's
actually show you enough of my my
blathering on my soapbox yes i will type
in my password
is 1234 don't judge me ah and so what we
have here is we have we have a device
here our Nexus 6 who would have guessed
a microsoft guy would have a nexus but
here is and we have a nexus 9 tablet I
think all right and so we what we can do
is we can start to send messages back
and forth so for example I can type in
je s comp here and sure enough as
immediately showed up right here and and
how is that possible because if you can
see right there there is no sim card in
here nor am I connected to any Wi-Fi the
only thing that I that I have running
right here is is Bluetooth right now so
how it works is is that it actually uses
Wi-Fi direct for discovery purposes and
then it uses Bluetooth to do the data
syncing and why let's actually go
through a little bit of that of how we
actually built it so what we thought is
is well gee this could be a bunch of
Lego blocks that we can just put
together and why I'm here is because
well you always bet on Jas because well
everybody does right that's what
everybody builds their solutions on so
we might as well follow suit but just as
well thinking about it your phone here
is more powerful than servers that you
would buy 10 years ago it has so much
capability and so much storage that why
wouldn't you use it as a server in fact
companies such as uber and others are
already doing just that to offload a lot
of computation and a lot of storage
directly off onto your phone so we
really want to be able to to take full
advantage of everything from down to the
encryption stack to all the way
communicating its with the the Bluetooth
and Wi-Fi directly in node but note
itself doesn't exactly do that so
unfortunately since note is tied
directly to to VA
we want instead to run on every device
and JX core which is a kind of a forked
from from New bisa allows you to do just
that it has a number of additional
features that regular node doesn't have
such a shared memory concurrency and so
forth but but the the biggest part is
the fact that you can swap out which
which particular JavaScript engine that
you happen to be using and why that's
important is because now if you go to
iTunes or if you go to Google Play guess
what you can start shipping these kinds
of node apps today they have they have
right here the the Wi-Fi shopping list
and this is from the from the J explore
folks on how you can just share with
share with your friends I a shopping
list over Wi-Fi so like I said you have
all of this capability right in the palm
of your hands already today now how did
we actually deploy it well thanks to
Brian larousse liver and himself we have
Apache Cordova which allows us to
basically use it as a packaging
mechanism for us to deliver deliver the
data as we need to but it's not that
we're actually using any of the api's
we're actually writing all of our all of
our stuff as as node modules there's no
real cordova magic happening here and
when I was showing you the the post card
app that we have here which by the way
if you go to github.com / thali project
/ post card app you can actually run
this yourself what's what's neat about
this and even though the thereof I was
showing you just you know how
instantaneously this was going between
this devices you have to think it's
actually going through node and it's
going through pouch DB to synchronize
with one another but yet it's blazingly
fast and that's really cool too
see and really it's about enabling
communication so what exactly are our
phones and tablets today well what are
they the radios there are any number of
radios whether it's Wi-Fi whether it's
Bluetooth it all has the same capability
in terms of communicating with one
another so why not be able to use those
things directly instead of having to to
use the the wife a public Wi-Fi or
something like that now for security
obviously if you're carrying the most
important parts about your your company
your most private details you obviously
wanted secure so for that we're using
tos and public keys so for each of us
when you install one of these apps will
get a public key and that will be used
for authentication and authorization
purposes and not only that but we
actually will deep down to the pouch DB
level enforce the enforce those ACLs now
a good question to ask especially when
you're doing identity exchange with with
a particular device such as this is how
do you get exchange IDs with one another
without absolutely hating yourself and
that was a really hard question for us
especially because originally right oh
yeah QR codes that's easy enough just
walk up to another device hold it up and
maybe they'll line up and and then we'll
have a complete identity exchange turns
out that wasn't really easy at all
because I it it's rather terrible
actually so what we came up with was an
idea using the coin flipping algorithm
so that we could exchange public keys
back and forth with one another and yes
there are there are attack vectors that
maybe a one-in-a-million chance that
you'll get a man-in-the-middle attack
but for the most part we are using these
keys in such a way that we only
advertise it when we're
do identity exchange with someone so
that's a very very small window and not
only that but it's it's a small window
and chances are if there's a
man-in-the-middle attack it just
wouldn't happen at the right time it
would have to be very very coordinated
so really what we want is we want
something that just easily says that I
give this to tracy has one and I have
one and I said ok my number is 123456
she says okay yes my number is also one
two three four five six let's go ahead
and and pair these devices together so
that's that it is probably the least
painful at way we could think about
doing security now when we're talking
about doing these devices because we're
talking about supporting this on both
iOS and Android right now so basically
you can go out you can download Holly
and you can run run it today but what's
what's really fascinating is is the nut
the sheer number of Android devices and
the sheer number sheer number of
versions of that we want to make sure
that every time we do a delivery that
we're not breaking something so this is
actually our CI environment here which
is love as you can see ton of phones
just all hooked up to a single server
and every time we do a github push sure
enough it hits against our CI server and
spits out the results as a gist so we
live and die by this now where are we
going in the future well that's a that's
kind of a hard question because we there
are a lot of ideas of where we're going
right now we're still kind of an
experimental platform for building these
pure apps but there are very very
concrete things that we want to do for
example we will want to do mesh
networking so for example if I want to
start to send data to the back of the
room I might not have range to do that
automatically what instead I would do is
I would send the data at halfway around
the room to someone
Alice and then send it via another
couple people until it finally reaches
its destination in the meantime it's
still encrypted at rest so you might see
a little file on your on your device but
you can't actually open it and the other
thing is is getting around on the
general internet so if we're available
on the general internet then we can use
something like tour for example to
completely hide your traffic using tor
hidden services not only to hide your
traffic but to also get around the rules
that most people have on their most
people have on their on their local
routers which is to not allow local
traffic to go back and forth so we can
get around all of that that we're also
investigating for example radio
whitespace Wi-Fi and allowing that to be
used as well and what that is is
basically it's using unused channels
within Wi-Fi and it's able to right now
we're working with microsoft research to
to enable for example indian villages to
talk to one another by using by setting
up these Wi-Fi beacons between the two
just using that white space that nobody
else uses right now so as I said this is
no more than what you saw here than just
an NPM module so all you really have to
do is type mjx using JX core NPM install
thali and you're ready to go now you can
also go and visit visit our sites at
tully project.org but together I think
we can make the the pier web grade again
so with that thank you very much