so you'll notice there's only one of me
unfortunately the Ben and Dion show I
can't make an appearance today Ben has
got I think h1n1 flu and we've been in
Europe for the past few days and he's
been like holed up in a in a hotel room
and finally it was just too crazy so he
had to fly back so I really apologize
that you get the kind of the worst half
of the deal today so if you want to get
your money back talk to those guys we
found it a Jackson we went to Mozilla
and worked on this Bespin thing that
motored she did amazing work on we had a
lot of fun doing that and we're going to
talk a little bit about kind of stuff
that we did with the best been there and
for the last month we've been working at
harm trying to kind of really push the
web through the mobile web space and
I'll kind of took a little bit about
that too but one quick kind of a side to
begin with you may have noticed recently
that Google like two days ago announced
closure that they took their tours and
finally open source am I used to work
for Google and this has taken quite a
few years and when I first got to Google
they're really good at shouting everyone
knows that but once you actually get
there the code bases in perforce and
it's like one massive repository which
is kind of strange but the side effect
is you can look at all the code so being
a JavaScript hacker i went to the gmail
source code and quickly ran away as fast
as possible after seeing it but they
used this closure library two of the
guys here of the three actually worked
on this eric Arvidsson who has been
doing this stuff for a very long time
and at dan poopy sr kind of the two guys
that started this effort off and i just
wanted to give you just a couple of
seconds a bit of information just to see
it because it's actually a series of
tools it's not just kind of like a
library that you're used to so this is
the library side of things and it looks
familiar too
dojo in the required provide kind of
stuff and it's a massive kitchen sink
just like dojo and they also did this
kind of thing which if you're kind of
from the java community way back in the
day we have this X doclet thing that did
this stuff until we got annotations in
the language and they've done kind of
the same thing where they add kind of
features to the world by annotated in
comments so if you really like right in
Java code for your JavaScript you've got
another option right here with closure
but they have these vast array of
libraries within the you can peek at and
it's really fun just to look around of
the code because they people have kind
of been finding out there's some of the
stuff that they've done it's just you
know it's really obviously stood the
test of time and the stuff like the key
binding support i think someone talked
about the internationalisation stuff
localization stuff is really interested
in it's just kind of cool to take a peek
in the source code not you're going to
run out and start using closure but
check it out now the library is one part
but they also have a compiler and the
compiler is available just through the
command line or you can use this web
service and it's really fun just to kind
of play around with it and put in your
code and do things like turn on this
advanced setting over here and it like
optimizes the hell out of things and it
looks at the annotations to do smart
things as it does that compilation so if
earlier on you did like this is a
constant it'll go through and inline
that code and stuff like that so there's
a whole suite of things that it gives
you and you can just put your own code
in here in it does a better job them the
yui compressor on some code sometimes it
breaks and doesn't even work but another
thing to going to check out now out wait
oops does anyone know who this guy is
this is Steve Souders who will be at the
show and originally I was scheduled to
talk after his talk so would have made a
little bit more sense by when I play a
little bit of a trick on him when he
starts his talk if everyone can just
start doing a little buzzed just like
just to going to get him there is a
reason why Steve is showing up this is
his halloween party where is a
pollinating his wife Carrie he's
performance techniques are actually
baked into that compiler so when you run
the compiler it actually does
performance tests on the flying gives
you interest in output so the stuff he's
talking about kind of shows up a little
bit here which is kind of fun there's
also some other really fun things that
he did there's Firebug extensions that
take care of some of the stuff that you
get that's messy so once you do you know
compilers and you get this you know
office cody code out then when you're
trying to debug that it's a pain or so
what they did they do a bunch of stuff
in the Firebug extension including
having this source mapping where you can
say here's my source of the original and
so instead of getting that there's an
error on line one because everything's
lined one it's one big line it'll map it
back to what's going on so it's just
kind of cool to see you like it's not
just a libraries this whole suite of
tools and I think there's some
interesting things to learn from here
not that you're going to obviously just
kind of run out and use closure anyway
that's the aside so I'm talking about
the future of the web whatever that
means and you know obviously kind of a
high-level topic we're going to talk
about a bunch of different things but
when i started with been a JAX ian at
the time we were given all these talks
on like how to build rich web
applications and hardly anyone was
showing up everyone was trying to
innovate on the server side and no one
cared about the client side and then
Jesse James coined the whole Ajax term
and then that was actually one day
before a server-side conference that the
we're out we did a search and replace on
our slides from d HTML to a Jackson like
it was a full house but it a lot of the
people here at this conference are kind
of responsible for going in getting all
these like hacks and quirks and little
ap is that the browser's had and it kind
of felt to me when when this stuff was
happening that we'd kind of like found
flight with Ajax we could build these
finally kind of rich applications on the
web but it was all
of a hack and it was all kind of pokey
and the runtime was really crappy but
it's amazing like we flew with would
like how did that happen and we kind of
did that the people in this room kind of
did that but it feels like now things
are changing and we finally get in these
amazing run times and new API is an
html5 and all of this stuff that's going
to enable us to get away from kind of
the crappy stuff that we had to deal
with and really kind of build some
disruptive applications in the future
and that's why I kind of at this time
I'm like amazingly excited much more so
than when the Ajax revolution kind of
you know hit to begin with what we have
available and it's kind of fun to look
at you know what's happened when you
look at what's happened to browsers out
there from the kind of clunky Netscape
let's put everything in a browser and do
your email and everything else to fire
bug where we kind of streamline things
and then to Chrome which kind of takes
it trying to take it to the extreme with
have the browser get out of the way the
browser's gotten simple are on the
outside as far as like my mom's
concerned it's the same thing as just
like a little bit less stuff but we will
know that the engine is drastically
changed underneath we've finally got
something that's kind of you know up to
the the class that we have with the JVM
and the CLR and things like that which
you enable us to really kind of do stuff
with that jet plane so Ajax used to mean
this when we did our first like Ajax
experience it was kind of a grassroots
thing just like this conference I think
these conferences like by far the most
exciting and all the talks are all about
like little things on top of this Ajax
thing and quickly we saw our whole slew
of libraries come out to like really
make it easy to do that kind of stuff
and give us a facts and interesting
things and then we kind of drew the
universe and now like once a week I get
a new email for like a new Ajax library
we've kind of nailed the remoting thing
at this point I think but as we look to
the horizon we're really seeing kind of
going way beyond have
this one little oh oops and think it's
been way too much time on on these
slides I apologize for that it's just
keynote and so fun yeah it's so easy and
when Ben and I kind of looked at the
horizon with like talking about all this
great html5 stuff and we're like well we
need to like really build something on
top of this and and see what we can what
we can really do and that's why Bespin
actually came about we wanted to going
to play around with all of the new
technology and we're geeks obviously so
you thought what's an application that
you wouldn't really think of to do on
the web and make it happen and so for us
it's a code editor that's what we live
in all the time if we could make
something that's kind of desktop class
desktop quality then that will say a lot
and so we we went about trying to do
this and we tried it actually a few
times and the platform wasn't ready the
first couple of times that we tried it
was just really clunky and really kind
of annoying and I didn't work for us but
it's only recently that we finally got
it to work and so if you haven't seen
this is Bespin web-based code editor and
this is all you know canvas doing the
rendering and we were able to like
really focus on the performance side
that's all we really focused on at first
was to be able to scale up because we
saw a bunch of different editors that
are out there on the web and we've all
been there little kind of web-based text
areas and once you get past you know a
few thousand lines it all just kind of
breaks down you got a million Dom nodes
and it's it's craziness and it was only
when we got to using canvas that we were
able to scale this thing up and we in
our prime we had this one session where
we had 50 thousand lines of code at 83
people simultaneously edited on it and
it hold up and that's what we were
really trying to do was be able to kind
of like prove that the web can do this
kind of stuff and best buds got a long
way to go but that's kind of the key
thing that was like okay I think that I
think that we're kind of there and it's
really exciting so the technology that
we use not to invest member that we're
particularly excited about with the web
right now is the graphic side obviously
with things like canvas
finally having a decent JavaScript
engine and a whole slew of them that
we're seeing going on right now in the
industry web workers and the notion to
finally be able to do background tasks
that don't just going to freeze the
browser and then also kind of breaking
through this Web sandbox and being able
to like access the underlying core
services on whatever device or laptop
you're on is all so exciting and then go
and beyond that to the world of mobile
which we're obviously excited about with
a new position okay so we're able to do
stuff like gmail with primitives like
text little divs and images and that's
it and like you know how many posts have
I put up on a Jackson about how to best
do a rounded corner like it's crazy
right that we have to work in this world
where everything is a hack to do any
kind of thing that you want to do on a
UI world and again it's amazing that
we're able to do these great
applications with these primitives but
now we can go beyond that and we can do
cool things like this using canvas and
it's you know natively working with the
browser so this guy in here is just like
images that we can do things with and
rotate and do interesting experiences we
can do real-time physics within our
application and then of course we can
have gratuitous games and finally we can
do whatever we need in our particular
experience so we can have a really
immersive experience kind of for the
first time and when you take that
further and you marry it with other
things that we get in like video this is
an example from the Mozilla guys in
France where a video is playing they're
capturing the frames there do an
analysis to find the the white lights
that are coming out of their iPhones and
then they're real time putting in
different elements which can be videos
their own canvas little games and things
on the fly this is kind of like holy
crap like the web can actually do this
stuff now in real time like this is
pretty amazing like we haven't really
kind of taken use of a lot of the stuff
and again because canvas is native to
the web
it allows us to really tie into all of
the other technology that we have
available which which i think is
incredibly excited so we've been able to
do this with flash and now Silverlight
so you know what's the big deal well
there's a few things that make canvas a
little bit different startup did that
delay is one of those things like with
best one we really didn't want to have
the kind of loading situation where you
have to wait there for a little bit and
we're able to do that because
everything's already booted up it's just
using the browser pipeline then there's
also the ability that you can use this
on mobile devices right now a whole
bunch of them support canvas so you can
start doing these kind of rich things on
mobile devices you have rendering
fidelity with the browser and if Ben
were here he's like particularly I you
know about this stuff he can like look
at any fun and know everything about the
aliasing and what's going on and all
that kind of stuff and so it like really
bugs him when he's working with a flash
application or something that just
doesn't look quite right and we probably
all kind of felt that in different areas
with flash and because canvas is just
using the browser to do the rendering it
really just kind of fits in and the text
looks Ryan and everything just kind of
fits in nicely and there's no bridges so
if you want to talk through you know
there's a lot of things that we've done
where we kind of bridge over to flash
and then get things back and that's
great but we don't need that because
we're just using the JavaScript engine
itself to power the graphics ability and
and it's not a plug-in so we don't have
the separate life cycle and the secre
separate beast that we have to worry
about it's just built in so fact canvas
is gray it's just a way to have this
kind of immediate mode API to draw
things to the page but then we get these
guys who come along that kind of rant at
us at about like oh this canvas element
it's like I go into my Firebug explorer
and it's just canvas and I can't see
what's in there this just isn't the web
it should be all damn it should be
really easy for me to go in and kind of
peek at it and for that we have you know
SVG which does have its own Dom when all
these things and you know has been
problems with SVG it kind of came out of
that
XML world an XHTML and there's been a
lot of issues with what that means just
kind of getting it working with with
HTML but we're finally getting past that
and Brad Neuberg of google has recently
released this thing SVG web which allows
it to also run on ie using flash as a
bridge to actually rendering what's
going on so if you're one of those kind
of purist that likes having a world
where you have a DOM and there's things
that are a lot nicer about it you don't
have to roll your own eventing and
things like that then SVG is definitely
becoming more of an option we're
obviously more canvas guys getting fonts
you know Jonathan Snoke gave a talk
frontiers and amsterdam all about fonts
and the power of typography and what we
can do and finally on the web we can
actually do really rich fonts and really
kind of take the experience into our own
hands and it's kind of ugly right now
there's all these different warring
formats and stuff going on that we used
to in kind of dealing with browsers but
it's really exciting that we can play
around with this stuff and there are
sites out there and tools like type get
that are really kind of helping us get
over the cross browser nonsense where we
can just slap in a bit of JavaScript and
get the fun that we want to deliver the
experience we want without having to use
like a flash wrapper or something to
give us that particular phone using
Sephirah or coupon or what have you okay
so we've got these like amazing graphics
abilities new fonts really cool stuff
but none of this would really be
possible with the engines themselves
hadn't radically changed like we've been
living with these you know crappy VMs
for a long time little interpreters
running our code and in that gmail
codebase that I ran away screaming from
like fifty percent of the code was
trying to get it to port perform well in
certain browsers and it's just not the
fun stuff that we as web developers want
to be working on we want to be adding
cool features and delivering great user
experiences but you know at the same
time roughly Brendan Eich of Mozilla
when and kind of found his academic
peers mainly
on the East Coast and took the
actionscript vm from Adobe and built
trace monkey this trace Bates ginning
platform that allows you to really on
the real time observe the code and
compile paths that you're using
repeatedly into native code and we get
amazing performance improvements from
that and then Google went and grabbed
Lars from from Denmark and had him kind
of come out and he built the small talk
vm he built the hot spot in Java and
he's kind of done it again in the
JavaScript world and what's excited
about this is it's not just like twice
as fast and so it's exponentially faster
and stephen levi who writes for wired
and other things when he first started
playing around with chrome and seeing
this v8 stuff he just suddenly kind of
you know realized when something gets
redone exponentially faster it's not
just different it enables new things to
happen and we're seeing that I think
with with being able to have this core
engine and they've only just begun right
like there's tons of stuff that they're
doing and this is just kind of the
waters rising for all of us to like
really be able to do the things that we
want to be doing one little thing that
that's kind of interest in under the
scenes is the the whole world of memory
management javascript is traditionally
just been mark and sweep and so you see
this in your application law if you're
like running little JavaScript game and
things just kind of pause now and then
right it's pausing because it's doing GC
and it has to go through the entire
memory set to go through and kind of
deallocate what's going on in the memory
well v8 finally introduced generational
garbage collection which you know other
platforms like Java have had in a long
time where you have kind of the young
generation here of new objects which we
found you know eighty percent of the
objects that we create things like in a
for loop that we can reclaim quickly and
there's only a few objects that kind of
live around later and so instead of
having to go through the entire memory
space we can go along clean up what's
going on in the new space and then come
along later
move things that have kind of been
hanging around for awhile and so this
will finally help us get rid of these
pauses that we see in our applications
when we build them on the web runtime so
we're really excited about that too then
there's new things that are out there
like VA has this notion of snapshots and
just like really really wicked cool
stuff that's going on on the low level
that again it's just kind of a general
enabler but then we have this question
and it's easy to kind of make fun of
these guys and it's kind of fun too but
the good news is that recently tons of
different Microsoft people have kind of
been coming up to us sometimes like oh
don't tell anyone this but you can
imagine we're working on this really
cool new JavaScript vm and we see them
kind of coming out and helping with the
canvas spec we're so far helping means
taking it out of html5 but hopefully
they're actually going to implement
canvas and things like that and we
actually think they're going to do this
this time so hopefully an IE 9 will
start to get this stuff so 15 years from
now we'll be able to actually use these
technologies so we've got this really
fast JavaScript which is great but
there's always going to be something
that you do computationally that's going
to take longer than point one second and
therefore our users going to notice it
so here's pics tastic which is like a
little kind of photoshop thing and what
we're going to do is desaturate this
image over here and notice it's kind of
freezing the entire browser and it's
going to go long enough because it takes
five seconds to give us the script
warning and it doesn't matter how fast
the javascript is there's always going
to be things that take this long and so
you know this is obviously a horrendous
experience for our users and we need to
get beyond that so what we'd normally do
in kind of the desktop world is we'd
have a background thread that actually
does the desaturation but we don't have
threads in JavaScript and we're not
going to get them because Brendan Eich
you know did this whole big post about
our you know thread sock and we have
people like Doug Crockford who don't
want any innovation to happen at all I'm
just just it's just kidding so we're not
going to get new features no we're not
going to get threads but we actually
something that you know arguably is is
better with workers because with workers
you don't have all of the issues that
you have with threads with shared stayed
and just all of the pain that we have to
do when we work with threads and I've
worked with you know genius software
programmers that still always get the
threading stuff wrong and it's just like
incredibly painful to actually get this
stuff right and so I'm excited that
we've actually taken a different
approach to get stuff working with with
web workers to enable us to do this so
here's you know a little example of what
happens when you start using web workers
when this guy spins the Firefox icon
that means that the browser is
responsive and we're going to do a
little annealing calculation at ups the
browser is already frozen and it's going
to calculate the fastest path between
all these points and at this point like
the entire browser is just frozen for
the user and we have to wait for a few
seconds for it to be done and then the
browser comes back again that's
obviously not very good when you do it
with with workers though that's not the
case because it's going to do all of
that calculations in this background
process so it's going to send a message
over to a worker that's running
somewhere else is going to do the
calculation then it's going to speak
back to the main browser thread and it's
going to say okay here you go so now
with workers we can like all of our
mouse overs are still working
everything's totally responsive and then
we get the results so we have the
JavaScript execution speed and now we
have the beginnings of the ability to
actually do and you know things off of
the main UI thread which are enable us
to deliver these great experiences and
we used this stuff actually motor did
the work for this to have things like
the syntax engine investment run off of
the main UI thread because you don't
want to like freeze someone typing as
you're doing the syntax calculations and
if you're doing code completion you
don't want to like hit period and then
start to type in the browser freezes
while it works out the completions you
want to push that off into a background
worker where this actually came from is
related to the database stuff that we
have on the web when the gmail guys were
trying to do gmail offline
kind of through the guise of gears the
problem we had was whenever we're doing
anything with the database from gmail
the browser would freeze because that UI
thread of the browser was locked talking
to the database and so at first they
could just kind of like do a little hack
and make all the database access work on
a different process a different thread
but that didn't scale to other problems
and that's where kind of web workers
were born as this worker poor API or
it's like let's give developers the
ability to do that somewhere else we
have you know this offline storage now
which you need for the client-side
applications and once again though we're
in this kind of well weird little fight
where a bunch of the browser supports
equal but other people like Mozilla
really don't believe sequels the right
answer for local storage on the web it
doesn't feel webby enough for them they
prefer kind of the couchdb kind of model
but beyond that kind of you know kind of
almost religious debate there's also the
issue of what does it mean to say that
its sequel ian Hickson when you know it
kind of seemed like the sequel stuff was
going on was literally going to go
through sequel liar and standardize
that's dialect of sequel and so we're
basically binding everyone to use sequel
line but I II can't use sequel light and
you know opera can't use sequel light so
it's really a bit of a predicament so
hopefully we'll see some other things
kind of take off there now the GPU
hasn't been really available to us
through the web platform before
everything's being kind of software and
but we're seeing us being able to kind
of wire into the GPU in interesting ways
and again this is another kind of
technology that we need to be able to
enable really interest in applications
one way of doing this we're seeing is
with WebGL where we can just take kind
of the opengl world and now in firefox
and in WebKit nightlies ending in chrome
nightlies to you can actually start
having these really rich experiences
which is fantastic to see and we have
the o3d stuff from google
is kind of another take which is a kind
of higher level API and we can do
amazing things like this it's fantastic
look at that experience but teapots even
but the problem is that web hackers you
know a lot of them don't think in this
OpenGL kind of world so it's it's kind
of tough to say like here's how you
could a really rich experience go learn
OpenGL kind of a dialect is not really
what we want to do luckily apples really
stepped up here and there deliver in
these GPU accelerated 3d things just
through CSS and so you get a lot of
benefits out of this you get this
rotating cube here but you can then do
text selection and it all just kind of
works it's all like built into what's
going on and it's all hardware
accelerated for you and you don't have
to think about it it's just declarative
and if you take something a little bit
more fancy this is just a hole like
sedatives and you can do immersive
experiences like this without having to
do much at all this is just all CSS
transforms and it appears Lakhia on the
screen here than it actually is because
of the video that we're taking if you
actually kind of play with it you know
it feels like it feels like you're
really kind of immersed in this
experience and it's pretty trivial to be
able to deliver this stuff now so we've
got amazing rich things coming the
Mozilla team is working on CSS
transforms I'm sure other people are too
and it's really excited to see how we
can just declaratively do amazing things
like this and also push it through with
with javascript to so we're able to do
amazing graphic stuff we've got
applications like this really rich
applications but as soon as you start
working in this world you want to kind
of break through from these applications
so you're working with your email app
you really like to be able to tie into
your address book or something for
example and we're not able to do that
traditionally through the web because
the web gives us this kind of sandbox
world which makes sense on the security
side but it doesn't help on the
functionality side luckily we've got
some kind of technologies that can help
us do some of this stuff fluid in prism
two technologies that
allow us to kind of take our apps and
kind of bless them and have them run and
kind of like their own shell and you
have to do things prism is you know
cross-platform fluid is Mac only and you
can then kind of put user scripts in
there so in the gmail world I can plug
in a user script that says now when I
get an email to a little growl
notification for me and like really
customized stuff that is really quite
cool but it's the kind of stuff that we
would use but it's not the kind of stuff
like my mom's going to use and then
another approach is air and titanium
which enable you to just take your web
skills and build desktop applications
and that's interesting too but what I'm
like more excited about beyond this
stuff is we're actually seen the
browsers kind of take on this challenge
so Mozilla's been spending a lot of time
thinking about what it means to have a
really rich trust model using something
like Jack pack to kind of give you the
extensibility and then kind of layering
on you know technical security on top of
that and then social trust networks on
top of that even so my mom can see odeon
uses this little plugin so I'll trust
him and i'll use it to and give me
enhanced abilities chrome has the notion
that is playing with called app tabs
which allows you to take your gmail tab
and kind of bless it and say I want
gmail to do more things and it just kind
of pins it in and allows you to do
richer things for those particular users
so I'm excited to see his kind of
breakthrough that sandbox and that's one
of the reasons that Ben and I joined
palm is that that's exactly what they
did when we saw webOS kind of showing
off at CES last year when they got up
and said like the phone is just like the
platform is the web it made a lot of
sense to us and a lot of people come up
to us and we just had an event in London
kind of talking about mobile web stuff
and they're like yeah it's great that
you can like build your app using the
web but surely your native apps like
your mail app calendar SMS that's not
built on the web right use native stuff
in that and it's not at all the whole
proof point of the webos stuff was all
of the apps in there are just web apps
and in fact we make the source code
available to you guys so you can even
take a look at the mail app and see what
it's like what's it like touchy write an
application like that and then they had
to put in a bunch of device a
is that we have to use to get access to
the native world and so this is kind of
one thing on the mobile side where it's
going to pushing through and break-in
through the sandbox to give us really
rick trunks out functionality does
anyone know this guy is not a me it's
dave thomas not the Wendy's guy in the
US but a guy writes some Ruby code he
always says on panels I like my name is
Tia now mayor and I manage at Ajax guy
he's as my name is dave thomas i'm a
program and that's what ever says but he
runs the pragmatic book series and ben
and i wrote a no fluff just stuff
symposium tour and someone asked this
panel that we're on you know what's the
future of software and this is the time
where flex had just come out Adobe AIR
was just being kind of banded around
called Apollo and the WPF staff from
Microsoft and so Ben got up and gave
this like rousing speech about rich
internet applications and immersive
experiences and all these great graphics
and then they've got up and he just took
his phone that he had at the time and
put it in the air and said this is the
future of software and Ben started to
argue with him about like look at this
crappy screen is like a green screen
like how is this the future we've got
these amazing graphics abilities on the
desktop like this is in the future of
software but we're finding that you know
they're both kind of right and the
mobile experiences stuff is really taken
off and it makes sense we've gone from
the world of you know the PDA to the
smartphone and finally with the iphone
we realize that we've actually just got
computers in our pockets that also
happen to be able to make phone calls
sometimes badly but it's like finally I
have the hitchhiker's guide to the
galaxy I've got a three year old boy
that asked me questions and I can kind
of get on the web and ping Wikipedia and
tell them what it is like it's amazing
what we have available and it's just
really exciting because now we've got
things you know that are really small
that we have this whole world of devices
out there and we're only limited to our
imagination on the forum
act like we're going to see watches that
are these devices are we're going to see
my classes will be able to do this stuff
like it's it's not far out there and I
get really excited about it but then I
also get really worried when I look at
all of these boxes and I see that every
one of these is like a different
proprietary API that I have to learn and
sometimes it's like this weird sea
dialect just after the disaster further
but you know what would the world be
like if if we could unify that and it
was kind of fun to think about like most
of these devices have this little guy in
it with WebKit that just kind of snuck
out of K HTML and in Safari that has you
know a pretty small share but a decent
share but now it's like everywhere in
mobile devices like it's amazing the web
is already there you can do great
experiences on the web across these
different things and then we obviously
upon kind of tried to take that to the
next level to make it the way to to
build native apps and so the reason that
we really went to Palm was to see if we
can make the web the unifying platform
for all of these things can we get to a
world where we take web technology and
we can deploy it to a whole slew of
devices that are coming out there like
right now we think of the mobile web as
being you know 320 by whatever on an
iphone screen but that whole world is
changing right it's I know that I'm
going to sit in my car my phone's going
to talk to the little nav screen and
display my email like I can't wait for
this stuff is really exciting about how
do we deliver these applications and so
we think that the web is going to be
able to deliver that and that's not just
about Palm webOS it's about a whole slew
of other really exciting technologies
you know Brian's here going to be
talking about phonegap being able to
take your web skills and deploy it
across a whole slew of devices that are
out there and titanium mobile has got a
set of tools a different de phonegap but
are interested in their own route and so
I'm excited at palms are going to work
together with the whole web community to
build the web platform as the way to
deliver these experiences we don't want
to have like a palm specific proprietary
API we want it to just be the web
okay a little segue these conferences we
get excited about the engine I get
excited about all the new cool
JavaScript API is and what's coming with
html5 and finally we have api is that
are aimed at building web apps and not
web documents and websites but it's not
really the engine that that matters and
I have to keep remembering it it's
actually the experience that really
matters and we kind of see this in a car
i remember when Ben and I first saw this
ad I don't think Benny ever knew what an
Aston Martin was before he saw this
that's just watch this resented
so I'm not even a car guy which is
heresy in Germany I know but like I want
to buy that car now or like that looks
really fun i think i would have a good
time in that car even if it's not a
German car but that's what matters like
you know if I put my foot down to the
floor like it may not be as fast as some
other car but you know a lot of the the
unkind of Motorhead's don't care about
that stuff and so we're seeing a
dramatic change that we only probably
just saw when we went from this world
where everything was just kind of you
know simple screens like this and this
is kind of like the web one point o
world or what have you to now with the
html5 world with Rick's experiences but
the problem is that the complexity is
totally changed like the web used to be
really ugly and crappy which was great
for me because I'm not a graphics guy so
I could build things equal equally
crappy and ugly but everything's changed
you've got all this WebGL and all this
cool stuff now the bar is being raised
and the complexity like building
something even like a rich client you
have to think about things you just
didn't have to think about with a
typical kind of terminal screens and one
thing we have to really kind of spend
time on is is kind of the craftsmanship
side of things this guy Alan Cooper
wrote out a whole book kind of talking
about craftsmanship and kind of going
against something that joel joel on
software talked about to do with like
hey if you're in IT like you don't have
time to be a craftsman and kind of
debunk that but he also said it's our
duty to really be craftsmen as we build
in our case these really rich
applications and one example that Ben
and I saw recently was just when the new
version of Firefox 35 came out we
watched the UX team kind of iterate on
it and like how can you like make this
better like Firefox as an icon everyone
knows you're not going to change it and
we just watched him like slowly
iterating through this icon like I'd be
like that's good enough like that's fine
no they keep going keep making subtle
changes they're like arguing about
what's better this than the other which
part of the world is it show
we don't want to show one place and make
it seem like that place is better than
somewhere else they just keep going keep
going and that's what they end up with
and it's like wow this is like crosman
ship you need to keep iterating and like
building your craft and building great
products and that delivers these amazing
experiences and this brings us to kind
of what's happening a lot to do with the
fact that when the bar raises
expectations totally change and we saw
this comedian and do a little bit that
really hit home for us as we see these
expectations so we're going to just kind
of play this for you for a sec
everything is amazing right now and
nobody's happy like in my lifetime the
changes in the world have been
incredible when I was a kid we had a
rotary phone we had a phone they get to
stand next to and you have to dial it
yes you know you realize how primitive
you're making sparks in a phone and you
actually would hate people with zeros
and their numbers because it was more
got 20 screw that guy yeah and then if
they called it you weren't home the
phone would just ring lonely by itself
and then with you wanted money you had
to go in the bank for when it was open
for like three hours it is stay in line
raise up a check like an idiot and then
when you ran out of money you just go
well I can't do any more things now hey
I can't do any more that's it yeah that
was it and even if you had a credit card
they died go oh let me bring out this
whole chunk chunk Anita right yeah uh do
you have to call the president
it's all things you had to call the
president yeah it was ridiculous yes do
you feel that we now in the 21st century
we take technology for grant well yeah
cuz now we live in an amazing amazing
world and it's wasted on the on the
crappiest generation of just spoiled
idiots that don't care because this is
what people like now they got their
phone like uh it won't give it a second
it's going to space can you give it a
second to get back from space is the
speed I was on I was on an airplane and
there was internet high speed internet
on the airplane that's the newest thing
that I know exists and I'm sitting on
the plane and they go open up your
laptop you can go on the internet it's
fast and i'm watching youtube clips it's
am in an airplane and then it breaks
down and they apologize the Internet's
not working the guy next to me dos
boobies both
like how quickly the world owes him
something yes he knew existed only 10
seconds ago lying is the worst one
because people come back from flights
and they tell you their story and it's
like a horror story it's they act like
their flight was like a cattle car in
the 40s in Germany that's how bad they
make it sound right there like it was
the worst day of my life first of all we
didn't board for 20 minutes and then we
get on the plane and they made a sit
there on the runway for 40 minutes we
had to sit there oh really what happened
next did you fly through the air
incredibly like a bird did you partake
in the miracle of human flight unite
contributing zero this really hits home
it's like you suddenly realize that crap
like first of all I keep complaining
about flight so I won't do that anymore
and secondly like once expectations
change you look at the old thing and
it's like what and we see this in our
industry in like games like this was
cool this was amazing I've got a paddle
when it can like play this game but now
we expect this and like kids are today
playing this and be like you kidding me
like that's crazy i want immersive
applications that look beautiful 24-7
with like all my friends it can do great
things like expectations change and that
happens on the web as soon as Google
Maps came out you go to mapquest and be
there Mac OS like that sucks you mean I
hit up and has to reload the page that's
crazy that's so bad and I think we're
about to see kind of a similar shift as
we get all these really cool html5 apps
that do love these really rich things
again the things that today people used
to and think are okay they're suddenly
going to seem really really primitive
and so I think that's where I'm Kylie oh
man I I need to like start doing this
other stuff otherwise I'm going to be a
dinosaur now kind of how sexy and how
cool things look actually makes a
difference and here's an experiment are
there any ladies in this a geek
France there any women there's a few
good any other ladies out they would
like to go out with this guy is kind of
a bit of a kind of dough boy a guy bit
like myself anyone would like to have
coffee of this game no one how about
this guy ah so I smile over there that's
good they're the same guy it's jared
leto an actor that put on this wait for
a part and what's funny is that while
the implementation is the same the
interface is totally different perfect
he's a nice guy in both of these but
like we react very differently to how
we'd want to interact with one of these
interfaces over another so there's the
universal truths that some of the
psychologists talk about we talk a lot
about like getting to know users and how
they want to use stuff but there's a few
uniform truths one is sex sells and we
see that obviously in the media and
movies and stuff and one little fun
example we got the stats on the
Transformers movies so this is the
original one that came out kind of the
height of when like all the kids we all
had transformers and the cartoon was our
and everyone loved it and opening
weekend it buddy do million million in
1.7 million that's pretty good but then
the new one came out and 70 you know
just a little bit better even if you
take into account inflation and then you
know there was a particular part of the
movie that I think drew a certain group
and Hollywood work that out so the next
one and 108 million and if you saw the
movie it's kind of awful and was just an
excuse to get her on screen and so how
things look actually matter and that
that kind of goes through the software
too even though it could be kind of
weird so there was a study that was done
all about different UI elements like
like buttons and over here we've got
like these two buttons and it's it's
weird to look at these and be like one
of these is better than the other one
but you could kind of look at this and
be like hey that doesn't even really
look like a button so i could see how
people may just think it's just got a
border and stuff but what if you put
something that everyone
knows as a button well it turns out that
people really didn't like these
interfaces and people enjoyed using the
other interfaces a lot more even though
they were the same and there was a study
that Don Norman I believe did where he
took an ATM system and had exactly the
same interaction one of the systems was
just kind of the usual like black screen
with green writing and the other one was
like a rich application and they made
sure the interactions at the same time
and everything else and at the end of
the study everyone like thought the one
that had the pretty stuff was so much
better even though the interaction was
the same there's another study that is
even scarier that talks about how people
react to different things in this case
phases where they took a whole slew of
people and they took all of like the
Senate races that happen in the US and
people had to predict who won the race
just on looking at two people who were
running against each other and everyone
instantly kind of picked the
better-looking person and that was a 71
percent indicator that that person
actually won and they studied that like
within like the first half a second
people were making this judgment and
that's the same indicator as if they're
already in office like it's crazy that
they'd look at people be like that guy's
more capable and the funniest part of
this was at the end of the report just
to make sure you know people like to sue
each other in the US they said
unfortunately no good evidence suggests
the inferences drawn from a person's
facial appearance can predict character
or skills so they had to put a
disclaimer sand the good looking guys
aren't necessarily better their job just
kind of bizarre but there's a thing this
is called the halo effect and we see
that on the web and another study done
in the University of Ontario would take
different websites here's an example and
again within like half a second people
would make assumptions based on this
website they were like look at this this
thing versus another one and they'd be
like is this a trustworthy business
would i give my credit card to these
guys are they competent and would
instantly make these judgments and it's
just kind of intrinsic to how is you do
stuff in our brains so this stuff really
really matters
and to hammer it home again is a little
case study that's fun does anyone use
delicious library on the mac does anyone
use that few people over there so
delicious library this is the first
version so the latest one it does a lot
more but the first version that came out
as this application that allows you to
take your DVDs and books and you can
kind of put in the information it gives
you this like virtual deck that you
could look at and when I first saw this
is I oh this is cool like maybe I could
like double click on the DVD and it
stopped playing it nope can't do that
maybe I could read the book click on the
book no can't do that I could literally
put in my information look at this or
look at my bookshelf unlike that was it
and the innovation was this feature here
was kind of cool at the time where you
could put the the code up to the webcam
and it would scan it and automatically
put in the information and you could
like drag a book to a friend and it
would say like you've loaned it to him
but that's it you could use Excel really
easily to do that you could use one of
the millions of like inventory systems
out there but he basically took
something made it look really nice had
amazing attention to detail and did it
matter well yeah he sold 500,000 in
three months yet this is literally his
car he bought this car and as a bit of
an ego so he blogged about buying this
car and a fifty four thousand dollars of
profit in the first day without doing
any advertising at all he literally took
something that had a little bit of use
not too much made it just beautiful to
use and people bought it I bought it and
I've used it like three times and it's
just like so nice to use you want to use
it this stuff actually really works and
that then bought him time to go ahead
and like innovate and add features and
stuff so this like directly really
really matters but I'm not trying to say
just like make put lipstick on a pig and
make it look better because that goes
wrong too
so remember the campaign it was all
about the WoW starts now and all this
kind of stuff it's not just about the
visual side of things you've got to get
the into the integration stuff worked
out well and jef raskin talks a lot
about this and i kind of shows you why
vista did so badly is like the
experience of the interaction just
poisons you and like we've all been
there we've been working with different
programs you get frustrated you want to
like throw the mouse out the window kind
of thing mr. did that all the time right
we're just like pop up are you sure you
want to click on that go away and so we
need to make sure that we obviously
don't poison our users and given
fantastic experiences so there's
actually kind of two sides to design
there's the visual staff which I'm never
going to be good at I just don't have
that feel that's just like a fashion and
we talked about that's importance but
then there's the interaction design
which is the geeky nerds like watching
exactly how people interact with things
and yakima nielsen talks about you know
one of the laws which is you have to
make sure every interaction there
directly manipulate in those objects if
you're able to do that the user's brain
can stay in the flow and they feel like
they're really enjoying that experience
and this again ties back to the fact
that now we can do that with web workers
and the javascript engines we can make
sure that we do this kind of stuff
whereas before you think about you know
even before ajax every different thing
you did record every a reload like that
would obviously be longer than that for
every every bit of time and there's a
little tool out there this on zai Jian
on Ben's I that allow you to kind of
play around with that just click on
these things and kind of see how you
feel when you're working with these
different kind of time lapses and you
really notice the difference you know
particularly around here been you know
thinks is a really high tuned individual
so he even knows the difference up here
but you really notice it really really
matters the other kind of thing that we
have to do is make sure that everything
a user does is sacred and so we see that
in different UI is with
you know saving stayed and restoring our
sessions now and getting rid of the
notion of actually saving something and
we all know how frustrating this is like
the web has this notion of sessions but
users don't care about it and it drives
me nuts when I go to something like a
travel side and I get a phone call and I
come back and says sorry all that stuff
you put in like got to do it again and
we run into this again and again and
again and so we have to make sure that
we actually do a better job and these
are just kind of two there's millions of
things we could talk about with
interaction design but if we make sure
that we do good on the responsiveness
which we can now do on the web and make
sure we really take good care of users
input we can get a long way so it feels
like when we first started to do browser
apps like nothing changed for like ten
years in the browser I was incredibly
frustrated in place for us as web
developers to try and innovate and
deliver great applications and then Ajax
came along which made the winter a
little bit nicer to live with the
browser still weren't really helping us
but now we've got all of these fantastic
technologies that all these great you
know speakers are going to be talking
around you guys are going to be using
though enable us to finally deliver
these expectations that are going to
take us to the next level and they're
just going to make the web amazing and
make people's lives actually a lot
better and so you know the web has a ton
of stuff going for it right now I'm
incredibly excited about where we're
going and most importantly you've got
job security on your side because
there's a TV show in the US that's a
sci-fi show and if you zoom into the
user experience of the the show this is
in like 2500 they use JavaScript so make
sure you keep your JavaScript skills and
i'll see you at a jazz conf in the