you
so I named my top government j/s but it
won't be political so don't fall asleep
or leave you can fall asleep because
it's super comfy in here but that being
said hopefully I can challenge your
perceptions of what a political party
can look like and if you want to there's
a lot of links in this talk so the
slides are online for clicky stuff
because I might move past the slide
before you have time to click on things
so you can go to the github to see the
slides so last year I are about two
years ago I quit my job I was working at
a market research company and it was
kind of how you would expect working in
a market research company would be not
the most exciting place in the world and
I got offered to go and move to the bay
area and work for this place called Code
for America I'm from America my
affiliation with that country is that i
was born in it and it's it's an okay
place however i was given the
opportunity to go work with the city of
Boston through this program and Code for
America basically the way it works it's
like Peace Corps but for nerds and you
work with cities so the idea is you put
these people who would never be hired by
a city government into city government
somehow and they do crazy things for a
year and it's a fellowship so you get to
kind of dink around and try to do
something interesting and so uh this is
one of my favorite photos of me because
the entire time I was there as told I
supposed to wear a tie but nobody really
knew that I wasn't because I could hide
it pretty well and the mayor of Boston
he's in his fifth term now Thomas M
Menino he's such an awesome guy he he is
just a really funny character and this
is less in City Hall and it was a great
time I heard later that people would
like there was like this murmur
throughout city hall that have you guys
seen the bearded guy in the elevator yet
this is crazy so like within the first
couple days the idea of culture change
like the whole point of Code for America
is to introduce culture change stay
introduce modern technology but also
culture change into a city and i think
it was working like through my beard
virus or whatever we also got featured
in governing and magazine a prestigious
publication and two of the guys that
work in Boston City Hall Chris and Nigel
they
do an amazing job of kind of there like
an innovation department inside of the
mayor's office it's a two-man department
and they basically just try to do the
coolest things that they could possibly
do to make the modern modern government
of reality so there they got quite a lot
of recognition and their departments
growing now so what I was basically
doing is trying to go inside the
government and work with it and fix it
and that's one class of strategies that
I want to talk about and I have a lot of
examples so where I worked it's now I
mean almost two years old I think it's
like one year eight months old they have
275 github repos everything that the
organization does is open source there's
too many projects to keep track of
frankly so what I've done is curated a
list of the the ones that have worked
particularly well but if you want to
check out what Code for America produces
you can go to their github but let me
just go through and as fast process as I
can some of the examples so you can get
a better idea of what I'm talking about
and I their motto is all open all the
time so you can totally talk to the
people who write the projects for kit
get involved what they really really
really want is if you live in a city to
take one of their projects and set it up
in your city and implement a solution
that somebody else built but get it into
your civic context wherever you live so
this is called route view let me refresh
and refuse in Honolulu it's a smartphone
app that you put in routing like in
Honolulu if you go from Honolulu to
waipahu it shows you a route and then
along the way it shows any government
owned cameras and it can give you
traffic conditions from your smartphone
instead of having to go to some horrible
government website flight status is in
New Orleans you put in a property that's
blighted which basically just means
abandoned or old or dirty there's a lot
of that in New Orleans after the
hurricane and you can have this
beautiful you I that shows you the
status of that property instead of
having to go and search through records
in a basement of City building somewhere
and this makes it really easy to figure
out like hey this
this is kind of like the timeline of
this property and here's when it's going
to get fixed or it's not going to get
fixed or was too cost-prohibitive we
have Honolulu answers which is basically
like ask jeeves remember ask jeeves like
it was the dream of the 90s and you
could like simplify computers by doing
like human style question asking turns
out doing that for the whole internet is
kind of crazy but doing it just for one
city government website is super awesome
and a huge UX win so Honolulu answers
you do things like you type in a box how
do i renew my driver's license and you
get back kind of stack overflow style a
bunch of other people that have asked
the same question and then an actual
workflow for how to figure out who do I
call what do i do what form do i fill
out so it simplifies interactions with
government I should also mention that
everything in this particular set of
demos were all Code for America projects
in the last year or two prepared Lee is
for disaster prevention you can
basically sign up it's I think it's in
Austin Texas you can sign up your
property and anytime that there's like a
fire in the property or maybe a
hurricane or tornado you get a text
message alert and other things you get
emails that help you prepare for a
natural disasters it's super important
we have neighbor how which is like a
wiki for doing things in your
neighborhood and kind of a citizen
driven like tactical urban activism it's
kind of crazy it's like a wiki for how
to go crazy and put a bunch of bike
racks inside of parking spaces and it's
a min a bunch of different communities
now local data is like a mapping tool
kit so that you can allow people to
crowdsource data really easily because
every app that crowdsources data right
so everything from scratch and it
doesn't work on certain phones or makes
a bunch of trade-offs local data is
trying to make it really easy to have
like a toolkit for just having citizens
report problems on their phone about a
place which is a ubiquitous problem in
government hacking texts in is cool it's
like you put up banners on bus stops or
anywhere that people can can see a phone
number in a city and you can give them
like a question like what would you
think of a new subway line coming along
this road text your answer here so it's
like a lightweight text message the
right tool that's easy enough for city
officials to use this is one that I
worked on last
discover bps it's like I like to think
of it as like Airbnb but for parents to
find schools for their kids so Boston
has this insane list of requirements
it's like a 27-page PDF and it basically
is way too much information for all
parents in Boston to read it talks about
you have to live in this neighborhood
within a certain radius of this school
to go to this one and if you went to
this school last year you can't go to
the school over here and did this school
has this after-school programs what you
have to qualify with blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah so we made it
into like a web app that's really easy
to use and it's being used by the school
district now this is another one that I
worked on which is real-time bus data I
will fight the nature God's they're
trying to they're trying to stop they're
trying to stop these ideas from being
spread um it's basically like there was
a big snowstorm in Boston the week that
I got there februari 2010 for 2011 and
some of the school buses got to the
schools that like 11 p.m. at night they
left at four pm and they got home at
11pm because there was so much snow on
the freeways get that the school buses
were just stuck in traffic for like six
hours and parents were calling like
crazy where are my kids and it was 11pm
when they finally got home so we made
this app so that parents could log in
with their school account and actually
see where the bus is on a smartphone who
cannot hear me everybody can hear me all
right I can put the mic closer to my
mouth it was awesome we're going to
bring it down um there are new this is
actually powered by JavaScript there's
this company matte box that does tile
rendering in a streaming fashion and so
my girlfriend Jessica actually works at
Code for America this year and she made
this map of the city of Macon Georgia is
transit infrastructure and she styled it
made it modern made it work on mobile
smartphone browsers and then this the
city actually up streamed it and
embedded it in their website and
previously they had a flash applet that
lets you zoom into a PDF Oh God
let me save the venue really quick
here's I'm just going to keep rolling
with it here's a budget visualization
tool kit called see penny work and it's
the cool thing about this is that it's
super simple so city employees are
overworked and they don't have time to
learn web frameworks so what you do is
you sign up for a free wordpress account
and a Google Doc you put your budget
spreadsheet into the google doc and plug
the google doc ID into the wordpress
site and you get this it's like a budget
toolkit so it's being used in the city
of Macon Georgia to visualize to the
public a bond referendum basically
people take another penny off of every
purchase and get a fun parks and they
fund new rail lines going in but people
never actually understand how the
government uses their money so this is a
way that's super lightweight that city
employees can sign up for in like ten
minutes and start having open budgeting
and here's a the penny tax in Georgia
implementation site and then this is
awesome in Honolulu you can adopt a fire
sorry a siren for tsunamis because
there's all these sirens but there are
things like I think they had iguanas
that would start living in the sirens
and the sirens would malfunction so
neighbors that lived around the sirens
can adopt the sirens and it's their job
they get to anthropomorphize them so
this guy named his siren Vernon Kay
bedoya after his own name Vernon Bedoya
he named the siren after himself some
folk sirens have different names but now
he'll get text messages that say hey
have you checked the siren this month
like it might be screwed up and this app
was actually adopted in Boston we built
the thing called adopt a fire hydrant
and adopt a fire hydrant was the same
exact idea but you're supposed to shovel
the fire hydrant out after a snowstorm
but this guy in our Lulu set it up see
quick fixes ubiquitous thing now they
sent a lot of cities it's not a Code for
America project but it inspired some
Code for America projects it lets you
report like potholes from your
smartphone in the city when they fix
them you get a push notification that
says hey they fix that pothole you
reported last month so based on that we
made a dashboard of all open three on 13
11 requests across many cities so you
can see which cities are fixing more
requests there's like text message
interfaces for cities to use to report
new things this one's kind of like a
video game mayor Emanuel
in Chicago this is a like a video game
version of the mayor running around the
city fixing potholes and it shows like
how the city's actually responded to
triaging the civic infrastructure issues
and 311 labs which is like kind of like
starting to convene a community of
people trying to make cities more
efficient in the way that they spend
money on fixing infrastructure so that's
fixing government from the inside
there's also groups fixing government
from the outside such as here hi Malta
shorten interruption when the talk is
over you all have to stay here oh if we
if we're stuck or else the place will
blow away so don't get up yeah I have a
captive audience is that what you're
selling me maja let's talk about anarchy
um i already am you just don't realize
it so this is actually a group in
Germany in Berlin they don't have the
word Civic in German so they're using
Scotland which i think is city and state
and it's basically like civic coding and
what they're trying to do is without
working directly with the government's
just from a community activism
standpoint do the same exact kind of
things so they have this app wheel map
which is for a crowdsourcing wheelchair
accessible places there's this one which
is awesome which if I google translate
made me understand it's basically if you
have a bunch of bottles and cans you can
find people that come by and collect
bottles and cans in carts shopping carts
are however and you get their text
message number and you can tell them hey
I'm going to leave my bottles and cans
out next Tuesday come by my house on the
curve they'll be there super awesome
this one is basically if you request
information from the government instead
of just taking it you can post it here
and then everybody else can get it so
you don't have to have two people
requesting the same thing from the
government and then they also have open
three-on-one style system that was in
the UK for like the last ten years this
fix my street has been like it was like
the original three on one implementation
and this is like favorite project this
guy stefan put all of Germany's laws on
github and mark down amazing so for
instance this is the actual law of the
German government and then now the
pirate party in Germany has been sending
pull requests and so they're they're
changing the law and imagine how my in
vilonia it would be
if any city employee merged it's just
like ah it gets me so excited so uh the
third strategy is kind of a hybrid of
the first two you have inside and
outside government and then Tim O'Reilly
who I worked in directly through him
he's behind Code for America here I
wrote this awesome SI there's a link in
the presentation called government as a
platform so that's the hybrid strategy I
think it's the most promising one and
it's this idea of a civic startup and
the word startup could have positive or
negative connotations but in this case
it means fixing something so what is the
civic startup here's an example from
Vancouver Canada this guy Luke made this
thing that was originally called van
trash but he changed it recollect net
and it's a funny pun if you think about
it so in Vancouver every time there's a
holiday the garbage day switches to the
next day so it might be Tuesday Tuesday
Tuesday and then there's a holiday and
now the garbage is on Wednesday
Wednesday Wednesday and then there's a
holiday so you can't recollect the time
of the trash pickup so he just made a
thing where you put in where you live
and you put in your number and it text
messages you every time trash day
changes so you don't forget to take out
your trash super simple also something
that's super simple to a web developer
but something that cities are not going
to be able to have time to implement so
what he did is he figured out he could
sell that service to the government City
Vancouver and the City Vancouver would
pay him for every citizen that signed up
cover his costs allow him to the to make
some money and also allow the government
to me you know it's a win-win-win
situation so this is a lot of software
that still runs in government this is
the Assessor real estate system in New
Orleans I actually personally like this
aesthetic I think it's rad that they're
rolling with it but it's sad that a lot
of government software is still looking
like this today so I want to propose
there's many ways to hack the system
here's one that I've kind of gone deep
with so um right now the way government
by software is you have sales people
that go into City Hall I witnessed this
when I worked in Boston City how I was
kind of disgusting there's these
salespeople to get real chummy and they
say you know our enterprise platform
added a new let's say like a student
information system to its product lineup
this year and so the school district is
like okay we'll spend a million dollars
on that and it takes three years to
install and then it's there for ten
years
for 20 years and they're stuck with it
and they go through this process where
they have all the sales people from all
the big enterprise companies come in and
say are we going to give you a million
dollars are you a million dollars like
we'll have you battle for three years
and they finally pick one it's horrible
they are making the biggest like
vertical stack purchase as possible and
then they're running our entire
government infrastructure and using our
tax dollars to like it's crazy so what
if we had low cost for Kermit what if
governments could like try something out
and then turn it off just like how we
buy I don't know service as a software
on the web today and because it's such
low amounts of money you don't need a
competitive process because cities can
like any city employee like a CIO or a
CTO or whatever they can bust out like
50 grand on something without it without
having to go through a competitive
bidding process so there's a pretty high
margin for in terms of money like a
window that we can start inserting these
more like tech based solutions into
government and getting them to adopt
them so to get even more idealistic what
if this is a crazy idea I've been
dreaming about for a while what if we
had a government as an OAuth provider so
identity platforms inside of government
you go to a website maybe Mary here
right so an app called register a new
business calm and i go there and it's
like sign in with your city of berlin
account and it oh ops you through the
city of berlin site and now i can
interact with mary site and click a
button that makes me fill out a form
about how to do a new business and then
i click a button and it submits it to
the city's API that way a web developer
who knows what she's doing can make the
UI citizens can use it and the
government gets a better new business
applications and there's a ton of use
cases where this would be a more optimal
system it also sounds a lot like
developer ecosystems and what has made
these companies really successful but
nobody's done it for government yet um
so it's kind of like I wish procurement
officers had Heroku add-ons basically
this is a dream of mine so you can go
and you can click a button you can get
Redis on your Heroku thing and money
will start coming out of your account
but if three months down the road you're
like oh and switch to that other one you
can switch and money
stops coming and going to read us to go
it'll go to the other guys or whatever
and there's all these add-ons and
there's different levels and their plug
and play and they can form to like a
third-party ecosystem standard but again
nobody is doing in a government because
government is dominated by these big
enterprise companies here's an example
of an actual place that is doing this
right freakin Estonia is awesome so why
Estonia I went to this crazy meeting uh
with the president of Estonia don't ask
me how I got there that's me and that's
the president of Estonia he's an amazing
person he told me that you learned a
program on a PDP 8 when he was in middle
school and that has formed and he's
basically a hacker and so he is like he
writes assembler and he is now a head of
state like how many heads of state can
write assembler I I think like one and
what it's done is it's informed like he
has a native understanding of data and
privacy and all these important issues
that governments have to tackle and
Estonia actually has these really cool
things so each department in the
government has its own a
compartmentalized data storage mechanism
for doing whatever digital innovation
they have to do and only that department
can access it and the citizens are in
charge of allowing picking which
departments get access to which parts of
their data it's not one creepy big
government data set and it wouldn't work
it's a the United States federal level
but they have ribs and spine so we have
the backbone the spine the standards and
each department as a rib that connects
to the spine in a standardized way but
the cool thing is that they just bought
that software because they said here's
what we need what company is going to
make it and they bought this platform
and integrated it but they don't run
their company like a software or they're
they're not a software company Estonia
is a small government that has made
smart purchases and innovated because
they have the right platform in place so
you can do things like when you park
your car you text message what
neighborhood you parked in and when the
person who comes by and checks your
license plate they see that you're
currently paying for parking it's and
you could you can pay a you can vote
online you can vote in any election in
Estonia online they're the only country
where every election you can vote online
they rank really highly in a lot of
different areas but they're not it's
better to think of them as a
medium-sized city when we're talking
about a
opting our ideas for other places
they're only about a million people in
Estonia but there's a million people in
a lot of cities that have some very
similar issues so another problem who's
going to advocate for this good software
we know that there's better ways of
doing it than what government is doing
and bureaucrats are evil right so who's
gonna be our champion MC Hammer that's
who you guys remember MC Hammer he's
kind of a big deal he is actually from
the neighborhood that I know now living
in Oakland and this is that code for
america last week we're actually like
three days ago Ron Conway is a
well-known investor and Tim O'Reilly
brought MC Hammer an to talk about
laying it down government getting them
to be more efficient um this is kind of
a joke slide but this is basically
representing that this issue is getting
bigger and bigger people like MC Hammer
are starting to pay attention to it so
you know it's a big deal um and we all
know that government is going to always
change slowly but government technology
is actually moving really fast for
instance in boston they have this cio it
came in 07 and he was able to acquire
quintuple the tech budget they went from
using five million dollars every year to
run their technology to 25 million
dollars so he made technology a bigger
deal they spent more money on technology
but what they did was it made it the
internal systems operations more
efficient and they actually saved about
250 million dollars overall in the
budget by better leveraging technology
the federal government the United States
spent something like 200 times the
entire like net amount of iphone apps
that are purchased the government bought
200 times that last year in just big
enterprise software but technology is
making big leaps and bounds even in
government and why am I talking to Jas
comp Jas is everywhere and it's the
fastest growing thing right now it's
ubiquitous and if you're going to build
an app that fixes government all the
examples examples that I showed earlier
they're going to have a jazz component
and our community has this history in
the last few years of kind of moving
forward at the most efficient route
possible and not worrying about legacy
compatibility so there's no way that we
can change all governments overnight but
we can define how it looks to fix
government in the future and then
most important thing is there are cities
that are interested in this at that
meeting with the president of Estonia we
were supposed to come up with policy
ideas on how to actually like hack the
system and fix government and I proposed
this procurement lightweight procurement
idea and I had 15 cities express
interest and say hey we're super
interested in this code for america has
worked with like 30 cities so far in the
last couple of years they just announced
the cities for next year and they
include San Francisco and Oakland and
they worked with like Chicago and some
of the other bigger cities that have are
doing a lot of interesting stuff there
are people that are being hired as chief
data officers now so Philadelphia just I
hired a guy who used to work at Code for
America to be in the cabinet in city as
C do and it's a totally awesome new role
because it's his job to just make sure
that all the data the government's
collecting can be interacted with with
citizens um so my pitch to everybody is
whatever government you live in find a
bug figure out how to fix it fix that in
in a way that does it better than how
the government is attempting to fix it
now turn it into a product and there's
now this interesting like early adopter
network of cities who are going to adopt
it and potentially pay you to fix the
problems that they're not capable of
fixing because government shouldn't run
like software companies so I think of
the node community as a political party
in a way it's very self-directed people
do what's fun or people do what's
interesting and we have these
lightweight rules around the core of the
community they're very small but people
are moving forward very fast and what
I'd like to see like with government
hacking and the JavaScript community is
people pick different parts that are a
little bit tarnished and they they find
a way to polish them and they're
implementing small things incrementally
and that's kind of like how JavaScript
has evolved over the last few years we
have a completely horribly ugly system
but we've been able to make a lot of
beautiful abstractions inside of it or
just see it for what it really is as a
kind of a beautiful core so like
government the good parts so thank you
everybody
uh this is a Isaac's looters cat
Aristotle from the node project just so
you wanted to know I have a four minutes
for questions if anybody has questions
I'm glad we didn't die also do we have a
mic for questions I don't even know
maybe well I'll just repeat it I'll
restate it so first there's many
projects so it's hard to find them but
you're trying to get governments to to
adopt them and to be able to switch
easily between them and it seems like
discovery is a real issue here what how
can we fix that how can we make it
easier to find what the government needs
or have them find it for themselves I
think one of the things I learned in
working for one city and then going into
another city and trying to adapt the
same solutions was every city's
different and it's hard to write a virus
that infects multiple cities like you
come up with one cool thing but one city
might think it's cool and another city
might not so you kind of have to it's
all about more people in more cities
getting involved in telling the story of
their individual city and what they need
and what I'd like to see is more like
local developers working in the cities
they live in with the cities themselves
I think right now it's only a couple
years of people really tinkering with
this stuff and more and more solutions
like the adopt system adopt a Hydran
adoptive ha siren that's been adopted
like 15 cities now and that's one of the
cooler success stories of like in the
last 12 months since it started but it's
still the early days and I think that
it's hard to find universal solutions
it's more like you have one like the van
trash thing how many cities have weird
trash schedules a lot of cities don't
have that problem so it's it's
complicated but I think it's getting
better Mary oh yeah
um I'm interested in why the things
you've described of predicated on the
involvement of government so the
overarching theme seems to be making the
world run better but why is the
government the sort of Nexus of all of
those solutions I think that government
is so hard to understand right now that
it on one hand I appreciate the idea of
building a completely new system that's
not connected and maybe like rage
quitting on government and and you can
do a lot if you if you're not trying to
back forward everything but I guess that
that's a really good question i think
that maybe like the core debate is do
you try to fix something that's hard to
understand because what if we could like
no oops sorry what if we could know what
our government's doing at all times in a
way that's not creepy transparency but
positive understandability like if we
could truly understand the system and
all collaborate and actually do it
together which is the dream of
government is everybody doing everything
together then that would be great so I
guess I guess at a meta-level I would be
happy with these systems working in
society without the government's
involvement but if you did build a
system that did work it might turn into
a government eventually anyway so it
might be inevitable it's it's a
difficult question and with that I am
totes out of time and apparently don't