all right so what we're going to talk
about today is building a gesture
recognition system with machine learning
Arduino and JavaScript so all together
but before I start just a little bit
about me my name is Charlie Gerard I'm
recently a senior content of apparently
fie and outside of my job I'm also part
of two tech communities called the
Google developer experts and Mozilla
tech speaker I'm not going to go too
much in detail right now but if you have
any questions about these two we can
talk about it afterwards what this talk
is more related to is my passion about
human-computer interaction so if you
don't know what this is it is kind of
like the study or the research of how
humans interact with computers so when
you think about the way you interact
normally with technology on a day to day
basis you might be typing on your
keyboard or swiping on your phone but
there's a lot more types of interactions
that we could actually program that
would be a lot more playful and a lot
more interesting than that and well the
like one thing that I'm going to talk
about today that this talk is about is
to build prototype of a street fighter
game that you play with your own body
movements so instead of punching with a
keyboard you actually what we're going
to talk about we're going to go through
the process of how you can play that but
with your own body movements so when you
punch you actually punch and how do you
can and then uppercut so we're gonna
have three different gestures so this
was the idea that I started with so what
are we going to need to build this so we
start with some hardware because we need
to gather data about motions about
unlocking body movements so to do that
to be able to gather the data we're
going to use a bit of hardware that
we're going to hold in our hands the
second thing that we're going to need is
machine learning to kind of find
patterns in the data that we gather and
put that we're going to use tensorflow
but we are at a scomp so we're going to
use JavaScript so we're gonna use
tensorflow
GS all right so this is the material
that we're gonna need and now that we
kind of know what we want to build and
what we're going to need the first step
is gathering data again we it's machine
learning so we need a bit of data to
find patterns and recognize what makes a
punch or what makes a Hydra cane or an
uppercut so we're going to start with
that and to gather data as I said we're
going to use a bit of hardware so the
first time is that I put the type this
little project I used this so this is an
Arduino but this is not like the you
know that
with my if you just get started without
we know this is a maker 1000 and the
reason why I use that one is because it
has built-in Wi-Fi if you play with an
Arduino Uno you have to be plugged to
your computer so you're not really free
in the movements that you make you know
if you punch you might just like totally
disconnect from your computer's which is
not really what you want so this one is
so it has beauty in my face you can just
be you know remotely connected to your
laptop you can be anywhere in the room
and play that game so it just felt like
it would be easier but the board itself
doesn't actually gather any data it runs
a program but you don't actually get
anything from the board itself so to be
able to get data from motion we're gonna
add an accelerometer and gyroscope so
this module gathers both accelerometer
and gyroscope so it means that you get
data for X Y z axis of how fast you're
moving but also in terms of the
gyroscope that takes care of the
rotation so when you're you know if you
think about when you're punching you
kind of like retaining your arm that way
so you're mixing speed and rotation and
this particular module can give you the
data about both so in the end we end up
with six points of data XY 0 of
accelerometer and XYZ of gyroscope but
that's not it to make it a bit easier
for me to build this I also added a bit
and the reason why I did over N is
because when I gather data I want to
gather data only what I'm doing the
punch I don't want to gather data on
when I'm resting because that's kind of
a pollute my data set so the reason why
I did Oberon is that I want to be able
to press do my punch and record the data
while I'm doing it is only when I
release only gathered the data so while
the button is pressed and I'm doing the
gesture I only save this so that then I
can do whatever that is not the gesture
that I want and it won't be recorded so
if we imagine that we wired all of this
together we have a Burin extramental
java scope and arduino this is for the
hardware this is what we're going to
hold in our hand but in terms of code
we're going to use a bit of node.js so
we start by requiring the support module
is called client to establish the
communication between our Arduino and a
laptop then we use johnny-five
which is the main JavaScript framework
to interact with hardware and the last
one that we're going to need is oh no I
don't want that what right so way back
ok so so yeah so we're gonna we're gonna
need the final system module because
we're going to record our data but we
need to
fabien file so we can use it later then
we accentuate our board where we
establish the connection with the host
and the port of our of our Arduino and
when the board is ready we have to tell
it where the button is connected to so
mine was on pin a zero but it can be
anything then we create the stream that
we saw the file that we're going to
write to for this little code simple you
know I had like simple punch zeroes like
the first punch that I'm going to train
I'm going to call you know I'm gonna
save it in a text file but as to repeat
the gesture a lot of times to create
your data set you would change that name
of the file over time then we also
accentuate an IMU sensor which is our
motion sensor we give it the pins that
is connected to and the type of model
which was an MP u 60 50 and unchanged so
every time that we're moving every time
that you get data from that little
module you actually keep all of those
six points of data into a variable and
when you're holding the button you're
writing to the file system so you're
writing to the stream all of the data
that you get and on when you release you
close the stream so you end it so all of
a sudden you're not writing to the text
file anymore and what this code sample
gives you in the end is a file like this
so that's like a sample there's a lot
more lines depending on how long you do
the gesture for but you expect that kind
of data on the x-axis of the file you
have your six points of data so X Y Z of
X parameter and XYZ or gyroscope and the
number of lines is how long you're doing
the gesture force so and you know like
you don't have to read all the numbers
but it's quite precise so it means that
there's quite a difference that it
really records your entire gesture for
how long as you're pressing the button
so that's really cool so we did step one
we got the data this is like for only
one sample the first punch but you would
imagine that you would have to record it
probably a hundred times for each
gesture so you wind up with a lot of
files so the step two that we have to go
through is that our processing because
at the moment all that we did is
recording data into text files but we
didn't do anything else so if we go back
to our data that looks like this it is
just strings inside text files and we
know that indian we want to use
tensorflow J's and ten topologist
doesn't really work with strings so we
have to transform a data data by little
so first of all we're going to have to
transform it into objects of features
and labels and features and labels are
words that are related to machine
learning so
what it means is that we're actually
transforming text files into so features
is the content of the text file so what
makes a punch and the label is going to
be like the name but again we don't use
string so we transform the name into an
index so if we have a gesture of
Hadouken punch and uppercut label one is
index 1 which is going to be punch so
it's kind of like a way of transforming
our data so we end up with numbers and
no strings so this would be for only one
gesture so my first punch all of the
data would be in the features and label
one would be punched but as I said you
have to gather quite a lot of data so
you end up creating the same thing for
each of your files so each of your text
file actually becomes an object and you
end up with a giant array of all of your
data sample ok so that's the first step
the thing is tensorflow doesn't really
work with objects it works more with
something that you know like arrays this
would there be another step afterwards
but so how would you then transform
these objects into another arrays so
what you have to do you end up with
multi-dimensional arrays and this is
where it gets a bit complicated to
explain but I'm gonna try my best so if
you look at you're going to split the
labels and the features so if we look at
the first layer of our multi-dimensional
labels array you have all of the zeros
so you have all of the hydrogens that
you trained and it's mapped to the first
layer of the features multi-dimensional
arrays so if we go a bit further and we
say our first ever hadouken that we
trained it's going to be mapped to the
first the first array of features in the
first layer of peaches and then so if
you do the second one is going to be
mapped as well so your second hydrogen
is going to be mapped to the second
array of features etc and then we move
on to the punches it's going to be the
same everything is mapped so it's in
like the same position but it's in
different arrays because in the end now
we're finally getting to a format that
tensorflow can work with now we don't
have strings we don't have objects we
have multi-dimensional arrays which is
closer to what to what tensorflow works
with and so I don't know if you noticed
well I didn't show any actual code
sample because so far it's not any
tensorflow specific code its
transformation of of data in a race and
objects that you would do in like
standard JavaScript if I could say so
but now now that we have
that resembles what what test we can
work with we can we can finally
transform that into tenses so if you
can't it's a bit small but don't worry
about really understanding what these
lines of code do because if you've never
played with tensorflow before it's going
to be like reading it will not really
make sense it's more about I only put it
there to show the amount of coordinated
to do that but what is really more
important well I'd be happy with is if
you understand more the process to go
through if you know if you want to know
exactly how to write a the repos are on
github or the documentation is pretty
good I'm sure that you'll figure out
later on the understanding the steps is
the most important thing so first of all
before transforming the our data to
tenses we have to shuffle it because if
I just go back to the slide before
everything is in order and you don't
really want to give your data that way
to a machine learning algorithm because
it's just going to get used to the way
you feed it so for example it's going to
look at it's gonna be like oh well the
five previous samples that you gave me
we're all hadoukens so this mean one
must be a hadouken it's not really going
to try to find any pattern in the data
and that's not what you want you wanted
to really understand what makes how do
you know what makes a punch based on the
data so it's not by shuffling it and
then you're gonna use the tensorflow
methods like tensor 2d because our
gestures are two-dimensional we have six
numbers over a certain amount of lines
so it's like an x and y axis for your
data and the labels is a one-dimensional
tensor because the label is only one
thing it's either either 0 1 or 2 or
more if you decide to do more classes
the next step is to splitting between
training set and test it so you just
have to calculate the amount of your
data that you're gonna split so the
reason why you do that is because you
have your entire label data set and the
training set is going to be given to
create the model so you keep 80% of your
data set to to create the model and you
keep 20% of it for the test set so the
test that is going to be used to
validate against the model that you
created because your test set is already
labeled again it's something that you
trained and you labeled yourself and
just to check that the accuracy of your
model is good you're going to use 20% of
your data set to train it against so so
yeah you end up doing that so you slice
your cereal tensors between training
features and testing features training
levels
testing levels once again if the code
doesn't make sense it's fine it's more
about the steps and now finally our data
is processed so it's it's ready but we
still haven't done anything so the step
3 is to create the model at the moment
we just reformatted the data so that we
can do something with it so to create
the model so this is more this at the
part where it's more of an art than a
science when you want to play with
machine learning you might not know in
advance what model you can use or what
parameters do you see it's more a step
where you play around here I use the
sequential model I could not explain why
it just worked so I used it and then
there's this other types of models but
it works for me sardine changing then in
terms of the amount of layers in your in
your own neural network you have to but
you can have four or five and the
parameters can be changing as well so
I'm not going to go in-depth into this
because again what works for you just
keep it then we we just add like an
optimizer layer as well and then finally
what's important here is that the fit
method is what is going to train the
model so you pass it your training
features and training labels and you
have a parameter of validation data when
you give your test set as well so this
step is actually going to be the
training process and in the end once
this is done with all of the data that
you gave it you can save your model in
your file system so now we actually
gathered our data which once formed it
we created the model but okay step for
prediction you actually want to use that
model you're not going to go through all
of this to like know run predictions
later on so the final step of all of
this is the prediction so to do this I
like my application was more of like you
know GS fine but you can do that in the
browser you don't require tensorflow GS
instead of Tesla J's node but basically
you you import the framework we have a
gesture classes arrays that has how you
can punch and uppercut we load our model
to be able to use it and then if we go
back to our our code to get the data
from the accelerometer and gyroscope
when we hold the button we we save all
of our data into a variable we push it
into an array and this time we're not
setting it to the first system because
we are not training an algorithm we're
predicting life data that it's never
seen before
so we tip Laura in the variable
and when we release the button we're
sending all of that data to a predict
function and what our predict question
does it's going to transform a live data
that we just had in a variable into a
tensor as well so it can be compared to
what the model was trained with we call
the predict method with that input
that's been transformed and in the end
the prediction that you get is going to
be an index just the same way that our
label was a number the prediction is
going to come back as a number as well
so we have to look up what it means in
the gesture classes array so if the
prediction comes back as 0 it means that
is the first index in our gesture
classes which is going to be the
Hadouken or punch or a pocket whatever
okay so this is this was like a very
short version of everything that you
have to go through but as we can see
it's not it's not that much code I think
then the like the thing that takes
longer is to record the data and to
understand what's going on but once you
have an understanding of the steps it's
about finding the right syntax it's the
same way that you would do if you were I
don't know migrating from reactor to
view you know what you have to do but
you have to learn the syntax okay so now
that I told you what you should do or
what yeah I thought I would try to show
you how it works and this is where I'm
always like so excited but then it
doesn't work okay so I'm gonna try but I
have quite a bit of time so I can try it
like until it works so yeah so I'll just
put like a little gift in case it
doesn't work but what is supposed to
happen I'm supposed to do this and then
it's a point so there's a delay but
let's not talk about the delay and this
normal that there's a delay but yeah
that's another talk but I'm supposed to
be able to read these three gestures
okay sorry okay so I'm going to exit my
slides okay so Bluetooth is on and I
have that okay I okay I just need to
check that you didn't break oh yeah
there's errors in the console but not
everybody
okay so if I do like sorry I was
thinking it's not gonna work okay let me
try again I just want to
oh it's still okay still on so if I do
wait can I do like oh sorry
Wow they work the first time like it's
the first time that it actually works
the first time so I'm like super excited
cool like there's once I had to try it
ten times and I think people wanted me
off the stage I was like I'm not leaving
okay
so this was for Street Fighter okay cool
but maybe you don't like Street Fighter
so I built another one hopefully it's
gonna work as well but I put a little
bit hint I don't know if it's gonna load
okay so once movements so maybe you
don't like Street Fighter maybe you like
Harry Potter so I know you know that
spells have a name you can say hello for
more our experiments but they're also
happy shape so you can be a real wizard
now hopefully okay let's see if it works
so for this demo I'm I'm hopeful that
it's really gonna work cool okay so I
still still know okay so steel air is
still fine
wait okay so I'm just gonna check it I'm
still I'm still on okay so I have I
think I have like experience nope so it
was too good to be true
it did crash so then that would be
another talk about why it crashes I
dunno why it crushes but I don't want to
talk about it so if I do like
oh we're good so this is how I spend my
weekend I have another one I don't so
the only one is Loomis I don't know if
it's gonna work no I'm gonna try again
because now I have time I have time
crushed okay okay I want to do there
Loomis I think it's funny all right all
right anyway it's just to show you that
the process is the same like I was still
recording data I was still processing it
still training a machine learning model
it's just that NBN I was training
different gestures so you had Hadouken
punch and a poker the name the other one
you had experiments and dumas but the
process is the same so then you can just
replace bits to create what you want you
probably might have liked better ideas
than what I just did the what else so
the thing is that I really the reason
why I like playing with that stuff is
because I want more people to do it but
in the first versions that I use so I
used an Arduino and everybody has we
knows where I also used like a daydream
controller sensor that is kind of like
the same but different and but the thing
is it's stuff that you have to buy and I
don't think that's really cool I think
it stops people from trying so I was
thinking do you know what else has a
gyroscope and accelerometer your phone
so the phone that you have in your
pocket if you have one of the motor it
doesn't even have to be an iPhone X or
tennis you don't know how to say but
none of these like even even an older
phone probably still has an X parameter
and a gyroscope and the way to access
this data in JavaScript is using the
generic sensor API so again you might
you would probably have to refactor the
code because all of a sudden window in
node anymore we can just do it directly
in the browser but the way you would do
this is you would essentially eight and
it's really too small I'm sorry I'll
share the slides later but you have a
gyroscope and you have an event listener
for reading so whenever the it's
streaming data you have the same for
accelerometer and it gives you the same
data it gives you the XYZ axis of the
gyroscope and accelerometer and when I
say that you can do that I actually I
did so I did I'm not going to show it
because now I have less time but
I have like the repo is on github so you
can play around with it as well so it
means that without having to buy any
hardware you can actually play with
training a machine learning algorithm
just by using your phone all of it in
JavaScript so I think this is pretty
cool but anyway just a little bit of a
recap because there was a lot of code
and if you've never done that before it
can be a bit overwhelming but again I
think the steps are what's important so
you have to get data somehow I used
Arduino daydream and the phone but any
other any other piece of hardware that
you know transmits data you can actually
use that as well then you have to
process the data because when you say
that it's just strings so you have to
transform it into tenses it somehow then
you have to split to be able to test and
validate that your predictions are
accurate then you have to Train
well yeah you have to train to generate
a model in the end and then you have to
run the predictions so once you know
that this is the steps that you have to
go through then you can you know look at
the documentation of a few different
frameworks and you'll get there
but anyway I'm almost done but just
before I finish I really wanted to say I
say that all the time but I feel like I
still need to say it so I know that all
of that stuff is not something that
you're gonna go back to work and you
know make millions with definitely not
but I know that it's maybe you know what
you came here for maybe you wanted to
learn something that you call useful but
to me it's really you I'm not making fun
of people who think this is useful
anyway so the reason why I'm saying that
is that I learned a lot during the
process and for example there's a lot of
times where you look at machine learning
and you're like oh I don't want to like
just crunch data into spreadsheets it's
like boring but the thing is you end up
being able to take machine learning and
put it into something playful and that
you know that makes you keep going to
learn more about that technology by just
playing something that gets you excited
and you just you know so much if you if
you end up doing that kind of stuff you
would learn about Arduino and machine
running and WebSockets to go from a node
to the browser and just play like
industry would learn about
human-computer interaction as well which
is I think well something I'm really
passionate about but anyway that
sometimes I really wish that I was
seeing more of these playful things that
play with technology rather than you
know some of the fights that we have on
twitter / CSS engineers but it's like
that's what I know that to me useless is
not worthless it's definitely worth it
if it just makes you excited for like an
hour that's definitely worth it
but anyway I spoke very fast as always
so I am done I will share the slides
later on on Twitter if you have any
questions I'll be around as well for the
next few days but thank you so much for
having me and thank you thank you so
much