solo everybody um welcome to JS conf
2011 it's awesome thanks for the or
thanks to organizers and Malta and yon
and holger for having me here and
everyone else who's helped out Berlin's
an awesome city so thank you to everyone
who lives here for showing us all a good
time so prologue let's talk about making
lasers for a bit when I was a little kid
I I wasn't pleased with video games or
anything I really got her harass my
parents constantly and I would always
come to them and be like I want to make
something I don't want to just do
something I want to make something and
so the stories that I found anything I
could find my house would kabul them
together into like the weirdest arrays
of what i called robots or lasers and
basically laser was a flashlight and a
mirror and a prism and old telegraphic
photo lens that focus light and i
thought it was the coolest thing ever
and it was all strapped to like it was
strapped to my job just a big wooden
board and that was that was that was
making something that was me then you
can check out my sweet awesome Beethoven
the movie long sleeve shirt because
that's how cool I was um that's my
little brother too so quickly about me
I'm the Sami guy if you recognize where
the source pictures from you get a beer
I'm the CTO of a company in the u.s.
called paperless post we do online
invitations and stationery we have a
pretty large team in a pretty large app
and we're growing pretty quickly but
thanks to them I'm out here and can talk
to you guys I'm the lover of food the
lover of food i'm a lover of food i
start a thing called code food bar if
any of you guys came on friday night
last night
to the dinner that was actually I did
nothing for that that was all Tiffany
and we can thank her for that but I
started a thing we're nerds get together
and eat because I like eating better
than I like drinking to be honest but
when you combine combine them both you
know that's the real magic so today's
talk the title changed a little bit it's
called your framework sucks and so does
mine but it's going to be a little bit
of a rant and a little bit of maybe some
knowledge will be transmitted so I'm
going to go over kind of myths and
truths of frameworks and specifically
client-side web frameworks and what that
means so there are a couple minutes that
that come up when you talk about
client-side frameworks and they mainly
revolve around like creation myths and
then like propagation myths like
creation myths as in how these things
sprain works came about and came into
being and propagation myths like how
they became popular and how why they
should be popular so probably the
biggest one is emitted extraction and
you know it's it's a real myth because
frameworks aren't like these immaculate
conceptions they're not like all of a
sudden there was an act and then out of
this app sprung this framework the
greatest framework that ever that was
ever created and the the you know the
most popular myth is probably rails and
or so Molina gave a talk at i think it
was scottish Ruby come two years ago
where he talked about kind of actually
went through all the in a very very
nerdy in like comic book guy way went
through all the the mailing list
archives of Ruby laying around the time
that rails was released and it was
really really obvious that base camp was
happening and rails
happening but it wasn't like base camp
and then pull the rails at a base camp
that just didn't happen they frameworks
grow they don't just spring out of
nothing and frameworks what they really
are like combinations of a couple things
abstractions like trying to pull common
things into abstract patterns that can
be reused tools like generators and
stuff like that patterns actual not not
forcing you into a pattern or or not the
abstractions of the patterns themselves
but just patterns like MVC and M vvvvvv
c and stuff like that also frameworks
can also be combinations of existing
frameworks and a lot of JavaScript
frameworks these days the bigger ones
are built on top of jQuery or combined
jquery and something else to make the
new framework what they also are
experiments in the framework that I
created in what really brings me here
today is Sammy J guess and Sammy jess
was really I'm not going to lie I didn't
extract it out of some awesome app that
i wrote it really was just an experiment
it was can we take something like
Sinatra which is a ruby framework that I
really loved and was super simple and
translated to the web and translated
into JavaScript so this is what a
Sinatra application looks like you don't
need to know Ruby to read this but
basically you define an app that's just
a you know a class that descends from
Sinatra application and you define a
route which is a path and then what
happens in that route where you render
the index temper it's really really
simple so this is what it looks like
insanity I mean the original original
sketches for Sammy were literally just a
gist I could probably point people that
just but it was like you know since ruby
has blocks and JavaScript has these this
call back or you know first class
function pattern we can do some similar
things and hey maybe this could be
interesting maybe this could have use
cases beyond just an experiment and
actually it was Alex over
standing next to me who realized that
hey this pattern of having a controller
is really useful for things like couchdb
where you don't have necessarily have a
middle tier and you can just have Sammy
and this controller pattern living
completely in the browser and living
just in the database itself and I talked
about that last year but it's a really
interesting pattern in it's not
something that I initially thought of as
a use case for Sammy but it ended up
being the best use case so another myth
is smaller is better and this is kind of
a recent one and I'll have to like fist
fight with Jed about this but basically
the myth is that you know it doesn't I
mean obviously obviously there are
reasons to have small code especially on
the on the client side it does actually
matter but the myth that it matters for
most is is kind of ridiculous most
people cite the need for speed you know
that that you know were you know
obviously we're downloading all the code
in the browser so the smaller your code
is the faster it'll be are the faster
download but really were most people are
running I mean most developers at least
are probably running on high-speed
connections and the difference between a
kilobyte or two really really once its
cache is not really going to make that
big a difference and what ends up
happening is people extract so much of
the coro that they really end up with
less when you're going to take stuff
away you take stuff away obviously
there's a point where you can actually
refactor stuff and make stuff smaller
and make it faster and make it better
when you're actually taking a whole
chunks out of a framework or whole
chunks out of out of an existing tool
you're probably losing some stuff and
that stuff you might end up having to
recreate and create your own version of
it which might not be as good as the
original version so less actually means
lessons smaller doesn't always mean
better really it's about balance and
balance is a couple things but here I'm
talking about readability and
maintainability versus the lines of code
so you know you can
right everything in 140 bites you can
write your entire web framework in the
length of a in the length of a quick an
endlave within the length of a tweet but
really that's not gonna you know if you
actually oh now we want to add support
for you know actual hash hash matching
or or some other kind of patterns like
oh how am I actually going to go in and
do that so you know there is has to be
some kind of ballast and i'm not talking
about like naming all your methods you
know does connect to device so that it
can you know there's there's a balance
there's a balance and the readability is
truly important especially if you're
working with the team for the speed
demons for the people who actually do
care about speed and not only care about
speed but it's of utmost importance i
spelled require wrong they their code
loaders like lap dance and require which
allow you to load stopping is
synchronously so you don't have to load
everything and you can just load you can
split up your code base you only load
the things you need and of course we all
know compilation the compression you can
compress your code after the fat and
there are tools that you can use to do
that in their ways you can write code
that's still readable but compress as
well so you know that those are two
important things also component ization
like only taking what you need from a
framework in making framework small
enough so that you can basically split
them up and obviously ender is probably
the newest example of something that's
completely componentized so that you
only really need to take what you need
so this is more of our where we go into
more of a rant section but there's kind
of this myth that's not specific client
side frame works at all but this myth of
the one true way and the funny thing is
that the truth about everything is that
there is no one truth I don't know who
said this no one I said it no I mean
there it's someone much greater than me
realize this a very long time ago
probably when they were arguing with
someone in a cave about how big
mammoth was or something like that but
the truth is if there is no one truth
and that's kind of a Taoist philosophy
but you know there there there is a path
and there are things that are better
than others but it's really case-by-case
and this idea that frameworks have
become these religions that just boggles
my mind that people can believe in
something so much that they're willing
to sacrifice all out and Ellison really
be zealots for a for a for a framework
it's kind of crazy so the way this the
way you express this is by saying I'm a
rails developer or I'm a backbone
developer or on my sami developer I'm a
no developer obviously there are
differences between platforms and
frameworks but at the baseline tying
yourself to a single anything and
labeling yourself like that you know
really makes it so that no one can talk
to you and there you have only have this
one frame of reference and I'm this and
everyone else's other and it's not it's
not really a good way to live the basic
thing is that there is no untrue so
you're all wrong but you're also all
right so if we all agree that there is
no untrue that we can all agree that we
can all have coexisting opinions about
how things work obviously certain things
are true and certain things are faster
and certain things are slower but it
really is a case-by-case basis and what
I'm trying to say is that altruism
doesn't really belong in web development
there's a reason we have different tools
and people will use different tools and
the idea that we tie ourselves to a
single tool and keep pushing that
forward makes us not open to the rest of
the world and excludes people and that's
that's the worst thing you can possibly
do so I'm not even talking about being
framework agnostic but just be agnostic
in general and that doesn't mean in a
religious sense that means questioning
things you know so it's okay that
question is this the best tool for the
job and is this the best frame not only
is this is the best framework for now
but is this the best framework for me is
this message cool for me and that's what
it's really about we're all different
people and we all have different
problems solved and there are many many
tools out there that
all these problems very differently and
the idea that someone can go on hacker
news and say like this framework is the
best framework just I mean it's crazy
okay I don't understand how we can
actually think like that and expect us
to move forward as developers and as a
you know as a community so the next
thing is tied into that in the mix of
the next specs next next best thing and
that's that when you label yourself
that's also a fashion statement so if I
said you know I'm a COBOL developer then
I'd probably get made fun of I'm not so
don't make fun of me but um but if I if
I was I would be like oh okay you're a
cobalt developer you know have you been
online in the last 30 years but there's
there's it's really about fashion
statements is about showing off that
you're on the bleeding edge and the
bleeding edge is cut to you there's a
reason it's called the bleeding edge but
really the best practice is the
knowledge that best practices change
them I'm making a lot of you know
paradoxical statements but the best
practice is that you know best practices
are always going to keep moving forward
and it's funny to think that to try to
believe that at any given moment you're
doing the absolute best practice like
you know three years ago or four years
ago obviously browsers change and
everything changed but Steve Souter said
you know hey everybody the best practice
for delivering JavaScript to the web is
bundle everything together into a single
javascript file and serve it cached to
all your clients okay everyone was again
now everybody bundle now and
everyone did and now three years later
it's like everyone split up all your
files into different small components
and use lab j as to require to load them
asynchronously it's like yeah let's load
them asynchronously and it's awesome
that we're so into these different you
know movements and changes but being
prepared for those changes and knowing
that it's not
the ultimate solution is the only way to
really move forward and what that means
is also you know be prepared but don't
the second you hear about something new
it doesn't mean you have to jump to that
conclusion the fact is that if you're
working in a big team in a big app like
making rewriting everything it just
really isn't easy and you want to keep
moving forward not sideways so moving an
entire app from Ruby to node you know if
you have three weeks and a million
dollars you know do it I applaud you you
know test out the new thing but it's not
really what we're you know rewriting you
might learn some new things but it's not
our goal as developers our goal as
developers is to create new things and
rewriting is hard I've done it before
it's not fun so this is going to offend
some people may be but the myth too is
that this is this equation you know it's
true that you know fame and fortune you
don't doesn't come from open source and
even though in the age github you know
we're all pushing things constantly when
you write a project you're not big bear
you're not instantly you know gonna
gonna get blunts and bears with
sunglasses and piles of gold and it's
just not going to happen that doesn't
come from being an open-source developer
maybe you get to go to conferences it's
awesome maybe you get to speak like I'm
doing to you but in the end it's not the
end all be all there are other ways to
get to where we are and there are other
ways to be successful so this is a this
is a message that close source isn't a
pure evil I mean this is kind of
contradictory to why I'm up here as an
open-source developer and someone
contributes a lot to open source you
think that I want to open source
everything but you know what I mean I'm
a man of many beliefs and I think that
closed source is not a pure evil it
doesn't necessarily mean that if you're
writing something not in secret but with
a team and working together as a team
with other people that that won't create
a good product and i gotta say that
actually over the past couple months in
past couple year
I've done some projects that are open
source and I've gotten great feedback
and it's moved them forward and I've had
other projects that I've kept myself and
developed not a secret but with a team
that's uniquely focused and not this
wide world that has a vast array of
opinions about what is good and what is
bad and I've put some stuff as open
sourcing you know the fact is when you
put some stuff is open source you have
to maintain it forever basically that's
the that's the contract and you know
there are some really great things that
have come out of close our software and
I'm not going to even list them because
they're probably too many lists
obviously there's things that come out
of open source but the fact is that you
know if you actually the point is don't
don't care about pushing first you know
write something do it well and then
maybe if it works for you it'll work for
someone else but it doesn't necessarily
have to work that way right what's good
for you ok so now I'm going to go into
the truth so the truce of common
client-side development is that it's a
perilous path from with pirates and
wizards dragons vengeful gods and you
know it's really really really hard I
mean it's a lot easier than it was ten
years ago but you know it's still really
really hard we're fighting against this
ever-changing platforms you know not
just a single platform but ever-changing
platforms that are constantly changing
without us even knowing or or have tiny
bugs like Monta was even saying today
that chrome you know dev channel breaks
the Twitter authentic often that's like
an example of we don't really we have
very little control over all the
platforms that we deploy to so it's very
very hard and but what doesn't kill us
makes us stronger and you know the fact
is is that there is no perfect platform
and there is no perfect framework and
there are things that we can extract
from these tools that make a lot of
things a lot easier but it still is
going to be hard but so I have a list of
what you should demand from a
client-side framework and my demands
personally your demands might be
different are just that it has a clean
consistent API it has enough
sure to help but not hang you and not
slow you down and its most importantly
it solves a problem that your app has
you can find a framework that solves
that solves a problem your app doesn't
have and a lot of people do that and
spend a lot of time working on that I
like frameworks and tools that solves
problem solve problems that I have so
Sam and Jack solve a problem that I have
and I'll tell you about it first of all
samia's not for everyone but and it's
not for everything but it's off some
problems really well the core thing that
it has is a separation of paths or
routes with a restful ideology now rest
is like a you know not just a buzzword
but it's really you know another term
rock with a lot of discussion and
different people believe different
things about what rest actually is but
the basic idea of having patterns that
Matt URLs to methods and have that kind
of functionality where URL is mapped to
a to a clear a clear tool so in this
case this is what a simple sammy app
looks like we define some routes we say
get users are posted users and we get
users we get the list of users and you
know I commented out what the actual
method bodies do but it's just pure
JavaScript you can you know glowed users
from from server and can load them from
local storage or whatever you want and
then post users where posts were we're
mocking a post request basically in
accepting a form submission into Sammy
and then inside of the route we get back
a params hash that has all the form
elements that were our form inputs that
were in that post um it also supports
put and del not delete that's because
deletes a reserved word in JavaScript
and it just breaks everything so the
other thing that it's good at really
good at or i think is template rendering
and munging so this is the exam this is
an example in Samuel 7 of like what
rendering floating your partial and
rendering
template looks like sorry and it's all
it's it's chained in chaining in this
render contacts format means that it's
asynchronous it's kind of like promises
but even though those all are could be
or make might be asynchronous cause they
all happen in the guaranteed order so
you're loading a partial which is just
an HTML template that replaces the page
then you're loading a JSON object from
the server that has a list of users or a
user by ID and then you take a template
out of a script tag which is that user
template mustache which is a mustache
template and then replace the user
selector with that template with the
data from the server lunged into it and
that does a lot and if I think it's
pretty clean it's obviously if you don't
like chaining you probably won't like it
and there are other ways to get around
it but I think it solves the common
problem of wanting to have data on the
server and templates in the client or on
the server and munching them and merging
them together and putting them on the
client so what it doesn't include is
data modeling really it's trying to be
as simple as possible and not decide how
you should model your data so you have
to really bring your own and for me that
means that I have some api's that are
just JSON I write a lot of standing
opposite don't even talk to a server
that are just client-side and it does
that without having bringing extra
weight of having to tell you how to
define your model it's not opinionated
in that way it's agile meaning it bends
well and it can bend a lot of different
use cases so for example my favorite is
prototyping it's really really really
really good at prototyping I don't want
a to my own horn so much but it I find
that because it's so small and you can
just include it in a page and basically
define how a flow should happen entirely
in JavaScript and low templates and do
that stuff I've used it in a large
number of cases
in my team when I can't I'm not a very
good I'm not I'm not very good at
talking I don't know if who knows that
but I explained I'm better at explaining
things through pictures and through
through actually real workflows and I do
that with my team all the time where
I'll say oh you're supposed to click on
this and then it goes to this page and
then it redirects back here or oh you're
supposed to have this form on this page
and logs in and it should show you this
you can do that and prototype that in
Sami without touching a server and just
having an index HTML template that you
vote in the browser and if you're a
JavaScript developer that you know can
work with just that then it's really
great as a tool for that it's really not
great for complex data or complex
behavioral challenges I mean you can use
it for that but it I I would not
probably use it for very very large apps
and it's also not for the developer who
needs conventions for everything if you
really want pattern to stick to and just
stick to it then it then go for it but
it helps my team and I do our job so
this is the new paperless post design
tool that we've worked on for a while
and one of the cool things that so so
Sammy is just a small piece of this like
there's a lot of going on here and
there's a lot of calls to the server and
there's a lot of client side templating
and all that stuff and Sammy really all
it handles is basically driving the
state of the application so you can kind
of see up in the URL probably not
actually but there's a path that has
kind of a sháá hatch at the end so the
way we work this is that the Shah hash
represents a tool state and what's going
on in the design tool and as things
change now as you update state the hash
changes and if you reloaded the page it
would go exactly back to the Play Store
in the design tool which is pretty cool
and it's great for that but the actual
methods of the tool and the way the tool
works and the interactivity Sammy
doesn't drive that it's really not our
entire app as I said it's it's and I
don't think any framework wherever will
ever be there's too many specific things
that we need that no framework solids
really well
and I think a framework with a framework
that we'd have to drive that would have
to drive the entire app would bind us
too much to a single philosophy and we
really like experimenting so this is
kind of a detour in the last piece but
the truth of work so the truth of work
is that it's really really really hard I
don't know about you but I like my job
but it's still really hard and good
developers what they want to do is make
their work easier and basically make
tools that make their jobs easier so
here I'm going to go in a little tangent
but a couple years ago we had this you
know transition where everyone started
calling themselves developers instead of
programmers and I tried to find the
source of where this really started and
I I couldn't track it down but there
were a couple mailing lists threads
about it in my 2003-2004 but at some
point where web developers not knock web
programmers and I think that's an
important distinction programmers make
machines work they're the guys who sit
behind a keyboard probably in one of
these vaults and you know tap the button
every every 40 minutes to make sure that
the world didn't explode and that's what
they did they just made the machines
work they programmed the machines to
make them work there wasn't really an
interaction ok yeah so sorry so you guys
get it that's it we're here so then this
guy's a developer um right he's like
building stuff he's going into the
ghetto with bulldozers and just knocking
it down right and building is bright new
brand new complex of of shiny apartment
buildings that rich white people can
live in with their dog so it's like that
sort of developer does he doesn't just
he doesn't just make a machine he isn't
drives a bulldozer in tight and just
going that that's what a programmer does
developer thumbs up I'm knocking down
entire cities
so what developers do is they build and
they bulldoze and recreate they they
they develop something they don't just
program it they recreated constantly and
they keep making it better that's the
end of the tangent but so what have we
lost sight of have we lost sight of what
we developed you know there's a lot I
mean we're here at Jay has come so
obviously we're talking about JavaScript
all weekend and it's really fun but what
is the core of what we are we do I mean
at least for most of us javascript isn't
our job working on the language of
JavaScript and working on frameworks in
our job there are a couple of people
here who are lucky enough to have that
job and a really good at it people who
you know work on node or work on
browsers and really they're their
product is the framework in that tool
itself for most of us most of us
frameworks are really just made to make
our jobs easier they're not the end goal
so they're really not our job so why are
we spending so much time talking about
them it's kind of weird I mean why am I
here for a half an hour talking about
them but really frameworks are there to
let them guide you and make your job
easier but really what they're supposed
to do is allow you to build something
awesome and that's my message to you
guys today is that you know it doesn't
matter what framework you use use
whatever you want and whatever makes
your job easier but the end result
should be that you're building something
awesome and there are tons of frameworks
that let you do that if you let them but
if you just argue about you know mine is
better than yours it's really just you
know it's really just a pissing contest
and it doesn't move the web and our
tools further and doesn't move us as
developers further so my goal as
developer is to bulldoze all those
housing projects of the web you know the
blink tag and everything and I'm going
to make a awesome site that does
something awesome for a lot of people
and is it the tool that I use to do that
doesn't really matter in the end the
users are going to be the ones who are
using it
and they're going to be excited and
they're really not going to know that
Sam ejs was behind it and they're not
going to care at all so but if you build
something awesome with it that's that's
the real that's the real goal so that's
my time thanks everybody I'll make you
finally after and won't drink beer