um today we're going to be talking about
a project I've been working on for about
six months in my free time it's been an
especially difficult project for me
because I don't have a computer science
background and it's kind of important
for this project because the goal is to
make updating filtered lists logarithmic
which could have the potential to
significantly speed up your applications
depending on how often you're filtering
lists right this is to do MBC I'm sure
lunch you recognize it so you know it's
the simplest app you could possibly
build right so we claim we're going to
make this app well not this app but
we're going to make the most commonly
used utility in this app and the most
commonly implemented feature across a
wide range of apps something that's so
common it's even in the to do MVC app
we're going to make it go from scaling
like this which is linear to something
like this which is logarithmic it's very
exciting stuff so here's how we're going
to do it first we're going to examine a
eight naive filter by feature
implementation we're just going to do it
as stupidly as we can we're not going to
rely on any tools we're not even write a
code but we're just going to do it and
it like as if we were just writing in
jquery and we didn't know any better
we're going to improve the performance
of this implementation using a small
diffing algorithm and then we're going
to kind of try and gauge how that's
going to scale over you know time and
then we're also going to take a tour of
our logarithmic filter algorithm that
I've been working on for six months at
the very end hopefully we'll have time
to actually demo our implementation so
that's cool let's get started so in
order to help visualize how the arrays
are being filtered and how memory is
being moved around and whatnot came up
with this kind of like template the goal
of the template is to kind of give us a
an understanding of where we're spending
the most time and how how it's changing
as we go from the original update of a
filtered list to the update of our Dom
so on the left here see we have this
kind of like objects land section
operations that occur here cost one unit
of time on the right you'll see there
Dom land operations that occur there
cost 10 units of time it's mostly
arbitrary it's just chosen for the sake
of argument inside of object land you'll
notice we have kind of two columns there
one of them is our to-do list this would
be like you're just raw list of all of
the to do's and that map like to do MVC
this is the unfiltered list of to do's
and then the second column being
completed this is our filtered list of
completed to juice so only to do is ever
completed we'll wind up the missus and
finally on the far right in dom land
there's a node list and this is what
would be in the browser representing the
the completed version of the to-do list
right yes cool most importantly in the
bottom right you'll notice there's this
little cost counter so as we start to
conduct operations on these lists and
this Dom we're going to kind of keep
track of what it's costing us in order
to do so cool so um let's get started oh
also one quick note what we're going to
start from this point right we're going
to start with an existing list of to
do's we're assuming we already have it
like a member you don't have to go do
some async requests and build it and
then we're also going to start with its
filter counterpart the completed list
right so we already know that these two
items are will be filtered out of the
main to do this list and then we're also
going to start with our rendered Dom
elements already the reason we're doing
it like this is because everything that
happened before this can't be optimized
it just is what it is and I just hope
that you all trust me on that
let's see so we're going to update this
list on the left to do's by adding the
new item to it called run so now we have
hop skip and jump and run escape is the
only one that's not completed by adding
this run element or item to the to-do
list we really have to refill tur
completed right so what will first have
to do is ask are all the elements in
completed and then afterwards we can
start filtering through the unfiltered
to-do list so look something like this
first we'll hip hop hop is completed so
we'll copy it over to the completed list
skip is not completed so it will not be
copied over jump is run is notice the
cost is going up every time we have that
little red circle touch one of these
elements in the list so now we have our
completed two dues list everything's
been filtered and this is you know we're
halfway there to getting what we wanted
you just got to get it into the Dom but
we already have a couple items in the
Dom so we're gonna have to empty it and
that's kind of expensive we just notice
on the bottom right there we like
increased 20 units because there's two
items in there we remove those two items
it's 10 units per operations or up to 20
units just for that one little thing
it's kind of expensive but hey we're
just you know building a filtered list
we don't really care about performance
right now so now we can start rebuilding
that Dom list so represents the
completed list so we'll start iterating
that and then as we do we'll add those
elements to the node list all together
over the course of this entire updating
of the filtered list I'm sorry of the
to-do list and rendering the filtered
variation we somehow got up to 55 units
of cost so this is our baseline all we
have to do is really improve upon that
and I notice some wasteful stuff while
we are doing that I think we can
probably pretty easily drop it down some
so the first thing that I noticed
that when we were refill Turing the
completed list after the to do's like
the run to do was added we unnecessarily
removed these two items hop and jump
because we were kind of starting over
from scratch right and that was really
necessary because we had to go back to
the original to-do list and reevaluate
each of those and then put them right
back where they were so there was no
real change from the time that they were
first there when we started updating the
filth the to-do list and after we've
updated the to-do list so really all
that changed in the end was that we're
going to add a run element to the end of
the completed list but in doing that it
costs us three units which you know
maybe not too bad but yeah it's
something the next thing we noticed is
that when we were rebuilding the node
list and we're updating the node list to
represent our new completed list we had
to like I said invest 20 units just to
empty the thing out and start over that
was really expensive but then also
putting the items back in was really
expensive 20 units per and again these
elements didn't change we took them out
we put them back in and they're exactly
the same after so it was kind of like
unnecessary if we had touch them at all
everything would have just been fine but
we did and so it costs us if you were to
kind of break down what we thought was
necessary and not necessary what you'll
find is that 12 of the units were
absolutely necessary and 43 of those
units we just invested were completely
unnecessary that's very very very
inefficient so we we know of a way to
improve upon this right we've seen
diffing algorithms and to speed things
up by by moving some of the computation
over into object land instead right this
is the kind of thing we want we just
want to know what changed and then once
we know what changed then we can just
update the dumb as efficiently as
possible so let's give it a run right so
we're going to go back to the beginning
we're going to update the to-do list
right
add that run item in doing that we're
going to filter the to do's all right we
got to update that filtered list but
this time instead of just like dumping
the completed list and starting from
scratch we're going to save a reference
to the completed list or i call it
previous completed i ran out of space
there then we could kind of discard the
completed list and start rebuilding or
refill turing from the to-do list all
right so we'll hit hop again hop is
included skip is not jump is run is
excellent so now we have our new
completed list we have a reference or
old completed list now we can actually
start doing some dipping and hopefully
update the Dom much faster or in total
spend less units accomplishing the same
test right so that's let's begin with
the diff really simple we're just going
to traverse the lists together
simultaneously we're going to visit each
of the note of the items so first we're
going to visit the first I've been
completed in the first item in the
previous completed and we're going to
compare them see if they're the same
they're the same cool we can keep on
going jump and jump again the same
nothing needs to be done here this where
we get to run run is new and in their
previous completed list we did not have
that so this is you know a change that
we have to actually apply so we're going
to patch the Dom the node list with this
change so just to get there we were up
like eight units not bad but we haven't
done anything in dom land so we're doing
pretty good let's update the dom with
the new item the run item which the diff
informed us we need to move over 10
units we knew we're gonna have to do
that no big deal and here we are we've
accomplished the same thing and we're at
18 units which is a huge improvement
over what we previously did we could see
here now what we see is that we only had
about six units of wasted effort right
because 12 was what we absolutely needed
to move the to update the to-do list and
then to move that node into a filtered
list and then to move that filtered item
into our Dom nodes are yes our noblest
so the question though is did our
solution that we just implements scale
right can we can we rely on this being
like ultra fast and performance even
when were you know doing hundreds of
thousands of items if that were the case
of our browsers couldn't handle that
kind of stuff so we're going to scale
the example up entirely instead of three
initial items will have 30 initial items
and instead of one of those items not
being complete there will be 10 of those
items that aren't complete similarly
instead of doing one update we're going
to do ten updates right so if we go
through this and I don't diagram it all
out for you I just do some little math
on a notepad here and we come to this
conclusion find out that if we were
doing that many items we are wasting 600
units of work not really accomplishing
anything the only really important
things that actually mattered that word
that like could not go without were
these 120 operations so it's like super
inefficient and there's room for
improvement there right so we can keep
on going ideally we would do something
else let's take a look at what I ideal
approach would look like so now we're
going to go through this whole process
again we're going to implode the run
item to the dues list something is going
to happen we don't know what but it's
going to be probably more efficient we
want it to be more efficient anyway and
we're somehow going to get be able to
tell that hey we should move this one
item in to-do list or into the completed
list cool and that would only cost us
one unit that would be great if we can
figure that out really quickly then we
want to do it again basically right we
want to in some way shape or form figure
out how we can update the node list and
Dom land without a whole lot of overhead
and and get our fantastic result and
that would only cost of 12 units like we
can't really make it any faster than
that right we just copied the exact item
over but it's not really like that
simple right we can't just copy that one
item over and
say it was that easy because it's really
not trivial the run item was added to
the to do list here but we don't really
know at what index we should put it in
the completed list you know we can do
some work to figure it out but then
again we're just doing more work right
like there's not we're not gaining
anything we're just changing the style
of work maybe instead of refill turing
the list we're just going to iterate and
search through the completed list and
find an insertion point that's not
saving us anything with stuff to do that
work and if it seems like you know maybe
I'm overcomplicating it try really
quickly to figure out where this item
belongs in its filter variation it's not
super obvious I mean you can figure it
out but it's going to take you a couple
seconds and have to write a program to
do the same amount of work it's also
going to be inefficient right okay so
this is where I decide to get clever
where you have to think outside of the
array brackets and or box after many
failed attempts and a bunch of help for
my co-workers I learned that no matter
how I try to work with these arrays I'm
not going to be able to update them
quickly or efficiently but if we look at
red black binary trees they offer a
couple properties that we can maybe take
advantage of and i'm not sure if any of
you guys are aware of how these work or
remember how they work for me i had to
learn them so they're fresh on my mind
but i'll give you a quick run-through on
how they how they work so first we add
like the first item in our to-do list
into the tree and this becomes a root
node next we try to add the next item
the next item would be skip it had an
index of one so we'll compare this new
item we're putting into the tree against
the root node and you see here that skip
has a value of one because that's its
index in the to do list and then hop has
an index of zero so one vs 0 we need to
put skip to the right of hop so that's
what the tree does that's
tastic now what happens is we want to
put in a third item right and so jump
tries to go in it's cotton and X 2 hops
got the index of zero we compare them
and then the cool thing above tree is
that it basically does the same exact
operation but on in the next node and
the next node in the next node until it
runs out of places to search to compare
nodes and it just assumes this is where
I belong right because I used logic and
reasoning to get here so jump compares
itself with skip and it says I've got to
go to the right of that fantastic so one
of the beauties of binary trees is that
they drastically reduce the cost of
operations on them like insert and
remove or find because you don't have to
visit every item in the tree right so we
can kind of just like split the size of
the data set like in half every time we
kind of try to find that information
which is super helpful but in order for
that to happen the red black tree has to
balance itself right it right now this
is like a 3 3 tier or tree or like that
has a depth of 3 nodes and so I would
have to compare myself against two nodes
to get to the third one but if we
rebalance rotate you know now the depth
is much more shallow and in order to
find the note i can find it in one
operation instead of two right this is
constantly happening as you're adding
elements to the tree it's just it's it's
a very efficient and it's a really
clever design so then the question
becomes how do we use these red black
trees Lloyd black binary trees to filter
arrays because that's kind of not what
they're designed to do initially so
we'll take a look at our model again
this is um this is the algorithm right
the results of the algorithm and it
comes in a couple different parts and
they're really intricate little bits and
pieces I hope you guys can see it but
I'm going to go walk through it like
step by step and kind of show you all
the different little moving parts so
this would look like when it's done
right look on the Left we see we've got
the to do list it's already got the run
item in it
we've got this thing called the
predicate tree it's in the center area
below that is a pleated tree and on the
right is the node list that we're
familiar with so all we really did was
take out this filtered array that was in
the center and we replace it with these
two trees okay so let's look at the
predicate tree the predicate tree has
two primary roles for every item in the
to do's list there's going to be a node
in the predicate tree so it like
maintains a one-to-one relationship
obviously they're structured differently
to do this list has like indexes and
they're all one after another and then
this tree has this kind of strange
pyramid shape and has no indexes blood
but that's his job the predicate tree
just make sure that it has all the same
items that's to do the tree to do this
list has also if you were to be more
generic we would just call that the
source list because this can be applied
to any any less obviously the next thing
that it's meant to do is match the order
of the to-do list so if items are moved
around or added to the beginning or Matt
at the end it's it's going to match that
to like it has to say one hundred
percent in sync with the bolt they order
the number of items so on and so forth
perfect the predicate functions nodes so
the squares in sorry not the pretty the
predicate tree the nodes in the
predicate tree hold on to something
called the predicate result the word
predicate I don't know if everybody
knows what that means it's probably find
it like lodash documentation or
underscore documentation it's the
function that you use to compare against
each item so if you said to do is that
filter function if completed return true
and everything that returns true is
going to be in your filtered list at
that function that you pass to the
filter method that was your predicate
function it's used to determine if the
item should or should not be included so
the predicate tree has the
responsibility of holding on to the
result of that function but it also can
be made to
bind to its source item right so if my
source item changes so for instance if
hop got renames to hopping that
predicate function can rerun and make a
decision about how to proceed so that's
kind of a neat thing to do cool keep
going I think that's right the second a
tree and our algorithm here is the
completed tree it looks a lot like the
predicate tree except it's missing some
some nodes the print the completed tree
contains only nodes a Soviet associated
with items that were filtered from the
to do's in this case right so this is
this tree only has items that we want in
our filtered result set okay simple it's
just our filtered list but it has like
this kind of one nuance it has
references to its sister nodes in the
predicate tree right so you see these
little asterisks that I have in each
node that's just meant to represent that
any one of these nodes can very easily
get access to that predicate tree and
potentially traverse it if it wanted to
I'll call those sister nodes so the
nodes of both trees have a couple things
in common they're not 100% unique
between the two of them each one of them
each one of the trees is nodes maintains
a left count a right count and a gap
count and what that means is if you look
at the skip item kind of the right of
the false you've got this colon you've
got one pipe zero pipe too so the one
implies that there's one item to the
left of it 0 implies that there is no
gap to the left of it so like if you
were to create an array where you put an
item at zero index and then you put an
item at the third index you just created
a gap in between those two right so
using a left count and a left gap count
we can calculate what the index of that
node is right so with a left count of
one and
no gap we can easily assume that this
node is that the first index but the
important thing there is that we didn't
have to like store that information we
can calculate it on demand at any time
another thing that each node has is a
reference to its left child so for
instance skip has a reference to hop you
can see that pen through the lines there
and then it has a reference to its right
child assuming it has one similar on the
right skip has a reference to jump and
then also its able to implement a linked
list a doubly linked list so this hop
I'm sorry I don't actually have an
example here but essentially if you had
two leaves that had split apart right
and then they'd come back together and
the furthest rightmost node in this leaf
and the furthest leftmost node in this
leaf they're not actually sharing a
child or a parent directly but we can
still relate the two using a linked list
which is just fun and then the other
most important thing is that each one of
the nodes in both lists I'm sorry both
trees has a reference to its parent this
is super critical because waffle expect
later let's continue actually I think
that's everything cool that's all I
prerequisite algorithm teachings so
let's just review real quickly the
predicate tree has the predicate result
the true or false should this or should
this not be included in the resulting
filtered list and then the completed
tree has a reference to nodes sister
nodes in the predicate tree and every
one of the nodes within its own tree has
as a way of linking to other nodes in
the tree friends and siblings children
and parents cool
so I think we're ready to to actually
model the solution so we're going to
start with the same place where we
started before with the filtered list to
do's is just got the three elements in
it hop skip and jump and then we're
going to modify that right but in this
case we actually have a little bit more
infrastructure built around it the
predicate tree already has those three
nodes associated with the to do's items
hop skip and jump and also has metadata
about them with regards to their indexes
or their left counts and their gap
counts and then it also has already
solved for the predicate result so we
know true false and true yes it's um yes
hop is completed skip is not completed
jump is completed and then finally not
finally actually our completed tree has
references to the relevant nodes in
order to filter the news list right so
we have the hop node we have the jump
node they have their left and right
counts and their gaps and then they also
have their references to their sister
nodes in the predicate treat let's do
the update and see what happens we
insert the run item into the to-do list
just like we've been doing all along
when this happens the predicate tree
finds out and starts to insert the run
item into the tree now the run item
currently inside of the to-do list has
an index of 3 the skip item in the
predicate tree has an index of one we
were able to calculate that based on
this left count and it's gap count we're
going to compare those indexes and we're
going to say okay run has an index of 3
we have an index 1 we need to traverse
downward to the right so run is now
compared against the jump node because
we have a reference to our parent the
jump node can calculate my parents has a
left count of one my parent represents
one node in space and I'm the node after
it so I must be
in the number two index position right
so the run being in the third index jump
being in the second index we can
continue to insert to the right and
that's what happens the run item in the
to-do list wind up being a run node in
the predicate tree and you can see that
we got the predicate result here this is
going to be a true thing we do want this
in the filtered list our left count or
right counts and our gaap count or zero
because it's very lonely down there in
the bottom corner of that tree but
that's okay so now that the predicate
tree has been updated the completed tree
is going to catch wind of it and it's
going to say well I probably need to put
this in my tree let's see what the
predicate result was the predicate
result here was true and so we take the
index of the run node in predicate tree
which we've calculated as three and we
compare it against the calculated index
of the jump node in the completed tree
and we have three verses too but this is
actually a little more clever than it
looks because we have the reference to
the sister node and the predicate tree
right so we were using not the index of
jump in the completed tree for using the
index of jump in the predicate tree
while we're traversing the completed
tree so it's like where we're going to
make the operations on the completed
tree but the logic that we're using to
base our operate are our actions is
actually coming from the predicate tree
we're making decisions about how we're
going to interact with the completed
tree based on things outside of the
scope of the complete the tree which is
kind of cool so let's try this one more
time I'll make sure I get this across
the jump node in the completed tree has
a reference to the sister element in the
predicate tree that's the one whose
index we really care about right so we
want to put run in
the completed tree relative to where it
belongs in the two dudes list we can't
put it before jump we can't put it
before skip or we can put it before hop
so when we compare the run node to the
jump node in the completed tree the jump
node currently thinks it's in the first
position but we know better it's
actually in the second position so
that's why we've referred to the
predicate tree and that's why the
predicate trees sole responsibility is
to maintain at the same order as it's
useless and you may ask like that seems
unnecessary like why would you just
duplicate all this data you know we we
already know that jump is the second
item in the to-do list except when
except you don't actually know that and
the best way to solve for it is actually
industry where we can just kind of keep
crawling up the binary tree and
recalculating all these left counts and
gap counts it's much faster than like
starting on one end iterating towards
your item you know finding the item and
saying oh we kept track of our index and
that's called an index of all right so
we can put our run node into the
completed tree that's exciting and then
knowing that the run node was added into
the completed tree at the second index
we can very efficiently say hey add one
Dom node to the node list and Dom land
so let's take a look at it
now I've got a dash mirror let's do this
excellent okay cool you guys can see
this I'll start this over so this is an
example of a source list on the far left
it's made up of a couple of items with
some random numbers generated and then
on the right or from there on every one
of these is a filtered variation of this
source list so the first one is all even
items from the source list that can jizz
all items from the source list the third
is all items less than 50 from the
source list and then the fourth is all
items greater than 50 from the sources
so if we remember our original example
in order to solve for this we'd have to
call filter for x which means we'd have
to iterate source for x which means we'd
have to go do some pretty clunky Dom
manipulation four times for every change
that happens to the source so if I were
to do this we would notice an item was
added calculate calculate even calculate
calculate odd so on and so forth but
because of the binary trees it's really
super efficient like we said earlier
logarithmic so I can do something like
this and we notice no lag at all that
was really fast right and I can keep
doing this watch the dots count at the
top which is going to go and go and go
and we can type them have my repaint
rate at the bottom it's doing pretty
good now we will see to drop off just
because the cost of the repaints is you
know going to get greater and greater as
more dom nodes are added but we know for
sure that on the JavaScript side we are
we're not taking an exorbitant amount of
extra time to accomplish it fast also we
can randomize all the items in the list
just jam on that and this is filtering
over and over and over and over and over
again every single time we change a
number on the left list it's filtering
and that would typically be really
expensive but it's not anymore let's go
to react this is react sorting the same
kind of lists right we've got the source
list even odd less than 50 greater than
50 forget
how many nodes we have here yeah it's
100 notes oh cool so let's bounce this
up to a thousand nodes so let's curl you
so you can see react struggling through
this list and it's a it's changing every
one of the numbers and we can't really
see it outside the screen but they
filtered lists that are based on where
that are derived from that source list
are updating removing items from them
adding items back in removing atoms
adding items from the items and it's
it's using our native array filter in
order to accomplish that right it's in a
pretty good job here's can derive the
project that I've been working on doing
the exact same thing it's managing to do
it at 50 frames a second though which is
a whole lot cooler let's go back to camp
to react this is 30 frames a second this
is 50 frames a second here's what
happens when we take the Dom out of the
equation we're just going to not display
any of these items well Oh a little bit
here
why aren't they hiding out so I'm not
thinking
ok now the Dom nodes are actually being
influenced but they're not being
repainted on the screen so this is
happening really fast if you guys can
see it's like 120 frames a second and
something like that or 120 operations a
second reacts doing the exact same thing
unfortunately it's limited by how fast
dot filter can chug through those items
and it really can't go any faster even
though the render is like you know
really intelligent and can make a lot of
smart decisions the filtering is what's
going to slow it down it can't go any
faster it still has to go through a
thousand items four times every time
single time there's a change and then
having do that means that items are
going to added remove from the Dom so on
and so forth so this is this is the
project I've been working on for six
months that's all I have to present for
you you guys have questions I'd love to
hear them it's sometimes really excited
about hopefully I'm gonna be releasing
it to you if you want to take a look at
it it's in a repo called can derive the
reason it's built on top of kin is
because we want to be able to observe
lists and maps and then also the
objective for the can drive project is
not specifically just to filter list the
goal is to make it super efficient to
update all sorts of data transform so
Maps group by and even sorting which is
a whole other conversation but anyway
thanks a lot guys I appreciate you