I'm just going to talk to you about low
friction development and what I mean by
low friction development is I'm going to
share some experiences that we've had
transitioning our our development from
lamp stack onto old JavaScript and to
end I hope it's going to be interesting
to you I hope maybe you'll there'll be
something in it if you take away so my
name is Peter Alta i'm co-founder of a
company called betta pond and we do
social media applications branded social
media applications primarily on on
facebook i like i like simple things i
heard a guy this morning talking about
how he like simple things i agree simple
things are great I've been doing
software for a good while now initially
in very very kind of low level c c++
stuff in kind of nuclear fusion research
and moving across into other areas telco
as well then i got enlightened on
JavaScript a couple of years ago that it
was in fact this really incredibly
powerful language and not a lot to kind
of toy language in a browser and I've
kind of grown in my my appreciation of
it and how it can be used to solve
problems and and that's culminated in us
now moving all the development
development from our company across from
from a lamp stack onto end-to-end
JavaScript and the approach we taken to
do that is to is to leverage as much of
the existing tools are available but
build our own very lightweight framework
this specifically tailored for doing
social up dev and just a quick aside I
heard a guy this morning talking about
he was talking about how it's really
good to learn lots of languages and I
have to agree with that the structure of
the languages that we use affects the
way we think and I think that's
particularly particularly true in in
JavaScript as you can see there's a
bunch of guys probably bit on myself
that have been developing
high-performance service for years
thinking about mutexes semaphores block
like kind of stuff and they're suddenly
something comes along that does it
differently because it has a different
tool set I think that's that's in a very
interesting and so learning lots of
languages is good so what I'm going to
want to talk about I want to talk a
little bit about the problems that we
have I'm going to talk about the the
sources of friction that we experienced
in our development that gave us gave us
the question how are you doing things I
can talk about the the range of options
that are available to us and then what
we did I'm afraid I don't have too many
flashy generals or anything like that so
I hope you're not too disappointed with
that so we need to rapidly develop
branded social apps and by those by
brainless social apps what I mean is
some examples here and so this would be
an example one for the Royal Wedding
predictor we can go on and predict the
royal wedding what what was going on the
day what dress they'd wear or another
example would be New Orleans tourist
board where you can where we're giving a
am a leader board of based on check-ins
of the top attractions in the town so
it's tying tying bits of data base from
location-based stuff into social media
and now that that means that we have a
lot of apps that you need to run most of
them have a very short life lifetime
maybe two three months something like
that they're all pretty much single page
Ajax apps and we need to run run lots of
them lots of little apps and each one
will usually experience a fairly fairly
sharp traffic spike depending on the
media spending that happens and then of
course on the viral sharing on social
networks will give us a spike of
trafficking we need to handle as well
and we need to go faster handle more
traffic with less effort i guess nobody
really wants to go slow and no one
really want to handle less traffic and
weather but we particularly feel it
because because of the nature of the the
applications that we're developing
so sources of frictions we experienced
in in developing these types of apps was
as you know that the typical lamp stack
requires five languages so you HTML CSS
JavaScript SQL and what have your server
language of choices and and I've heard
those described as being well you know
SQL is like a box and maybe your mid
tier language is a triangle and your
JavaScript your browser is a circle and
they just don't really fit together and
tessellate didn't fit and so there's
definitely a mental discount that occurs
when you're moving across tears building
applications and that can slow you down
and that in my experience causes teams
to break down into front-end back-end
specialists along those language lines
and that causes friction and development
as well because what it means is that
your front-end guys are often waiting
for for mid tier or database guys to do
stuff I don't speak the same languages
and wait for you to finish or for you or
and that causes blockages of course
relational databases once they're great
for in a lot of areas they're not a fit
for what we're trying to do and you they
introduce the burden of schema
maintenance and management we also find
that server template in gets in the way
of designer styling show everyone here
is experience that problem so we became
aware of the whole new range of
technology that's out there based on
JavaScript sono sul stores obviously
note that Jas and all the associated
modules client libraries in the
frameworks that are available is a huge
range of mail there now attempting
engines animagic managed cloud hosting
is a whole bunch to choose from excuse
me and some of them worked and fitted
with what we wanted to do and some of
them didn't fit exactly right so we took
the approach of we want to keep things
really really simple I like simple I
like to build things really simply
because I find that that's the way that
you're going to get stuff done
over the long term we definitely didn't
want any any server temper team because
we needed to get styling done quickly
and not get in the way of that we wanted
a model whether we pulled pages together
on the client and we want it we having
looked at the sources of friction that
we were experiencing we felt that doing
end-to-end JavaScript would be an
approach that would work for us so in
order to do that we put together a very
light lean framework based on top of
node and and jQuery on front-end and so
what we built out was on the server on
top of nodejs a very thin no SQL driver
layer and a very lightweight controller
and model structure a simple and
consistent file system layout for the
applications controllers responding with
them with Jason tation review references
and all of our static assets everything
static so all of the views to be served
down statically no server-side
templating and on the client very
lightweight controllers binding to the
Dom models connecting to back-end logic
let lazy loaded views and we're not
mandating any particular widget
incurring work so let me just give you a
quick view of that that's a very very
simple architecture I think it was a
very simple architecture outlined this
morning simple is good the request
response cycle we put together is very
very simple we just do a get or post in
forum data the server then is going to
return us data in one stream and the
view as a static asset to be rendered on
the client so what we're doing is we're
pushing a lot of that rendering off
client-side and so we've reflected that
in the structure of the application
layout we've got in this breakdown here
at the top level we've got controllers
and models that run server side and then
under public we've got controllers and
models that run client-side
so that they're different beasts on the
one side you're controlling and binding
into the Dom sending requests up server
side you are then forwarding on
connections into an SQL store and then
data being sent back down with static
views that are rendered on the client
and then of course acceptance and unit
testing baked in as well we have a very
very simple configuration structure we
would have a global config just pointing
to where all the applications live and
then for each application we would
configure a name and then any other
specific social stuff that we need to
plug in there so we have particular
modules and so forth and so on with
Facebook that we need to to use we found
this has really been helpful to us and
it's reduced the number of languages
that are guys need to writing down to
three languages so it's JavaScript end
to end the whole scheme of three scheme
of free pictures has helped us a lot and
it means that we're not maintaining
models we can go a lot faster and we can
do the design a lot quicker when it's
when it's template free and early
results are that we're getting obviously
still going very very quickly for us we
can divert the applications a lot
quicker we're avoiding all of the mental
context switching and we're getting a
lower operational costs because we are
we are not having to run so many so many
server instances and okay that's it I
think I've kind of caught up on the time
and I hope that was kind of useful we
think the JavaScript stack is early
stage obviously but we think it can
become the universal language
application development both client and
and server side and I have to I'm
learning an awful lot here so so thanks
thanks so much of your time and any
questions sure
I haven't we haven't released it open
source yet because we've got some there
are some bits of it that a proprietary
that we need to take out we're going to
be open sourcing it hopefully if not
next week the week after we're looking
to put it out it can sometimes like a
bit clunky but if you're rendering
within Facebook most most of the loan is
clunky anyway right so the outside frame
is loading clunky right so it doesn't
really really matter too much people are
fairly fairly understanding about it in
that context I think in different
contexts it might not be quite the same
but the rendering is pretty quick these
days anyway right that's good sure okay
thanks for watching time guys appreciate