alright thanks for coming to this talk
it seems to be my luck that at
conferences I'm often up against people
i admire at the same time in the other
room and that is the case here you
should definitely check out James long's
works on ensuite je s macros for
JavaScript since we came to this talk
and you're missing that but since you
did come to this talk I think you're in
for a treat I'm going to talk about a
project called regenerator which is an
effort to take one of the really cool I
think the coolest feature of the next
version of JavaScript acma script 6 and
simulate it using javascript of today so
you can go ahead and use that feature
from the future in the present or in a
browser more to the point i'm ben newman
and i work at facebook a release
regenerator with my my team at facebook
which is the javascript infrastructure
team and we have been maintaining it
actively so it's not just thrown over
the wall if you want to talk to me
specifically in following up on any of
this stuff or just get to know me i'm
benjamin without the eye on most forms
of social media as you can see there so
when we released regenerator wrote up
this sort of call to action page and
posted it up on hacker news and got into
like the top five and the the comments
were all really surprisingly
appreciative there was very little
backlash and one of the things I think
went well about this launch is that it's
it signals just from a headline like
this that you might need to have or want
to have a little bit of context a little
bit of experience with the idea of
generator functions before you have an
opinion about you know the way we did it
was correct or the best way of doing it
and so I I live in New York and one of
our local meetups is Brooklyn j/s at the
last instance of Brooklyn jas Brittany
sister Rose gave a talk about technical
writing and she gave me a term that that
now sort of helps me conceptualize this
this idea so you have low context and
high context audience members and you
can write in different ways and you
should write in different ways when your
audience comes in with some context
versus when they come in with much
context and so I'm making a bet that
jayus conf and the group of people who
have come to this talk stand the best
chance of having a little bit of context
around these issues of anyone anywhere
so I hope you don't mind if I abuse you
with what I would consider to be a
pretty technical talk there's a lot of
code and I would just encourage you if
you if you want to follow along at all
look at the slides read along with the
code as I'm talking about it otherwise
if I'm just talking about it and you
know you haven't been looking you may
find yourself lost which is totally fine
i'll try to change the tone of my voice
when there's something like sort of
independently interesting and you know
maybe you can get back on the the path
but with that warning out of the way so
calls to action right are something we
often feel like issuing when we've built
something that we're proud of we think
other people should use it we think it's
a better way of doing things then the
way things have been done in the past
and we want to tell ourselves that we
and everybody else should have been
doing it this way all along and github
is indeed littered with better ways of
doing things really better ways for
someone of doing something
that never quite caught on and why is
that well I would claim that in addition
to having a bright idea about how you
ought to have done something from the
beginning you can't just go back and
start over from scratch if you could it
would be easy to do it the right way
from scratch but they're also you also
have to have a second clever idea which
is how to get from where you are right
now with the the application stack that
you've inherited to that new place that
is as if you started from scratch with
all the right ideas so there has to be a
way forward not just backwards and then
forwards again and I would go I would go
further to claim that programming
languages are notoriously difficult in
this way they're difficult to fix
forward so if i can ask inflammatory
question that may not be so inflammatory
here because this is a JavaScript and
not a Python conference what why is it
it's been since 2008 and Python 3 is
definitely a better language in a lot of
ways than Python 2 and Python 2 is one
of the most successful programming
language in the history of programming
languages why is it that big projects
haven't switched to python 3 Django for
instance and so I don't know how many
people have used python of any version
in the room almost everyone maybe eighty
ninety percent how many people have
written a line of Python 3 that runs in
production all right all right we can
walk away from this discussion okay so I
don't want to go into this too much but
Python 3 is a lot of new features some
of which are fairly trivial to switch
over to they have a two to three script
to convert your print keywords to print
function since that's so like small
cosmetic thing that changed but there
are also differences in the semantics of
like Unicode handling in Python 3 that
are definitely the right way to do
things like byte strings in Python 2 or
a source of a lot of trouble but you
can't just switch one day and start
using that feature of Python 3 and
because it's one big language that you
have to start use
in all at once you've got to sort of
swallow the things that are difficult to
swallow along with savoring the things
that you actually want so to bring this
back to what we care about how can echo
script six which is the technical
standards name for the next version of
JavaScript avoid this trap the Python 3
trap if you will so my crazy idea which
I'm giving myself too much credit to
call my idea but it's something I've
become passionate about in the last year
or so is that we might be able to ease
ourselves into the new version of the
language by simulating its most useful
features in the current version of the
language right so why would we want to
do that obviously there's a cost to
simulating features and if you could
just switch to the next version of the
language native support for all those
things and wouldn't you be better off
well i think that the insight here is
that at every step of this process you
have this like perfect hybrid of the old
language and the new that suits your
needs exactly and you know exactly why
you've adopted each of its features you
get to prove them out even before
they're fully standardized and you you
just you know that the language you're
using is the language you want to be
using and there aren't these like hidden
dragons that you're going to have to
confront at some point so a phrase that
I might have come up with for this is
linguistic time-travel we're reaching
into the future and selectively taking
parts of the future a future of
JavaScript bringing them into JavaScript
of today so what's an example
well this is not generated related this
is a sort of simpler but also cool
feature of ECMO script six arrow
functions are a nice way of writing you
know the hundreds of little throwaway
callback functions that you need to
write in JavaScript so you get to do
away with the function keyword and you
can just have an expression instead of a
whole curly brace delimited body with a
return statement in it so these two
things are equivalent if you're running
a six but there's a fairly
straightforward translation from the
futuristic syntax to the syntax of today
and if you find these slides online
you'll see that this is all sort of live
editable in case you want to play with
it and see how it works and now I've
ruined it oh well okay so how does that
work well we've got a tool chain that we
have to face book that I've worked on
and that is open source it actually
predates my time at Facebook started
working on it when i worked at quora
it's called recast and it has some
utilities for traversing what are called
abstract syntax trees which are these
sort of object graph representations of
your code and ways of telling what type
of node you're looking at and also ways
of building up new kinds of nodes so you
call recast at parse with a string of
code that gives you back this tree and
then you need to modify the tree hope
you can see this the slides are at
Benjamin without the idea hub I 0 / jazz
camp 2014 if you want to pull that up ok
so we're traversing the tree starting at
the root of it which is typically like
the program type node and this callback
function is going to be called on every
node and we just want to only do
anything for the arrow function
expression it's because we're going to
try to get rid of those and turn them
into plain old good old-fashioned
functions so we grabbed the body of the
arrow function expression if we find one
and if it's an expression function that
is it doesn't have a curly brace block
statement body with a return statement
in it we want to turn it into
one of those because expression
functions are not legal until we have
xmas cryptic so I guess that's a another
feature that we're supporting here and
then we want to create a new function
expression using all the same properties
as the arrow function expression
basically the only thing that's
different is the the type this function
expression now instead of arrow function
expression and then one of the
conveniences of arrow functions is that
they automatically bind to the value of
this in the enclosing environment so we
have to simulate that as well so we're
going to make a member expression out of
our function expression and the
identifier bind and call that as a
method passing this to it right and then
all that remains is to replace the
original arrow function expression with
this bound expression and then you call
recast I'd print with that same abstract
syntax tree grab the little code
property off of the object that it
returns and print that however you want
or write it to a file and it prints out
the thing that we were trying to create
cool so that's sort of a warm-up example
of transforming code at the abstract
syntax tree level and if you already
have a build stuff for static resources
you can have this newfound ability in a
matter of minutes if you use browserify
or some other static build pipeline so
what is this recast thing well I came up
with the name when I first wrote it I
thought it was clever because it
recursively traverses abstract syntax
trees so wreck AST sort of makes sense
at that level but it's also a word an
english verb which means to like melt
some metal down and reshape it or you
know arrange something again remodel
supply a theater work with a new cast
sort of thing so i also like to think it
has some poetry to it so how do you use
recast just to recap you require it you
call recast at parts on the source and
then you get to do literally anything
you want with the abstract syntax tree
recast
care it does bundle suggested traversal
tool but you really don't even have to
use that and I'm not even super thrilled
with it so I recommend you find anything
that works and then you call recast up
print with the modified abstract syntax
tree and you know do whatever you want
with the resulting string so that's
that's how it goes and what's magical
about this like you could just pretty
print the result and that would give you
working code you'd be able to use Eknath
script six today which is part of the
promise here but there's another
property of recast that's pretty cool
that's I think best described as
non-destructive partial source
transformation so it will try to use
reuse original source code for parts of
the tree that you didn't modify which is
cool both because it lets you write
transforms and then generate human
readable diffs and I've done this to
great success in my job at Facebook and
because since the printer knows where
those original fragments of source code
are coming from can actually give you
really good source maps for free totally
automatically for any arbitrary abstract
syntax tree transform you might want to
write so if you like source maps that
might be pretty appealing so this
presents a moral hazard of sorts you can
start writing scripts that you know
rearrange the furniture in your code
base ad nauseam and appear to be you
know the most productive program or
anyone has ever seen and the laziest at
the same time or you can in the Gandhian
sense be the change you want to see in
the world and I my confession is that I
gave in to that temptation the first
temptation for a time there was a couple
of weeks or months at work where I had
written a script that would translate a
lot of old idioms for defining classes
in JavaScript in our code base to the
new ekman script six class syntax and I
was just running it over tens of
thousands of files coming in in the
morning and like you know spending five
minutes or so doing that and then like
waiting for humans to review those gifts
and it's remarkable both the people to
review them and that in a lot of cases
they didn't realize that this had
actually been generated by a script
the beauty of recast and all told I only
converted sixteen hundred or so files
for like a combined hundred fifty
thousand insertions and deletions worth
of diff and I guess you can tell from
this we have about one class per file so
1658 classes the cool thing is that we
now have 3,500 almost 3,600 classes in
the code base today and you know you
know that those extra classes got
written by people who just looked around
at the code base that had been sort of
boot strapped into the new style and
they did what they found everywhere else
they mimicked the style as you should do
in any large code base so that's the
real value of this kind of automatic
source transformation if you get nothing
outside of this talk there's a cool unix
tool called parallel that lets you write
really simple as you know
single-threaded scripts that take one
argument and then run a whole bunch of
copies of them appropriate for you know
the number of cores I've 32 cores and I
my def machine at facebook so i was able
to do something like 230 sort of
subjected seconds worth of work in 12
seconds so that's cool i give a whole
talk actually about this project a
couple of months ago so these these
links will take you there ok so what
about something little trickier as
promised we are going to talk about
generator functions so here's an example
of a generator function and I apologize
that it's not like Fibonacci or
something like that it's a little bit
more sophisticated this had all of the
things that I wanted to talk about in it
so that's why I chose this function for
printing out the or rather yielding each
of the permutations of a given list so I
did look this out to remind myself how
to do this ah so the way it works is if
the list is just 1 or 0 elements that's
the only permutation of the list so you
yield that otherwise you take the list
consisting of just the first element in
the list and then you take all the
permutations of the rest of the list and
for each of those child permutations you
sort of walk the first element
it at each place so you you know none of
those permutations contain that element
but then you put it back in at each
possible place and so when you yield
each of those things you're yielding all
the possible permutations of the list
and here's an example of how you might
use it with the list 132 and get some
water so if you're used to generator
functions in Python you may not be used
to the next method of the generator
object returning little object that has
a value field and a done field but
that's the API that we've decided on for
Agnes crypt 6 so in each of those cases
the value is one of the permutations and
done would be false but then at the very
end done is true and the value is
undefined so that's that's what that's
about there's also another syntax for a
prettier syntax for iterating over the
values of a generator the four of loop
so it's easy to confuse this with 4n but
iterates over the values of its argument
instead of the keys
so how hard could it be to translate
this futuristic syntax into something
that runs in a browser today well this
was like May of 2013 I thought it was
funny to tweet cryptically about having
almost finished my life's work and boy
was that hubris because I wasn't
anywhere close to being done the project
was actually called degenerate at that
point sort of self-deprecating is my
style i guess and i was i was so far
away from being anywhere on top of this
project that i'm glad i didn't actually
identify in this tweet what what i was
talking about it's basically the
trickiest code I've ever written which
may say more about me than the code
itself but I also think it's bad as
tricky as translation or source
transformation gets so if you absorb any
of this then that's great you've
absorbed you know something that is
probably the best example of a really
nasty source to source transformation
and you can do anything at that point
okay so here's our original function and
what's the first step well it's going to
turn out to be convenient if we take all
of the variable declarations from inside
of this function and waste them to the
the top of the function which is
something that JavaScript does anyway so
first PSP and i are now declared at the
first line of the function and wherever
they used to be variable declarations
those are just assignment statements
right so why do we do that why does that
matter that doesn't actually change
anything yet well then introduce a
couple more variables some temporary
variables and a loop variable I yeah
okay the reason for that t0 and t1 is
that we're going to turn the four of
loop just into a while loop so that we
can treat it the same way as any other
while loop so if you if you see 4p of PS
it's now going to change into this call
to the values function of our little
runtime object wrap generator and then
just going to iterate over that
generator calling next until it's done
and each
time it will assign the value to the
loop variable P so now we've got a plain
old while lib don't have to care about
four of loops anymore okay so still
haven't really changed anything still
have yield expressions and it's still a
generator but now we're going to return
a an anonymous generator that doesn't
take any arguments it's just a closure
that has all of those variables in its
scope and so now now we're beginning to
get somewhere and so this is a big leap
but we need to turn the body of this
function into something that can execute
in JavaScript of today and my idea for
how to do that is to have a switch
statement inside of a wild true loop
where the cases of the switch statement
are jump targets that we can sort of
jump to as if we had a go-to statement
in JavaScript which sounds like the
worst thing in the world but ends up
being pretty cool so the first one is
case zero as you might imagine and this
is going to test to see what the length
of the list is if it's less than two
we're going to jump to case five and we
do that by setting contacts next to five
and then breaking which you'll note
breaks out of the switch statement but
not the while loop so we loop back
around for another iteration context
next is five and then case five will
come later you may remember in this case
that we wanted to yield the list itself
so the way we do that is by returning
the list so that's the answer to what
happens to the yield expression it
becomes a return statement but we want
to know where to come back to after we
call back into the the generator next
function so we've set context I next two
three in this case which is the next
case and if you remember in that case
after we yield that one value of the
list we're done so we're going to jump
all the way to the end which happens to
be a case 19 as you can see over there
on the side which is called context stop
shuts everything down and freeze some
memory and so that's the like you know
abort abort case but in case the length
was not less than 2 then we were going
to jump to
the fifth case and here it is this is
where we call where we get the first
element as a list and then the rest of
the permutations and the values of those
that permutations object and we
deliberately fall through which is
another thing you should probably never
do when you're writing a real switch
statement but in this case it is
intentional that we fall through to case
8k say it exists just so that we can
jump back to it by the way and then if
we are if we are done with the generator
we're going to jump to a case 19 which
is the the final case otherwise we're
going to set the loop variable to the
value of the most recent thing that was
returned by the generator next method
and now here's our sort of obliterated
vassar rated for loop or setting I the
loop index variable 20 and the loop head
location is this case 11 and while the
while I is less than list of length
we're going to jump to 17 or in case it
is not less than length we jump to 17
otherwise we plan on jump in back to 14
after we yield this expression and I
think this is a good illustration of
what's cool about recast so this these
comments here this like practice that
people have some people of lining their
comments up vertically especially when
all the words are the same link finishes
so visually pleasing that's that's very
idiomatic it's very hard to capture in
code to identify the intent of that
formatting and try to like recreate it
later if you're pretty printing so the
fact that recast is able to just take
that whole rate up prototype duck and
cat dot call blah expression and just
copy it over to the output and you'll
notice it's actually indented it by two
spaces means that in large part the
parts of the the tree that you haven't
touched just carry over all of their
idiomatic formatting and you don't have
to apologize for that when you submit a
diff for humans to review ok so we're
yielding that permutation which is
concatenation of a prefix and the first
element and a suffix and then coming
back to case 14 the next time we call in
to the generator and this is the update
case of that for loop so we're
incrementing the loop variable and then
jumping back to case 11 which was which
was the head of that loop where we test
the length and eventually I is not going
to be less than the length anymore and
so we're going to get jumped to the the
case 17 here and where is that taking us
let's see Oh remember we were inside of
a while loop so we need to jump back to
the head of that while loop and then
continue testing the result of the
generator to see if we're done finally
there are a lot of permutations of even
small lists so you can see how this ends
up generating a lot of them but that's
it that's java script that runs in a
browser today with one exception I still
haven't explained where this context
object comes from and I'm going to sort
of wave my hands here but we're going to
pass the whole anonymous function to
this wrap generator runtime function and
that will return the generator object
that has the next method and also make
sure that the context gets passed in in
each case okay so if you stuck with me
through that then you understand how
regenerator works yeah well that's a
good question yeah yeah I if I could
make it prettier I certainly would but I
will say this is a function that has
like multiple yields in it and loops and
everything so it's like a good example
in a fairly compact space of like all
the features of a generator which is
contributing in part to it looking
pretty messy but you could imagine
stepping through this and debugging the
code with a little bit of context I hope
maybe that's wishful thinking all right
so that's all well and good you can
convince yourself if you stare that
could long enough that it kind of does
what it's supposed to do generate some
permutations but how in the world do you
programmatically generate code like that
from ECMO script six so i'll show you
how a for statement which is you know
the normal like three part for statement
rather than a for n if we rub statement
gets code generated alright so this is
an actual case from the emitter code for
a generator so when we encounter
something of type for statement we first
create a series of locations and these
are sort of like uninitialized literal
numeric values that are going to end up
becoming jump targets and case labels in
that switch statement and so if the for
statement does have an in a net part the
like variable declaration thing we're
going to explode that which is my sort
of made-up terminology for turning it
into like a state machine if it contains
any yields and then we're going to mark
the head to say you know now we're at a
place where we would want to jump back
to if we were doing another iteration of
the loop if there's a test in the for
statement and it doesn't have to be a
test then if the test is false we jump
to the after location and note that we
don't even really know where the after
location is yet but it's still fine to
plan on jumping there when we do know
and then because this is a loop we want
to keep track of what loops were inside
in case we come across a break or a
continue or return that we need to
interpret in that context so there's
this leap manager leap is my made-up
term for a break or continue or a yield
or a throw that knows how to deal with
those things and there's we're putting a
new loop entry onto that stack and then
exploding the the body of the loop
and now after the body we are going to
omit the code for the update part of the
for statement and so we need to mark
that so we can jump to it if there is an
update part I guess I might have been
able to avoid marking it if there wasn't
but I did then we generate code for that
and we met some code that jumps back to
the head of the loop so we're going to
go right back to the test part and then
mark the after part and so now we've
marked all of our locations they have
actual numeric values and can be used in
the code that generated and now we're
done so we break out of this case we've
successfully emitted code for a for
statement so how does look work it's
actually dead simple simplest thing in
the talk it returns a literal abstract
syntax tree node object initialized to
negative one just as a sentinel for this
is not good yet and then when we mark it
we're keeping this listing of all of the
statements that we've emitted so far so
we know what the next one what the the
location of the next one is going to be
so mark assigns that location to
whatever literal node you pass into it
and goes I haven't initializes it and
had some assertions about it not being
already initialized and so forth so once
we've marked something we know that
we're going to emit a case statement in
the in the switch statement eventually
all right so b dot literal and in that
literal maybe a little confusing those
are actually provided by recast if if
you recall you could say require recast
at types that builders that literal and
require recast at types that named types
cool
right so this is an example about how
that jump if not thing works and it's
pretty straightforward but I'm not going
to spend time on it right now basically
you do some assertions and you try to
avoid having double negation if possible
just because that was a problem that I
could fix and it makes the code nicer
and then you emit an if statement that
sets the context next property to the
next location that you want to jump to
and also admit a break statement so I
know I race through that but I think it
will be self-explanatory if you were to
go back and look at it all right so
explode statement is the last of the
sort of drill down examples that I want
to talk about I don't think I actually
have time to go through it but the
interesting part about it is that recast
or sorry regenerator understands whether
a statement or an expression contains
any yield expressions or any problematic
breaks or continues and if it doesn't if
it doesn't in my terminology contain
leap then we can just omit the statement
as it was so a large part of the
performance promises of regenerator are
that if you're not using yield in a
certain part of your code it just is
left untouched you could imagine you
know exploding everything out into a big
state machine that is much longer than
your original code and that would be you
know perhaps logically correct but not
performant or very easily compressible
okay another exciting part is what
happens if an exception gets thrown in
the middle of the state machine and the
secret to that is remembering where you
last knew that you were and having a
little map that can be inspected to
figure out what try statement or catch
block or finally block you're inside of
and sort of twiddles context next and
then calls back into the generator and
so you appear to resume at the the place
where you expected to for instance you
an exception is thrown by this block
you'll resume in the code that was
emitted for the catch block so this
whole example actually works and ends up
being surprisingly short and I'll I'll
leave that for free to go through if you
are so inclined and then here's the
runtime code that supports all of that
and the interesting thing about this is
that it's invoking this in the very
middle the inner function that's the
function with the switch statement
inside of it that we've been talking
about so far and so that's where you see
it's passed in the context and we get
the value back out if everything is ok
we return the object with value and done
properties if there's an exception then
we call context dispatch exception with
that exception value and that's what
sets everything up for control to resume
in the exceptional control path all
right so the good news is as mentioned
earlier this is pretty much as hard as
it gets which may not sound like good
news but like this was a hard project
for me I'll be honest and it took a
while to wrap my head around these
things and so it's means nothing if it
if it takes you a while to wrap your
head around them as well but if you pick
up on anything here at least gotten a
sense for like how complicated this is
or in the end how tractable it is then
that's great and you can do a lot of
smaller things like adding support for
async functions and weight expressions
to the language in like this much code
this is the entire run time for that
really cool acma script 7 feature that's
coming down the pipe and that's already
implemented in a pull request for a
generator but I just mentioned that's a
necklace crypt 7 feature not echo script
six so we're not just bridging the gap
here between today and whenever acma
script 6 is fully supported we're always
going to be looking into the future so
my motto is always be transpiring
because incremental translation is the
key to avoiding that pythons 3 trap for
JavaScript that's how we bring about the
future with
choking on it and it's how we know that
the future is actually going to be
pretty great because it's as I said
before linguistic time travel of a sort
still really hard not everything can be
transpired I don't know what to do
without prescrip symbols and st
transforms don't always play well
together to transforms could be
competing to be like the thing that adds
something to the first line of a
function and who wins well it just you
have to figure out which one should come
first you have to break that tie and you
can't really do that automatically you
really need to have something like
source maps when you're hugging
generated code like we just went through
because it's not as readable as the
futuristic syntax for sure and the
language specification can totally
change out from under you a saint can
wait not specified yet might have to
rewrite that pull request but it wasn't
too much effort in the first place so
I'm going to try to track those changes
as they come so my team at Facebook
JavaScript infrastructure is gonna be
working with this as long as it takes to
make the process seamless and it's all
gonna be open source we're just getting
started and you are absolutely more than