welcome to jazz Fantasia maybe the first
conferences introduced from underwater
for me personally reject is way more
than just the conference it's it's a
very special place with very special
people and they're all gathering here
and it's it's about much more than just
technology it's really about the people
that are here and that's very very dear
to my heart so that's where Cascadia jas
came from it was heavily inspired by JS
com JS con tu l xjs node comp all of the
conference's that you think of as being
the best of what a developer conference
can be and we put on this event in
November of 2012 and it was just it was
a huge success you know we pulled
together just over 200 amazing people
for two days of fun and it was just one
of the most rewarding experiences I had
ever had
javascript what are you what even is a
class why should we care about any of
this I gave a talk about how I changed
careers in one year from no programming
experience at all to a hired program it
was rough it was hard but my talk is
about how I got so much help from so
many people in the community and how
awesome that was and trying to inspire
other people to help out I don't know
the whole atmosphere is just so friendly
and welcoming and all the talks have
been great and just the people seem
great
okay so here's our video stream and why
not when I wave thread at our robot
after we take off through this web app
well so the LEDs will flash and it will
drive forward one such as x-ray
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript virtual Dom
javascript is so much more than syntax
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript for those of you
are not familiar is pseudo code with
semi-colons on the end of every
instruction there are a few conferences
i have in my head as my favorites in
europe and this is my first time at jazz
convey you and it's right in at number
one what's going to be awesome before I
came here and it's just what I expected
and just a little bit more you topped it
I wouldn't have missed CSS columns the
second edition for anything HTML had
hamill and CSS hats s but jayus had just
yes that that
now CoffeeScript has brothers at ur
style of its own but there's just one
little problem when ever thrown
k
number hit in yahoo
it's enough to make mistake with
JavaScript till source maps land or
hello
hey Jas conf I'm sorry I'm not there but
I can't be but I'm happy I was all the
time that I was hi Chris and Laura thank
you and also everybody I'm sorry and I
hope the pool is great I'll see you all
next time thanks charlie also by so
fiddle is fuck it do it live this entire
thing this weary moat is bridged down to
an Arduino board spliced today that's
bridged into Johnny 5 which is running
nodejs that's controlling the Arduino
that's reading from the we thing that
talks out to the node copter we have
bound every single button to do
something the start button appropriately
starts it and because we have a windows
person in our group it also ends it go
figure the left goes left the right goes
right the forward goes forward the back
goes back just like a video gas goes up
why goes down B goes something and a
does something else we even programmed
in the konami code that does double
flips and so enjoy this is the new style
of gaming that we'd like to interact
with javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript what
are you virtual Dom
you may have heard it's not called
es2015 we plan to feed new plants be an
early adopter early as twenty sixteen
features we decided we decided to change
we decided to change the name of yes six
yes 2015 and he s 70 that's interesting
class was the most requested new feed
class was the most requested new feature
in white Eden is a Class A Class was the
most requested new feature in JavaScript
and all the requests came from Java
programmers but it's really really good
whiskey don't do the accent I'm thinking
of organizing a fun conference in
Ireland and he said don't do I'd love to
go to a fun conference in Ireland he
wanted to do it in a hotel Jess conf in
Berlin 2009 was the first time I
actually felt like I belonged to a group
of people that were into the same things
that i visited no said I didn't I said
well I was held in a hotel other people
who came to phone calls when Don decided
they were gonna do their own conference
funk off one was 70 people on a bus
comes to was 80 people in a castle
funcom 3 was 110 people yeah on an
island Chris was there and ok Chris
wasn't using the castle actually have a
video of him going Luther Luba the llama
came with the donkey guy owned the
donkey said I have a llama you want me
to draw him in to Chris and Laura's
passion and dedication change the course
of mighty my life and a huge part of F
Delta to Jana lenhart soon why don't why
why why why I see Joey it's misha palma
cambia August with me or no seguir con
fun friend sayain of gamma sana Argus
finish august cash lon I Roscher ich
kann future I'm come I wasn't I was
absolutely inspired by a wonderful
weekend in Berlin I met Chris J's conf
Berlin 2010 me to ruin the first
somewhere
erin quinn snide eyes like guys are his
names aren't Quinn no Aaron Queen all
you would actually love to see her and
Quinn to turn his hand to Irish food the
follow-up to the pizza book is the
potato book obviously I'll be microphone
is picking all the shit up kherson Laura
we love you thanks for making JS conf it
probably wouldn't have realized Amanda
lives you touched at the time Laura and
Chris our hearts glad to you you just
wish you all the best done yeah there's
a lava hands every weekend here where do
love this come from not not hayirli
that's a nice balloon hat if you're
shipping I often absent and dream of the
box you'll make you think about going
native but X goes a big headache think
of things like PhoneGap or whatever it's
called this week it helps you to solve a
web app without any need to speak
objective-c runtime to see objective-c
project to see don't need that rap or
get in the App Store take it from me
help us run the room just make sure he's
sober when you do have to be shipping
when you are skipping objective-c Wow
phone cap sounds really useful thanks
pretty awesome you just the thing is I
mean you think like oh just use phonegap
and will solve my problems but it's
actually it's kind of actually not that
easy there are a few catches okay yeah
yeah I'll tell you about it right now
if you build both sides you can skip ie
you think es5 makes you feel alive so
long jquery
too bad gingerbreads
still so damn i tread sure it's still
WebKit but it runs like shit android 2.3
hi everyone my name is Juan Pablo yotaka
i'm here with quyen duket we're both
Colombians we are part of the organizing
team for jay's from Colombia and very
thankful for chris's and Laura's work
thanks to their inspiration we started
an event in Colombia that happen 2013 it
also happened 2015 overall we've run
these two events with about 50 speakers
have had 700 attendees I've had about
100 of the bursary scholarships and it
has had a great impact in our community
who Liam why what can you tell us about
the impact well we started being the two
communities in the most important cities
in Colombia in Bogota a meta-gene a call
voltage is a magazine jes and after the
Fuji is conferred to thousand thirteen
there were more people interested in
other cities in Colombia to star
JavaScript communities so as the date we
have more than 10 she discovered about
JavaScript and we have more 3,000 people
were history in the community for from
Colombia so we are one of the most
important a large community in all Latin
America this as being thankful to the
whole this calm family of events and the
word that you have been gone so thank
you very much and keep this magic
happening yes keep up the great work on
our other co-organizers coming local are
Katherine Lopez the VW neta thank you
very much we wanted to see see on their
behalf we know it's not the last event
will see you in huge hugs from Colombia
for everyone bye we love you
really really good
javascript is javascript is javascript
is so much more than syntax why should
we care about I in this
because we'd like challenging now we
want to solve problems or software
engineers
what in his a class and the Sigurd what
even is a class and this is a group I
didn't is a class and the good question
and like frankly the community does not
have a good ontology around what object
orientation should be no really what
classes are at all there's nothing that
works there's nothing you can read
there's nothing to look at I'm going to
tell you what's going on but that's all
there is and no one has come up the
pixel website i sided well fix it
well Victor javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript chaves chaves
crypt what are you virtual not
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript is so
much more than syntax javascript
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript what are you
virtual knob javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript for
those of you are not familiar is
pseudocode semicolons on the end of
every instruction I just I just wanted
the browser to be nice like note is nice
we can solve problems by removing
complexity by adding it so at javascript
burnham is your extremely used to
destroying data and we don't have to do
that
and we don't have to we don't have to do
that you don't we write to your full
application every five minutes and we
don't have to do that you don't rewrite
your all application every five minutes
and we don't have to do that these are
not using so did not render these are
not design of new things I did not
invent them you don't rewrite your whole
application every five minutes and we
don't have to do that what's gonna
happen after JavaScript and I I have to
believe what's gonna happen after
JavaScript and I I have to believe that
there is going to be a next language
because if javascript is the last
language that's just gonna be really sad
hi I'm Traci Hines I'm one of the
organizers of Cascadia Jas a conference
in the Pacific Northwest for web
developers by web developers we started
in 2012 and we've run for events for
over thirteen hundred awesome people in
Cascadia we've been inspired to push
ourselves in a growing community we want
to see every year ever more inclusive
bigger hearts and pushing rad JavaScript
boundaries cascadia wouldn't exist if
not for Chris and Laura or wish them the
best and were honored to carry on the j
s comp tradition in the Pacific
Northwest hi my name is trivoli I want
the organizers of variables here in Oslo
we are now working on our 5th edition of
wearables and so far it's been a hugely
nice and great experience I started
doing web development in the mid-90s and
the way no community for us doing the
development for many many years and then
suddenly Jays comp comes around Cavazos
went to case conf in US and in Boyle and
we just have a home from day one
certainly there was actually a commune
d for us and that made us want to do our
own conference and build our own
community here in Oslo and so it is and
it's just been an amazing ride so huge
thank you from this award on this lousy
it's a spirometer
we might work we find out
Oh
final
burn this together we're all in this
together these people that are sitting
in this room with you they're gonna help
you can draw your next job you're gonna
help you you have a bad day and they'll
send you a funny cat just like super
awesome these people are really going to
change your life right here the ones
that are sitting right next to you and
those of you watched falling along at
home come to a conference and let this
like totally transform you my favorite
thing about jazz calm the conference is
great to get me wrong really really
great coffee and like jumping in the
ocean it's like super fun oh yeah um but
what I love about it is the community
that it spawns cuz like it's not just
jazz comp anymore it's like all the J's
comps in all the countries and then all
of the meetups that are like modeled in
that jazz comp you know kind of culture
which is super super awesome so thank
you Chris thank you thank you I entire
Jess comp team and I want to say let's
say hi from our okay oh man we love you
guys I'll record it that's a nice
balloon hat
you