hi my name is Alvaro i am from other way
originally but bimbo I mean living
abroad since seven years first in China
for three years building a big website
like a big dating site for Germany from
there I moved to Switzerland since four
years i'm living there and i work for
RabbitMQ i wrote the book about RabbitMQ
and i also work for the core team of
rabid rabid EMU is messaging and queuing
server the idea is that you can delay
processing of tasks for example in your
in your website like just a canonical
example like your images instead of
researching them while the user is
waiting you can just kill them and send
a message to a worker that could be
written in no door closure java whatever
and then do the oldest processing in the
background to save resources on the
front ends so rabbitmq is actually
written in ireland but is implements a
protocol called n QP advanced message in
queue in protocol which has clients in
many languages for for example
javascript java and PHP closure python
ruby and so on so users can actually
benefit a lot from this because they can
have the front ends in node and today's
like very fashion to have micro services
and you can have your own micro service
like for resizing images in java let's
say one for sending emails in know Jas
and you can mix and match all these
languages very easily thanks to RabbitMQ
and entropy the talk was about doing
replication with RabbitMQ so i gave like
a brief intro of how n QP works and then
jumped into how to do replication would
rabbit with the tools provided by by the
server i actually my first time here was
this november for a different conference
and this is my second time we went
inside effectively so it's very
interesting yes it's quite a like amount
of video that took a more bit on inside
I think in the area of rabbit for
example the main thing today might be
the micro services like more and more
architectures are moving to the cloud
and to have this very small micro
services that you can deploy for example
with doctor or using cloud foundry or
this kind of tools and rabbitmq will
become like a core part they're 2 to do
all this message in synchronization
moving data around the time I travel a
lot actually and go to many conferences
and I'm really really surprised by the
venue by all the the billboards
announcing how to get here I mean she's
just those small details that make the
conference a better experience for for
users and big tops are a great they have
a great selection of speakers I mean the
creator of javascript is here so what
else to ask and the location is wait so