you
hello
with any better hello hey so the tight
the title of the talks changed a little
bit that was originally representing
microwave and sling microworld it's no
revisiting Wendell managers hey when I
originally submitted the talk proposal I
I hadn't written a line of code but I
had that had an idea of what I wanted to
present and I got to work a couple
months later as always happens with your
own ideas they they they kind of take on
a life of their own and it morphed into
a rather than something like logo it
turns into something more like a window
manager so I I have a love-hate
relationship with it with the desktop in
one hand I love using the mouse I love
the idea of of the the affordances you
get from looking at an interface right
in front of you graphically rather than
having to explore it as using the
terminal and at the same time I'm
constantly frustrated by the
capabilities that and modern desktop
environments gave us and I find them
clunky I don't like the way you interact
with things I don't like the way
applications exchange data or don't
change they don't exchange data for that
matter so quickly bit what I want to go
over and some of the key things I
dislike of a desktop environment and
then suggest a few maybe improvements
that that we could implement in the
future so the first ones when the
organization it's setting up your
workspace and one of you start like
whenever I start working on a project
you open up your text editor can maybe
open a couple of terminal tabs you put
your browser over to the right or maybe
to the left and then you called away and
then that's all good you close it down
and you've wasted all this time setting
it all up you've got to move you're
going to nudge the windows about you can
take your hand off the keyboard you've
got to move the mouse and it's all about
it's a little bit frustrating so why not
treat the desktop is a malleable space
just right rather than thinking about
booting windows on the desktop consider
the desktop as being a space that you
can you can bend to your well so we can
actually take a knife through it and we
split it in half split it again you
split it again even if you want to go
all the way through you can just split
up the whole thing and then the whole
thing can be resized and each window
you've created can be going to resize
them dependently and then you can summon
your your tasks and to here to get to
get your job done so that's one thing
bigger applications we used bigger
applications every day you've got web
browser as we get Photoshop we get emacs
all these applications that do tons of
stuff and very often you just want to do
one little thing and you think I'd be
great if I could just take that one
little piece of functionality from this
application and use it use it by itself
so let's try implementing something like
that let's make maybe a text editor so
we'll split the work space here we got a
text editor component and we can have a
command bar and I'm going the two
together so rather than having a single
application we have small chunks of a
functionality that can tail blocks what
to do I can't clean a visual programming
now I'm unprepared and I haven't got a
fail to play about with here so
so there we go we've we've hooked it up
and know we've taught there the
application how to how to load the
contents of a fail and what what have
you wanted a like a buff a list of your
open files of your if you're working on
a bigger project again what we do is we
just split the space and will say well
let's have some history in here and
we'll connect make the relevant
connections I know next thing we open a
file they as itself to the list and
double-clicking it again a double
clicking it should reopen it if you hook
it up correctly so there's another
another example and we can we can do so
we can do something similar if we could
we could we could replace the text
editor where the browser component hook
the two together and dad want a wife I
hope you can trust me that I actually
works um so that's an ass another um
frustration I have a desktop to the fact
we can't completely compose chunks of
functionality as you would do maybe on
the console or in the terminal if they
easy to create pipelines whereas
traditionally in a graphical environment
you're stuck with what you've got makes
frustration recall so it kind of ties in
with the first point of a building up
your workspace but it seems two strikes
me is absolutely ludicrous a nest in age
that once we've set up a workspace
there's no way of just saying give me
that same thing back you know you were
working on all these files you set up
your box base is out the way you wanted
that why can't you the next time you
turn on your machine just have it being
exactly the same way all say it's all
state saved so what we can do here is
introduced the concept of macros and so
going back to our browser example you
can save that quebec by clicking the
Save button and
again we can split the work space and de
for and this time we just say well give
it that we've got a new macro appeared
here you could just see give me that
browser back and we can afford them that
all work independently and if we inspect
the way they've been connected together
we see each one's got its own one set of
connections scripts ability so modern
desktop desktop environments they treat
the Wendell the windows are very opaque
you've got your window manager and it it
just gives a block of video memory to
your to your application your
application just draws jaws its wedges
and it's got this complex object model
represents those wedges but then once
it's rendered onto the onto the screen
not like that representation is gone
you're just stuck with um the raw bitmap
hey whereas if they're if the window
manager had a greater a notion of what
what what these components actually
represent a it would be possible to
disrupt it through chords soft for
example we can set up a text editor you
will have to text editor talking to each
other and what we can do is we can have
the concept for a mark so we've got a
solid get cursor that we can we can
click about and by clicking on a part of
the screen we see this is where I want
any future messages to be sent so I'll
target the pane on the right and then
the pin on the left
so so there you go so by selecting by
highlighting some system command within
the left-hand window and executing it we
then caused an actions appear on the
window that we targeted we could
actually target itself and enter it and
I would hopefully replace the active
document the reinvention I mean we've
all seen output applications like
netbeans Eclipse them and they all have
they all the implement the same things
they've got tabs they've got five views
they've got um there but we are docking
frameworks for moving a little sub
Wendell's about and despite all the work
that's gone into these things their
stems are still incredibly inflexible if
I'm using an instance of eclipse and
decidable I want to eat I want to look
at something in Firefox there's no way
for me to inject a Firefox instance in
there so why is this we should be able
to again cutting up our area too well to
what we want I'm just using a gesture
say will give me some tabs here oops
give me a file system west here text
editor and what we're doing is we're
customizing the space to exactly what we
need for that the task at hand rather
than accepting the the functionality
that we've been given by the big
inflexible applications that work that
we've got shearing so a comment
frustration you've got you've got 22
you're working with not with two out to
desktop applications and the right
beside each other on the screen but you
can't get data from one to the other
it's like there's they might as well be
in different countries um you know we're
aware as us most of us assume or UNIX
users we've got we've got less wealth of
primitives we normally were to be used
to using for passing data between
processes we've got pipes we've got
system 5 IPC we've got the main sockets
we've got all this but when it comes to
a graphical user interfaces all we've
got is save as we have to save the file
and if we're lucky the other thing will
reopen it and and I've just I've just
actually done the top for the next slide
so just yeah but well carry on on this
theme with their that there's no way to
to get these two applications to
communicate whereas what we really want
to be doing is having the two talks each
other directly so what could you do
about this so let's start with our a
browser that we saved earlier and I'll
get rid of that because we don't want
that and we'll go and look at
so
they've got a wee diary if they might
have sleep 5 managed to get over the
last week and now what we work what
we've got we've got this this data on a
web page but we want to do something to
that data now I've encountered the
situation loads of times on my life as a
freelancer where people want a scrape
data off a website and only what you do
is you'll goes curl and you'll copy
Attila your your local system and then
you'll run it through some sort of
script that works track some data and
then you'll turn to csv file or
something why should we have to do that
why can't we say well oops oops hook it
up and see kree the document
and if we want to get they say that the
second column we could just give it a
little creed ii to run and we go and
then all that all the data just goes
from one process and to another they
will notice there we've got that theta
isn't particularly useful because it's
it's come out as HTML elements whereas
what we really want our numbers so let's
split this up again sculpt something
called the sculpts process which is kind
of our general purpose transformer when
one when one task doesn't issue data in
the right format we can put one of these
in the middle and we just tell it how to
change what it gets given which in this
case is a table cell and there we go
we've got another another say eventually
is underneath on the list they give this
extract those numbers as numbers and to
enter a table that we can then take one
later and manipulate we could it's easy
to see how we could do aggregate
operations on that or how we could maybe
export it to a variable honest and a
script or something okay so the final
the final frustration is well that it
was actually IPC was what I just covered
and I'm going on to sharing but sharing
so if I'm I'd say i've been working on a
really important document text
I was up all night writing that note
I've written this document no he won't
if you want to if you want to show
this with a friend there's various ways
you could do it if you're the less
technical I tintable will save it as a
file that upload it to their email and
then they'll send it as an attachment if
you're a bit more technical tire you
might save it to your hard drive and
then start but we local web server and
share the URL you might upload it to ftp
but this text document it's not just
stuff I wouldn't go into a file it's a
data source in itself so why can't we
just say give me an HTTP server and
serve the contents of the file and then
if we go and visit it on
we'll see we get we get the content
coming up so we haven't had the bones to
desk there we've just taken our
environment and asked the environment to
work work to our needs rather than I was
um to worker in limitations of the tools
that we've been given so why the 80s why
my what was this obsession I've got with
the 80s anyway why not
um the 80s I mean the 80s are mostly
known for bad news and worse fashion but
there it's also for me it was it's maybe
the closing of one of the golden golden
ages of maybe research into experimental
programming languages and environments
you know it really the heyday of
environments like small talk self box
our Oberon all these and all these
environments were these were all created
in the late 70s early 80s late towards
the late 80s how all this amazing stuff
that was both this disappeared for 20
years and that now is starting to make a
reappearance and the 1i have plundered
the most from is over on Oberon's are
it's an operating system but not an
operating system like we'd probably know
it today it's a saying it wrong it all
runs in a single process so it's really
just the colonel it's single-threaded it
has an event loop and it manages a bunch
of recursively lado rectangles I might
sound familiar it's it's very like a
browser it was all written by by two
guys one Nicholas worth and somebody
else and as I this I don't know his name
thori and there's a fantastic book on it
there um if you can read that URL it's
um the book actually contains the entire
source code for the operating system so
it's a 400-page book but more than half
of that is called but it's what what's
amazing about it is how simple the code
is so it mean obviously they were
liberating at a time what he didn't have
these complicated machines but the the
the serious beauty and the simplicity of
how it all falls together so what's the
goal of what I'm doing here I'm trying
to create more what I have termed
disposable ad-hoc computational spaces
sounds like a mouthful but really what
I'm what I want to do is I want an
environment i'm not interested in
creating something that can be polished
i'm not for a minute seeing you could
use this to
three world-class applications that's
just not the goal the goal is that a lot
of the time you've got you have ideas
and there's all this boilerplate in the
way on acting upon your ideas you know
if you want to if you want to do some 3d
you've got to say I set up a WebGL
context then you've got to find a
library that works if you want to talk
to nard we know we've got to download
the software and then install the rate
libraries for the peripherals that are
correct connected to your machine if you
want to if you want to make a website
you've got it you've got to download all
that you've got to start with with your
you know your template HTML document and
install all that your style sheets and
you're a bootstrap and whatever anyone's
using these days where does what you
really want to do is you want to verify
if the idea is possible if it's feasible
if it's something you want to work on
properly for something that's worth
going to the effort to do all that work
that can a ramp up for and that's there
that's that's the goal behind the system
that we're building not i'm not
interested in the underlying elegance
the idea here isn't to create lots of
little components that do really cute
things and then have to assemble
hundreds of them to get something useful
we're trying to find that pragmatic
middle grounds where we get these
components that are there are useful for
specific tasks and themselves and if
they're not it doesn't matter if there's
a bit of overlap and functionality here
and there what's useful what the point
is is that you can actually just just
use them and finally I don't care about
performance I mean this this is all
implemented in JavaScript it's not for
rain world-class games it's not for made
in bitcoins it's for it's just purely
for experimentation why do it in
JavaScript well we've got there the
hierarchical display model that I
alluded to earlier it's great for I mean
you can see the minister slideshow
itself is running inside that the same
the same system for slicing and this is
the hierarchical display works perfectly
you can just nest your dev since I each
other CSS is great for rapid prototype
inventor faces it's a joy to work with
if you've ever tried building interfaces
with the likes of java swing or cute
demo this year little the tiny amount of
time it takes to actually prototype a
new UI concept is
it's great multimedia support you'd be
crazy to try and make an environment
like this without good multimedia
support we expect there to be videos and
audio support and the browser's got all
of that flexible object model we're not
tied down to two classes and rigid
inheritance and that's great for messing
about with different concepts because if
you you don't have to go to that that um
that if of designing a class hierarchy
you can start off with you know a
function returns a couple of closures
and then you can move on and then
extract it into something in Belgium let
your object model evolve with your
system and finally it's everywhere the
thing that what worked against all these
systems in the 80s like small talk and
the self's and all this stuff is there
were no machines about that could
actually run these things that were in
the hands of their everyday people
whereas know we've all got this
incredibly powerful runtime on every
pretty much every system in existence so
maybe that that's what I would do my my
the abstract my talk when I said maybe
this is the time for tools us to to
start coming back so i think i've got if
I got time for a quick demo job tries to
fit on um so when I the initial
motivation for building the system was
actually teaching a teaching children
programming and when it comes to
teaching I I like to like to take a
concept exists in the real world and
then I try to work out how we could
maybe implement night in code and then
build on that solution so I've taken a
very simple idea a set of traffic lights
so we'll start off with our traffic
lights and some code now what we're
doing here is we're wiring up we create
something called a context which again
as I said is like in a black box for it
contains all the state that the the
programming language uses and so we
borrowed those up
and we'll need a button because the
context can be starting stopped started
and stopped button bar here and then
I'll I'm gonna cheat not writing any
code today so let's let's start that
hope it works so there we go so running
a bit of code there and it's just we've
just about to start off for the first
two states flashing between red and red
amber I don't know traffic lights
working Germany our home I've been run
over almost remember three times since I
got here so this is how they work where
I come from so we just got to add a
either few lines so after that we go
green so we'll add a little bit cold
here green on and will delay there and
hopefully yeah and then we'll add the
state that goes back to yellow they
probably notice this language i'm using
here doesn't really look like javascript
it doesn't really look like ruby it
doesn't really look like python but it
looks a little bit like all of them it's
it's a when we were teaching when we
started teaching kids there according we
found that they had enormous amount of
problems with things like timeouts and
you didn't mean to do this in javascript
an idiomatic JavaScript not not talk
about generators infant but you would
have to have a couple of state variables
to track the amount of time a light had
been on a specific state and and the
current state and the next day the
lights we're going to go into and for a
beginner that is a lot of stuff to track
just to make a simple sequence occur so
we we developed this really simple
language that allowed them allows them
to to write avec they called in a more
synchronous style so we've got that
working let's let's take into the real
world so a
so that's the you see that yep so that's
that's the week are we've got them we've
got a BF of traffic lights there so
again the thing I want it like i said i
mentioned earlier about getting rid of
boilerplate so we've got this we've got
these flashing lights and we're quite
happy with that but we'd like to make it
we'd like to make an effect in the real
world no normally if you want to start
integrating with hardware you've got it
you've got to find the right you've got
to find an environment to use you've got
to find you've got to find the right
libraries that work with the thing
you're you're wanting to do and I don't
like that I would prefer to be services
you know why can't we have a service
that just offers you access to the
relevant hardware and then we can
interface with that so let's do that so
we'll create well it's called imp but
will create and we just tell it which
pens we want to use for the
microcontroller and I'll say up a few
others for later and we bite we just
bind this to the the same the same
script in context and by doing that it's
just given those the functions that
control those lights to to the same code
so now we can see pen for right false so
excuse me but I do this pin 6 false and
then in here so it's radon so that we
pin for right true and hopefully a got a
late oh so be go see it and then we can
we can we can go out and fill the rest
then I'll just do one more so what we've
done there is we've taken us that we've
taken that we've taken a simple
programming solution so a simple program
programming problem and we've we've
solved that now in a couple of ways and
we've we've done so without having to
mess about with libraries having to mess
about with setting up you know canvas
bootstrap code without having to do all
the stuff you
normally have to do to get off the
ground and we can we can immediately
start focusing on problem solving and
yep I'll leave it there
you