I guess sound like there's actually some
people in the room this is good alright
so name of the talk is touch me I dare
you there are a lot of touch devices out
there in the world and this talk is
about how to work with those and more
importantly how to work with them not
just with touch but also there's a
tremendous number devices that are out
there that are very similar to this one
which is you know I've got the the
surface pro here and it's got a full
keyboard and it's got a mouse and I can
actually use a pin and I don't know how
many people have seen the pins they come
with the the service pro and other
windows devices they actually have a
radio tip on the front of them which
means that it better more than a
capacitive pin a capacitive pin is able
to be a big finger basically or slightly
more accurate finger a radio tipped pen
with the right digitizer very much like
a Wacom board is pixel perfect in its
accuracy and it has tilt and it has
pressure and it has a whole bunch of
other things and so there's a whole
bunch of things that we can do with the
pin that we can't do with the finger but
in addition to that you know there's
also touch devices and mice and
keyboards and so on so that's what this
talk is about all right so he's over to
gesture at this one because this one's
actually on screen that one is actually
not on screen now so I can water bottle
so you'll see a lot of weird as I go no
over here so my name is josh holmes and
you find me on twitter at josh holmes
you find my blog at josh homes.com and
i'm josh dot homes at microsoft com I've
worked at Microsoft for about six and a
half years the last three of so were in
Ireland the last three weeks have
actually been in redmond on the Internet
Explorer team so brand new to the
Internet Explorer team so we had at
least a week more of I'm new to the team
I don't know okay so when you ask me the
tough questions expect that as a
response okay all right so
why does touch matter touch matters
because of the incredible proliferation
of touch devices that are out there in
the world and I mean it's something like
twenty five percent of all the windows 8
machines that are shipping are all touch
devices obviously a tremendous number
the mobile phones all the tablets
ranging from the the ipad over to the
the surface like this one even the new
chrome books so if you look at the the
Chromebook pixel it's a touchscreen
device so there's a tremendous number of
touchscreen devices that are out there
that are shipping and you know so you
need to figure out how are you going to
deal with them and there's kind of three
basic strategies that you can take at an
uber level you know so the first one oh
sorry I forgot touch devices are
actually even going into weird
interesting places like I don't know how
many of your staying at the hotel when I
got off the elevator this morning I saw
this touch it says uh touch the screen
to interact with the Amelia Island
Plantation like cool so I touched and
sure enough there's a touch browser in
the damn hotel on the TV okay this is
cool I like this so what is your
strategy for dealing with touch it's
absolutely a legitimate strategy to
ignore it if you know what you're doing
you know so if you can consciously say
you know what I'm not going to worry
about touch it's not my target
demographic or you know what touch you
know the mouse is simulation on touch
devices is good enough okay and and I'll
show you some examples of this here in a
little bit but mouse emulation on touch
devices is good enough in a lot of cases
actually you know I'm going to jump over
to one of the demos now and I'll show
you this very briefly so this this is a
little bit of code if you've done any
Mouse work you've seen code very much
like this so I'm going to grab an event
mouseup mouse up and mouse move so all
I'm going to care about is when I click
and when I move the mouse right and so
I'm going to run
projects and it's this one that i'm
looking at here okay and so what this is
a little pong demo and you can see i
move my mouse and that works decently i
move my mouse to this side and that
works decently excitement excitement
right okay so I'm going to click that
and so I can go play pong badly and it's
accommodation kind of pong and break out
anyways so this all looks fine right
this is this is working so i can ignore
touch no no actually I can't and there's
a couple of reasons for that the primary
one is your user has more than one
finger so what happens when they want to
move over here because that actually
does work okay but now this one over
here doesn't anybody have a guess as to
why this one doesn't while I can move
this one over here because mouse there's
only one right so what do you do here
you start programming for touch and so
you start start using touch as it's
meant to be so the two other things you
can do here is you can retrofit you know
touch on to your application or you can
design for touch first and I'm going to
suggest that if you design for touch
first you'll actually be in a much
better position and because all the
things that you do for touch should work
for the mouse and keyboard as well so
there's a couple of things that you have
to remember when you're designing for
touch first and foremost is hover sucks
don't don't do it don't don't use hover
because you actually you know the thing
with touch is it's touching you have to
actually touch if you actually click in
order to get something to happen because
this computer has no idea that my finger
is a millimeter off the screen it just
doesn't okay someday we may have
computers that can do that but I'm
betting it's not to be built into your
mobile phone anytime soon now there
there's a lot of great scenarios where
browsers are compensating for this and
so on it's still not ideal don't use
hover instead use click or better
actually build a menu that is designed
for touch okay obviously hopefully use
touch size buttons okay now the reason
for this is that the average human
finger is about 11 millimeters okay now
basketball players they're up kind of
the 19 20 millimeter range the babies
are kind of in this seven six seven
millimeter range but when you get to
this range you know it's it's kind of a
love it well I've got these big Moose
claws it's like 40 but anyways the so
one is obviously big touch things but
you also have to remember where your
users are so your users are going to be
using your device all over the place
they could be on the couch they could be
walking they could be on a bus and the
bus is kind of jiggling back and forth
you don't know where they are and so you
also have to remember that the touch
devices that there's a very large
percentage of missed taps okay where
they're tapping somewhere else in the
screen so bigger buttons bigger landing
zones account for the fact that they may
or may not actually hit the target think
about that as you're developing your
application okay remember where your
users are touching the device so if I've
got a phone in my hand and I'm going to
touch a button on the top that on this
big ass phone is uncomfortable okay
touching down at the bottom actually
fairly comfortable okay same thing goes
on a slate okay on a tablet I mean
anybody pick up their slates and hold it
on the sides and where can your thumbs
reach that's comfortable okay anywhere
beyond that and it's not so think about
where you're putting your interactions
and so when you're thinking about your
interactions you should be there's a big
stand right there you should be looking
at kind of the very bottom and the
corners being the best possible
interaction so for example if you're
developing a game make sure that you're
putting the controllers on the outside
if you're developing a blog reader in
order or a blog right make sure that
you're putting the controls you know to
navigate to the next and to read the
next article out on the sides and down
towards the bottom so that is more
comfortable and easier for people to
touch i think is that's that's not
get a counter to Mouse it's exactly the
same as the mouse it's just that we're
used to putting all of our stuff up at
the top that's just the way that we've
designed it because that's the way
newspapers worked and so we designed it
that way okay so think about where
you're going to be doing things and then
you're reading areas are exactly the
opposite okay so the things that are
kind of up towards the middle and and
centered those are the best reading
areas partially because nothing gets in
the way of them if you have your
controls out of the sides and down
towards the bottom okay remember that
there's more than one finger okay so
this gets to the part of a part of the
demo there was there is more than one
finger and so we want to be able to
scroll back and forth and and use more
than one finger for things like pinch
and zoom things like controlling both
sides of the screen there's a whole
bunch of different things that we can do
there and also remember that there's
more than one type of input okay so more
than one type of input you know I
already talked about the mouse and I are
you talking about the pin a little bit
the mouse and the pin are very important
parts of the user's input so from a
technical perspective now i'll talk
about the design side a little bit how
do we actually do this okay and so the
exciting part is there's actually one
set of events that we can catch that'll
actually catch all those different types
of inputs and can handle multiple types
of inputs okay all the same time and
it's pointers okay pointers is a is w3c
pointer standard Microsoft has been
working on this we've submitted it he's
telling I should be doing this one
here's a big grin on his face back there
so the events here actually very similar
to what you would be comfortable with if
you've done any Mouse work so pointer
down pointer move pointer out pointer
over pointer out and cancel okay those
are all very similar events to what you
would have for for a mouse so if you've
done anything with the mouse you're
ready to go with pointers okay the
exciting part is this is a new candidate
recommendation and what this is going to
do is capture all of our different types
of events and what we're going to get on
a
given event is we're actually going to
get the width of the touch okay are the
width of the of the the pointer we're
gonna get the height of it we're gonna
get the pressure if it's a pin you get
the tilt if it's a pin where do you get
the rotation if it's a pen or a mouse or
touch so if I touch it this way that's
different than if I touch it this way
which is different than I've had touched
it this way we may want to react to that
differently okay you get the pointer
type so was it a finger was it a and
actually I believe it just says touch
was it a pin or was it a mouse and it's
open for additional types of inputs as
we go forward the pointer ID you because
you can actually have more than one and
so we can have you know the demo I'll
show later I forget how many touch
points how many touch points to the
surface pro have five ok so I'll show
five plus a mouse and i'll see if i can
get a pin in there as well and then then
that you know the event type and so on
and so forth so there's a lot of
different things that come in with that
alright so let's go back over here and
let's fix this demo here so first of all
it's coming out that killed there okay
we don't need that code anymore and
instead I'm going to not that that is
the comment so you're gonna block
comment on that as well but oh well
alright so let me scroll out a little
bit and I'll show you what I just
uncommented there so this is exactly the
same code it's just copy pasted with ms
pointer up ms pointer up ms point or
move and ms pointer move what we're
doing here is we've got two basic blocks
and we're setting up the MS pointer up
and Emmet swinter move for the left
overlay and for the right overlay that
way we can actually control you know to
the two different sides the deuteron
paddles at the same time okay and so I'm
going to save that I come back over to
my little game and let's refresh and
we'll pick our little block here now but
now notice as I'm touching here both of
them are working one on either side
because there's more than one type of
touch and we'll see if we can get a one
little game here between the two of them
now what if I dropped my mouse over here
that's cool too so I can now do mouse
and pointer all at the same time and
that's fine or if I wanted to drag the
pin in here oops boom I've now got a pin
and mouse and finger and all them of
them will work at the same time okay
cool I think that's pretty awesome
alright so now this begs the question
though what happens and come back over
to hear so well you're a little too
briefly go through the code here and
then we'll then we'll take a look at the
need a little feedback on the mic I'm my
phone is way over there so i'll take a
look through the code a little bit and
then we'll then we'll talk about the the
obvious question what's the obvious
question
nobody what's that browser support very
good all right so very similar to how
you would do with a touch events we're
going to if you've done any that with
that one on iOS we're going to iterate
through just the list of pointers here
and say for this pointer we're going to
you know act upon it okay it's very very
simple to roll through you get a list of
those and you can get all the other
items off of like the pointer type the
tilt and so on and so forth if you're on
iOS or on Android you get these events
which are very hard to read it I'm
seeing from the cheap seats there in the
back but this is touch start here at the
top and then there's also touch in touch
move and so on and so forth the thing
both of those those events is that a
they are just touched they're not touch
and mouse and pen and everything else
second of all those are not a standard
they're not a w3c standard and are not
likely to become one because there are
multiple patents on the implementations
of touch start and touch end that are
not going to be licensed out to the
other browsers so there's there's some
issues with those which is why we
recommend staying away from those the
are not not recommend staying away it's
a don't use those as your only and we're
not going to be looking at those in
internet explorer but it's touch starts
and then we also have to add the mouse
here because we're doing both okay
because the mouse and touch we don't
want to just react to one of the other
now does anybody spot the flaw in this
code here besides if you read it so at
the beginning it says if all in touch
starts in elements sorry
document.documentelement so if we're
able to do touch my button event handler
sorry did add add event handler touch
Starks blah blah blah else add the
14 click for mouse can't do both at the
same time which means that a device like
this is very very frustrating as i get
to your websites and i have seen this in
probably three or four dozen websites as
i've been researching this this talk
over the past week i get to the website
and i can't use the mouse anymore
because it detects that i have a touch
screen and freaks out whoops okay so so
don't do that so instead what we're
going to do is and I'm going to blow
this code up if i can and i zoom in a
little bit on this two hundred percent
and see now that is unworkable so I'll
just walk you through it sorry about
that the resolution on the screen is
crazy so what we've got is we've got a
if ms pointer enabled so are we able to
do the pointer events if so add those
otherwise we're going to add the touch
starts and the click and so on and so
forth okay so we're going to do a fall
back but I'm actually going to tell you
don't do that instead use one of the
polyfills for pointers okay so this gets
to the browsers support question which
is hand j s polymer pointer events and
points jas are all decent fallbacks
decent polyfills 444 pointer events a
hand j s is the one that i've used the
most at the moment that doesn't mean
it's the best one it just means that
it's the one that i've used the most of
the moment so let me come back over here
to this code and let me show you first
of all what happens in chrome at the
moment so we bring them to bring this up
in chrome let's go to our bricks and we
click and we try to touch and right now
it doesn't understand what pointers are
so no alright so so you've seen that it
doesn't work in chrome so let's go
polyfill that what i'm going to do is
now
oops and so we're going to uncomment
that and we're going to do the exact
same come on out the buttons are just
slightly different places than what I'm
used to hear i'm realizing i
accidentally deleted that paste so now
what we're going to do is instead of ms
pointer we're just going to do that
move copy paste all right so now we've
done we've added that support in but I
also need to go ad in hand is to my HTML
file comment uncommon to that and so now
so you see the reference here to hand
Jess and here is the little bit of code
so if we have MS pointer support great
let's use that otherwise we're going to
polyfill the other browsers to to give
them the amount support as well sorry
the pointer support so now I come back
over here to Chrome Oh again buttons are
in the rug different place here so we're
going to refresh that now and now we
should get so here is with pointer
support in chrome rock and roll oh cool
Multi multi touch support is that easy
okay all we did here is come back over
to this we're using pointer events and
pointer events are going to be a
catch-all for Mouse touch multi-touch as
well as your pins of pork and that type
of thing and han jae s is going to give
us a decent polyfill backwards to other
browsers there is actually a lot of
movement on this particular spec it
moved from a you know we submitted the
spec on sep tember of last year and in
May it became a candidate recommendation
like setting land speed records to get
to candidate recommendation point
because the industry sees that this is a
need this is a problem if you were
watching any of the google i/o stuff
last week Boris got up and talked about
pointers and what a great thing that
they are they are going to be
implementing them in chrome there is a
sample implementation for chromium
firefox has stepped up and said that
they're going to be implementing it no
word from other camps believe that as it
is and so anyway
so that is the the meat of what I wanted
to talk about here with the pointer
events questions on any of that yes
is ie going to are we going to remove
the prefixes in the next version I can't
speak to future roadmap and also three
weeks on the team I don't know that to
be honest but I mean I would assume
whether that's going to be coming at
some points because I mean where you are
going to implement the spec as the spec
is reads and the spec reads as the
polyfill reads which is right here with
the pointers so okay other questions yes
right so so the question was could I
actually remove the MS pointer bit at
the top and the answer is yes I could
remove that and it would work the
problem there that you would run into
there is performance okay because the
image pointers are actually even been
implemented natively on the browser and
are incredibly performance and the
others of polyfill make sense okay but
you could do that if you if it's not a
performance issue for you yes
yes so in the event you'll actually get
that so let me go back over here to the
slides so on the event object you
actually get all of this information and
more okay so one of them is the pointer
type and that will tell you is it a pin
is it a mouse is it as the touch what
kind of pointer is it and you'll you'll
be able to react to that differently yes
there there are constants for those yeah
and I I forget I think they're just one
two three four five type of a thing so
yep yes
okay so browser support for pressure
tilts and hoes the other 10 touch radius
so the MS pointer events they they will
give you tilts and pressure off of a pin
they don't give you that off a touch
because the touch screens are not they
don't quite understand that yet the but
they do well they will give you that off
of a pin I and that as part of the spec
and so the other browsers should be
coming on board with that at some point
in time but it'll be depended upon
devices that actually support the pen
okay all right with that I think oh no I
still have three more minutes yay so you
want to see one more cool thing alright
so one other thing and this is this is
actually a one more little vendor prefix
thing unfortunately but we're getting
there so there is ms scroll and there's
snap points and snap type and then
there's content zooming so i'm going to
go over to a couple of demos here and
show you both of these real quickly so
let me go back here to Internet Explorer
and let's do the carousel first so this
is the traditional scroll so I've got a
oh sorry I need to point at this one I
have a list of images here at the top
and they're just in a list box and we've
you know so you can see there we're
moving and I can move this way and that
you know you see the momentum and you
know but notice where it stops and stuff
okay as it's doing that so then the
other question the other thing i can do
is i can use a this is a jquery touched
carousel okay and so I just touch it and
it's going to slide to the next one okay
but watch watch my fingers I move and
then I release see how that feels ok now
this works right it works but it's not
great I don't really out love it okay so
instead what I'm going to do is I'm
going to come down here to the bottom
one and this bottom one is using the
prefixes that I just talked about here
the
the emesis scrolls snap and snap points
and so now notice it's right underneath
my finger and if I release right there
in that nice i like that a lot ok so
that was that's one of them that I that
I've been playing with recently and I
really really like that one the other
one that i want to show you yes
currently it's that that's an IE thing
okay as far as i know i don't know for
sure I don't know alright so here is the
other thing that's so this is the
content zoom and so ms content zooming
and so we're just going to put that on a
particular div or something like that so
now right right now if I grab the
picture and I'm going to zoom notice
that zooms the entire page that's not
fun right so I'm going to turn that off
I'm sorry maternal in the content zoom
bit and so now notice is just growing
the picture that's cool huh yeah so I
like that one as well what's that so no
it's oops sorry let me go back to their
so it's actually just it's actually set
a zoom level as well and so I can only
zoom to a certain point but that's as
far as it'll zoom to right there but all
that's within inside of the div right
there and it's fine okay all right now
if I close that now go back to here now
I can resume you know that way so all
right so I've done that wrap up a lot of
the stuff that I've talked about is
talked about at the again this one
docstoc web platform org slash pointer
events as well as modern-day e the other
thing with modern data is that modern IE
is a site where you can go up you plug
in your website and it'll actually scan
and look for a lot of common issue
across a lot of different websites so
for example I showed a guy this morning
and it turned out that he was using a
lot of vendor prefixes in his CSS and
was missing the upper ones as well as
the dash ms ones so it's going to look
for those kind of things it's going to
look for responsive web design are you
enabled for touch so on and so forth and
then Doc's that web platform dot org is
a place where we at Microsoft have been
contributing a lot of docs and working
with a lot of other people to make sure
those docs their docs are up to snuff
across all the browsers and so we've
been talking about the pointer events
and then of course go look at the w3c
and see what they're doing with pointer
events and you can always find me at
joshua's com joshin Allah Twitter
dropped at homes at Mexico com feel free
to email me questions and because if I
don't know the answer I'll go see if I
can find it and there will be times i
can't answer but i'll try anyways thank