so hello everyone
Theodore engineer in an applicant
tracking system called workable you can
find me online with under the nickname
wordless and I flew my way here from
Athens Greece actually the verse from
the very same neighborhood the current
aim and being the people air Jensen
takubo was born and raised so today I'm
super excited to be with you because I
have the chance to talk to you about one
of the most interesting projects that I
have ever had the chance to work with so
today we're gonna talk about how
JavaScript and accessibility can can be
used in real-life situations
before we start though it's really
important to take a step back and take a
look her community has evolved over the
past few years we are extremely
extremely blessed to have so many great
people among us
people that have actually broaden our
aspects and our vision so we can talk
beyond code so we can talk about human
rights about inclusivity and more often
about accessibility so what's
accessibility all about if we take a
look at the dictionary term of
accessibility we will find out that
accessibility fair or refers to all
these actions we have to take in order
to create products environments or
systems accessible to everyone as far as
we concerned those software engineers
web developers web designers we are
mostly focused into creating accessible
communication systems like we want to
communicate with our end-users so we are
using semantic hTML we are integrating
external software like screen readers or
external hardware you will be very
surprised though if I tell you that the
very first accessible communication
system was introduced nearly 200 years
ago so this is loose bright bright was
born and raised in a small city outside
of Paris in the early nineteen
chewing and as a child he suffered a
terrible accident that left him
completely blind from both his eyes but
still he has managed to excel his
education and finally got accepted at
the national institution for blind youth
in Paris it was back then where she
found out that the reading and writing
system used by visually impaired people
back in the days were how can I say bit
absurd so people who are using brush
strokes trying to create and boast
letters trying to recreate the alphabet
used by the sighted people
so at the age of 15 yeah 15 she created
the famous brag system brag is a tactile
system it actually it's actually the
very first binary encoding system ever
made so we can actually say that Bragg
was the great-grandfather of computer
science right so usually bright comes in
to a shape of six positions and the
system encodes characters letters or
symbols using combinations of raised
dots and spaces in its very first form a
sly a slate and stylus were used in
order to allow people to write and brag
so the readers can use their fingers
their fingertips trace down the letters
combine them creating words sentences
and so on brag system quotes good it was
actually so good that hasn't literally
changed since its birth as we speak brag
is translated more than 200 languages
and has found applications from math to
music composition and so on okay
so soon after Bragg's death typographers
used heavy weight paper and make endless
type sets and books and brags get start
getting out in public
soon after in the early 20th century
typewriters were invited so modified rag
typewriters allowed the gives provided
the users with a semi-automatic way of
writing break by the way the happy
typing lady you can see in the video
this is
Keller Helen Keller was a famous
American author and activist about human
rights for people with disabilities and
also the very first blind deaf person
that has managed to graduate college
Buckner's third line the last person in
our puzzle was introduced in the late
1990s 1919 so this retro-looking devices
are called a refreshable blog this place
as you can see in the bottom the bottom
device there like a fixed set of bragg
cells brake artists are also known as
bright cells so the users can load text
or they can pair these devices with
external hardware like laptops or mobile
phones so let's recap the year is 2019
organizations and individuals
individuals are raising concerns about
literacy rates over around the globe we
have the tools we have the assets we
have the mindset we have this system
that actually works for so long
so someone could say that we're good in
a really good shape right well actually
wrong numbers and statistics ours are
heartbreaking I called according to the
world World Health Organization 2253
million people are living with visual
impairment all around the globe most of
them are suffering poetry or living
within war zones only 10% of these
people can have access to be appropriate
education material or even a chance to
get a job and someone could say that
cannot relate with within these numbers
right so we're talking about developing
countries or I don't know people living
in Syria or Libya right bear with me for
a moment according to the National
Federation of the blind
90% of visually impaired children living
in the state are not capable of reading
and writing because they're not being
taught brag or a given access to a
proper educational material just to give
you a perspective
about how low these numbers are I'm
gonna compare them against the literacy
rate of Ethiopia Ethiopia is a country
that has suffered poetry and civil war
for more than 30 years but still fifty
percent of the citizens of Theo Pia are
capable of reading and writing the most
important fact about these numbers is
the fact that these numbers are
increasing as we speak year by year but
still bright literacy rates for excuse
me
literacy literacy rates for visually
impaired people living in the States are
stuck since the 70s and we have to think
ourselves what did we do so wrong so
what actually causes this disaster as a
matter of fact we're lucky enough we're
lacking of assets so books brilliantly
brag are like super expensive that cost
three to eight times higher than a
regular book and also just 1% of the
available books are also available for
bribe professor will brag this place are
like super expensive they cost five
hundred to eight thousand dollars
depending on the number of the cells
provided and last but not least
typewriters are super expensive as well
and although the typewriting acknowledge
its a bit observing people are still
using them because they're like a more
appropriate way and they provide the
users with a more delicate way of
writing brag and now imagine that
someone hunched give this problem like
he was a member of the JavaScript
community is there anything that we can
do in order to help these people when I
first tried to test myself break I was
stuck with this problem like lot and I
thought think about I keep thinking
about the like a lot so I have decided
to trying creating a device advice that
we could actually try to mimic how
refreshable break this place work so I
want to try small maybe starting with a
single bright cell and maybe scaling up
as the person as my prototype could
start taking shape before we start
though have to set up some goals right
so since I had no prior
experience with hardware or embedded
development
I wanted my advice to be as simple as
possible obviously it has to be
accessible to everyone and finally I
want to make my device as simple as
possible but how we start is it even
possible for software engineers like me
to prototype hardware device apparently
piece we're gonna accelerate that our
development process using a piece of
technology called micro controllers so
micro controllers for those that are not
familiar with the subject are like tiny
computational units they're usually
coming into the shape of a board they're
relatively cheap and easy to get our
hands on Arduinos raspberry PI's photon
just name a few so for the purpose of
this experiment I have decided to one to
stick with one of the most famous one
Arduino Uno I purchased mine online from
like a couple bucks as you can see the
board has pins popping out from the
device so labeled with numbers so we can
actually expand the functionality of the
board just by attaching or detaching
external modules sensors and so on so
for the purposes of this experiment I
want to start coding and experimenting I
will try the hello world hello world the
project of hardware development like
flashing an LED light so I have attached
an LED on pin labeled 13 and the ground
just power up the LED but how can we
code a development board so they are
doing a comes with an IDE called the
Arduino IDE obviously and we can use C
code just to write code for the device
assemble piece of code for flattened LED
would look like this so we're
initializing the pin labeled 13th we are
doing of house building functions like
the setup function show we're setting
the the appropriate pin as an output and
it has also a loop function that runs
all the time so we're gonna blast the
LED look high and low using a delay
of 500 milliseconds and that piece of
code actually works but as I was trying
and experimenting with different modules
and I was trying to integrate my device
with maybe a web interface
I found myself stuck just be honest with
you haven't written C since my college
years so it was really hard and luckily
there was stumped up on the project
called John 5
so John fives an ID in a platform
developed by Canadian company called Bo
coop that allows us to write JavaScript
code no Jes code for microcontrollers in
some cases like the raspberry PI's we
can create standalone prototypes in our
case using the Arduino we can actually
remotely johnny-five creates a think
lines so we can actually remotely
control the device from our development
machine and we can actually rewrite the
flashing example the flashing LED
example just like including the
johnny-five module initializing a new
board and using the callback when the
board is ready we're going to flash the
LED using the blink LED the blinking LED
function and I can barely hear some of
you whispering what's wrong with this
with this guy why does he want to write
JavaScript for a freaking
microcontroller okay
when JavaScript was born it was the
implementation was how can say a bit
naive so we will use JavaScript as an
event-driven programming language and
this thing actually works the same
concepts work for microcontrollers
you're gonna integrate external external
components with your device so you're
gonna you have to listen for buttons
clicking or flashing LED and so on and
JavaScript feels way too natural to
program these boards also you can use
the registry we can use whatever is on
the registry and enhance our development
experience so we can use loaders for
utilities you can use the Bluetooth API
web service whatever you can imagine if
we can bring the same experience from
the web
to the micro controllers also
portability it's a real thing
so even within the same family like they
are doing a family we have different
software and hardware specs from device
to device so they are do know is totally
different from the Arduino none of the
Arduino mega and so on but we can use
the same code for different devices and
that's actually awesome
and finally least but not last we have
to admit that it's in our DNA we are
trying to run JavaScript actually
everywhere so we want to make developers
have using JavaScript giving them the
ability to actually create products from
the web for the web for the server for
mobile devices smartwatches
so when not giving them the ability to
run code for a microcontroller right and
next up that was really rough period I
had to teach myself using something like
a 3d design software so that piece of
hardware that looks like a blue lasagna
that's a brag sell my original idea
please don't judge so my original idea
was that I could somehow create
individual bright cells that could be
easily attached or detached with the
device since this was a prototyping
period I could I used my own 3d printers
so it was really relatively easy to
design something evaluate the design and
keep the process going on and finally we
have to think how are you gonna actually
pop up in how can we translate data to
motion so as I kept experimenting with
different modules I have decided to
stick up with this little fellow this is
called the solenoid so solenoids are
like tiny push and pull actuators they
have a tiny electromagnet inside they
are actually used for watering systems
or electronic lock so using six
solenoids combined I can create a brake
cell since they're like six positions
per
CEL I purchased mine I purchased a bunch
of them for like a couple of bucks
online and finally we can bring
everything together so first things
first we have to think how we can
actually encode text brags so taking up
the alphabet numbers and symbols as you
can see we've done allocate an array of
six positions so zeros stand for Adel
pins and once stand for rest pins
unfortunately the brag alphabet ins is
not deterministic so we have to actually
create a map of all the available
characters letters and symbols and
afterwards we can create a symbol
utility function that takes up a
character as a single parameter and
turns the brag representation next up we
can create a really simple class that's
cell class in the constructor we are
using the allocated pin so we want six
pins from the board in order to control
it solenoid so we're using six pins as
an argument for the constructor and the
journey 5 instance and finally using a
private method that accepts a single
argument we can decide we can look
through the through the array of the
race the middle pins and decide if pin
is up or it's down so the this class is
stateful so we don't have to we don't
have to reset the pins it's time the
characters change and finally our main
product would look like this we're
including the 25 module we're including
the cell class we're initializing the
board and one of the board is ready
we're creating a new instance of the
brake cell using just six pins as an as
arguments and finally printing out the
character a so I think most of you are
quite bored right now so why not bring
up a live demo for you
okay let me break down the slide a bit
so as you can see I have here I have
life in from my camera this just be
honest with you this is my very first
time in the state and I got really
scared of getting detained at the
airport so so I had to break down a
device and I just bring with blood with
me a single character so my
interpretation runs using javascript and
HTML in my browser so um I have a live
feed from my camera on the right side on
the left side I have I'm using a
brilliant typeface called bright knowing
which will give you a visual
representation of the characters pretty
doubt and using the input text field on
the top I can write something and print
out print it out from the device just
like that so let's try to write
something meaningful rather than hello
world okay cross your fingers
thank you so much so apparently our
prototype works it works have every
single time I promise you so let's bring
up some results as you can see I had no
prior experience with embedded
development but the embedded development
her family as well as the JavaScript
community are really helpful so building
up this device was relatively stable no
sophisticated coding no sophisticated
modules everything was purchased from
online so we can say we have achieved
that goal next up we can actually expand
this device so based on the number of
pins provided by the device we can
expire we can attach or detach browsers
on demand and finally we can bring up to
12 cells just for 40 bucks so we have to
think ourselves oh sorry what's next so
I wish as we speak I'm trying to
improvise the device I'm working on the
second version and I'm trying actually
to improve the design and get feedback
from from static groups from people that
could actually use this device in order
to learn bright also so naturally
beautiful prototyping but they're a bit
clunky and they're energy inefficient so
I think we can improve the design using
a piece of module called micro snipers
these are tiny tiny stepper modules that
are used in controlling camera lenses or
DVD Drive so we can actually recycle old
parts and improve the design using a
bunch of them and finally using micro
stepper motors we can bring we can
improve we can actually reduce the cost
of the actual device finally I think
people can use this same piece of
technology and create their own devices
like attach creating something like a
weather station for people that need to
know that weather using sensors modules
and so on and actually you can go beyond
25 and try different frameworks like
this premium one which is actually
project that runs JavaScript in the
microcontroller and for the past one
year and a half I kept dot I keep
talking and presenting this device to
people and I keep thinking I have
different talks with some colleagues of
mine and people that I meet at various
meetups and conferences and I have
thought about maybe trying to seek for
funding or raising crowds crowdfunding
campaign because I want more people to
have the ability to use this device and
actually help people but instead wanna
ask for your help so the entire
prototype is open-source and you can
find it online you can actually build
this device for yourself for yourselves
I think it's a great project to get you
started with the IOT world in the
upcoming months we I'm planning of
delivering the very first bright
open-source bright britain printer that
runs JavaScript as well so we're
experimenting with some wearables so
great things to come and I actually
think that we as the JavaScript
community we can do more so somehow we
do actually care and we are now openly
speaking about things that actually
matter this beyond the digital world and
if there's something that you can take
away from this presentation is the fact
that we are we have power in numbers
and we can actually really raise
awareness and at the at the very end we
can somehow affect the world thank you
so much for your time and patience
[Applause]