hi thanks for coming I'm of me and I'm
Chris you may know me from organizing
events such as jazz calm I also
unfortunately have become somewhat of a
community person for better or for worse
and as part of running Jays comp and
being amongst everybody I think it's
vitally important that we try to talk
about and address our issues whatever
they may be and I think that the issue
of diversity in terms of gender and
racial diversity within our community is
a vitally important thing that we don't
talk about as much as we probably should
there we did we've tried to make jazz
conf a platform in place that we can
talk about these issues and hopefully
try to change them last year we did the
gender diversity drive where we were
able to donate over $3,000 from your
efforts to local outreach programs where
they would teach young kids how the
computing Sciences work in a hope that
that lasting moment would carry them
throughout the rest of their lives and
they would enter into our field I see
this dialogue as a vitally important
thing and something that isn't meant to
be a point in time but meant to be the
start of something that we continue for
a longer period of time thanks Chris and
as a woman and I I do appreciate like
Chris's approach to this and attempts to
to try to improve it because i've been
working in computer science for 15
almost 15 years now I I was 19 when I
started developing I was in my first
programming group and I was with all
males and it and I think when you're
that young and you see a lot of women
today when you're that young you're
really impressionable and you accept the
status quo because you feel like okay
this is what it is and you feel like
okay I
have to kind of live with what the
current state and it's taken a long time
for me to come around to a
transformation in my thought process to
see that yeah maybe I can affect change
maybe I can help increase the number of
women or increase diversity in computing
and to realize that I don't have to
accept things when I'm not okay with
them so I that's why this is important
to me and that's why I wanted to have
this discussion the last couple of years
I've been working with the random acts
of kindness and the Grace Hopper
conference to try to increase numbers
like try to get at least twenty percent
at hackathons try to get to get more
women coming and participating in trying
and the way we want to approach this is
to not look at specific instances we're
not looking at instance definitionally
want to look at a class definition we
want to look at it more a holistic
approach and see if we can define and
help define help start a discussion
about how to approach this and see what
can be done and with that we don't we
don't think that this dialogue is going
to solve anything we don't we don't want
to pretend that what we're hoping is
that it's a long fix but it is a fix
that are a change that does happen it's
a longer-term sort of thing that will
require many discussions and this is
just one of those just to start so what
are the benefits of diversity studies
have shown that you know actually less
integrated groups do actually function
better so and that's I mean if you think
about it kind of makes sense if
everyone's like you in the group you
think that it would work better it kind
of somewhat feels right but that that
goes against what we're trying to talk
about here but we wanted to if the
research shows that we wanted to sort of
talk about that first off right and I
think it's a tendency of people like to
be around people who are like themselves
right i mean you kind of have a sense of
comfort around people who think like you
and you can actually get a lot done that
way but so so why do this what are they
what advantages does diversity give you
and and what we're fine like what we're
like after Chris and I read a lot we we
found like what you lose is you
basically are you're losing a larger
pool because you have thirty to forty
percent of the population that's
untapped and we need more computer
scientist we need I mean there's so much
work there's so much good stuff that
still needs to be done that we need more
people to do it and by being non-diverse
we lose it we lose a huge segment of the
population it's also a great way to grow
your community I don't yeah JS comp is a
crazy experiment that sometimes fails
sometimes succeeds and I would argue
that the more diverse ideas you have
from diverse backgrounds whether whether
it be gender diversity or racial
diversity we all come from different
life experiences in different life
scenarios we all that crafts our view of
life and if we were to be blind to the
other experiences of life we might miss
out on our own experiences that we might
be able to have just because we are like
somebody else might mean that we're
missing out on a good deal of life that
we would otherwise be better served to
experience if someone once told me that
ninety percent of the response that
somebody gives you or it like if you if
you tell someone something ninety
percent of the response is based on
their history and ten percent is
actually from what you said and I think
you lose when you don't have all that
history you don't have all that
background you lose a lot of experiences
and a lot of perspectives that you can
you can have into your products into
your market into your into your culture
and studies have also shown like the
reverse which is that when you do have a
woman in management you have a better
retention of your women developers
because they're
it's against the like the you know being
around people you like or being around
people who like you that's not right
being around people who are like or
similar to similar to you and it's it
it's when you when you have that support
in management it allows the developers
to know yet they're okay too and they
have the support from the company or the
community that they need I'm going to
stray away from this for just a second I
would argue that we need to look at this
not as we would look at software many of
us are or use almost all of us i would
guess at this point our use at least you
have a phone that is open source
developers where we believe that ideas
should be free and that multiplicity of
ideas is better than singularity of an
idea otherwise we'd all run windows XP
so in that same realm I view that we
should have an open mind about cultures
backgrounds experiences and ideas and
you know it really makes life a lot more
richer all around there is a recent New
York Times article that's that
bilingualism nikki's makes you smarter
so there's that too that's okay
different cultures different
perspectives make a stronger group so
statistically speaking so what are the
numbers and I think and I think to
understand like how we can solve this we
have to look at the current state and
the current state actually has its it's
in in in the corporate world it's
actually twenty five percent women it's
really it's it's you know it's pretty
respectable but numbers are actually
declining because nationally only
fourteen percent of women RCS graduates
and and of course it keeps going down
from there and open sores it's two
percent all right and if you look at
that I think Chris was talking about a
huge aggradation yeah one of the things
that I've been a proponent in discussing
is that we're at a pooling problem there
are less women who go into the computing
sciences as younger individuals and
their that leads to less women in
college curriculum
computer science which leads to less
women in the professional field which
ends up out of various different
conferences having an even lower thing
and as this is going to continue through
generationally it's just going to get
worse unless we try to stop the problem
not at the end but all the way at the
beginning pool if we can increase the
number of people at that beginning pool
it may take a while generation or two
hey I believe we're going to talk about
an exam state yeah it starts young we
have to start we have to fix the problem
at the root otherwise we're looking at
it too short-sighted and it'll just end
up right back where we are yeah and
change is happening I mean we it can't
happen and it is currently happening
like I was looking at this this has been
pretty well talked about that Harvey
Mudd College their president Maria Chloe
she put into place she basically changed
the cs curriculum in order to increase
the number of women in the program and
she attacked like she approached the
gender gap issue by basically offering
three types of introduction to computer
science courses because she kind of
realized that one Java wasn't working
for everyone so she switched to python
and two for the intro for the intro
language and two she realized that a lot
of the guys came into the classes with a
background in programming there's a
class for that but now there's also a
class for beginners and then there's
also a third type of class which is a
class it's called cs4 scientist which is
like a leaning toward biology so too
because they're there is already a large
percentage of women in in the sciences
so she figured well if we kind of tie it
to that maybe that will make them feel
more comfortable and it's worked because
if the numbers have gone from twelve
percent to thirty-five percent and in
2011 the class has forty percent women
so that's a phenomenal change that she's
been able to do I think in like five
years and then I think there are more
examples like that at the boss at PyCon
the Boston Python users group talked
about how they doubled their membership
and went
up to fifteen percent women by doing
just one year of workshop and I think
what we I think in in the JavaScript
community I think we are the community
right and I think we need in order for
change to happen we need more more
action like this yeah and I think it's
it seems hard seems almost impossible
because the numbers are declining but
let's give a parallel to medicine
medicine in the medical field in 1905
had a four percent female to female
ratio to ninety-six percent mail by 1994
it was at twenty-five percent female and
last year it was at fifty percent almost
parity which is impressive it's almost a
to generational change and so I would
challenge I think both of us would
challenge everyone here and ourselves to
see if we could get to that to
generational change or ideally do it in
less time odd generation it's going to
take time it's going to take discussion
and it's going to take action and we
have to start that somewhere so how many
of how many of you here know a girl or a
woman in your life that's like either
relative or a daughter or a nice or do
you guys have I think everybody has a
female some proximity to their life
right if you aren't we have a bigger
gender diversity issue it should be
about fifty percent right a 51-percent
statistically okay so that's an
immediate impact you can have right
there someone who's close to you because
this this affects that you know this
this affects them you want to we want to
create a world where it's not like they
have to choose computer science but they
know that option is there I think that's
the key it's it's that they know that
option is there and they're free to
choose it and they don't self-select out
of it and I think it's interesting like
medicine has changed so much that you
know women don't self-select out of it
anymore because the culture has changed
but and it's interesting to maybe
discuss why why do women self-select out
of
em fields why do they self select out of
computer science and engineering and I
think everyone had every reason is
different but we want to you can make a
direct impact with the people you know
yeah and I think if everyone thinks back
to where they first got that inspiration
that hey computers are cool you're
probably going to come back to a point
where somebody who was older than you
orden you know in proximity to you made
some sort of change in your life made
some sort of reach out some sort of
encouragement it might have been an
apple two gs that your parents bought
you in carmen sandiego and then you
figured out how to hack the rom on it
but there was some sort of catalyst
point that drove you down this pathway
so one of the things that we want to try
to put out there and we've got some
supplies here is to try to be that
catalyst to try to go out and you know
people in your community in your
proximity who are young and
impressionable impress on them to go
into the computing sciences that it to
not self-select out of it essentially we
have do want to tell what we have yeah
you and do it now you doing all right
I've already had my Oprah moment today
all right so we have this is so we have
a hundred html5 intro HTML Remy's book
basically so and you can only have one
if you're going to share it with a with
a girl or a woman and or or a or a non
well represented race grouping at a
general tech conference and basically if
you look to your left you look to your
right those are roughly not going to be
the people who we want you to take these
books and teach we want we would we want
to go for that generation that next
generation of change yeah if you're just
willing to share it if you're willing to
share it and and by all means you can
use it to impress in purse a you can use
it to get men or boys into computing
science and and that's great but also
try
think to get other people yeah and other
other people we also have 15 Arduino
kids this is think 1515 Arduino kits for
you to share and build something we have
10 USBs with the Alice program from CMU
and the scratch program from MIT on it
and those are really great learning tool
learning programming languages for for
kids we're going to hand those out after
this so don't everyone run up on stage
right now acha source we have access
cards yeah I don't know if those came in
then Mozilla is doing a thing called
hack a source which is actually really
cool if you've never heard of hacker
source what they've done is they've
tried to make web inspector a fun game
like a learning utility game check it
out I think it's just typing hack
asaurus into google or something and
you'll find it and that's a great way to
you know if you have a daughter say hey
Virginia in my case going back to my own
personal experience Virginia let's go
play with the web browser and figure out
how to inspect the DOM and that gives me
a chance to spend time with my daughter
which is great she's gonna love dad the
youngest btg author next year yes she'll
be running the conference all of
disappeared but I do want to say is this
another slide oh that that's our
challenge so our challenges to take
these items and go and help make that
generational or sector you know to
generational change that if we can do
this we can accelerate it yeah and I
think Chris and I were just discussing
right before this which is when you're
at a conference I was telling him about
the Grace Hopper conference which is the
exact opposite of this it's 2,000 women
and maybe like 50 men and it's it's a
huge difference in the way I feel at a
conference and it was odd because I got
you with some questions that were like
the inverse of what we normally would
discuss and I think the result was to
push each other to go to different
venues yes to try to go to a conference
that made
you you don't you might not be the
majority and also like when you're at a
conference where you are the majority to
reach out to someone you see who who is
not I tend to be more of a Wallflower at
the conferences where I'm not the
majority but I'm totally different
person at the conferences where I am and
I had that experience very recently
where Laura she's a floral designer and
so I attend an event with her and it's
incredibly flipped I would almost say
this is more diverse than those events
and I wallflower died I felt the
awkwardness and I I don't want to say
that I understand by any means how it
feels but it's good for us to push
ourselves as individuals and as a
community to do these events to go to
different events that we normally would
not go to so we can try to get to a
point where we all have some common
level of understanding of what it's like
to be I hate the term but in that
smaller demographic and then by that way
we at least have some level that we can
have intellectual discourse on these
items and I think the last point we
wanted to bring up was that it's like
just to be inclusive and that everyone
makes mistakes think and really it's
just about just acknowledging it and
then moving on because nothing is
irreparable and I think the one one
thing in health care because I work in
healthcare now at mgh and one thing I've
noticed is like health care
professionals always talk about instead
of saying someone is autistic like for
as an example they would say someone has
autism and because when you say someone
is something it kind of permanently
describes them as as having that
attribute versus when you say somebody
has something if a little more temporal
it can change can improve you know can
you know because I can be used by a
wider group so like you could say that
some some comment has sexist tones to it
versus calling the individual and and
that as men in this gender diversity
specific component of it we should be
willing to say that comment has sexist
tones to it
because then its temporal and we can
help the the group or individual that
set it to change or see the potential
error in how they were viewing it helped
to make the overall dialogue a lot
better and I want to make that point
more as an empowerment to the majority
male group here that it's our
responsibility just as much as the
female responsibility to make those
items known and help try to change them
that it can't just be you know a
balancing act and I think there is a
large there it can change I think it can
get better and it will get better I
think there's there's a huge there's a
lot of smart women a lot of smart
diverse people dying to contribute dying
to learn and I think we just need to be
a little more inclusive accepting of
them I mean when you're outside a group
you're just learning so I think is just
to just to be accepting and answer their
questions and start that way so please
take the challenge please try to show a
girl in your life a girl or a diverse
person in your life how to program and
or just something or invite her to a
common invite her to an event invite her
to a meetup there's so many of them out
there just please please take the next
step I think we can we can definitely
make a change and marco are you out
there thank you if you haven't read
Marcos post you really should and thank
you very much
so like I like we had mentioned this is
not meant to be a just a quick dialogue
or a quick talk we want to have the
discussion lets you know continue the
discussion we have the next day and a
half to have some really good dialogues
and i welcome you out there to have
dialogues with each other as well and
that's the only way that or the best way
that we can get to a better
understanding of everything so thank you