I'm going to be talking about Orion
which is not an online IDE it's
different but you'll you'll see that if
you're curious right now you can just go
to that URL it's eclipse.org / Orion and
you can sign up and play with it if
you're bored by my talking because I'm
going to just start with this a few
things that don't actually demo Rhine
because I want to make a kind of bigger
point here so um ok my name is Boris
Michalski should probably say I'm an
eclipse guy so I have this Java
background I'm transitioning to
JavaScript learning a lot it's a lot of
fun and but really originally I'm a
small talk dude so anyway so to start
off first some authorizations
observations as software developers who
are one of the few professions that can
actually build our own tools and we
enjoy doing that so it's like a
carpenter might build out Jake or
something that helps him get his work
done faster we do the same kind of thing
and we we enjoy doing tools and software
development as it started was stuff on
the command line and it got really
powerful so you can do funny things and
the command line is really nice because
you can add new tools and all these
little tools that you can build yourself
or get from others are integrated by
accessing the file system or using those
pipes and filters and their scripting
but distribution is a bit of a problem
because if you've written something in
some language that and you want to give
it to somebody else they have to have
the same kind of environment they maybe
have to recompile that stuff so
but it's it's a nice way to to develop
software you have all these tools and
you can add whatever you want so there's
a another way of working of doing
software developing that's those big
IDEs this is the one that I've been
working on for a couple years and I the
ease give you deeper integration so for
example in Eclipse you get not only the
file system but you get change events as
an eclipse plugin there's integration in
terms of the errors and warnings all
appearing in one place there's a certain
level of you I consistency it's a UI
level tool not a command line tool those
kinds of things but it's pretty
difficult to write plugins or two right
tools that run in this environment and
get this kind of deep integration and
the distribution problem is not solved
at all you have to package up your stuff
you have to give it to somebody else
they have to find the place in eclipse
where you add a plug-in all those kinds
of things so my claim now is with the
web we have a third alternative of doing
things and and why is that well
obviously our software developers we
spend a lot of time in browsers
especially web developers but but
everybody basically is doing
backtracking planning tracking bills may
be browsing documentation in the browser
already and then there's tools like
cloud 9i te and Orion that address the
core development activities like editing
code navigating files and folders
running unit tests debugging those kinds
of things and then there are lots of
little tools and what do I mean with
lots of little tools I mean these kinds
of things where it's really easy for
somebody to just make a tool available
out out there on the web and when I say
a lot of little tools I really mean a
lot of little tools so i spent 23 hours
just googling for web-based tool various
flavors and these are some of the things
that I found
so there's stuff for CSS and rounded
corners build related things picking
colors coming up with a scaffolding for
website sharing code snippets
understanding regular expressions doing
what requests for formatting code and
it's amazing the amount of innovation
that's out there is amazing
and it's a lot I don't know so um how
many of you have built such a tool and
put it online somewhere only one can't
believe it how do you end up with these
many tools so i think the web is
becoming a platform for software
development tools because all these
things are part of the software
development workflow and it's really
easy to add those tools and you just get
to them by urls and the distribution
problem is solved as long as those
things run in all the browsers and the
big open problem is integration how do
these tools work together how how can
you ensure that as you transition from
one tool to another that you don't have
to download or upload stuff into one
tool download results and then upload
into the next tool and so on and so
forth and this is what Ryan is about
it's about figuring out how we can make
those tools work together so and now
it's demo time
so all this was running from within
Orion so it's um was a little bit risky
or it's still risky running this from an
external site this is the orion editor
and there's the the rhine navigator and
let me close this to make it probably
hide
ok so I'll navigators so it's basically
files and folders and you can get to the
root by clicking here and then you get
get into things and all these things are
links and there are links because then
what we get is all the browser gestures
for doing things that browsers are good
at for example open stuff in new tabs
and by doing this I I was able to open a
second instance of that navigator on a
seven-second browser tab so um that's
what I mean by this is not an IDE it's
not putting and not translating the IDE
concepts that we like I've worked on for
the past couple years into a web app
that's on one tab but instead using the
web itself as the platform and then if
these various places that you go to for
example the navigator and the editor I
know you go here and that replaces the
navigator with the editor code and by
doing that you can ensure that as the
functionality grows as you add more
stuff to this you add more stuff by
adding more pages or new pages to it and
you don't get the load problems
airplane mode okay yeah sorry about that
I need my notes so um and but the editor
itself so it's it's a standalone thing
on this page and if i go back i get back
to the navigator mm-hmm so all those
navigation things work let me just get
to a place where there's a little bit of
JavaScript
so for example here so there's the usual
things work in the editor that I don't
know commenting out a block of code
giving stuff up and down undo redo copy
paste all those things and it's it's
really fast like ace so not a problem
getting too I don't know over 100,000
lines of code and you can still type
down here and you get the syntax
highlighting and doesn't work only at
the bottom you can go to the top two if
you try to reload you get the the prompt
and yes I do want to go back there
support for error um checking and
displaying errors and there's nothing in
here okay let's do something bad
so if it was somewhere else I could
still see there's an error up here that
moves me up there I can hover over that
and get the wonderful jslint error
message so as you can see this is not
something where we have invested all of
effort into making those error message
is really good it's more that we think
our focus needs to be on making those
integrations and the basic
infrastructure available and to that end
we make things like the ruler work and
have plug points where people can add
tools or we can add tools like jslint to
this story there's also a well that's
not very helpful but it's a place where
you can jump between different places in
the code and this information is also
coming from jay is lint okay so i said
it's about integration how how do you
make those tools work really well
together and you could always go to jays
lynch right you could go on to the
jslint on page and you could copy paste
your code in here but things like that
you want to pull into your editor
environment and make available there and
that's what we've done so we have this
the jslint code coming here as a
so-called plugin so a plugin is
something that we run on the page and
it's a hidden i frame and then we talk
to that thing using windows window post
message and in the example of the error
checking we give it the current editor
buffer and it comes back with a list of
problems so that could be jslint or it
could be jeaious hint or it could be
something entirely different what this
also enables is as I because it's an
iframe that we talk to we can make
things
we can enable things where the code that
gets added is actually coming from a
different domain so for example if i
went to something that was minified code
and wanted to to have that formatted i
could either copy paste this code into
some other web site like I don't know
Jay is beautified or org is one
possibility but again that's something
that doesn't really flow well so what
we've done is we've built something
which essentially is the JS beautify org
code plus a few lines of blue stuff that
talks that window post message for the
call to the Orion editor and I can go
and take this URL and install it into
Orion so that installs that plugin for
my account and installing that thing
will run lotus called once and cash
metadata about it like the the name of
that thing and an image and then next
time I come to an editor which should be
somewhere here okay so this was the
place where I wanted to format and now I
got this new action here which is
formatting my JavaScript and if I click
that at that point we load the iframe
and apparently it's kind of slow stop
using the Internet okay so loads the
iframe and then sends over the editor
buffer to that code it formatted in that
hidden iframe sends back a new buffer
and the same kind of idea is behind the
navigator so um yeah like this page so
in the navigator for example we're
currently browsing files on the Orion
server but this is pluggable and we
could be talking to some other server
that maybe speaks a different protocol
like
dev and display that in the Orion
navigator hmm ok how how have I run this
demo here this is this was basically I
went and forked on github actually this
is the the Orion clan code is up on
github too so you can take this URL or a
read only thing and and in Ryan clone
that so we have a good support there and
that gave me this this directory J is
conf and then I can go and see what have
I changed so we have a little bit of get
you i implement it already so there's
things like my local changes i can see
the diff here I can if I want show that
in side-by-side this is something that
the eclipse guys um wanted to see here
where you have the old and new side by
side you can go back to the git status
page and you can leave that open as a
new tab and then whenever you go
somewhere else and you make a change you
go on the get status tab again hit
reload and you would get a new result of
of running gift status essentially and
from here you can say stage this stage
that enter a commit message
okay I think I've run through most of
the features of Orion and maybe another
point that I should make is that there
is a server that implements this and
because we're we used to be Java guys we
implement that server in Java but
there's nothing in the concept behind a
line that says it has to be one server
so for example this this full-text
search feature here is implemented using
solar and leucine oh no matches wanna
know maybe slide okay lots of matches
this is running in one Java VM right now
on the server side but it could well be
a different server that just calls my
resources calls my files and folders if
I have given access to that other server
so we've architected our servers such
that these things can be separated and
others can come along and say we have
much better code search so maybe the
google code search could crawl your
stuff and then make that and then plug
their functionality into with the plugin
mechanism into this search box up here
or there's a way to to basically launch
or make your your content available on
the web so that's similar to what cloud
nine is doing to and this is the URL
that my slides were on no it's not in
XHTML anyway making that available on
the web like that makes it possible to
go to other tools that are out there on
the web where you can just put that URL
in and then Google PageSpeed online
analyzes your stuff and gives you
results gives you hints for how to speed
up things so we're looking for those
kinds of things where there's other
tools they're out there already and how
can we make those part of your
development flow without everybody
having to write to a particular
api and with that i'm just going to give
you a few more links here the client
side of Orion has recently been
relicense and it's bsd license now and
the server side is EPL licensed and if
you want to find out more i would
suggest you go to that first URL there
any questions yes do we have local
history know right now we don't I would
like to implement something like that
but I would like it be part of the gate
support or you just have a micro branch
that's generated for you automatically
that shouldn't be too hard anything else
okay if you have other questions or wood
or have a tool that you think would be
interesting to integrate with this talk
to me and i'll be there snack i think
upstairs now and i'll walk there and if
you want to grab me that'd be awesome