if everyone can hear me and if not use
your imagination so yeah my name is dave
stevens i am here from zappos hence the
oversized logo behind me there and I
just wanted to talk to you about using
happy plugins to version your API and
try not have this fall off my ear while
I do so quick thing on me because I'm
not famous as you may have noticed
started using node back in 2010 going to
hold this down here because ice flying
all around me ok cool and first use
happy at the end of last year on a
personal recommendation of a friend and
we actually managed to get something
into customer-facing production at the
end of last year and then a/b test for
6pm calm the mobile views which is our
sister site and we have happy eight in
production today on internal analytics
API not quite Black Friday at Walmart
foot we're doing our best so quick
project setup for what I'm going to go
through I'll keep this brief I wrote up
a big long post about how I like to
organize happy plugins that bit ly URL
will take you there if you would like to
know why I've structured it in this way
but we've got this one controller which
is going to give us information about
our API the info controller and our main
application just uses glue because i
like the compose functionality that got
removed in version 8 to set up a server
and run out and 49 thousands pulling in
the info module is a plug-in that plugin
looks like this very simple it captures
the root of / version and has a handler
there which we'll look at next and it
just replies back with the name of the
API the example API and a version number
which is one in this instance okay so
once that's running
this co request will return back this
JSON response which is very exciting I
know you're all dying for me to push
this live but unfortunately it's just an
example but now we've got to the point
where everyone was so excited by it we
want to go on to version 2 and improve
it because it you know didn't do too
much and we're going to introduce some
breaking changes but we're going to be
good net citizens we're not going to
break the previous calls for anyone that
is relying on it and we're going to
version our API so before in the modules
section we just had an index j s and
then this version handler which itself
at an index j s we're now going to break
this down into version 1 and version 2
of our api first thing we're going to do
we're going to take the current version
handler and we're going to move that to
version 1 the idea here being that
version 1 is the one that was already
there so this will then become your
default as well so anyone that doesn't
update their code will later receive
this and achieving that just by moving
it into that folder version 2 gets
really fancy almost as big of a
announcement is happy version 8 today is
that we now give you a status code and
we we have our breaking change instead
of the name in the version being
directly ahead in in the response object
we now have this application detail
object so then when we move over to our
version handler this is where we're
going to start looking at the versioning
okay so what we first of all do is we
check to see whether an api version
parameter has been certain in the route
and we do a quick test to make sure that
it just matches the v and then a number
format with a regular expression just
for security purposes never trust
anything the user puts in and then we
require
the local folder that matches that
version number here and we passed
through the request and the reply below
that we have our default full back as I
mentioned before which says if no
version is specified give them version 1
because that's what they'll be expecting
the info plugin we now have a slight
change we've added in another route
which has the API version specified and
that's the only change that we do there
we leave versions still pointing to this
dispersion handler that we just saw so
once we have this set up like so testing
on this URL parameter if we curl as we
did before we get the same response so
we're not breaking anything for anybody
else but if we put in v1 as our API
version parameter again we get the same
response because the default is version
1 but then we change it to version two
and now our responses from the the other
handler when I was looking in subversion
a pis there's a really good article by
Troy hunt feel familiar with them on the
three wrong ways because no matter which
one you choose and you say i'm going to
version my api this way somebody has a
complaint about it so if you've done a
bit ly URL so you can look up that
article if you're interested he
describes the the three different ways
that he likes to version api's the first
we've already covered but then they
should actually say custom request
header but everything's about customer
where I work so apparently i just typed
customer when i was making this so we're
going to add in the ability to handle a
custom request header that we've
specified API dash version as a way to
specify which versions the API we want
the requests come to be handled with and
that gets at this happens here and the
second piece where again we test to make
sure that it's nothing malicious coming
in and then again we
I require from the folder that matches
the version that's passed in so here we
are a curl to test it because doing
things old-school is the way I like to
do everything and we get that that
version one back if we pass in version 2
than the responses from the second
iteration that we came up with for a
fancy handler but you'll notice that the
URL in both of those stays the same then
the third method he suggests is the
specifying accept error with the
application and then the vendor in there
which we can again test on in a similar
manner and then require based on the
value that gets passed in so again this
is what it may look like for the example
API company name I don't have a start-up
you might have noticed I'm other than
naming things this is an example of that
as much as it is an example of the API
so you pass in v1 and you get the first
response and you pass in v2 and you get
the second response if you can imagine
here we've got this set up that I showed
earlier where we just have these folders
based in different places this is a very
small application so that works out
quite well if you can imagine in a
larger application or in a large company
where you have different teams doing
different things each folder could
actually be its own mpm module on a
private repo or even the public one if
that works for you devil-may-care and
all that which could then have its own
repository so everyone could work
independently and then you can just say
okay in this folder I want to pull in
this version of that controller in this
folder I want to pull in the next so
finally go we'll be back through to the
ends these are the various ways you can
contact me if you
are so inclined trying to put out as
much as we've learned unhappy on medium
at the moment so if you follow twitter
you'll see those and then also at the
bottom there is a repository with the
example application for you to try out
for yourself if you want to play around
with it also the slides from today if
you were just blown away by those and
finally the concept of doing that
testing on the three different ways you
conversion your API I was a very hungry
at lunch so I turned that into a plug-in
itself so as soon as I've come up with a
cool name for it which as I said I
struggle with I'll publish that and show