yeah this is my personal subtitle of the
talk which is why you know give me one
point oh and it's kind of funny actually
because that subtitle is really sort of
the crux of the talk but before I go
into that I'm trailer Robbins I go by
the index zero on the Internet I started
a company called no jitsu with some guys
back there and that little seal there
everything is that we made this so and
when I say that no one point 0 is really
the crux of this talk is that it's just
what's the problem right how do you run
something in production that is by
definition unstable right like it's kind
of a it's a catch-22 right it's a
Occam's razor you know it's no good what
do you do let's start small right like
little things right you probably want to
be listening for errors so this is a
pretty common pattern but what the thing
is in a lot of this code that I see
people don't include the last line right
so they don't include process not exit
so that means that oh I've got something
went wrong and I'm just going to assume
that that things are fine and things
will fix themselves that's that's wrong
don't do that you're gonna you're going
to kick yourself later I think I could
name five off the top of my head your
HTTP parser is borked you know the
sockets are going to stay open when they
should be half closed like the list goes
on just don't do this use this snippet
log your log things somewhere if you're
really good you can log it in database
so you know grey log 2 we use log liat
no jitsu it's great service hoptoad I
know people use that too and you know
when I talk about listening for errors
you really gotta listen for errors like
all of them even the ones that aren't
documented as errors and this is a great
little snippet this will get you so this
is we're going to make an outgoing
request to google com really really
simple straightforward stuff and the
HTTP module is going to return us a
request and that request actually throws
an error event if something goes wrong
in the inner socket and that little code
line on the bottom is where this error
gets thrown and you can read through
that if you're really interested but if
you don't catch this error your apps
just going to crash for no good reason
so you want to look at where the error
events are you want to read the docs and
see what
aventa meters throw the error event and
this little you know string error is
significant in that anytime you emit
error if it's not trapped it's going to
get thrown as a process unhandled
exception error so it's going to
escalate immediately to exiting your
process which obviously is something
that you don't want to do I mean you
want to keep your process running as
long as you can so that everyone get
that we got eighty percent of people
using your prodding this before it's old
news another one is that you know I
mentioned events and a vented I oh I'm
sure that's come up a lot and you need
to watch for these things right this is
a we rent run and maintain a project
called node HTTP proxy which is a basic
straightforward reverse proxy written in
node it's pretty fast you know it
competes with things that are like NC
which is kind of whole point of node
itself but this was a fun bug defined
which is that you know the event in
meters we're getting more listeners
every time so there was some sort of
weak in my event emitter listener and
that's can be a real problem i mean
let's look at this code sample right so
I've got the events module I'm going to
require that and then I'm gonna you know
do something right and when I do
something i'm going to say you know
return event emitter and later on and
MIT the done event and this is a pattern
you see all over the node code base that
HTTP example that i was going through
earlier was pretty much the same thing
but the problem is is that this done
event only gets emitted once right so
why would you use the first block which
says hey I want to listen to this done
event in perpetuity in that there could
be many done events being emitted from
this particular event emitter over time
versus I know as a user that this
particular event emitter is only going
to vit the done event once so I should
use that once which will remove the
event handler once the event has fired
the first time and you know you ask
yourself well this doesn't really matter
right you know I'll just have latent
event two meters or you know event
handlers around problem is as garbage
collection in long running processes
because if you actually have some
thing in the event handler that's
outside of the original closure scope
that you would have wanted to get
garbage collected if that event emitter
or throw that event handler for that
particular emitter is not removed then
that function is still around and it
needs to maintain that reference over
time and this can be really tricky and
hard to debug so just be aware that over
time you should just be as conservative
as you can about listening to events and
adding functional listeners so use a
process monitor upstart monett I wrote
this thing called forever I'm going to
walk through a little example of it it's
all written a note I've gotten some some
crap for you know reinventing the wheel
but I like this to a lot that's what
kind of why I wrote it right so let me
grab my tool and so let's imagine that
my resolution was terrible and i need to
change it Oh back to the back to the
monitor problem 1024 x 768 no that's
that's the right size oh well we'll do a
live sorry about this guy's this is just
the wrong size
let's try this one this one looks better
yeah here we go okay cool so I'm gonna
jump into the project and I actually
have it open over here and it's a good
little sample of some of the just you
know simple code samples under this
examples library that I use to say hey
what are the common cases that people
are going to do and how can we prevent
against those things miss behaving badly
even when you accept the concept of user
error so things like you know just
always throw I mean what happens when I
just run a process that always throws an
exception right that's probably not a
not a good thing to write or in this
case this is probably the simplest hello
world app that you're ever going to see
a node right we grab something from the
command line we create a server we
listened on the specified port we write
something really really straightforward
stuff and what happens what I want to
run that kind of forever right so
forever start examples server and I can
continue to pass command-line options
through forever tooth child process and
so here I'm going to tell it to listen
on 80 80 and so you know forever saw
that process that script and now I can't
fight and tight we can see that that guy
is running we can see that it has to pee
IDs right so this is going to start up a
forever process and to monitor the child
process that it starts for you and in
that case the significant one is that
the first one is the child process
second one is the forever process so if
I kill 1925 now I have a new process all
right restart it for me and you can see
that the uptime on the left there has
been reset so it will just keep going
forever it's kind of a whole point and I
can stop it right and now it's not there
anymore so this is useful I really enjoy
using it and we actually have some other
tools at nerd Jitsu that we're going to
be talking about on thursday at no time
that this play is really nice with so
back to the talk which way is it this
way there we go so listen forevers use
process monitor great the next one
really is you want stabilize your
dependencies I think this is sort of a
catch-22 of the node community that a
lot of people who are new to know don't
necessarily pick up on immediately think
there are a lot of modules out there and
that is at the same time a great thing
but also kind of bad things you need to
know which ones are good who's
contributing a lot who's writing these
things and also just include them in
your package JSON files this is one of
the ones that I love to find in people's
production environments right you just
forgot to install this particular
dependency on that box and now it's not
there so how do you solve that problem
if you're not diligent about reading
through your own code and finding your
dependencies beforehand before you
deploy and in this case I wrote another
tool to do this and it's called the
required analyzer and it will do it for
you so let's walk through that again in
another small sample so in this case
let's just run it on forever so when I
talk about package.json files I mean I
kind of assumed everybody seen one but
here's the forever package.json so it's
got some repository some keywords and
some dependencies right so a bunch of
dependencies in here I've maintained
this myself but let's just kill those we
don't want those anymore we're just no
dependencies there's going to be a bad
application developer but now I'm just
going to find them again so it's going
to analyze the raw dependencies find
them for me and find a subset of them
because right now it's only going to be
looking at the package.json for my main
property so
when I say that I mean main right here
as in it's actually kind of a fun tool
to read through because what it actually
does it goes out and it spawns off a
child process for my mouse it's always
lost it spawns off a child process for
this and this is actually really simple
a little file all it does is it kind of
monkey patches the internal module load
inside of a node.js and then outputs
everything that goes into your require
statements and processes those and
analyzes them later obviously you would
never want to include this code in
production which is why it spawns it as
a child process to keep everything in
isolation and then it just sort of reads
through and says oh well what's I 9pm
what's a local file and then just build
that out right it back to your
package.json so in this case we go back
to the forever package.json we see we
have some dependencies in here now I
actually want to keep by a long list so
I'll keep those so this is a little
thing I mentioned at the beginning of my
talk but we're actually be pushing this
out to all the projects that we use and
maintain in production and no jitsu so
if you look for this seal like we're on
top of it I kind of have a reputation
for not sleeping and it's true I all I
do is work so if it's broken I'll fix it
the next kind of big catch-22 in node is
that people don't really structure their
code at all or there is just no
convention commonly accepted that is the
right way to structure your code so this
is a pretty common example of how I
choose to structure my code but you
should just pick something and stick to
it so here you've got you know bin is
basically all of your runtime files I've
got some configuration probably with
environments and then you know under lib
is all of your app code and I typically
will have another folder underneath that
called you know app name and then app
name Jas and just to name space those
things a little bit nicer and then some
public static files and some tests
similarly named spaced vendor I guess
that's probably a draw over from the
Ruby days of various gets
modules that you can't get through NPM
and you'll you'll thank me when you
start running big apps in production and
you actually use a code template at all
because I've seen way too many Express
applications that just have one giant
server file and it's it's really
annoying to debug so lastly here is
decide on a network architecture and by
that I really mean you know to proxy or
not to proxy that is the question and
you're probably looking at me like what
is he talking about so the first option
here is that you can share a file
descriptor between multiple servers and
this is actually written into a library
that I like called cluster and what it
does is that it essentially says okay
i'm going to start up as a server then
i'm going to make a file descriptor that
represents a eunuch socket for a
particular port and then i'm going to
spawn up a bunch of children that's the
second code sample here and i'm going to
pass them those file descriptors and
tell them hey you should use this file
descriptor for your STD of course the
second option here this doesn't scale
horizontally right you can only do this
on a single machine the second option if
you're ever going to do any sort of
horizontal scaling is to use a
round-robin proxy and a forward HTTP
proxy which is what we do at no jitsu
because we scale out your application to
a bunch of small machines and then we
basically do a variant of simple
round-robin proxying pretty much like
this so you can see up there we have two
IP addresses and the port's that they're
listening on and then we create a proxy
server and we just say hey grab the next
address proxy to the target a pen that
to the end of the list rinse repeat just
keep doing that so you can start up your
application on different ports on the
same machine and then just round-robin
proxy between them so i think i actually
have a couple of minutes to take some
questions so anybody yeah
Oh
so the things that it misses right now
and the thing is is that it has a
full-fledged API in code that you could
find those for but right now the CLI
tool just looks for the main property in
the package.json so if you have bin
scripts that have dependencies that
aren't referenced by your individual
main library it's going to miss those if
you have test dependencies that it's
missing but I'm going to probably adding
that in the next week or two of you know
just add extra properties look at those
files run them that kind of stuff
yeah I mean that's a good point you know
I've seen some other libraries there was
another require analyzer that I saw that
was just written so ridiculously poorly
that I had compelled to write it
correctly and you know the main reason
there that wife was written report is
that all of the interesting code was
under their bin folder so there was
absolutely no opportunity for you as a
developer to use that programmatically
and so if I I didn't jump on the network
because I don't feel like getting pooped
on on Twitter so I don't have any
internet right now but I would jump to
the project page and show you some of
those samples but again both of these
projects they're on my github there on
the ninjutsu github so check those out
open an issue I usually respond to the
same day
you know that's that's a good question
it's it's a question that we answer
differently at no jitsu I think than
most people because we write 75% of all
the libraries that we use in production
but generally you probably want to have
some upper bound or instead of just
having an upper bound just have a
straight equals and then you can track
those and manage those yourself as you
go up but honestly for sort of where
nodes maturity is going back to the
subtitle of this talk overall you should
be looking at the packages watching the
commits like as Michael Rogers one of
the organizers of note comp and Jas comp
says that note is the first technology
to grow up in a post github age and
that's really made a lot of difference
like you should be using it you should
be following people that's how I stay up
with things and it's really become a
necessity at this point all right thank