okay so this is a little hard for me but
I know what I gotta do here so hi I'm
Rick and I'm sorry there was more
difficult than I intended I'm just gonna
I'm just going to say in our day hi I'm
Rick I'm a politician I didn't expect my
life to go down this path you know I
started talking politics with friends
over beer on Saturday nights on Friday
nights out in the pub like that was no
big deal right and it gradually just
increased in my life before I knew it
there was where some politics with
coffee at work I discuss some politics
with friends as I went up in the morning
and it gradually took over my life and
before I knew it I'd founded a political
party that's now spread to 50 countries
put multiple people in the European
Parliament and I've nominated four times
100 most influential people in the world
it can happen to anybody in this room so
I am a politician like I said politics
it's kind of an odd subject to talk
about it can be a little bit
inflammatory I try to tone it down and
talk about religion instead but Chris
wouldn't have that but still the topic
here is how we all can make a difference
and you'll notice that my Twitter alias
is fun giving you just my last name I
kind of like seeing that on Twitter so
whenever you hear me to say something
worthwhile take the opportunity
to begin with a quick intro how many
here have seen Ted calm recently okay a
couple oh that's quite a few you if you
look at Ted I'll come right now you'll
see a similar talk as this one featured
like crazy this is one that I was
intending to give to Ted Ted Ted calm
but they wanted just half of it so you
guys are the first to see it as it was
intended quick intro how many here have
heard of the Swedish Pirate Party before
let's see a show hands that's pretty
pretty much I'd say that's about half to
two thirds which for some reason is so
consistent no matter where I present no
matter where in the world that I put it
in the slides and for kicks how many in
here have heard of any other Swedish
party let's see a show of hands yep I
see two maybe three hands so who are we
at the end of the day well why the fire
party well we love the net we love
copying and sharing and we love civil
liberties some people decided to call us
pirates with that and rather than
feeling ashamed which I think was their
intent we decided to stand tall about it
and as a result of standing tall and
proud about by what we believe in we now
have two seats in the European
Parliament 15 seats in the Berlin
Parliament four seats in the saarland
Parliament we have about 200 seats on
local councils across Europe and we've
been copied and founded in about 56
countries at last count
Thanks and just yesterday there was a
poll in Germany which gave the german
patent part i twelve percent of national
support now i know that might not sound
like much in a u.s. setting but remember
that Germany has proportional
representation this translates to twelve
percent of the seats and if you want to
get an image of just how panicked the
other politicians are in Germany imagine
you'd found a party that had that held
twelve percent of the seats between the
Republicans and Democrats so both needed
the support of this party to get
anything done that's how much influence
were getting and it started out on
january first 2006 in Sweden as piero
party yet the next couple of minutes
we're going to talk about this politics
and policies of protest as people call
it a little bit about my story on this
and what can we learn from that so
politics like people call this politics
of protest like you're just a protest
party come on you have no you have no
authority here you got no right to say
anything here as in that was something
bad right we're not talking about
defiance here for defiance sake but
there's dissenting is always legitimate
as an not agreeing with the current
dedmon administration not agreeing with
the status quo saying this can be done
better is dissent by definition
protesting is not bad it's saying we can
do this better ourselves and we could we
can thanks oh and if you look at the
cycles of history I mean we're not we're
not the first by far to go down this
route the Greens 40 years ago what were
protesting pollution and they went from
there saying that okay maybe it's more
than just pollution maybe we have some
sort
ideology here that we can put a lot of
policy from the labor movement the
workers movement eight years ago
protested exploitation of workers by
factory owners and rich capital owners
and same thing there they started out as
a single issue protest and matured to an
ideology that now holds quite a few
majority seats in Europe 120 years ago
same thing they're liberals took power
protesting a single issue and
overbearing power from royalty and the
church and they had this weird idea
about individual rights and got into
political power about 40 about 120 years
ago we see that there's a there's a
cycle of history here about 40 years
that every new generation recon kurz
democracy so we're right for a new
movement and if you're thinking about
what happened 40 years ago when the
rallying cries of the youth were peace
and love usually combined with smoking
the odd exotic plant to get the right
tone of voice
this later this concept later matured
into sustainability which has many more
syllables and so can't be pronouncing
quite the same manner but it's become a
political mantra for the past 40 years
except some things happened in a value
survey of 17 year olds which is a great
predictor for the political trends to
come in the following decades
sustainability is no longer at the top
of 17 year olds agendas something else
has taken that place and that is
openness and free speech and I think
that there's bears great promise and if
you want a simple explanation of this it
would be just leave the net alone don't
interfere I mean you're seeing
governments all over the world
interfering in panic with our freedoms
of speech with our ability to
communicate although they're not very
successful at it and the net at it's
very core infrastructure if you want a
great example of how they don't
understand it about a year ago ex
president mubarak tried to shut down the
net as people as people were protesting
his rule and if I can if I can see just
one example of how they don't get it is
that he wanted to keep people indoors
and as a result he thought it was a good
idea to shut off the internet
we're seeing four things worldwide we're
seeing censorship we're seeing
wiretapping we're seeing track ability
and we're seeing identifiability being
rolled out across the net threatening
freedoms of speech threatening anonymity
threatening our very basic civil
liberties and this happens pretty much
in every country the interesting thing
is that only the excuses for why you do
it differ here in the West we are seeing
terrorism we're seeing file sharing and
to some extent pornography being the
excuses for shutting down freedoms of
speech in predominantly Muslim countries
it's usually sanctity of the Prophet
that's being used as an excuse for the
exact same measures in China we're
seeing security of the nation so the
interesting thing here is that it's not
about the net at all it's about control
it's about freedoms very basic freedoms
of speech how many in here have heard of
this bill it was passed last last week
okay so a couple of hands up what this
bill says is that it extends harassment
criminalizing harassment to the net and
it widens it completely to making a
criminal to even pause post annoying
messages online so I mean do you realize
how ridiculous this is when I go to my
favorite fantasy forums and sit and
write a post there how I saw the Lord of
the Rings trilogy welcome while flying
over here and I gripe about how
hollywood's greed has made this
masterpiece of a trilogy into a book
and and at that point I after having
written that I just rolled back and i
bring out the big bowl of popcorn and
enjoy the show now that's all of a
sudden illegal here in Arizona it's
criminal what we're demanding isn't
really rocket science we're demanding
the same rights that our parents had
offline to apply for our children online
if you're looking at a letter in the
mail for years ago you and you alone
determined whether you identified
yourself a sander on the inside of the
envelope readable only for the recipient
on the outside readable for the Postal
Service and everybody who have the
letter or frankly not at all nobody have
the right to open this letter in transit
just in case you'd copy a drawing nobody
had the right to stand at every mailbox
and make lists of who's sending what to
whom and I think it's perfectly
reasonable that our children have the
same rights as our parents had in the
environment they live in now there are
some people that will object to this
notably the copyright industry who says
that if anybody can send anything to
anybody we can we can't make money
anymore and I say so what a
entrepreneurs job is to make money given
the current constraints of society and
technology they do not get to dismantle
Thank You Noah entrepreneur gets to
dismantle civil liberties even if and
perhaps especially if they can make
money otherwise that's a completely
illogical argument civil liberties
always take precedence and if they can't
make money with sustained civil
liberties tough job go sailing
mayonnaise entirely regardless whether
somebody can no longer profit do you
recall forever young song by alphaville
let's see you show handsome men to
remember that okay most people here how
many have actually listened to the
lyrics not many because you remember
this very soft ballad which we dint
where we're dancing cheek to cheek
before going home with somebody and in
the eighties right this is what it's
about the the lyrics go let's dance in
style let's dance for a while heaven can
wait we're only watching the skies
hoping for the best but expecting the
worst are you gonna drop the bomb
bowknot forever young do you really want
to live forever kind of puts a new
perspective doesn't it I survived the
80s I was a kid growing up in the 80s
and it's kind of tough to explain to
people growing up in the 90s but the
nuclear scare was so everywhere that we
went to bed and knew that one morning we
would not wake up that was reality and
as yes as tomorrow's turn into
yesterday's and years turned into
yesteryears we realized that we had a
gift we got a gift that we'd never
expected we had never dared hope for it
middle-aged
so and ironically that this tune was
published in nineteen eighty-four of all
yours so my point here is that don't try
to tell me don't try to justify these
tracking laws these snooping laws these
these wiretapping laws by the world
having becoming having become a more
dangerous place I survived the 80s I
know it's not more dangerous anybody
claiming that is using a very common
political method now you know every
every profession has its own lingo right
like if you're an avid chess player
you'd know that there were sequences
like the mutual queen pawn opening or
the famous Bobby Fischer sacrifice or
the Tony Hawk gliding Bishop grind but
this particular this particular
political method of claiming that the
world has become more dangerous and so
we need more more see more wiretapping
is not is known within Parliament's as
lying like a filthy weasel
and Enzo freedom of speech we're seeing
politicians everywhere being totally
confused by the youth rallying for
freedom of speech as and we have that we
introduced that 120 years ago why are
you rallying they generally do not
understand they do not understand that
the laws they are making is the
equivalent of putting microphones under
every cafe table if they understood that
they would be horrified but they don't
spend time online they don't live online
they don't make friends online so they
don't understand what it is they're
doing so it's up to us to educate them
and the net here is the greatest
equalizer mankind has ever invented and
that is what people are feeling that is
with a net generation is feeling for the
first time in mankind's history a nine
year old school gun in Paraguay who just
got our first laptop under the one
laptop per child program has exactly as
strong a voice as me a middle-aged white
male in the privileged parts of the
world and I think that's fantastic and
if there's one thing I love about the
net
but there are some people who don't like
this and that is the previous one
percent that were able to interpret
truth for all of us who were able to
dictate what was true from what will
relies and that were able to say that
only their eyes and ears were valid they
have lost a privilege and they're
fighting to get it back and to the
generation growing up this attitude from
the old guard is more than offensive
which is why you're seeing rallies
across here Europe against acton I think
this is pretty impressive maps to be
honest these were the anti actor rallies
so with that said with my motivation in
place how do i do all this crazy stuff
from an ugly webpage and seriously it
was real ugly to putting people in
Parliament's in 2005 three things
happened there was a software patent
debate in the European Parliament which
as activists fortunately one there were
no software patents in Europe after
which the European Patent Office went
ahead and issued them anyway but that's
a separate issue there was yet another
harsh inning of the copyright monopoly
in Sweden which the politicians didn't
care about but it was just everybody
everywhere else and there was the data
retention directive which turns all our
mobile phones into governmental tracking
devices this last thing was just the
drop for me so I decided to register the
domain peter party at SC and see what
you can do of it so i put up this web
page realizing that politicians here
weren't evil they are doing their best
in their using their knowledge to give
us a better world the problem is that
whenever it's something they don't know
they asked around and lobbyists are
experts at just happening to be there
when they ask around most politicians
are not evil they're doing their best
but they're caught in a system and you
have to find a personal motivator
to break that barrier and to motivate
them to research the issue further I
found that the threat of getting them
fired was an excellent motivator it
really made it personal to them so i
posted a manifesto i wrote two lines in
a chat channel Hey look the pirate party
has its website up now after new years
and the address that was all the
advertising i ever did and it just
detonated on me three days from there my
photo was on the front page on a
newspaper in Pakistan it was a photo ID
I'd taken myself with the camera like
this and you can see the toilet door in
the back room it was awful so just
detonated I had three hundred activists
on the first day in IRC challenge just
holding out their hands to me like this
thing I want to be a part of this just
give me something that was fantastic so
I realized this was my chance this was
my chance to change the world for the
better and now I had a high I had a
good-paying IT job at the time but I
realized I had a choice I could just
fade back into the mainstream but if I
done that I wouldn't have been able to
see myself in the mirror for the rest of
my life it wasn't a choice in practice
it might have been in theory but the
rest of my life would not just have been
one big what if it would have been
giving up on my dream so I took a huge
loan to live off of to the next election
and quit my job in that order very
important
now to say I decided to go for it I
decided to build a pirate party in
Sweden full-time the election is 2006 I
mean this was the first this was in New
Year's our elections are in September so
I had a full eight buns right we are
entrepreneurs we wear coders we know
that you can solve a you can solve a
problem in a weekend turns out politics
works a little differently most not
differently but just very very very
slower it works on a glacial scale so in
the first election we got point six
three percent now I wasn't very happy
about that at the time but I realized
something where they treated us as a
joker party before the election they
realized that there were actually some
support for us so media treated me
completely differently after this
election which I think had allows the
result but we were on to something then
I ran out of money this loan didn't last
for forever obviously so I asked the
swarm for money said ok guys if you want
it if you want me to do this full time
and have a little bit of money out after
the week after the bills are paid please
send me some spare change so I live it
off a begging for 18 months and of
course the tabloid scandalized me for it
as in oh he's living off of begging yes
I was that's what passion does do you
Thanks and then came to European
elections where we just took the world
but completely by surprise as we became
the largest party for people under 30 we
took twenty-five percent of the vote
securing two seats out of Sweden's 20 in
the European Parliament now two seats in
the European Parliament out of 750
something might not seem like much but
what it did was that it kicked some
politicians out of office over not
understanding these issues and that had
world wide repercussions because that
had never happened before so people
understood that there was something here
that they didn't understand and this was
followed by successes all over Europe in
particular now the German parabatai is
doing very well at the same time as
we're still in the European Parliament I
I'm now employed by the European
Parliament and by the way the tablets
tried to scandalize me over that too and
we're being claimed to be the fastest
growing political movement by major
newspapers so what do we learn from this
what can we learn from having observed
this there is a futurama quote which is
very relevant if and it says that when
push comes to shove you gotta do what
you love even if it's not a good idea
I mean
I mean what kind of idiot things they
could change the world by founding a
political party really this kind of live
idiot apparently and there's another
good quote here if it's stupid but works
it ain't stupid this was visit stupid
but it works we're starting to change
the world in Germany which is as good as
a superpower in the European Union as
any country can be we're making policy
so we're shifting policy in the European
Union if we're shifting positive in the
European Union we're on a tipping point
that's going to change the world that's
reality we can that's what you can do
so one key lesson here is that people
aren't evil your worst enemies are not
evil they're doing their best in their
context to make a better world and
painting them as evil does not help your
cause it does not define them but it
does something else that sees that's
important to remember it defines you and
that's that's a key lesson here d viola
fying your adversary and understanding
them as human beings makes your success
much much more likely so whether or not
you think you can change the world
whether or not you believe you're able
or unable to change the world my key
message here is that you're probably
right this is all about attitude this is
all about what you think you can do and
what you decide to do it's about
leadership you have a cause I'm betting
that each and everyone in this room have
some change they'd like to make and what
you need to do is to go out there and
say I want to change the world who's
with me there you go are you need to be
creating to be credible you need to be
inclusive you need to be tangible
credible as in just for sending a plan
for making things happen that people can
absorb that people can believe in you
need to be inclusive as in letting
anybody who wants to contribute to your
vision do so because more people will
want to contribute to your making the
world a better place then you can
possibly imagine and you need to be
tangible as a knot will make the world a
better place and peace man
but hey let's go to Mars I mean don't
shoot for the moon that's been done
already let's send illiteracy let's
teach two billion people to read each
and every person in this room has the
ability to make that happen just need to
sit out on it you need to believe that
this can happen you need to set out a
plan and tell the world I believe that
we together can make this difference
where many we're strong and we've
decided to make this happen and you can
do that just remember that for each and
every purse for every 10 activists that
join your cause you're going to have one
or two people outside the outside the
door saying you're believing it wrong
there will always be people trying to
pull you out pull you down d motivate
you saying it will never work don't
believe them you can change the world
each and everyone in here has a passion
they'd like to see happen you can do it
don't let anybody tell you otherwise
because a swarm a swarm of people is
empowered just like the net you just
have to let people contribute to making
your vision come true and it will it
will whether it's going to Mars whether
it's building schools and third world
countries whatever it is and here's the
key kicker I want you to take away from
this closing keynote of jas conf
everything you know about making open
source and free software because you
know about this you know how to do this
everything you know about this applies
to politics too it applies to going to
Mars it applies to ending world of
literacy each and every person in this
room has the ability to make this happen
and to the change you want to see in the
world change does not just happen
somebody makes it happen and the
question I want everybody to ask
themselves is do you want to be that
person so how many in here have tweeted
during this Kino let's see a show of
hands okay that's good I got something
else for you you remember I said in the
beginning of this that I was nominated
four times list of 100 most influential
people in the world I want all you to go
to this URL
right now tinyurl.com / Rick for the 100
and click on a small button called
definitely and I want all you guys to
tell your friends do the same thing if
you do that and these ideas of net
liberty and freedom of speech end up in
x 100 * list of the 100 most influential
trends right now we're on the most 100
most important people but I'm there as
carrier of the ideas it's going to help
Ned Liberty it's going to push back on
the people who want to censor the net in
a very dramatic way and that's it hope
you enjoy this and safe travels let's
get drunk