so high this is JavaScript and web
standards to the quickening are there
any Highlander fans out here the movie
Highlander yeah whew okay cool well I'm
only going to reference it once in this
presentation because I realized that I
don't think a lot of people like
Highlander so I'm realistic most of the
Star Wars but there'd be a high languid
for so get ready to get ready for it so
I'm John Lucas and I am an interactive
development director at a small rug
design studio I focused mainly in
front-end development but because we
have a small studio I've done some
information architecture design reviews
CMS implications we sort of all diver
and each other's jobs and I work at a
company called happy cog and it was
founded by this guy Jeffrey's admin and
he wrote a book designing with web
standards we also published a list of
part com which is a online magazine for
people who make websites and we do a
conference and event depart a few times
a year so happy cog we work with a bunch
of different clients from the Holocaust
Museum in the u.s. to Mozilla Georgetown
zappers and dictionary com which
actually you saw earlier I also brought
sporadically about Hades music unicorns
and my web crushes at John Lucas calm
and I contribute to the nerdery net
which is a website for developers and
lastly i love web standards it's losing
okay I think it's stuck in my hair now
saliva standards is this idea of the set
of guidelines that provide the greatest
benefit to the greatest number of web
users and the idea goes on to illustrate
that by using web standards you lower
the cost of production and so building
on a solid foundation there's less
upkeep in the future and so when
websites and browsing devices of all
people still be ready for it so my
highlander metaphor in the movie
Highlander there's a group of immortals
that fight to the death which kind of
doesn't make sense but they do
and they kill each other by beheading is
the only way and when they do it there's
like these giant lightning bolts come
down and it's called the quickening and
there's all this action and I'm every so
there can be only one and it's really
dramatic and it's kind of awesome um so
there can be only one but not really the
stuff I'm going to talk about today is
how i like to make websites the people
that come to us come to us because we do
standard support this isn't going to be
applicable to every project that you do
but for me this is how i believe in
making a web so Knollys reserve set in
stone but with that in mind my favorite
rule is your site should work without
JavaScript um the sites that I work on
the most important aspects of the site
aren't the graphic design or the
animations or CMS implementation it's
the content and so we want to make sure
that our content is accessible everyone
including users that don't have
javascript enabled and of course we do
that with our good friend progressive
enhancement and we all know that's XHTML
poster CSS plus your JavaScript or your
content your presentation and your
behavior so why do we do this well we
talked about the importance of content
but really how many people are we
worried about who really turns off
JavaScript anymore well first let me get
my audience participation going on here
and ask you one of my favorite questions
how many of you guys test for Safari how
many of you all a test for chrome and
how many of you test for opera yeah and
how many of you test your sites without
JavaScript ok couple different sites are
going to give you different stats on
this but here's a few and you'll see
that the numbers for users without
JavaScript are actually larger than the
numbers of people that use a certain
browser Safari um and I get it stats you
know you can read them how you will I'm
but now I'm gonna ask you another
question how many of you ride bikes oh
no one writes like okay
and let's pretend you were to ride a
bike if you were to ride a bike how many
of you would ride a bike with a helmet
okay a couple how many of you drive a
bike with a helmet if you're only going
a couple of blocks okay bad metaphor so
I always write a bike with a helmet back
at home because I can't control what
other people are doing so pedestrians
could be running across the street and
drivers in Philadelphia are kind of
crazy and I can't control what other
people are going to do so all I can do
is protect myself so if I'm quoting a
website and there's only one person
that's browsing and without javascript
but that person is the president of the
company of a site that I'm working for
well then I'm going to make sure that
they can view the content I recently was
working on a project and one of the main
stakeholders only tested the site
primarily on the iPad and that's fine
our site should still work on the iPad
but it just was new to us to have
someone primarily focused on something
as opposed to firefox or internet
explorer so making sure your site works
without JavaScript now make sure make
sure it will work with Java without
JavaScript later so if the kindle pre
pad 8g megatouch pod comes out one day
and it doesn't support javascript you'll
be all set and whether it been
improvements in how search engines want
to handle javascript the most foolproof
method to making sure you get the best
SEO and to read the content is to have
it on the page and to begin with so I'll
be the first to admit that I really
rushed the code on my personal site you
know it's got unicorns it's kind of
silly and when I look at the CSS it
really kind of makes me cringe a little
bit I rush through it I used to be
really careful about making sure my
youtube videos in bed but now I'll just
go on a kick and i'll just start copying
and pasting and nothing validates
anymore and so I'm guilty of it too but
if I'm ever looking to hire someone the
first thing I'm going to do is go to the
personal site I'm going to see how it
works with text resizing i'm going to
view source and then i'm going to see
how it works with javascript disabled so
if you want to make sure that your site
is a reflection of yourself then that's
something that i would think about doing
and then there's some of us that find
that reading with w3c docs is a great
to spend a Friday night and I'm sort of
guilty of this i really i really like
guidelines so making sure that your site
works without javascript is complying
with the wicked recommendations and they
require that your content and
functionality be accessible with
scripting disabled and that users should
be alerted if javascript changes any
content on the page so back to who turns
off javascript anyway you know
javascript can be a pretty scary thing
to the users of the interwebs it's got a
history of being the sneaky guy on the
block and breaking your browsing and
unresponsive scripts and errors and
those alerts that you can't ever get out
of so I have a confession to make I was
working on this and last week I started
thinking I'm like is this even true
anymore it seems like Java scripts
really sort of mellowed out and everyone
sort of been like oh it it's not that
creepy it's ok javascript and then the
next morning I was on the bus on the way
to work and I was checking my Twitter on
my phone and I see this and I'm like
what's going on Simon you know what's
what's what's your beef with the
JavaScript and so then as i'm sure you
all saw there was some of this going on
this week so then the tweets just kept
coming what's with all the garbage code
in my Twitter stream and what's going on
javascript code is automatically sending
things and then you've got the people
ready to abandon ship and then you've
got the people ready to make money off
this and i would totally buy one of
those t-shirts then you have people that
were trying to make it work but
unfortunately it didn't work without
javascript and then my personal favorite
we finally gone somewhere so when the
number 8 most visited site on the
internet gets a bad rap like this that's
when people start turning to things like
no script and that's when people start
turning to things like upping their
internet security and turning off
javascript in their browsers let's take
a look at some site examples so here's a
design studio and they've got this
really nice moving around going to
is there space there sky there's land
there's a contact form you can fill out
the contact form you could not fill it
out and then get error alerts really
nice and then seeing this with
javascript disabled so I now start on
the contact page and then of the links
are working anymore so I can still
contact maybe I'm not getting any
confirmation messages but why am I going
to contact someone if I can't see their
offers or their portfolio this is
another example and so clicking on about
updates the content but you still just
scroll so it's a little silly so you're
doing one shortcut but then still
needing to use the scroll bar and then
when you look at the site without
javascript and you're clicking on these
links nothing's happening so here's a
navigation that's not working and then I
noticed that there is still a scroll bar
up here so i can still scroll down and
get the content so that's one step
better because we're still able to
access this though I've got this
navigation that's really confusing to a
user because it doesn't work and then
I'm also noticing I've got this weird
horizontal scroll so what does this
thing do and so I spelled out oh look
here's the helpdesk form and so just by
making sure the navigation works or
jumps to something and making sure that
your styling is okay is a step on how
they could have made this better my text
editor of choices Kota I love it I think
it's fantastic and this is their website
and you can browse through to see the
stuff it does it's got this nice neat
interface you can use the arrows to
scroll through or the tabs and then when
I disable JavaScript and refresh the
page I can still get to the content but
it does this weird jumping down things
so now I have to scroll back up every
time I want to change something was
really distracting as a user I just want
to learn about your product I want to
buy it but it's really confusing and
then I still have these arrows here they
are trying to call this JavaScript but
of course nothing's happening so way
that they can prove this is you want to
write your arrows to the page with
and not include it in the source where
it's not going to work for someone so
let's say your site's just not going to
work with JavaScript it's just not
that's not your audience it's fine well
this is safer our do and this is what
happens when you come to this site with
JavaScript on without it you get an
error message telling you that you need
to have javascript enabled so fine at
least I know it's not user error when I
come to this site which is nice it's
given me a message I'm not doing
anything wrong I do need to have
JavaScript it's a little harsh here's
another site it's a design site and this
goes about it a little bit nicer and so
it says javascript is disabled in your
current web browser exclamation because
parts of the site or coated with
JavaScript certain features might not be
available to you if you have the
possibility please activate javascript
exclamation so you still can access some
of the other content on the site but you
also have this really nice polite
message that doesn't make you feel like
a jerk for having javascript disabled
this is what happens if you come to
facebook without JavaScript and again
you get an error message and it's
highlighted in yellow so you're
automatically drawn to it but the thing
with this is if you can't turn on
JavaScript you're still able to access
the site because they let you have
access to the mobile version so you can
sign in and you can still know that the
phillies are playing or that someone has
poked you but that's kind of creepy so i
actually wish they'd get rid of that I'm
moving on your site should be keyboard
accessible users with visual
disabilities have a strong reliance on
the keyboard as well as users you just
choose to use the keyboard for speed or
convenience this is another part of
adhering to web standards and when you
users hover over an event and it pops up
in information box or pulls in an ajax
menu sometimes we forget to copy that
over to the focus as well along with
that your site should also be screen
reader accessible so updates are often
missed by people with assistive
technologies because they expect a
change to happen with a navigate event
so if you click on a link or your submit
a form is usually when you expect
something to change so web apps often
use these techniques to update content
in the background and then users are
unaware of it
um this demo is really cool it is a
lightbox effects using jQuery UI and you
can go through the images with your
keyboard it's got a nice loader you can
also use your mouse I think it captured
my mouse but I'm clicking you can escape
by either clicking or pressing escape
you can still tab through using your
keyboard to all the other photos and
then what's also really neat about this
is it updates the URL so i can grab the
URL from this send it to someone if i
want to show them a picture of someone
walking out and then i can automatically
load that URL right away with javascript
disabled this still works i can still
get through with my keyboard access and
i can still go right to the picture this
does something else really neat and that
moves into the next point is declaring
yourself as an application and letting
users know that you're a nap so what all
of you are doing with javascript these
days and web application is becoming so
fancy it's a bit more complicated to
make your content accessible web apps
are emulating desktop apps and I don't
think a way that anyone or a lot of
people didn't think was possible and one
of the things that's been plaguing the
good name of Ajax is that updating the
content in the background and not being
screen reader accessible and that's
where way Aria comes in and this allows
web pages to declare themselves as
widgets or applications rather than
static documents we use the role
property and state information to
declare itself as a dynamic web app I
also extends the tabindex attribute and
so it goes beyond the a area but an
input object select and text area where
you would normally use those and allows
it to be applied to any element such as
a div or spam you can also use tab index
of negative 1 here and that will take
things that shouldn't be in the natural
tab order out of the flow of the page so
you have a nested tree item and you
don't want anyone to access that right
away it won't be until you
programmatically tell it to be so here's
an example of a spam that has the
tabindex defined
span is being used as a checkbox element
so you want to keep the tabindex of zero
because you still want users to be able
to access this with our keyboard if we
done negative one again that would have
left it out you'll also notice here the
role attribute and this is being used
here to specify that a span is being
used as a checkbox so roll attributes
were borrowed from XHTML and the idea is
it allows you to add machine extractable
semantic information about the purpose
of an element this paved the way for
Aria to use this and provide role
information to excessive technologies so
you can define things like alerts
dialogues menus tree items sliders
buttons progress meters etc along with
that you can also use roles to define
the grid in structure of a document
their document landmark roles and they
describe the area of the site a user is
in navigation article main complementary
search and banner just to name a few of
them arias states and properties tell
users how to interact with these widgets
so for checkbox you can define whether
or not the checkbox is checked by using
the Aria checked property and you can
set it to true or false or if you have
form fields and some are required you
can let a user know by using re required
equals true and this helps a lot you go
beyond the asterisks that some of us use
to define a check box or a form field
being required which really doesn't tell
a user very much if items are changed in
a document than are you uses live
regions and this lets a user know they
can do this though without using the
current place in the site with our you
arrive you have three choices you have
off which means the region isn't life
you have polite which means that users
are notified that there's a change but
not interrupted of their current task
and you have assertive for more urgent
priority content so if there's a form
error that's when you'd want to use
something like that and you can also use
the aria busy state and that's lets a
user know that contents still being
updated and you can use the earlier
relevant property and that will define
additions or removals of nodes in the
Dom I'm Aaron Gustafson made this tab
interface demo and it
really awesome not just because it's
about pumpkin pie but um so here's how
you make pumpkin pie and here's how it
looks with JavaScript enabled and you've
got your four tabs on top and each one
corresponds to the section like
ingredients and directions this is how
the site the site looks without
JavaScript so you'll see all the
contents still on the page and taking a
look at the source it's completely
semantics you've got your heading levels
with everything corresponding underneath
it and then with JavaScript it turns it
into the tab set and then you'll see
here that you'll see some of the Aria
roles being defined so the aria selected
equals true the role equals tab bre a
hidden and viewed and it's really nice
and then i don't think i have found but
if you want to go to this you guys are
going to be able to hear that right with
a screen reader this totally works and
you're able to hear what tab that you're
currently on and you can get to
everything that you need to if anyone's
interested in this link it's up there or
I can send it to you so next up with
javascript is you don't want to
interrupt the workflow javascript should
be used to enhance a user's experience
in a website not distract them or take
away and there's some sites that do this
really well um flickr is one of the most
i love the interaction of the site it's
amazing i I can do so much from my login
page without even leaving it i can add
people as contacts or cancel it i can
expand collapse almost everything on
this page and get an error but i still
get um not an error and alert message
this is really neat if you collapse your
groups thing it updates your message
with nothing new here recently bored
look for a new group so it's it's
responding to what the user is doing
there thinking oh they're bored of this
so let's give them something they can do
you can refresh content if you look at
your photo stream page and you can
update your titles right from there you
can cancel you could update it to talk
about that one of your bosses is eating
meat and then you get this yellow
highlight so you know that you've
changed something
you can delete things or you can cancel
them with us alert it's really easy to
use and I don't have to go through ten
page refreshes looking at individual
photo page you can add things right to
the map from here this saves the user so
much time and it's all about these
enhancements that make this experience
so great I mean I can't think of anyone
who doesn't like Flickr and if you do we
can talk about it later but um it's such
a neat website you can add contacts
right from here you can delete contacts
right from here and I think sometimes we
take for granted how easy the site is
for us and other sites that make you go
jump through hoops in order to be able
to do this content okay so internet
explorer 6 everything that's html5 and
css3 is really cool these days and I
know a lot of people are moving towards
this like let's not support ie6 anymore
and that may or may not be right again I
work with the types of clients that
we're not going to do that we are going
to make sure our sites work in ie6 but
you can still do this and push the web
forward sometimes a little bit of double
work but an example this is making your
forms easy to use and the wick ektu
guidelines state that you should help
users avoid and correct mistakes and one
of the ways that a user majority
interacts with your website is is
filling up forms and there's a lot of
room for user error you can use
JavaScript to help with some of this
with the client side validation but in
html5 there's some really neat new type
M additions that will help hopefully
take some of the burden off of
JavaScript the nice thing about starting
an implant implement these new input
types is that if a browser doesn't
recognize it so like type equal search
it will default back to type equals txt
if the validation of things like making
sure a telephone number is invalid
format fell to the browser's instead it
would save developers a lot of time to
focus on other things like accessibility
and like good interaction of course if
you are going to implement any of these
I would still say to do a JavaScript
back
for browsers that don't support this so
again it's sort of double work but it's
moving the web I think in a great place
to talk to a little more about search
here's an example of a site in safari
with JavaScript turned on a lot of
people have become really big on using
the placeholder attribute these days to
fill in the value in a search box and I
see here that the search here is really
similar to the search that's built in in
the browser so I'm familiar with how
this works as a user and I think that
without a submit button I still think I
can type and something will happen and
sure enough i start typing and I get my
suggestive results ok cool I find what I
want I select it and here my nice neat
organized results if i look at this page
in firefox with javascript off firefox
doesn't support placeholder or it didn't
on this browser don't think it does and
so here i'm not really sure here's a
square box because I'm a Mac user maybe
they think i know that's a search form
because I'm I'm hip to the web but I go
in I start typing and nothing happens
but then again because I'm a Mac user
maybe I'm used to forms that i can hit
enter to submit this form so it's emits
but as you can see you go to broken
experience and these are places if
you're using the placeholder for things
that are more important besides search
like enter a zip code and you're not
sure if you should enter a zip or state
or country those are places where you're
not going to want to rely on that I'm
going to skip through this because I'm
running out of time a little but css3
animations can be your friend if you
were once relying on JavaScript you just
add some enhancements there's some
really neat things that you can do these
days with the css3 here's a few examples
there's more if you want to make a nice
interface for your Michael Jackson CDs a
a tab interface it's a little wonky at
times if you if you go between the two
tabs then you'll have this and of course
if you're not on the first tab then
it's always going to default back to
that this site's really neat they did a
comparison of css3 animations with the
jQuery equivalents and you can pop open
the code and see what things are like in
css3 and then see what things are like
in the jQuery so that being said you
should be aware of distracting
unnecessary animations on a more serious
side of that the wick egg
recommendations also limit flashing
animations as it can affect people with
photosensitive epilepsy if you remember
a few years back this happened on an
absolute epilepsy support message board
and people injected this code that did
produce these animations with JavaScript
that had a lot of serious effects on
people on a less serious side i'm going
to skip to this one sometimes animations
are really cool for a design site and
they're going through and it's really
neat it could be a little bit
distracting but you're probably trying
to show off the things that you can do
so it's totally acceptable in this
content but there's still a ways that
you can make this a bit more accessible
if that navigation on the top was fixed
then someone could easily jump around to
content so go ahead and push the web but
also think about ways to make it more
usable this is a site that does it
really nice the animations are really
fast so you still get the effect of neat
little navigating around and then the
site still also works without JavaScript
I won't show you all this to save time
but it'll jump through to the proper
place choose your visual indicators
wisely and when you have javascript
functionality and users user should know
what they're going to do when they click
on something or something is happening
so here's a site for some ipad apps or I
wow I just forgot the word but you get
what I'm saying and you can see when you
click on these it automatically changes
the content on the right hand side so
this happens with almost all of them
except the first two when you click on
them even though the icons look the same
as the rest these actually open a new
page so as a user I wasn't expecting
that at all
based on the rest of the interface so
maybe a little you know arrow icon or
something to let a user know that
they're going to be taking off this page
that they were just on also you should
let your users know something is
happening if your Java scripts going to
take a long time to load something then
use loaders to visually indicate that
here's another example of site that
doesn't more of these navigational
things but you'll see they pop up that
loader to make sure that you know
nothing's broken your computer's
thinking and something's going to change
another aspect of JavaScript and web
standards is share what you have to push
the web forward it's really nice to it
will share content and how you did
things one of the problems with using a
propriety a proprietary system like
flash is that unless someone writes one
of those demos you're not going to know
how someone made what they made so
here's a asteroids game and you can
download the JavaScript source code and
it's using html5 canvas and JavaScript
and it's really cool but I can still
learn how someone made this and that's
going to help teach everyone of how to
keep making these really cool things
it's not going to help me be better at
asteroids but besides that it's still
pretty cool um lastly this was touched
on it before but use JavaScript
libraries they are doing so much already
of support these days it's so neat the
stuff that all you guys are making out
there the other great part about using a
JavaScript library is for your clients
there's so much documentation about it
when you're writing all your custom
stuff maybe when you're passing that off
to a client they're not going to know
how to build on that when you use a
popular library and then people can look
up anything and help maintain their own
site and so that about wraps it up and