okay hi yep I said I'm Tim ruffles I'm
currently working on a product called
psychic Jess which is a code quality
tool for JavaScript and today I'm going
to be talking about handling lots and
lots of asynchronous code big
asynchronous processes involving lots
and lots of inputs going lots of
different directions AKA callback hell
but i think we've got cool backhaul
wrong i think all the kind of typical
blog posts you see where people start
going on about callbacks being
JavaScript's go to and how you can try
anything complicated in javascript as
soon as you start using callbacks it all
turns into a big spaghetti code mess I
think they kind of missed the point so
in this I'm going to be talking about
how you can handle most callback stuff
with just the tools you already know a
JavaScript and then we can be looking at
what I think is the real cool back help
the real challenge is of asynchronous
code and looking at some new stuff some
libraries but also some new things in
JavaScript that will help you make a
simple game so pyramids pyramids of doom
do exist I've been looking at a lot of
code for sidekick it's kind of research
for what people are doing in terms of
their code and it's out there like if
you look on github some node code has
inline callbacks five levels deep you
know that there's no way you can reason
about this stuff it's just a nightmare
there's no way you could test this in a
million years there's really no need for
this kind of call back he'll like for
most of the code that I see it for
there's no need for it in the simple
cases like something like this so this
is a just some simple Express jazz
handler we're getting a user we're going
to update their profile we want to check
out you know did have a profile already
or are we creating a new one so just all
very simple stuff if we're writing the
synchronously it will be super simple if
you start just starting out node and you
don't you don't know any other way you
might end up with something like this so
we're handling errors all over the place
we've got quite a kind of deep stack of
nested callbacks we don't wanna do this
for two reasons first off it's
completely untested and I personally
find that
test codes without test is just not code
I don't really count thats code that's
kind of a hack that's like an experiment
without code I just don't trust it and I
wouldn't really trust someone else's
code I certainly don't trust my own code
if it doesn't have tests so how do we
test this code will there be no way we'd
have to dig right in so if you have a
look at the two points I've got these
comments saying we can't test this stuff
there's no way of getting in there it's
inside a closure we'd have to test the
whole lot in one go so all of those
callbacks or nothing so we're either
have to stub out every little bit of our
code there or we're just kind of give up
and not test it it's not cool just don't
it's not it's not doable so we can't do
this so we just can't do this kind of
stuff we have to name all are callbacks
and reveal them so we either reveal them
individually and the kind of no objects
just have loads of blobs of functions
just have a name so we can actually get
at them with our tests or we stick them
in objects and then we can get animo
test again so everything has to have a
name all your callback should have a
name you should be able to get at them
and test them individually and that
let's split up the input-output stuff
which is the complicated stuff the
asynchronous bit with the simple code we
have inside our handlers which say if I
have an error and a user what happens if
I have a no error and a user something
good happens all that kind of stuff it
suddenly becomes easy again as soon as
we do that reason be javascript already
has tools to avoid most of the simple
case kind of causes of complexity so the
named functions obviously but secondly
the function up bind so how many of
these are used function bind cool okay
so most of you well function up bind is
a really really nice little tool that
lets you get a new version of a function
that's kind of partially filled in so
let's say we if we have a look at the
save profile method here it has three
bits of context we're kind of going
halfway through a process so it already
has the user we've already got the user
and we're going to the next one of the
process we either get an error or a
profile so if we were doing this all in
line we'd obviously just reference the
variables in the closure but as I said
can't do that we can't test it how can
we get around that with bind well we can
use bind we pass it this which is the
context of this inside the new bound
function and we pass at some of the
variables which kind of fill it in and
get back what's called a partial
function which is exactly that it's like
a new version of the function where one
of the arguments has already been set
that's what you get so we've avoided
using closures and therefore the
untested bility just with pure
JavaScript so buying kind of fills in
the stuff we get this partially bound
function and we can apply it easily it's
nice and simple it's not ideal if we
have a look we've got our two kind of
solutions to this we got naming so we
can test we got bind so we don't have to
use closures we obviously have to
percolate this context down in our
functions it's a little bit fragile if
we need to change the context we're all
doing it by hand so it's okay but we you
know we've won hyung we we finished cool
back hell not exactly these simple cases
that people in blog posts say are
completely insoluble definitely have
solutions but they're still pay points
so what happens when we have lots and
lots of asynchronous stuff let's say we
have a list of files we need to apply
some transform to all of them
asynchronously or in this case we have
two processes we want to run in parallel
will bind can't help us their naming is
not going to help us there we need to
have some kind of way of saying when
both of these things are done progress
okay javascript doesn't give us any
tools natively to do that we can have to
start writing them ourselves we can have
to start implementing this flow control
our self which is not ideal because
every single time we do something we're
going to have to write some of this kind
of eight ad-hoc code same those sets so
innumerable zor collections of things so
for all the users do this asynchronous
process for all the files do this
asynchronous process again you can see
this is all very ad hoc code you know
I've just got this like done counting
how many of them we finish so far and
then finally it does the callback with
the array of the outputs of this
asynchronous process so it's a bit of a
pain point we're writing code again and
again and again to get round some kind
of problem there's something wrong with
our code that makes us continuous you
have to write this ad hoc code to solve
it well maybe you could just get someone
else to write the code for us you know
we can see these kind of patterns coming
up again and again someone else must
have had this problem and indeed they
have and they came up with something
called async Jess
whoo so aging jess is a nice library for
note all the concepts in it could easily
be applied to any kind of cool back
scheme so when I say note i mean the
node callback scheme in that you have an
error parameter and then result
parameter in your callbacks you could
change it for other ones and basically
it's all the code yet otherwise have to
write if you wanted to solve these kind
of problems so it replaces your ad hoc
code it's a library of code doesn't do
anything special doesn't require any
crazy language extensions and it handles
all the kind of passenger you might see
so a chain of processes where each
functions output goes into the next one
exactly the same as composed with
synchronous code it has a kind of a duel
in asynchronous code so we're water
falling down the coat or we might be
talking about parallel as I saying so
when all of these callbacks are fired
give me this callback and have all the
results in it we might be talking about
enumerations so mapping over file is all
that kind of stuff as I said it relies
on this interface this error result
interface it could rely on another one
if you wanted to rewrite it the kind of
concept is going on is that we can
replace the manual ad hoc code by using
an interface and just running a whole
library around it so it's not going to
do any good for you for like browser
stuff unless you do some adapting work
now the problem for me with async Jas is
it is still an ad hoc solution it's just
someone else has written a bunch of code
using the ad hoc solution it's still a
leaky abstraction what do I mean by that
is if it hasn't had it doesn't have a
helper for your precise situation you're
still going to have to write the ad hoc
code so in that simple example we had a
fetcher user fetch that users profile
and then using both for those bits of
information do something else so the
fetch the user and then fetch that guy's
profile is a is a waterfall it's a chain
but then taking both those bits of
information is a parallel thing we need
both those and if you look at the the
signatures for those functions
unfortunately can't do them both at once
there's no helper that does both at once
in a sink so we're gonna have to go back
to some kind of you know ad hoc co to
solve that problem out and this is to me
this is a classic example of a leaking
abstraction we still haven't solved the
it's root we're still having to write
more and more and more and more and more
code and a sings quite a big library is
not just one simple concept it's
basically a bunch of hairy code covering
all the different edge cases what is the
root problem i'm talking about what what
is causing all this hairy code well i
think it's the fact we don't have values
when we use callbacks so when you call a
normal synchronous function you get
something back night regardless how long
it takes could take 10 minutes it could
be blocking for 10 minutes but you still
get something back before the next line
of code executes and that means we can
do things with that value we can you
know use if statements we can follow
pover it all that kind of stuff but we
can't do anything in our programs with a
value that doesn't exist yet and that's
a problem with callbacks it replaces
values with flow control as in we jump
around the program we don't have a value
that we can kind of use in our programs
it just doesn't exist yet everything's
kind of easier value so this is a
synchronous version of our process you
can see it's just kind of you know
programming 101 stuff it's really really
really simple and that is our process
like the asynchronous honest of it is
not inherent if you say I mean it's just
an implementation detail it could be
this simple if our language was good
enough can we get values with async is
that possible what is there's an
abstraction called promises or futures
which has been around for a while and
the basic concept is rather than a
callback that kind of flies over your
head and you kind of don't know whether
the value is it gives you an IOU and
that's a value get back straight away so
rather than as I say taking a call back
in kind of jumping summer with the value
in a future point it gives you an IE
piece of paper saying I owe you one user
and then you can do stuff on that value
so just like normal normal code you get
your value straight away and the basic
API is it's later fulfilled as in the
user has appeared or rejected as in I
couldn't find the user or there was some
error in the process exactly once and
the other idea is it doesn't matter when
that happens so if it happens
immediately oh and you attach your your
call back later or your call back your
request for the value of the promise it
doesn
difference so it takes time out of the
equation it's a lot more like linking up
cells in a spreadsheet when you're using
promises and then the second really
important idea is that if you apply a
function to a promise you get a new
promise back which is a promise for the
transformed value inside that promise so
they chain so we have a look over here
we've got a promise for a coming back
from our get a function and then we use
the promise for a and we say then some
cool back and that will return a further
promise for value for B and we can see
the comparison with a standard callback
interface below so this is the bit where
it gets really useful so we got get a
then and we've got a function over a and
we're saying return get be so that whole
chain this changed just like jQuery or
lots of other libraries now returns a
promise for B and we can use that in
future bits and pieces the basic API is
just this then so you can see the direct
comparison we've got the promise for a
then call back an arrow back versus the
callback method where we have mm-hmm
thanks useful cool yeah so we and then
the call bad version we have the error
and then the the value so there's a very
kind of tight parallel between this two
AP is so it changed as I say that
promises the core idea one of the two
core ideas I think of promises is that
chains for reasons unknown Jay Curry's
API implementation doesn't chain so it's
not really a good implementation of
promises so I would avoid that like the
plague and yeah they just let make
things really simple again so if we have
a process here while we're trying to
threading through so this is from a
project I did called tweed are there was
like a machine learning Twitter client
and it needs to get a tweet and then it
needs to format the tweet and then it
needs to run a classifier on the tweak
and you can see that process kind of
gets flattened down we don't have any
real complexity there and the whole
process returns a promise for the final
value you seem so we got the Twitter
next week gives us promise for a tweet
then when we get the tweet we put it
through the formatter that's a promise
for a formatted tweet and then we get a
prom
for a classified tweet at the end and
because doesn't it there's no real
reason we can't have multiple consumers
for one promise it's easy to tag on
operations like logging whatever else
you need you can chuck it out and
everyone can get it so if we have a look
at the earlier thing where we're having
multiple dependencies because we don't
worry about time anymore we can just get
the first thing we can before we even
have it we can pass it into the process
that takes the first thing and then we
can use some method like all to pass
both of them onto a third process
without any nesting it's just super-easy
it's completely uncoupled to time we can
already start reasoning about stuff that
hasn't come back yet whereas with
callbacks would have to be doing all
this thudding via flow control a lot
more complicated and manual and
interestingly it works with a lot less
library code so if we just have promises
we don't do any other code at all we
just implement that to function API the
then thing we can starting really
interesting stuff because we can here we
have a map over three files we return a
promise for the contents of the file
each one and we map over the promises so
now have the final function here is a
pretty we get a variable contents that
contains a promise for the contents and
we can return a new promise which is a
promise for the transformation of that
content without any additional library
code because it's a value it works with
stuff like maps it works with every
other possible enumeration function you
could think of it's already there to
play with so we don't need to do
anything in particular we can make it
even better with with libraries but I
think it's a much happier abstraction
for that reason and you'll see
throughout the talk from this point on i
think promises solve that one problem
that you can never get away with if you
don't have a value which is you can't
talk about stuff until it appears with
callbacks where's your camera promises
so who only yet well we seem to be doing
pretty well but i'd say we still haven't
one we saw one core problem with
callbacks but i reckon there's another
one also to kind of pointers with
promises you need to ensure you catch
all the errors so when you do the then
promise doesn't have any idea of if
you're finished yet
and so we'll just soak up all the errors
in the rejection handler unless you say
done in most libraries to say like from
this point on just throw the error if if
it's if it's there and it's not being
handled so do you make sure you do that
and you still have to unwrap them so
JavaScript has all this great stuff like
tries and catches and for loops and
things that we just can't use with
asynchronous values whether their
promises or if their callbacks we can't
use them generically we have to unwrap
them from their process so they either
have to come into the callback and we
get them out of the callback but we have
to unwrap them from the promise and then
use them so we write a lot of additional
croft where are we effectively
unwrapping the async value from the
asynchronous process and then putting it
into our ifs or our fours or whatever if
you're really nice to be able to use
things like tries and catches and if
some else just straight on the results
of asynchronous values as if they were
synchronous that was what a library
asari a language that was designed for
async would look like like why make it
more complicated than it already is and
I think this is the kind of irreducible
hell of callbacks is that we kind of
break JavaScript all the JavaScript we
know and love we can't use with this
stuff we have to unwrap and then we can
finally get to it we can't just use it
natively but but there's a pretty cool
concept called a wait this is some kind
of pseudocode imagine a language it
supports away languages that do support
away at things like C sharp so we have a
trying to catch and we we await the
result of an asynchronous callback a
couple of times here so we can say okay
if a equals await the capital a so we've
got some asynchronous stuff going on and
it's just going to stop at that point
nothing's going to happen and then it'll
come back so we're using asynchronous
code you know it's asynchronous
implementation we can run loads of a
sinker once we still have the the
performance of a sink but we get back a
synchronous looking code which is great
because a language is not as
implementation it doesn't matter if the
language look synchronous as long as the
async IO is still going on the
background so we can support lots and
lots of users and all that kind of good
stuff so could we possibly do this I
mean we can't really do it in in
JavaScript surely surely this is the end
of JavaScript do we have to you
some kind of new crazy language that
compiles to JavaScript or just give up
no javascript has a new trick up our
sleeve coming very soon we had a talk
about es5 today but now we have es6 we
will have seen hopefully so there's a
concept in es6 called generators and
this will let you do i'm sure a load of
really cool stuff that no one even
thought of yet but what are the really
exciting stuff it does is allows you to
write code that looks like synchronous
code so before we go any further I just
going to talk a little bit our
generators they're in the draft es6 back
that's supposedly going to be finalized
december this year the lesson was heard
an update from that it's in the draft so
it's kind of if the spec gets approved
it will be in there and it looks like
this so it has a little star operator
next to the function to say i'm a
generator function or a generator kind
of constructor and it has the yield
keyword now what yield does is at that
point it returns control back to the
calling whatever's calling the generator
so you can kind of think of its kind of
intermediate return and it pauses
execution inside that generator so we
won't go on to the next line of code
until the generator is resumed so we
literally pause at that point so if you
go have a look at this code here we have
a wild tree loop which is never a good
signing code you see a wild tree loop in
your code you're thinking are there's
this a bit of a nightmare but it works
fine with generators because we control
when it's resumed every time it hits
that yield inside the while loop it's
going to return control to the cooling
environment and it's not going to go
around the loop again until we hit next
so it's kind of like we can pause them
and play it again so lets you write
things like I don't know things that
generate long sequences of code
extremely of numbers or something
extremely nice and concisely and you can
see the API here we cool we as I said
it's a it's a kind of generator
constructor when we call it we get back
a generator we get an instance of the
generator so we call it first count now
we have our counter it's the generator
itself and then we call dot next on it
and then we get back a kind of to Polly
thing it so it's an object with two keys
value and result and then we can have a
look at the sorry value and done and we
gonna have a look at the valley see what
we got out and that will be the thing
that's been
yielded so it's kind of like the return
key word in that respect and we also
have a done and we can check if it's
done and basically if it's done it's
fallen off the bottom of the generator
just like normal cool so what does it
look like let's look so here is a thing
called three queries you can see it's
relying on some glue code that we're
going to have a look at in a bit called
away table and we've set up three
queries a B and C we set ourselves a
result array and then we're just using
the standard JavaScript I know not quite
the standard with this is just a
gratuitous es6 demonstration it's using
the four of not fought in so we can just
just go straight over an array without
any indices or anything very cool
feature of es6 so we're going over the
whole array of our promises and we're
just hitting yield and that's going to
block at that point we get out the
generator and then we'll come back when
the promises has been fulfilled so you
can see that this is parallel we've done
all the queries we started off all the
queries on the first three lines so
they're all going in parallel and then
we're going to block on them all until
they're all done and then we're gonna
return the rizal a array so it's very
concise and clear but it's also very
fast because it's parallel async good
combination cool now this is this is the
point I how to like oh can I actually
explain this how does this actually work
well I'm gonna proviso this is a black
box the way you do the the generator
implementation you can kind of ignore it
we can understand it it's not very
difficult you can you can either do this
with promises or with callbacks in the
same way if you have an interface for
your call backs you can do this with
callbacks to I think generators with
promises are a little bit more powerful
for reasons I'll explain in a second but
let's have a look at how this works okay
so we this is the queue door a sinc
function so this is the thing that given
a generator returns a kind of away table
1 so generators as they could be used
for loads of different things not just
this but we're going to use a generator
for this await style keyword so we get
our make generator function and we
return a new function that's the kind of
decorated one now we set up a continuous
function that takes a verb and we're
using bind against its lucky I talks
about that
we make two versions of the continuous
function one that's going to go next on
the generator and one that's going to go
throw on the generator and the next one
just regimes it as we've seen before
okay so we start off just by calling the
callback which is going to go into
continuer the verbs going to be next
it's going to ask for the next result of
the generator so it's going to run until
it hits the first yield and then give us
back the promise if we throw an error at
this point then it's going to return a
rejecter promise it's fine if the
results done we're going to return the
value of that entire process but the
important bit really is if it's not done
we're going to say cue up that promise
because it's yielding promises every
time that's the whole idea cue up that
promise and when it's done if it
succeeds we hit cool back so we loop and
if it fails we hit arrow back so we
throw now throw is really super because
throw I hope have a try-catch example in
here mmm yeah okay not even javascript
is a bit unfortunate but throw will
literally throw an error from that point
inside your generator so suddenly you're
a synchronous processes work with try
and catch which is completely amazing
you can suddenly granularly put a try
and catch around each one of your async
processes that might fail again you can
use try catch is pretty amazing cool and
that's it that's all you need and
there's similar the glue code for using
it with callbacks is even shorter it's
amazing now like I say I mean this is
just one use of generators they're going
to be pretty amazing so having a look at
a dependent process we can just yield a
wait for it to come back and then put
into be it's just like synchronous code
we get the value back parallel processes
as I said a pretty easy we just kick
them off we get the promises from both
and then we can just loop over and block
now the point I was making about cool
boxes you still can't do it like this
with callbacks because we're still going
to have the same problem where we don't
have the value yet to reason about
there's nothing in the machinery that's
going to let us give back something so
we can have to block on the call back
straightaway just one at a time so you
can't do parallel processes with with
just call backs if you can with promises
a new rule is pretty easy just leaping
over arrays and obviously this will
works with async as well if you using
the callback style sweet so seems like
kind of a synchronous code is a solved
problem well the last thing that we
can't do with a sink and I think we're
ever gonna be able to do is to wrap the
async bit of our code and ignore it from
the rest of our code so we have a
synchronous bit of our code and an async
because we can never stop the
asynchronous code kind of leaking out
we're always going to have to deal with
async code everywhere in our code base
and that's simply because jay s is
always going to be single threaded and
there's no way of having what i call a
deep co routine where we block the whole
thread all the generator does is go back
to the calling environment it doesn't
block the entire interpreter and this is
a good thing if we have threads we'd
have all the kind of problems with
reading that we don't have with
JavaScript so it's actually good this is
the kind of level of pain we should
accept in JavaScript we have synchronous
looking code it's pretty easy to reason
about I think we won I think we've won
asynchronous code is kind of easy again
it's pretty exciting so we got
JavaScript back we can use ifs we can
use else's we can use falls and tries
and catches it's all pretty easy we need
to wrap our code with these kind of glue
code things and use generators it still
leaks the async ever in our code but
we're happy with that we avoid threading
hell which I think of on balance is far
worse than callback hell cool so to sum
up don't in line everything it's
terrible you need to write tests
javascript has the tools to solve the
simple cases and when they fall down we
have our kind of trio of tools we can
use async it's pretty good it's not a
great abstraction kind of leaks and when
it leaks we can use promises promises
also solve the whole time issue we
finally have a value of game we can
write code straight away we can kind of
link it all up like a spreadsheet and
then finally if we want
right some really nice-looking code we
can use generators you can generate us
right now by the way in Chrome Canary
and node 0 point 11 with a harmony flag
and they're coming pretty soon there's
also a tracer compiler that compiles
from es5 to es6 includes generators by
some crazy voodoo so you can use it
today and and firefox but is it still
the python generators or yeah i thought
it was sweet okay so firefox soon
firefox currently has an old version
generators but it was seen how the best
version generators thanks a lot cool
that's me come