oops I am extremely nervous right now I
feel like I can't breathe but I'm
extremely excited but first I have
something to share warning right now
your users are at risk users of the web
everywhere are frustrated in this very
moment with the applications that
they're forced used every day this is a
review from the internet somebody wrote
about their application hey Amelia
somebody wrote about their application
the new version sometimes slows down
this is a real user of a real web app
there's a real review it's from the
Internet so we know we can trust it
and here's another review sometimes it
takes a lot of time for loading the
contents someone else simply wrote it's
too slow this could happen to you and
this could happen to your users but I'm
here today to tell you that there is
hope my name is Wil Klein I'm from
Boulder Colorado where I work at workday
as a full stack engineer this is my
family and I also have a confession to
share I have built apps that have
reviews like these and when approached
with these complaints I will initially
reply well it works fast on my machine
but what about their machine what about
their browser I use Chrome but it turns
out there's this other browser out there
called Internet Explorer 11 and users
everywhere are forced by their IT
departments to use it to use
applications like mine and it makes my
life a living hell
what about their connection I have a
very fast internet connection at home
and at work but not everyone has that
and not everyone has a fast VPN either
sometimes their internet is fast when
they dial into a VPN across the world
everything slows down a little bit and
what about their data have you ever
seen a defect or a bug where the the
complaint is that they're they're rich
text doesn't actually render as rich
text but as HTML in a plain text field
users do interesting things with our app
that we don't quite anticipate all the
time and what about their data some of
our applications are configurable to the
user or their organization where they
can change their data model to have any
type of Ire have different types of
hierarchy and this can lead to lots of
performance woes that we can't very well
anticipate so there are many variables
that work their way into our web app
performance and our user experience and
this is a full-stack problem we can't
just look at the front end or the back
end we need to look at the full picture
and see what's happening throughout the
system to know what we might need to do
and there are tools we can use we can do
performance audits on our application we
can do performance testing on our micro
services we can monitor our services and
look at their response times and we can
even do application profiling on the
front end and the back end to look for
memory leaks and anything that might be
slowing down but none of these things
look at what's actually happening for
our users in the wild so how do we
observe our users applications in the
wild how do we observe their actual user
experience to know what's really
happening in their conditions when they
use our application we're going to talk
about that today and follow the full
stack trace and learn how we can
understand our app with the distributed
tracing my cursor is in the middle
screen I hate that so this is a
daredevil from the Netflix series and
daredevil is a very interesting Marvel
superhero he's blind but he had his
superpowers that he can sense everything
around him with his other senses so much
so that he's able to observe an
unprecedented way despite lacking any
vision so I wonder if there's something
that we can tap into that would give us
Bella / superpower
so we can observe what's actually
happening in the wild I believe we can
get that with distributed tracing zoom
is a little bit so this is a trace we're
gonna jump right into what this looks
like a trace is essentially a series of
timings and each row in this is a
specific timing where a specific thing
happens and each of those things is
called the span in this case the whole
trace is following a user request the
user request is going to hit slash
dispatch with the HTTP GET request and
then a bunch of things happen after that
there's other HTTP requests associated
with it to other endpoints there's
database calls to my sequel there's
access to Redis there's a bunch of
things that we can see happening when
this request processes now some of these
things happen in parallel the the first
four things and the blue and the yellow
on the brown they're happening in
parallel and that's that's good they can
happen at the same time and then you see
the next set of things happen afterwards
so some things are happening in parallel
some things are happening sequentially
and this is interesting because then we
can start to see with this trace at
least in our back in here we can see
what is happening how long is it taking
what can happen at the same time and
what's being blocked and this is where
we can start to see where bottlenecks
are happening it's also where we can
start to see what actually happens when
you use a request happens so this was
shown with Yaeger UI from Yaeger tracing
Iger is a open source project that is
managed by the cloud native computing
foundation there's several members of
the cloud native computing foundation
that are sponsoring and supporting this
project so hopefully it'll be around
awhile they have a number of other
projects like kubernetes so they're
doing pretty well
I was listening in this podcast last
week and was interviewed with Yura
Shakur Oh
one of the main authors behind the Jager
and about 12 minutes in the podcast
interviewer made a statement
everybody wants distributed tracing I
stop right there for a moment and I
started to wonder how many of you have
heard of distributed tracing before this
conference whew that's pretty good
but maybe like maybe half not everyone
and what I've found in my travels
particularly in front-end development is
a lot of people haven't heard of it and
if you don't work in enterprise software
or an organization that maybe already
has this on the back end you might not
have had exposure or the need to look at
this and the other interesting thing
about this podcast is this was about 12
minutes in they talked about micro
servers for the first 12 minutes and
that's actually where I think a lot of
the content around distributed tracing
is focused is on the back end and how we
handle the requests to our micro
services I want to look at that in a
different way today when I look at these
front end spans the the blue that you
see here at the top where it doesn't has
a front end before it these are
basically identifying when the request
came in from the front end there's no
other information about what happened in
the browser to kick off that request I
want to go a little deeper there if we
can so how do we apply this to the front
end the first thing to think about is
well what makes up a trace when do we
have a trace what do we consider a user
request so I think about two things
really when we're loading a page or
doing a route change we're loading a
whole view essentially or when there's
any UI interaction of any kind maybe
they're doing an inline edit or they're
doing a button click basically any time
the user interacts with the application
whether they're pulling it down for the
first time or navigating to another page
or clicking on a button that is when we
want to start thinking about what's
happening and that's a user action the
other way the other side to think about
is the feedback that we're giving to the
user when does the page render when has
your eye state updated when does the
user consider it to have finished when
they did something this comprises the
user experience from page load to the
page rendering from the button being
clicked
to the view updating this is what I want
to measure and what I want to capture
with my distributed traces so I go back
to this I want to take those blue
front-end bars and enrich them with more
child spans more things that comprise
those components so I can know what did
they click what happened in the browser
before the request happened when did it
request it in the browser and not just
when did we get on the back end so how
do we instrument our code we're going to
start with how we time stuff now when I
walk through some code examples here I
don't want you to get too hung up on the
nuances of the Samiha of the code or any
specific semantics it's intentionally
abstracted just to have the main idea of
what is a trace was a span how do we
time things and how we might bring that
into our application so our first
example is how do we start a trace we
need some API that lets us well start a
trace and give it a description did we
load a page or do we navigate to a new
URL it might look something like this
might give a description that we have a
route change and then we give it the
slug where's that window location that
we're navigating to and to record a span
within that trace more specific work
that's happening in the system for any
of work that we do we want to time it
again and here we're starting a span
instead of starting a trace and then we
want to do the work we want to see
whatever it is that we need to do could
be anything right now and then when that
work is done we want to stop the span a
quick example of that is maybe we're
making a network request maybe we're
making a request to a web service and we
need to start a span and record that
it's request and take a specific request
what's behind the API I've start tracing
start span not too much basic idea is
you want to keep track of the trace
that's active so I have a let for the
current trace and then my start trace
function sets that current trace to be a
new object
and then it has a start time and a
unique ID with those two things those
are the main components of the trace we
need to know when it started and what is
that what is its identifier because
we're going to need that later and start
fist ban is very similar we just need to
start the time for a given span and
maintain a reference to it for stopping
the trace we just record the stop time
we're just doing a new date get the time
and putting that on the trace and then
when we're done with that trace when
we've stopped it
we need to persist it in some way this
could be an HTTP request but do have a
warning there initially when you getting
started with this making an HTTP request
is great just to see what's happening
seeing that on the wire making sure you
can thread that through to the eager
back end and that it pulls up in their
UI but eventually you're going to want
to have strategies to not create
additional user web requests every time
the user does something so batching is a
really good strategy to roll those up
somehow and then send them all at once
so what does this look like in a real
application maybe we're using react or
view or angular this gets a little bit
tricky it will vary per application I've
done a lot with react and even with
react
there's react with redux there's react
with state manage by react context I
might even be using Apollo client with
graph QL and what this looks like in
each specific implementation looks a
little bit different so we need to roll
up our sleeves a little bit to see how
we apply those api's I suggested into a
given application
but there's one common strategy that I
advocate for we could approach all of
our UI components and all of our
requests code and instrument each one
specifically but then it's easy to miss
things so I like to opt into middleware
or plugins wherever possible so that way
when I develop a new feature it just
gets picked up by the system and
middleware handles and timings for me
I'll show you a light example and Redux
for this the bit I want to focus on here
is in in redox or really a lot of
middlewares there's this concept of a
next function
and the idea is that you can do things
in your middleware when you're
processing requests when the event has
happened you can do it before actually
acting on that action and you do things
afterwards so in the case of tracing we
want to start a span before say hey we
got a Redux action here's its type and
then we call next and when we call next
it's going to process it it's going to
actually pass it through the system
although middlewares can act and
eventually redux state can update it's
the same for other state management
systems and then after that we can stop
the span and record when we finish that
we also need to make this full stack I
talked about not just having the
back-end spans but connecting it to the
front-end to do that we need to share
the trace that we create on the front
end with the back end I'm gonna use a
plug-in example here I'm using super
agent super agent has an API similar to
I think Redux middleware and Express and
Khoa have something similar when you
plug in a middleware you say hey use
this middleware well with super agent
use a plug-in you can define hey here's
what my get request is and I can say use
for a number of plugins and I will say
use my tracing plug-in and then here's
the response body pass that back now
tracing plugins similar to the Redux
example the middle of our example a
little bit simpler though we take in the
request for it and we can set things on
the request like headers so we can go
and get the trace that we manage and
then get the trace ID and put that on as
a request header for the request so we
send that to the backend our back-end
code can say hey is there already or a
trace ID existing and if it is will
create spans and associate it as
children of that does this work what
does this look like in a full stack
application in a real world example I
have another confession I've been
working really hard to come up with a
deal for this but I wasn't able to do
that in time it's not trivial
but the value is incredibly high I'm
pretty close I'm very
to share this with you soon in fact the
current state of tracing in the front
end doing at full stack is well this
Help Wanted there's a repository called
year client JavaScript that's under the
Jaeger tracing project and there's no
code there's one issue extract the base
JavaScript client from Jaeger client
node so your client node is an existing
NPM module that you can pull in a node
back-end and get a bunch of utilities
for starting traces and starting spans
but it's right now coupled to node and
so there's some help wanted to take out
the node bits and make something that's
browser friendly the current state of
that is that nobody is working on this
at the moment right now but there's
multiple people before this and after
this comment saying hey we need this we
want this so I think is I think this is
gonna come up more and more of very
common cases that you already have this
in your back end or that your back end
developers will bring this into the
application first and you see that
opportunity there already solved on the
infrastructure problem and it's
something to look at bringing into the
front-end there's there's more benefit
that I think is behind this than just
finishing what the back-end developers
might be starting trust me it is
possible so five years ago I was at a
company that had this they had full
stack traces with a pre react legacy
front-end framework and when we migrated
from that framework to react we were
able to look at racism and the old
framework and then react as well and and
see the differences and see what was
improving and even what was taking a
step back so we were able to when we
migrated into flux and eventually redox
were able to look at where our
bottlenecks in the front-end and address
those things it is definitely possible I
know a number of companies have handled
their own but right now we're starting
to see this come out and open source
with Yaeger tracing and now we're gonna
see it soon in the front end I believe
there's another project out there called
real-world i/o and this is
basically it's like a new to MVC it's
been a couple years but they basically
have implemented react examples and
angular examples and view examples they
basically take in any of the frameworks
that are out there and tried to
implement a medium blog clone and
they've not only done the front-end
clones front-end implementation examples
but they've done back in examples so I'm
actually working on a real-world IO fork
right now and trying to create examples
of this with a full stack so stay tuned
so I think again about our users and how
we can observe what's really happening
in the wild I can tell you it's amazing
being able to see an actual trace that
shows like this didn't perform the way I
expected and being able to see things
that happen that I didn't expect as well
because when we look at our traces is
it's actually not just about performance
when I look at this I can see everything
happening in the system and if I include
the front-end activities as well then
everything in a potentially complex
distributed system is apparent in one
view not just what is happening how long
what's blocking what and what can I
improve about this and being able to see
this happen in the wild actually user
requests that is amazing and with that
we can better understand our apps this
can be an incredible tool not just for
debugging performance but for onboarding
new developers for seeing how different
parts of the system that we haven't
worked with yet work so checkout yogurt
racing IO there's a really good place to
start there they have an all-in-one
docker image that you can pull down and
when you run it it runs all the things
you need to to to aggragate and receive
requests for tracing and then see view
them in their UI and I'll share some
updates on Twitter follow me at Wills
lab we're kin hunting that real-world
example to share with you all and I'll
be around for any questions thank you
all for listening it's been a blast to
to share this with you and I hope to
discuss this more with you in the future
thanks
[Applause]