oh cool awesome i got gun all right so
not I think we're aware that not
everyone knows why we're here what this
is but we used to be a fun podcast about
JavaScript in front end development in
fact no big deal but brendan eich did
start his 2011 John visconti you keynote
with so I was watching a curry the other
day so not too bad no big deal no big
deal we were also one of the top two
podcast focusing on jQuery um also one
of the only two podcasts focusing on
jQuery from 2009-12 2011 um very popular
among people who watched podcasts about
jQuery and this year we got invited to
this year's jas comp after being the
lunchtime entertainment at the 2010 the
notes say 11 but I knew that was wrong
uh so you shouldn't expect to learn a
whole lot because we're really more
about being stupid but so obviously for
those of you who aren't up to speed on
what we do we we've compiled kind of a
greatest-hits montage of you know our
greatest hits ah so that's we're going
to roll that for you right now after we
give you a little background oftentimes
Adam would either just nail a sec way or
just really bomb them and so I'm glad
you guys were able to get a taste of him
really bombing one so a little
background on how this starts a lot of
people saw this in the show but we never
gave the background it so we thought
we'd give some behind the scenes info
okay so clap is like our etherpad that
use and a lot of people actually
probably seen something on Ethan okay so
clap before in the first episode I was
the editor and for a few I was the
really bad quality ones and Paul every
time you would start a sentence he like
okay so any clap his hands and I just
got really tired of it so I
register the domain and gifted it to him
so we ended up using that as the way we
would sync audio in the beginning of
episode so that's the story behind okay
so clap and how our montage starts boo
boo boo that's montage sound uh we
should do a klappa club lemme yeah sure
Alex oh wow oh yeah perfect
cuz we know this is not the jQuery
podcast but instead this is the yay-hey
query the Y a query podcast so we just
basically wanted to have a very casual
conversation about what's going on in
the jQuery in front end adame community
I think it might be time for a segment
that we like to call get up if you
missed it last year ge'ez conf 2010 is
on the horizon we loved Paul and I were
at this conference and I think everybody
here has actually signed up already
because it was just the best conference
of the year this year
you wanna talk call a gay query party
line this is Michael Taylor are you
saying there's a map method on a jQuery
object and there's also a map method
just on the jQuery the jQuery name space
itself much like after and before
Columbus's voyage to the New World there
are two different maps that we're
working with here all and I think we're
going to leave you with that along with
our best turkey impressions and a
Jonathan Neal song ultimately at its
core it's just JavaScript and what we're
focusing on is making JavaScript the
first class language that it is right
well anyway thirteen percent is like
it's more than 10 so I think that's
worth talking about it's not third to
set it's more than German speaking of
Jonathan nail in addition to console dot
log there's also console dot der ER and
ER door gir burn everybody that I think
console that di are also we found the
complete bunnies guide to jquery this
that's what we're calling it cuz we
can't read Japanese that are jquery for
bunnies or I think it's time for the
plug-in it's really really great with
the bug in Adams yet you're so going yep
no totally still going we're not to
finish those
sencha EXT foundation or whatever they
were I don't know a txt core inner
international they are now sencha we
have tonight with us Peter Higgins and
he is going to help us bring in a new
segment that we are going to call Nate
query yay query hey hey hey so I was
watching the food network this weekend I
wasn't watching the food network this
weekend but there's a show called
throwdown Frodo right go down and right
now that's what me and Paul are gonna
have Oh welcome to the 13th episode of
the Y a query podcast proud attenders of
the 2010 j/s comp we're gonna hop right
into our favorite segments it's the edit
what little tiny things yeah without UT
this week's hit enhancement is the event
constructor didn't know it existed
earlier well now you do VAR event equals
new jquery event capital e because it's
a constructor you can throw it anything
what's it good for nobody knows what's
next out so John I'd like to ask you if
you would could you name ten reserved
words in JavaScript for us please oh
well so we did not know about this John
I didn't even know if so was an operator
in JavaScript let's get to the content
guys that was very emblematic of what
j/s humph is which is just crazy so if
you get a chance next year or check it
out it is it is a wild and fun weekend
pandemonium and imodium we're joined
tonight by our good friend Ralph
Holtzman we wanted to tell you about
let's just call it let's just call it
the plug into the other plug another
and bug it all the way
yeah that was that was really weak guys
let's try good
I thought it was awesome I jobs are
still like a week stretched um I thought
you're gonna play the music oh no music
in post I thought you'd still play it
for us I know do you want to have a
sing-along no it's cool okay so let me
just tell you about sausage someone
asked what Crockfords opinion on jazz
hint was and he said some of the lines
of people will always want to do stupid
things and luckily for those people
there's jayus hint what's that word like
the something that sounds like what it's
fun in my 2pm word is what no I know
about it that's very wrong absolutely
not BAM that's wrong yay JS conf Kris
Williams put this on last year and it
was just amazing and we're all gonna be
there this year and we can't wait so
sign up everybody have a a a time until
jsk and we'll get you some of our
backlog videos up now that we're sober
again so like a little broth awesome
peace out
whoo I'll never do that again um so you
guys may have figured out by now that
there's no backlog of podcasts but uh
you know ultimately we're really proud
because what we realized was we kind of
kicked off a new generation of content
where people could just delve into
whatever they want it so he obviously
saw you know the first take on this was
the Danai query segment with Pete um but
then we were really surprised to find
out that then there was the naquin
starting the fruit strike zebra and you
know that's where horse jas got his
start and then from there it really
started taking off our Canadian our
Canadian friend God mom so the crazy
thing about this is when it really
started going viral because I Darcy
Clark wasn't the only Darcy Clarke who
wanted to get in on this turns out
there's a body builder named Darcy Clark
on and hey and a female bodybuilder a
protein shake and and just pile of whey
protein started way query um and the
Scripps Howard network owners of the
Food Network realized that like
inanimate objects are just stalking for
30 minutes was a great great content
idea so that's where they did on full a
query uh Benny a query chicken satay
query and of course then three
crustaceans and a supercomputer joined
together for Creek query I know what you
guys are all thinking that shits Cray
but that should what's really cry is
Kanye query
but you know ultimately Kanye query
turned out to be kind of shitty and you
kind of wanted to wash yourself
afterwards so that's why there was but a
query but then I showed that to my
grandmother and she was like oh hey
query um and we but we knew we were
going to start to jump the shark when
like the mainstream entertainment kind
of got involved and um a whip wax a tie
and fifty actual Shades of Grey joint
for fifty Shades of Grey query and then
Hollywood got in on the action with of
course Michael Bay query and you know we
had you know this really just goes on
and on we have at least 20 unused shitty
jokes regulo we're going to turn this on
its head and I'm go back to our roots
from gamescom 2010 and do a game show
it's uh it's game time cool so we did a
game show where we called like groups of
ten up last time during lunch everyone's
trying to eat now my god leave us alone
but we were in there and you couldn't
really ignore us and so this time we're
going to let you stay in your seats and
you're going to be able to vote with
your phones or you can use your
internet-connected device in order to
vote so we have URL do I say that yet I
don't know that I don't remember the
order I'm sorry so sorry so basically on
bootstrap is obviously taken off like
gangbusters the last couple years and
Jacob Thornton fat obviously maintainer
of that you know great personality great
guy so we decided to put together a game
show called dead fat tweet that oh so if
you followed that or even if you don't I
you know you'll probably be able to play
along so here are the rules we're going
to post the content of a tweet fat may
or may not have tweeted
are you can go to poli vcom / jquery
each of the poles will have a text code
you can tweet to a text 2 2 2 333 or you
can tweet the code at at pole and the y
at pole way to go guys um must know
someone at Twitter all right so we're
going to roll that do that right now and
will give you like 15 30 seconds to
answer play some tunes so the first one
is kind of softball you know whether or
not you follow fat I just vote and we'll
we'll see what everyone thinks oh nice
this one says I'm really excited about
the upcoming bootstrap 3 release
congrats to all involved impeccable
grammar a lot of fakes on this one all
right should we reveal yeah yeah that's
the the critical mass alright hundred
results it is fake it is fake yeah I
guess up Jacob would never tweet
anything like this there's a capital
there's an apostrophe he mentioned
technology at all so let's move on
burritos are my family so get some
results for this oh wow this is the
chicory dance theme dance party theme I
think beautiful massive 105-102 it's
fake we got you guys we just wanted a to
shake it up in the beginning so now you
don't know what to think so let's go to
the next one what if pizza is
uncomfortable with its reputation real
or fake guys real or fake Oh real I
think some people are on Jacobs Twitter
page it's already critical mass don't go
there it's real alright next one guys my
new doctor uses linux
oh very neck-and-neck Oh back to fake
real oh oh and it looks like let it wait
it out all right uh yeah it is really
worth mainline general tso's every day
see how far it got me real or fake wow
really take it up now these atoms I
believe I think you really nailed it ban
tannaz a lot of context there I think we
got she was enough all right holy shit
baby corn isn't actually corn what is
real life even that is real nice work
guys are laying in bed alone eating
Smarties period 27 no dude Oh coming
back no and we're we know yes it's real
okay got a hat today Twitter I like the
first person usage 104 it is real you
got you worst we'd ever am i right loli
been to this is the last one guys to
make account and it looks like it's real
it is real good look everybody all right
like you guys got like 50 prick crowd
was 50 55 next segment all right so we
had a segment before it was called let's
see if I can play this you want to play
for me it's like a come on oh yeah
that's cool let's do that oh it's not
that one no come on so this was one of
our favorite segments but we wanted to
kind of like summarize all the things
that we learned over the past few years
and kind of contextualize it and so
polish is jQuery anti-pattern for
performance of the decade is polishes
anti a pattern for performance of the
week so basically I wanted to just
apologize um I got caught up in like the
shiny performance optimizations the
kinds of things that you might see on
Jas perf and just like really dig into
those little micro things that overall
in the big picture don't really teach a
whole lot demo all right Rebecca said
you might not learn anything but we're
going to try something here so very
quickly I just wanted to point out Jess
when it comes to a speed perspective
especially on websites right jess is
often a small fraction of the picture
both unlike load time and on runtime
these are actually stats from when ie8
was released there was a good talk about
ie a performance but this is as true as
it was today as it was then I looked at
like the amount of JavaScript I was only
contribute to thirty three percent of
the time spent on the cpu on like google
maps and gmail but like regular web
sites around sixteen percent not a big
deal and so what i want to do is kind of
show you a more realistic view of
overall performance so what I have here
is kind of this infographic e parallax
site quickly going to scroll through it
just to kind of show you what it looks
like so we got kind of this explosion
thing and then over here this little
physics ii dots ago
hmm it's fun and then this action
parallax II fun stuff and then I keep
going down and then there's these dots
that kind of explode all over the place
it's pretty cool but what I'm going to
do is go back to the very top lit up
timeline and the chrome devtools and
frames mode start recording and then
we're going to scroll through the page
again same kind of deal but what you're
seeing on the bottom all these bars
coming up through is is that's giving
them the idea of the kinds of operations
that the browser is doing in this whole
time no I just hit close tab because
seems normal ouch all right frames mode
oh yeah yeah so worked so what we're
looking at here is kind of the
performance adds a narrative of going
through this operation towards the
beginning this green section here is
paints we have really heavy painting and
this is as all these orange bubbles are
coming in let me go into a bunch of
yellow this is during the physics
operation here this is actual JavaScript
being a pretty heavy then it's pretty
chill in the middle for the most part
we're hitting our frame budget goals and
down towards the bottom we have this
kind of white explosion and there's kind
of a lot of operations including a good
amount of purple spent in here this is a
time spent and layout but this gives us
a good view of kind of like all the
things that are going on so that like
for each segment there is actually a
specific well there are predominant
bottlenecks and this gives a good idea
of how to adjust this paint here
JavaScript here and if we wanted to find
out kind of what we could do for
JavaScript I think Peter Flynn from
Adobe showed this just the other day
record a CPU profile and switch over to
the new flame chart and get a view of
overtime kind of at each frame you know
what's the consistency of frames here
and what are we looking at per frame is
minified but you know you get what I'm
saying all right enough a useful content
let's go back to the show
yeah whoo so obviously as you may have
seen the plugin of the week was one of
our most cherished segments um you know
one mention on yake free plugin of the
week pretty soon you have like a
successful startup in a book deal true
wilson arm and but the thing is nowadays
when people release jQuery plugins they
end up on Acra news and everyone's like
you know what the fuck is this bullshit
why would you bother like robbing some
simple iteration sugar around like
something useful when you could be a
dick and not do that ah ah so as you can
see uh you know here's a hacker research
for why is this a jquery plugin just a
small snippet on so that's why when we
come up here to jas count we know
everyone's really sophisticated and if
we're going to tell you about a plugin
we want to be something that's really
modular we want it to be something
that's useful in you know a broad
variety of situations but most
importantly we want it to be something
that inspires thoughts of a romantic
walk in the enchanted woods with notes
of apricot nectar but most the petals
and tuscan cypress that's why our plugin
of the week for this week is the bed and
bath and body works well flowers
signature collection twilight woods to
pack refill boom alright so back in back
in two thousand nine when we got started
with this podcast we were kind of
looking to the future because that's
what what this podcast is about was was
being smart people looking to the future
and and so way back then we put together
a time capsule doubtful umm that smells
like the beer from yesterday uh it does
no really so so we don't really remember
what's in here but but we're going to
read these these predictions that we
made from from back in 2009 about what
the world would be like when when we
were here in 24 2013 it's a good thing
someone else is unfolding these because
microphone all right protection number
one jquery will need to come out with a
web app framework in order to remain
relevant
uh is John Dalton in here somewhere Oh
fuse j/s will be released oh yeah we
will definitely have modules in
JavaScript i I don't I don't I don't
think I should i do it no Paul's 15
minutes of fame will be over yeah I
don't know who wrote that hard to say uh
Apple Apple will totally cave on that
whole flash thing last one last one all
right we weren't very even about this
but thats that's all right jayus comp
seems like a nice idea but the Ajax
experience has way too much developer
mind chair for it to ever take off all
right so we just wanted to shout a thank
you to all the people who helped make
jquery such a success Kohi tray was our
illustrator on our site you'll see a
bunch of these fantastic illustrations
of mystical magical creatures thank you
very much go heat ray he's awesome
Snover who did our video editing a lot
of the stuff he softened montage that
was fantastically good after we fired
alex for doing such a great job I edited
the montage I edited his edits um thank
you to John Neal who made all this
awesome music if you it's great um if
you just Google jquery music you'll find
a band page of the entire soundtrack the
songs are incredible and last of all
probably i'm closing music or something
right there a walk off stage two and
then we'll slowly come back and get our