so I'm my full name is coven they busy
you call me coven easiest way to
remember k with an oven and for the last
few years I've been making interactive
and public art and more recently I've
been thinking about how to bring the
internet into that so how to make works
for a wider public and it's really
exciting for me to be here right now
because the JavaScript community has
been a big influence in the values i
have in making this work especially in
like the emphasis of building openly and
collaboratively and so i tweeted out
some links for some of the demos and
later on we'll try them out maybe
they'll work maybe they want but either
way we'll have some fun so a little bit
about myself I work at a company called
in bed Lee I'm coming down for Boston
and what we do is it's an API for
embedding media so people use it in
their apps or websites to create medium
a ship's or expressive media stuff open
sources tool recently player JS for
working with movie players or sound
players a few years ago I began a public
art group called new American public art
with a few collaborators and whatever we
make it must follow to principles one
its interactive so whatever we make must
respond to you and to its public if you
go to the peace you must be able to see
it or engage with it for free you know
you shouldn't have to pay anything for
it and we we did this because we realize
that there's a huge opportunity in
cities and public spaces for this kind
of work to create a platform for
conversation or just to have fun and
meet new people and just more citizen
engagement I want to tell you about this
group the austin foundation recently
I've been participating in and it's
because yesterday a lot of you made some
pretty awesome projects what they do is
there's several chapters all around the
states and once a month many of them
give thousand-dollar grants so if you
need some funding for materials send
your project idea to them and then maybe
you'll get funded it's not only like
open tech projects but just you know
various art projects or socially or
socially conscious projects or maybe
business prototypes so on making
interactive and collaborative art
traditionally like when we think of
traditional art we think about going to
a gallery and seeing a painting and we
take a picture of it but we we draw
meaning from it we could talk about it
with interactive art it's more of a
two-way street so here's a piece by
Daniel Rosen which i think is really
interesting there's a camera on it and a
whole lattice of motors and they move
they move these little objects that are
attached there to create what looks like
a silhouette and we can zoom in a bit
further so here's so I'm just moving
around it gives you like a little you
get a dialogue with the piece you can
explore it a little bit and when you
look closer it's all these bits of trash
moving around this is really strange but
it's something that's that's a bit
curious you can explore it a little bit
and I think that's interesting so we
move to another piece set that I find
really interesting is by design i oh not
only is this interactive but you could
do it with groups of people here people
are moving around and stuff and you
realize they're controlling these
animations and i love that that here you
have the space of play and you're you're
you you can go with somebody you know or
somebody you've never met before and all
of a sudden like everything's a bit more
whimsical and silly and fun
oh do it later um such as I know uh you
guys remember that beach ball what what
was going on like couple nights ago like
we could have gone for hours oh that's
not an art piece but like I drew so I
just loved it so much I was
entertainment what was going on the
boundaries of that were really permeable
you could join it you could leave it
like whenever you wanted but there was a
lot of smiling and laughing and I
thought that was really beautiful
whenever I make a piece that's what I
want to get to somehow so I'm going to
talk about a couple installations that
I've done and then I'll move more into
the internet based stuff the first one
plays with the metaphor of a dinner
table that you can get a gather around
and you know have a conversation and
Lego something that you can use to build
construct together or alone in this case
our dinner table was this giant beach
ball we covered in fiberglass and
magnets and our Legos were little metal
pieces and we took it to a festival and
we told people we've discovered this
strange planet with these strong
magnetic properties and we need their
help to build civilizations and some
people jump right into it some people
didn't but then you know soon they
wanted to well it was cool to see how
this this could become like like a
sandbox this could become a world to
explore someone brought a Godzilla and
put magnets on its feet that could live
on the planet and destroy some of the
buildings you would see things other
people made maybe you want to copy it
maybe you'd want to add to it you could
destroy things you could construct with
a friend or meet new people as you're as
you're working on these pieces and one
of my favorite things was that like
families getting involved too so here
you have three generations the daughter
the father and the grandfather all like
playing with this piece and they're
smiling they're having fun this is cool
here's another piece this is a really
simple prototype just a self-cleansing
it's some a microphone connected to an
LED strip and the louder the sounds that
it picks up the yeah there you go the
more it glows and so there's many like
this is very flexible you could put it
in a club you could put in a gallery you
can attach to a
sculpture I'm coming from Boston it gets
really cold in the winter so we put it
outside maybe you'd make the winner
better and it picks up the ambient sound
and so if you yell
it starts to glow and it's not really
okay to yell in public but this things
like you can yell it's totally fine
it's little
so what is it that that I'm that I'm
seeing that happens okay like people
this brings people together this makes
wherever we install it it makes the
space feel more welcoming and then like
four groups of people participating they
can get more creative and they can get
more playful and I feel like you get you
can build meaning together with this
sort of work so now we're looking at
this medium of the web where there's so
many tools for interact interactivity
and also collaboration can I can I make
those those similar experiences can I
can I bring them into the web similarly
like the only way you could yell at that
led thing is if you were there like but
what if I connected to the internet so
now you could yell at your computer and
then maybe it would light up so the
browser is a canvas all of these
libraries that are being written they're
being open source I can I can download
and I can use all the API is available i
can use this is a pretty powerful canvas
and its network too i'm making this in
javascript this you know there was a
reason for this the community is so
strong if i had a question i could find
the answer or somebody i know would know
where the answer is the ubiquity of it i
create something for my computer and it
will work on your computer and i work on
other ones if I tweaked it a bit and
just a general interest you make
something crazy and like people want to
know what's going on they're interested
in what's possible with these
technologies so the my first like kind
of foray into this of like public art
putting the Internet to it is inspired
by a piece by kusama there's his room
with furniture net painted completely
white and when you walked in you were
given stickers and you could put a
sticker wherever you want it and I'd
love to trust the artist gave in this
like yeah you can you can leave your
mark here it's okay so what would that
be like on the web okay like I could
draw circles on this web page and i can
add web sockets so like i could see the
circles you draw sweet cool all right so
this is like this is familiar to us we
all we all get this but like for some
people feels like magic you know and
that's kind of fun and then you get
these interesting patterns like faces
and circle pines but really once it's on
a screen then you could do a lot of
different things with it you could
project it on a building and like the
scale is suddenly so different it's not
about my hand in my in my head anymore
it's like my hands in my head it's like
my whole body like you walk in front of
saying feel it and somebody walks by and
rarely do you see something on this
scale in a city that you can
change but now you can you just go to
this website on your phone you could
change it I wasn't even here this was in
Grand Rapids I was in somerville I went
on the website and I changed it to it
was wonderful and it took like
screenshots it was felt really good
here's another building we protected on
in some of the patterns you know someone
wrote a que because I made it on here's
a happy face someone started drawing
hair on it help I don't know why someone
was desiring help through this there's
other channels like different patterns
like that a happy phase so we can try
you want to so like if you've whoa okay
cool so what's happening this is all of
us doing this together and it's working
great you're in my talk with me maybe
I'll return oh my god this is so many
gay ok so I'm going to leave that open
ok so now screens now objects this is a
sweet led peace by Leo via real and you
go through it and there's all this
beautiful shimmering I want to be able
to change that in some way so gotten LED
grid hooked it up to the browser nodes
cereal and all right now I'm drawing on
it okay once it's working in the browser
cool okay I build a housing so now I
could take it on the airplane doesn't
look as sketchy and then I could draw on
it with a phone like now it's with the
phone okay now one font control with it
then I can get multiple phones sweet now
we have a collaborative like piece of
art that we can all access with our
phones and you can imagine this in a
storefront and like that storefront that
area suddenly become so much more
activated and this is just a small
prototype there's like many other
possibilities I'm going to return to
this kind of stuff later on in the talk
now I'm going to go to other weird
internet art stuff tumblr as a medium
for art gifts are popular and tumblr I
was making some gifts and posting them
many of them didn't work out but some of
them did and that like triggers these
neural synapses and just wanting more
but I didn't have time to make so many
more like it takes a while to make one
that's compelling so I just set up a
script to make them these like really
minimal gradients because I found them
very soothing and i'd post them every
three hours I was joining them with the
canvas and then using phantom
to auto post them or up to to
auto-generate them and then i'd post
that then I wake up one morning and it's
like whoa just got a lot of followers
this is doing way better than I am what
does this mean about me on tumblr and
you see these numbers they make you feel
great but then you look at it a little
bit further and then I saw comments on
one of the reblogs if you're like me and
often feel over stimulated by visual
stimuli I recommend this blog like blog
I foot with all those graphics basically
it's just really nice and I read this
and I was like wow that's really kind of
you to say and I'm also really glad that
I made your day a little bit better
we're both really happy right now and I
don't know you and you don't know me but
you know things are going to be okay so
this uses p5 it's a rewriting processing
in JavaScript highly recommend to check
it out if you want to get into creative
coding it's amazing canvas and phantom
of course all right so now we have this
webcam we take selfies with it all right
what can I do with that i was looking at
pixel sorting yesterday we learn a
little bit about sorting so I wasn't a
pixel sorting and a like glitch art so I
was like what if I pixel sort of my face
there's my face boom pixel sorting okay
so it's like abstracted I don't know I
started thinking really deeply about it
I was like all right this is the end of
2013 when I made this it was the year of
the selfie but to 2013 over welcome to
another you'd like take your photo and
obliterate it mmm cool art and here's
here's like what the app look like you
get this gif of your face and so people
like started taking like I put it out
online people shared it and then so just
like random people started sending me
their faces getting obliterated and it
was like younger folks elder folks but
then also like I like this one because
it was like with the cat so it's like
cat selfie obliteration and then here
was another artist who like to do visual
effects in the browser forest and so he
saw what I had made and then he made
this and send it to me and then we met
each other and it was cool like or we
met each other online and that's always
fun to like make and then dialogue
through that so that used canvas
getusermedia for the image web workers
to make the pixel sorting faster in like
the best pixels world library
so forth and I like later on work
together on this other piece this
JavaScript facial tracking library came
out what so we were like let's use that
and we just added this is crazy visuals
on it like circles and things like that
it made no sense but it was really
stimulating and we added like little
screen shots in the background and we
just put it up for for art hack day and
it was fun like what's more fun than the
piece it's really something what's more
fun to seeing how people responded to it
it was like when they would they would
try to get the algorithm to recognize
him and then once they were recognized
it's like boom they were the chosen one
and then they'd start making faces at it
and then like they would just forget
about everyone else and then their
friends would like kind of nudge them
and try to be the chosen one and this is
like the best metric of success like
someone took a selfie with it was a
goose so that's like get user media clm
trackers the facial recognition tool
canvas all right beyond the web camera
using the Kinect is it possible to
stream buffers visual buffers to the
browser I tried it with socket i/o
things got really slow I didn't know
what I was doing I was recommended to
use WebSocket streams and then it worked
and here's just the visual buffer and
then the next question was can you do
simple computer vision stuff in in the
browser can you do smoothing so here's
smoothing over over space but then also
between frames over time and it was
working and things weren't slowing down
too much Wow cool next edge detection
can I do can I do edge detection yes it
is possible this piece was like less
about art and more about is it possible
and so it was working and then we I put
it up at the show and like this is I
kind of see as v1 but like you can you
can imagine like you can hook up videos
to this you could put sounds to it
anything that's available in the browser
you can now use to the user with this
sort of thing but like you could get
edge detection live edge detection in
the browser cool so that was with node
connect and WebSocket streams and again
just canvas I learned about more about
canvas earlier so i can even met can
make this even more efficient i like to
play music so definitely i'd mess around
with Web Audio toys it's fun to do like
little
projects so when I got a leap like
clearly I would make a theremin like
everyone else did so this is a hit alone
thanks so that's that's this my mom and
here's like adding some filtering and
this is this is fun like maybe a little
stressful but like it's hard to really
share this so so saying okay what else
can you do okay minimal minimal graphics
minimal graphics in the browser with
sounds cool
you
Morgan ads I swear the next move as well
but for some reason i was using d3 for
this if you don't use t-34 this collar
application I don't know why I did it's
like learning and stuff so that was the
stressful and here's one that's more
relaxing
nice moment oh sure so like you know I
can show that and see what happened but
really like none of this stuff really
really compelled me until this came out
this came out recently like a month ago
it like went viral and it was like the
Wow cool that's growing this came out
and and it was amazing you press a key
and sounds happen and visuals happen and
then you could just play beads but the
real thing the real component part about
is that it would also work on mobile on
the mobile browser and before one when
you wanted to do stuff that was really
low latency you'd have to go native but
now you don't have to now there's a
whole new set of possibilities for for
multiple synth apps and quick gestures
that you could start exploring and this
this was incredible because like now I
could share it and people can play with
it and it's even more engaging than than
you know just on this so like you know
simple simple one-off experiments like a
pig Gator stuff or taking like previous
apps that i made like this one has your
mouse position becomes like the input
for a synthesizer and i'll ask tom okay
that's done uh and it's it's like really
minimal but um
basically
sounds
ok so there's something that would
happen with this we're like when people
started synchronizing with each other
it's start to get like you start to see
that behind this dot and the simple
sound there's a person and and that was
really amazing like like when two people
start to synchronize um you start to
form a language between each other and
this this taught me something new that
you can create these minimal spaces of
expression but really start to connect
with somebody else and it wasn't just me
that felt it like I went on Twitter to
see people talking about it and someone
wrote I just harmonized with somebody
but I don't know who is that weird and
someone else responded it's natural and
beautiful it's like oh wow cool this is
you feel is and so I'm imagining like
all these different little playgrounds
that are very very minimal very simple
you don't even use you know you're not
using words but where you can connect
with people in a very deep and kind of
intimate way oh yeah we did the demo
maybe we could do it again later okay so
that's how could I o Web Audio API I'm
going to end with something I've been
working on most recently and it was kind
of taken this idea of open web are more
seriously and being very open about the
process and just sharing about the
process and that deal was that you'd
have some sort of projection and yet I
have your phones and then when you move
them around something would happen there
it was very broad I didn't really know
what it would look like but I knew that
I didn't want the like this tapping I
wanted like moving so it would be more
about your body and not about looking at
a screen and so this first test was just
gestures to sound and it's like totally
hockey looking thing
and that was like that's like the best
icebreaker ever like people ask me what
do I do and I'm like this is what I do
and I posted on Facebook sounding all
serious like try it out and a few
minutes later I get a response holy crap
I just annoyed the entire room for ten
minutes of bliss OMG just holding on and
run around away from people chasing you
LOL cool so maybe there's something
about this but that was possible because
like they didn't have to download an app
I just shared this website in that
browser supports web audio and the
accelerometer and they could just use it
right away and then share with their
friends and I love that oh here's that
video from before ok now it's stopped ok
so oh yeah so then over the next few or
you know someone showed me a vine of it
on their laptop instead of their phone
cool didn't expect that you just take
your laptop and then because it looked
so bad I think people like hacked on it
made it their own built a better UI and
made it collaborative and I love that
love like that it was comfortable to add
to it but then I worked on it made the
sound a bit prettier and and added some
visual component so let me shake it and
then they're so these bursts and we
should play with oh hey here's another
video of like take it to a show and then
shake it around
like one of the people the show was so
pumped about it like I go to shows and I
just want to be a part of it now I could
be more a part of it and I like that he
felt that way so we could try this out
if you want to so turn up your sound and
go to this website I don't know it's
going to happen like I'm really amazed
at that other something what that was
cool it got a little crazy though oh
that's a listen this is getting
beautiful alright so now we're on this
page and this is gonna like managed to
lose so you have a color on your phone
right now and that's the color of like
the screen of like whatever this burst
is and it's hard to see where you are
right now but I think I'm the green one
I don't know
anyway that's all of us doing this thing
together and making these cool sounds
with our phones
cool oh wow this is still gonna whoa who
did this who is this who is oh my god
someone did this that's so cool you rock
you're the best sweet well I've never
had so many people on it that's fun
that's fun I think I'll make it brighter
or something I gotta you gotta you gotta
test for scale like this oh that's cool
you don't have to stop I'll kind of like
this in the background so that's this
uses a bunch of things Web Audio the the
accelerometer of course and then sparks
is on top of three and it's a particle
system library really fun to play with
okay so we all can send each other
messages and get to know each other on
the internet like it's a medium and just
in the same way as before I was like
curious of all right we have public
space we have public art how can this be
a means to to know each other in really
beautiful ways this can happen on the
web as well and we've seen it so many
times and that's kind of like what I'm
interested in exploring more I realized
why I'm so passionate about this at an
earlier talk in the conference there was
a line that really resonated with me was
in it was in gen stock create a space
for people to feel safe to be people and
I want us to think about this again
because it's really beautiful when we
were all hitting this ball in the air
and laughing and being weird like we
felt okay and it fell okay to be weird
and I think when you feel okay being
silly and playful you feel safer just
being who you are and so like with this
work all right how do you do that in
public spaces how do you do that
bringing internet to poke so how do you
just do it on the web and when you start
when you start seeing things that work
it gives us new channels to get to know
each other friends who you've known
forever like or new strangers it gives
you new ways to be expressive and
playful with each other and most of all
what's important to me is it gives you
like new ways to find joy new ways to
find happiness new ways to laugh and
smile together and for me it's that's
one of the most exciting pursuits in
exploring new technologies and that's
what I'm looking to do with with
JavaScript and networked apps and the
browser as a canvas thanks
and I you know obviously couldn't do it
alone so these are some some of the
collaborators for this work i'm gonna
post these slides online you should
definitely check out their their art as
well but i'd love to talk about ideas
and possibilities I've learned so much
about building more openly this
conference and I and I want to learn
more and so let's let's talk let's hang
out later on tonight thanks so much okay
sorry that's two rounds of place you