you
so thank you for coming to our talk
instead of Tom Dale's awesome it's gonna
be awesome we also have seven talks to
give instead of just one we noticed a
lot of really cool stuff happening in
JavaScript and the magic internet land
lately and really couldn't figure out
just one thing to talk about so we
copped out and we're going to talk about
seven yeah so like if you get bored just
wait like five minutes so first we're
going to talk about education so I'm
Nick I wanted to find a picture for us
to all get to know each other a little
better that's really I was at the
dentist recently so these are my teeth
um my name is Edward apparently this is
me I swear this is not photoshopped the
other guy is another guy teach with so
we both work at Shopify which is a
really cool ecommerce and Jess and rails
company right and we decided that we
wanted to do more teaching I've had a
big big background in like rails
developments ruby stuff than i did some
developer advocacy and then I went to
Toby the Shopify CEO and I was like hey
I would really love to do more teaching
and he's like no problem we just struck
a deal with these guys called hacker you
and they're like a beginning hacker
school and we got to use our lounge to
teach the school in so this is about
like 30-something students not all of
them here but this is a picture of
Shopify lounge the students came from
across the world it was awesome in order
to do this thing I needed a co-pilot so
I like loop Nick into this was kind of
voluntold that I would be teaching
JavaScript and I kind of thought that it
would be like oh yeah one day JavaScript
course it was not you know as a whole
time nine eight weeks course where we
just like info dumped everything we know
about full stack web development into
these students I did not find this out
into about three weeks into the program
but is fantastic we decided to take a
different approach than a lot of other
boot camps we wanted to you instead of
like being a super pressured stress
environment it was learn at your own
pace you've got nine weeks and what's
also cool about this scenario is that
room is full of like professional
Shopify developers during the day and
designers and all the people who work at
Shopify so it meant that if you were
interested you can hang out and like
talk to people about what their lives
are like you know like things beyond
just the technical portion this really
worked out for us yeah it was an awesome
program and we learned a lot of really
cool stuff it's the first thing we learn
or the first thing we want to say is if
you're thinking about teaching anything
or even if you're not you just do it
anyways everybody ends up learning
something from it it's not just the
students it's the people around the
students it's the teachers and the
people who are connected to the students
lives it's awesome next slide right we
also discovered that the teachable
moments happen in those environments
where you let them happen just like
talking to somebody about how to do
something is not such a great way to
teach it's really like I'm going to
prepare a space in a time and a
comfortable place for you to like figure
out what questions you need to ask me
and which questions you need to ask
yourself in order to like index and
unlock some stuff in your own head
basically we started off the class by
basically giving the students a textbook
and saying here let's go through this
together and ask us questions when I
have them I was like I learned from a
textbook this is the best way and then
like seventy-five percent of the
students were like this is it did
work for twenty-five percent of the
students yeah that's like the important
lesson is that everybody learns
differently and what works for one
student won't work for for others to
write and like the whole like some
people learn visually some people learn
orally whatever also not really the case
people switch modes like everybody same
day yeah so we had some students who
were like I don't understand anything
but the moment you sit down with them
and you like draw a picture for them
about like this is what happens when a
request comes in and it goes through the
stack you like see lights turning on its
the best possible feeling you can have
so whatever interaction may be whether
it's sitting down with them answering
questions drawing pictures or building
apps together like that's when students
are going to learn the best right so we
decided to like not just do full
lectures this was something that we
figured out later on we lectured for
like 5-10 minutes would be stopped class
and then we
little workshops for like 15 minutes so
again like if you were bored you just
had to wait 10 minutes and you get
something totally different and during
these workshops it's not just like one
person working by themselves we really
encourage them to pair program and talk
to each other and get better at like the
non technical stuff like how do you give
feedback how do you take feedback how do
you work together on a team exactly that
kind of stuff so while they were working
on their own basically that gave that
freed us off to be able to walk around
answer questions help students out with
whatever they need it but the problem
that we ended up having was our time was
being to monopolize by single question
yeah there's only two of us asking and
answering questions from like 30 people
so instead of one of our students decide
to make a solution to the problem like
this was his first rails app awesome I
learned how to build this in class saw
problem in class that it was too hard to
get questions answered so he built
hacker q get it like heck are you but
with the Q rhymes like okay yeah right
so um what was amazing about this was
this was not something that we asked for
this is a student who was like this is a
problem in my own life I'm going to use
the things that you just taught me to
build out a better solution super cool
this is what you want to have happen
when you're a teacher it's really nice
it uses web sockets so people can make
submit questions pseudo anonymously we
see them immediately can login as
instructors or mentors answer the
question students can answer each
other's questions that reduced our
workload as well but like have any of
you ever taught and done something like
this like who here has a problem with
what we're doing right now is everybody
comfortable is this okay everyone
understands it's the worst it is so
crappy like basically you ask that
question do you guys understand is are
we good can we keep going and all you
see is yeah yeah like how many times
have you ever seen someone go like yes I
do actually have a problem could you
stop the class for a moment and like
tell me more never have happened
everyone is like either uncomfortable
they just say nothing or they nod their
head because they're like I don't want
to be that person that holds up the
class so
I may have flipped out in one class and
may be called people some terrible liars
I don't feel good about it but while I
was apologizing to a large group of
people some of them took it to heart and
decided to fix that problem with the
stuff that we were teaching them so they
built this thing called curry it has
nothing to do with the fact that one of
the team members is Indian that stuff is
delicious so curry is short for
curriculum and basically what it allows
us as teachers to do is go through our
curriculum at our topics for the day put
in different learning objectives and the
different topics and first of all this
really helps the students visualize and
like get a mental model of everything
that they're going to be learning so we
type this in they can see it during the
class they've got an idea of where they
are and then whenever we're like hey
does anyone feel uncomfortable like can
we continue do you understand instead we
just ask them to go to this URL and then
they anonymously hit one of these things
for where they are in the curriculum and
then we instantly get feedback that
looks like this so this is another
WebSocket app I to node server and a
rails back end and basically as a
teacher we can see this analytics view
and every time a student submits
feedback we immediately get this bar and
we can gauge how well the students are
doing do we need to slow down speed up
where do we need to spend more time
reviewing so this was super super
helpful yes we did not ask for this
super cool the students are actually
taking this and turning it into a
startup like tears falling magic dreams
this is exactly what you want to happen
yeah probably our students props to shop
vie for letting us teach the love of the
web all right very sweet ok next is
commerce guess we're doing neat stuff
with JavaScript at Shopify which is
incidentally a company that lets you
open up the store online exactly so we
want to talk about how javascript is
helping our merchants somewhere where's
and make more monies so I'm Nick these
are my teeth is ever looked like this
here there's a tiger we work at Shopify
we just launched shop by two so she'll
fly to is a gigantic single page
application it's our merchant editing
interface but basically it's you
it has like 100 different models
thousands of different views and
probably katrien zuv lines of code I'm
not exaggerating no it's definitely a
huge app and it's all built on top of
Batman Jas yo demo too many words we're
behind today this is quick demo I it
looks like this you can't see that oh no
oh it looks like this yeah there we go I
it's a little anyway it looks like that
like admin side this is what the
merchant or the customer is looking at
and they can drive their store what's
awesome about this is that it's super
fast there's no page reloading you know
the drill it's all pushed state it's a
single page app like Shopify the course
ID is instantly getting a lot smaller
like if you go put yourself up on github
they identify it based on its language
so Shopify is now JavaScript app
according to github because we've been
taking so much out of the rails side and
then producing this beautiful thing shop
why is just a rails API now everything
is golden and harmonious and exactly how
it was meant to be so that is shop fight
ooh oh my god alright alright we made an
embedded app SDK so at one point Shopify
makes this API so that we can stop
telling our merchants know when they ask
for complicated stuff because we're like
build it yourself or hire somebody else
to you build it for you eventually that
happens a lot and we're like maybe we
should offer a place to market these
apps so a Shopify app is really just a
website over here a web application that
happens to have permission to access a
shops API that's it so when you install
an app it's like I'm going to give
permission to this other web application
the downside is that okay right so this
is the backend the Shopify admin and
when I click on a nap I get this screen
which is not like super intuitive for a
lot of our customer base who weren't
super like self-identifying technical
people they got really compaq infused by
this like they got over it eventually
but they're like where did shop if I go
am I still in my store like what's the
deal where have I gone so instead we're
like it should be like this instead next
it should be like this instead
so this is a for-real working
application of the app is just like this
part here so there's a like a tiny
iframe going on in here but the
beautiful thing about this is that it
can interact with the rest of the
Shopify API or admin rather um so it's
an iframe but it's using post message to
communicate back and forth right so like
inside is this app if you're like can
you pop up some stuff that looks like
you're in the admin if you want to like
show spinners all these other things
modal style windows this kind of stuff
so if you're not familiar with
postmessage it's a really cool a fairly
recent Dom API that allows you to
communicate between different domains in
different windows of the same app
securely so that's basically what we're
using to let third-party developers run
JavaScript within our storefront right
so why are we telling you this if you
have a platform and you have an API you
want to do embedded apps this is the
pattern to go with we've been playing
with us for years and run into all sorts
of crappy ways this is the best way
forward and we've open sourced this as
well it's a brand new API but developers
are already making like boatloads of
money with it if you'd look play around
with it it's in github com / alpha /
embedded app example there's one more
thing we want to talk about with
commerce Edward have you ever built
anything that handles discounts Oh fancy
you ask me Nick why yes I have it's a
pretty complicated it is the worst so
like let's say I want to discount on gin
that just gives you 20 percent off your
order ok I can do that okay but wait but
only orders over a hundred dollars ok
that's not the bad wait but it has to be
a hundred dollars before you factor in
shipping all right ok but you can't have
any items that are on sale in your cards
I don't really know which means I like
on sale ok that's better but you can
only get a discount while the moon is in
a specific cycle you're like a Wiccan
yeah ok Zack no offense to Wiccans no
that's totally cool so I learned that
it's like really hard to build these
discount engines and yeah I don't really
want to do this like Shopify doesn't all
let you do this I don't think any
e-commerce platform would let you do
something like this
we wanted to fix that so we're working
on this prototype basically DSL it's
like a subset of JavaScript and it lets
merchants and developers build their own
discount engines basically you get a
blob of JSON of the order before any
discounts for reply you do you're like
black magic exactly that matter what
wicked magic it is and then you send
back a JSON blob of the order after
discounts are applied right and shall
fly handles the rest yeah so we're
producing like prototypes that are
working that are like little notes and
boxes of things we're still not there
yet but again overarching theme here is
sometimes your customers love good dsl
and you should give that to them instead
of doing the work okay right so sorry
talk 3 I quickly want to go through
what's new in Batman jeaious Nick teeth
ever tiger shelf i if you don't know
what Batman is Batman is a JavaScript
MVC framework that we built a child file
with the express purpose of powering
Shopify to it's similar to angular or
ember but where it differs is that it
really tries to follow similar
conventions to rails does not mean its
rails only its back on agnostic and
we'll work with anything within HX API
but if you are familiar with rails you
can start building apps really easily so
the main new thing that we've released
lately is the new site like I'm not
really quickly right this is one of the
major complaints about Batman when we
first released it was there are no docks
please make it easier for me to get
started using Batman so we built this
when you go to Batman j org now there's
a live tutorial right into site ooh and
it's a live code editor with all the
files that you need it walks you through
getting started building a Batman app so
if I add the Batman rails gem hit save
now I have some generators I can build a
new Batman app right in my web browser
yeah let's set up launch out so this is
actually a running Batman application
and it's based on the little windows
because i went to full screen mode oh
it's cuz you're in full screen yeah
there we go alright and now if i make
changes in this one
hey ojs conf and hit save then this
window will automatically reflect with
automatically update with all of your
changes so you can actually build a
full-functioning Batman application in
this little text editor and preview it
over here the tutorial walks you through
building a whole audio playlist
management application the other big
thing that we've been working on is docs
so one of the big complaints was that
our docs were insufficient or out of
date so we spent a lot of time investing
in better documentation and rail style
guides and a lot more of the framework
is documented it's still work in
progress but we're going to use this now
yeah it's usable now so all right yeah
ducks okay just released a new version
sky logical stuff new test suite
coverage Batman rails is a ruby gem
which is less applicable here at JS conf
but if you have a rails application lets
you immediately get started using Batman
with your rails API and we're going to
start pushing this as the best
JavaScript framework for rails
developers it was built for us to chop
by which is a rails application and
doesn't you are familiar with rails
you're going to feel right at home but
you don't have to use it doesn't
necessarily mean that you have to use
rails like it supported on nodes like
you can really have any back-end exactly
alright so coming out more docs clean up
somewhere api's better performance shelf
is already really fast but we want to
make it even faster Nick when's the 10
coming all this is going to lead to the
one point 0 soon real soon now all right
danke alright next talk for 20 hours for
you yeah ok teeth so yeah here's teeth
I'm Nick this is Edward by uh we worked
Shopify so something I didn't realize
until a talk at Jazz conf us last dis
pastor asked on x ray Daley was
javascript is becoming a tool used for
storytelling and reporting it's being
used in the media yeah just today Astrid
gave a great talk highlighting how
JavaScript lets her tell more
interactive stories it does a better job
of eliciting emotional responses because
three interaction the readers and like
the peep
who are getting into this story can
actually reach out and touch things they
can get into it so here's an example of
the New York Times's snowfall article or
story I don't know what it's called now
so if you have any this it's a gorgeous
article about the avalanches in the
water in cascade videos and also its
interactive stuff pictures infographics
like it's really amazing it gives you a
lot more data and a lot more background
about the story and what the reporter is
trying to tell you another example is
I'll snap arcade fire just released this
new music video yeah if you haven't
played with us yet do it it's amazing
I'm not going to do it on conference
Wi-Fi but basically use WebGL and your
camera and yeah well you're the phone
and you're like our like shining light
in two parts of the screen it's really
cool so it tells you a story it's a
music video it's amazing try it out it's
really cool play oh god play we're going
to die nope come back okay there we go
so snowfall Arcade Fire this is really
cool for a few reasons first the
journalism has attained a new level of
depth and a new method of delivery that
wasn't possible before but also it's an
indication that JavaScript has become
approachable enough that it's now being
used by people who again like wouldn't
self-identify as like a technological
person so at least our JavaScript
programmer once told me that they don't
actually like JavaScript or all of the
compile to JavaScript languages not
saying I agree with this but the reason
why is because it's become too easy and
it's lowered the barrier to entry too
much that it's really easy to make
really dumb mistakes or to spend too
much of your time thinking about other
stuff but I take away that I got from
that was it actually lowers the barrier
to entry it lets lets us push JavaScript
and technology into places like
journalism and commerce where technology
would not normally be used
alright doctor next talk quickly about
some dsls and api's and why you should
build them in JavaScript so I'm Nick
teeth Edward tire shop fly dsl's make a
lot of things more approach right I get
it a dsl is a domain-specific language
it takes into account what kinds of
words and meanings and subject matter
someone would use in their own domain
like let's say that I'm a journalist or
I'm a storyteller I'm going to use a
something that kind of looks like a
programming language but it doesn't
immediately make me think like oh I'm
playing with JavaScript or whatever and
so when you build a DSL a new developer
or somebody who's not even a developer
doesn't have to think about JavaScript
and the browser and the DOM and the
computer and all these different things
they only have to think about what your
dsl is actually providing like the
business logic they want to build a good
rule of thumb is that you shouldn't have
to write documentation for a DSL because
a new developer isn't going to know how
to read documentation a good dsl is
approachable so what does a bad dsl look
like does anyone know what this guy is
this is regular regular expression for
parsing a valid email address and it's
probably wrong this isn't even it like
this goes on for like fifty thousand
more lines so regex an approachable dsl
maybe to some probably not we can do
better so here's an example of an okay
dsl this is actually from Batman from
the shelf I code base I like this one
obviously because I made it but
basically it takes a lot of different
complex functionality from Batman models
and streamlines them into one consistent
syntax and this model really clearly
like explains its behavior the common
dsl throughout Batman is a class in apt
symbol to say hey this class should have
this behavior and then which API
function you want to call okay here is a
good DSL so our friend Daniel
other guy in the tiger picture he's been
playing around with educational tools
and products and he made this dsl for
learning how to program where's my
chrome take us there there we go are we
looking at this yes this is Rover battle
except it's cut off really yeah just
don't full screen okay not full screen
eight minutes it's an awful screen okay
it says that's good drag that over
perfect okay cool the big takeaway here
is that there is a robot there are four
functions in this dsl move down move
right move left whatever you hit run and
the robot does it it's stupid simple
it's designed to like get kids calling
functions and getting used to this idea
it changes as you type it so if you do
this you'll start moving oh there's no
like compile or anything you just like
use this little baby DSL so I've been
really a DSL like it's just for
functions but by streamlining all of it
into these four functions it's a lot
easier for kids to actually see what's
happening cool dsl's they expose oh god
basically they don't have to be just for
apps or robots or discounts or Batman
models you can add a DSL to just about
anything right and suddenly you expose
another level of functionality to people
who might not normally be able to add
functionality to your product and you
don't have to do anything you get this
all for free I implore you to think
about adding some api's or dsl's to your
product and just like we do with the
shop via API all right buying shoes next
politics Jess ok so we workshop by
Edward does not have a tiger I'm Nick
these are my teeth and my teeth and I
would one day like to run for public
office so let me tell you a quick story
my family got our first computer when I
was like six or seven years old and I
started a program
because I wanted to figure out how to
hack these awesome golf games so I got
some visual basic skills yeah what dim
everything game everything I kept
pushing and learning with this magical
thing called the internet eventually
started doing some freelance I got
pretty into cocoa and JavaScript and
eventually this framework called
cappuccino I then started University
pretty quickly figured out it was not
for me so I left went back to web
development and gets pretty sweet jobs
get to go to some awesome conferences
like this one and hang out with all you
wonderful smart people my story is not
that special it probably sounds familiar
to a lot of you as far as that story
goes and programming goes I'm not the
war the best I'm not the worst so isn't
that a perfect qualification for running
for public office it's something I'd
like to do at some point we could talk
about reasons why later or offline but
what it means that I spend a lot of time
thinking about politics and technology
and how they can work together normally
that evokes images of like
egovernment and stuff like that but it
doesn't have to thinking back to the
earlier thing about how JavaScript and
lowers the barrier to entry we can apply
it not just to storytelling and
e-commerce but to politics as well so
one thing we could do is for example
start hosting our legal code on github
or some github like service imagine
being able to access all of your laws in
a format and all the formats that github
provides being able to go back through
the committee history so you changed
what and when actually right now it's
like today there's a legal hackfest
showing off this new API that the
Canadian Association of lawyers have put
together so we're like hey we need to
catch up and offer api's and dsl's to
our own legal code so like that's being
hacked on today these are not just like
pie-in-the-sky ideas this stuff is
coming so this has actually kind of
already been done united states is a i
think somewhat parody github account but
one of the things he did is wrote a
scraper that scrapes the US legal code
and periodically updates changes to
github so you can kind of go get the
u.s. code from github it's just not
official another one
I recently had to go renew my health
card for Ontario and it took no less
than three different trips to City Hall
to actually get the card this guy named
Dominic come on had a really similar
experience with Germany's so-called
egovernment you can read this article
it's pretty interesting a sickly he got
access but couldn't do anything with it
right the kicker is like none of these
things none of these forms are so
complex or so private that you have to
go through 20 different people or 20
different provincial employees so if we
just had a simple system of online
identity which we don't yet but cool
people are working on it hey persona
yeah there's no reason that like at
least half of all the bureaucracy we as
citizens deal with all the time couldn't
be moved online all right basically just
keep pushing like keep building cool
stuff and like build dsl's like Chrissy
was talking about yesterday with persona
UX testing may be named one of your
personas after a politician and think
hey could this politician use this
application and if we keep pushing and
we all keep doing this then we can
eventually get to like a better more
betterer place government technology
harmony and that's something that I'm
interested in that'd be pretty rad
alright last talked oh ok the Sun never
sets on the JavaScript Empire the
JavaScript Empire is growing yes it's
now available in like hardware forms
we're seeing it in flying robots hey
it's like I don't know if you know this
but like you can embed JavaScript inside
a PDF and it will render properly you
can also use javascript to make a PDF
it's being used in operating systems
it's being used in tunes create
operating systems yeah there's another
operating system called ASOS where it's
just a whole OS written in JavaScript
but it's also being sneaky and not just
being used in different technologies but
different areas where technology would
not normally be used or where JavaScript
would not normally be used so I don't
know if you saw this but the new SimCity
disastrous launch terrible fraught with
DRM issues but whatever uses JavaScript
to do a lot of its own like
lui and a lot of the rules engines and
this other stuff we used it to help
educate our students more better
different newspapers are using
javascript to make their articles more
interactive and add more depth yeah
we're letting API developers do a better
job and let customers do our work for us
and like more and more politics and
government and technology is being
merged together and moving online it's
JavaScript and technology are being used
in hospitals in iPads in medicine in
university has admission processes
basically javascript is growing we've
become a massive Empire and we can say
that the Sun will never set on the
JavaScript Empire we agree with what
Brendan said last night that it's going
to keep growing and be the language that
you write yourself I'm going to keep
growing and be a low-level language and
it very well might end up being a
foundation for a lot of modern
civilization where we're all citizens of
the JavaScript Empire and we implore you
to help it grow as well I'm going to
keep pushing it in technology or in
politics and government yep I'm going to
keep pushing for JavaScript to go into
education and open data so maybe instead
of building that to-do app build
something that lets somebody else solve
their own problem build apps that solve
problems outside of our industry it
outside the bubble glory to the
JavaScript Empire and flora to the apps
if he gets glory to the JavaScript
Empire glory to us all huzzah hey we're
done