my name is Tito and well I'm here to
talk about my personal story with
JavaScript it's also a personal story
with the people that I run both within
the JavaScript community so actually
that I'm sending it with you I never
thought that will happen you know these
days when you feel like you can run
through walls and we do crazy and
don't care about it yeah I handed in
this proposal with lots of lots of typos
and never thought I were here today and
yeah the unexpected happens so I'm here
today and I'm very excited and i hope to
give you a nicer storytelling talk so
one thing there will be bad JavaScript a
hat I mean really really bad JavaScript
so if you can't stand it you better go
now so let's start with my story in 1999
to give you the perspective what 99 9
was like you know our smart phones right
now imagine no color no more cheering
Jones no no connectivity besides gsm
monochrome display and like this and
this this is 90 99 this was also when
NASA was found it so well it's really
long time ago so this is me in 1999 and
the theater it's called a goatee and
thus Cody put me right into the
questionable end of the trustworthiness
of beards Gail and I did questionable
things with JavaScript this is my
JavaScript from 1999 when you look at it
I maybe make it a little bit more
smaller better um you can probably tell
what it does this how I apply it
and this is oh great okay this page
doesn't scale but basically this is what
it does you go over an element I hacked
it up with my pirated copy of 3d max
anybody could you go through the door
amazing right this is what i use
javascript for a 90 99 and where is my
presentation hmm it's gone so let's
start again okay the technology is not
kind of me today so let's move forward
2003 so 2003 was the year then matrix
revolution was released the third part
of a probably very cool first part but
it goes down from there right or anybody
thought that bed was better than the
first part know right exactly and there
was well 2003 and my nationals first
part I couldn't wait to be up for the
other parts well this is me in 2003 i
get rid of the beard so i stopped done
questionable things with javascript well
mostly because i moved on to work for
caesar wrap and a speedo match besides
studying computer science so let's means
also i haven't much to do with
javascript on the usual stateless web
application stuff because don't have to
care of it asp.net with fuse days so I
had a nice a te with lots of distracting
detailed and well this is the view stage
so basically just encoded every state on
a verification in a very
and send us every post that is
manipulated on the server and then sent
back well I get some JavaScript as well
this is JavaScript from two thousand
four three what it does is ordering a
list so this function I just show you a
part of it was 64 lines long had four
four loops in it and six if statements
so you can imagine quite complex so this
is where needed it for for to select the
entries I selected from one site and
move it to the other side of the list
that's all it does but that's how i did
it in 2003 and actually this is my first
serious web application it was used to
search for multi resistant pathogens in
hospitals so it was quite serious stuff
it was really fun also yeah I had to
work with the net but well let's move on
to 2006 in 2006 I grew me a full beard
and long here so the thing with foo bit
is it puts you on the very trustworthy
end of the scale and yes obviously it
helps because this charming guy in the
middle is Alex he asked me back then if
I want to run a company with him and I
said well why not I have nothing else to
do I just when you're studying so we
found a company called a stream and
throw a stream and Alex I came to rails
and Ruby so rubios is all I do for
living but you won't see much Ruby today
and I also move from the IDE to an
editor so much less clutter much more
basic and well with Ruby and rails there
was prototype Jess and I first of all
Wow cool all these nice objects and I
know how to do that and the crew from
Los also prototype came with some lights
and little helpers so that you actually
don't have to program any JavaScript
because you just have to call
Ruby message and the build JavaScript
for you of course right into your mother
I mean this is still readable but if you
want to do something more complex and
you want to use Ruby to build something
this prototype it ended up like this so
this is a mixture of Ruby method calls
and javascript in between and it
basically built an implied click in
place selectable date selector well when
I looked at the club later and had to
update it is it was a help but sometimes
later I also came to jQuery and jQuery
was like oh cool because it was so easy
to access the dumb right you you have
this nice lecture syntax CSS selectors
you know then a little bit you don't
move it so I is also improved my CSS
skills oh yeah okay there are not much
not much skills but anyway and the coop
you could chain it and chain it and
Shane it and Shane it and chain it and
chain another really messy code if you
just go with it and have no idea what to
do that's me 2006 2007 2008 around this
time so 2009 that was ten years
basically ignoring javascript i used it
i had with me all the time but actually
I never really really used in the
serious way but that change then that's
the end thanks to Sammy Jess Erin thank
you for that and mustache I could use
something I'm familiar with from rails
basically I have routes I have a I have
a model I have a template that was
something familiar that and I used model
view controller okay I don't
thousand times Indra in rails so I build
my little first little seriously semi
application but they're small that
happens in 2009 basically this this guy
young I have the pleasure to know for a
very long time because you was one of
the first co-workers in a co-working
space and rod J has come to Europe with
jazz come to you which in 2009 cause a
lot of commotion because Ryan introduced
noche as her server site or it wasn't
the first but like the widely recognized
server side chairs and the funny thing
is Ryan road no dress also because he
was frustrated working on the app web
server for ubi because we could couldn't
get so much performance out of it
because ruby was always blocking on
something so you see there's a
connection everywhere so let's move on
2010 so that was good the last year so
in 2010 they want to first this guy
Bobin organized the first javascript
user group in berlin and right from the
start we became the biggest user group
um we asked a lot of user groups in our
space and they're the guys that
constantly go of our capacity right from
the beginning and there I heard Felix
talking about no jazz in more detail so
that was my first real contact with no
just because I didn't attend the first
day of school and I was really impressed
what their what they done there and with
all the other methods to easily work
with file system and alls I all stuff
throughout the year there are more
JavaScript's events that influence min
away and impressed me there was the Jays
1k contest ok let's try again to switch
the tabs they had lasers there and I was
really impressed with it lasers for
everybody accessible through the web and
somebody actually brought wrote a jump
run in 1200 1024 bytes actually 23 you
see that way and corner that was Marcin
who yesterday talked about dumb
optimization and he actually handcrafted
his code so he doesn't doesn't use the
closure compiler to minimize his coat he
does it all by hand and he beats the
compiler it's like there was well for me
it was really impressive and yeah a very
creative use so I don't know why this
windows always disappear are they
somewhere down here no they just
disappear this is not very helpful
so let's jump forward yes this is how
his coat looked like minimize this is
the jump and run so and I did my first
series mostly JavaScript project in them
and I did it with Robin and oh I have to
switch tops again so we will use loose
again what it does is oh we can scale
this I'm creelo th oh no Shh okay let's
give this so huh but this works okay
nice time so it was a vector-based font
editor where you can make nice ones
directly in the browser you had a
selection of phones and you can style
them and they're automatically Iraq
aligned and for this I used Raphael
which back then was already a great
library because it was easy to use and
I'm very happy now that there's an
update what we probably will incorporate
in this project so this is one part of
the code there and you see we have a
namespace we have something like a real
object there so things that make sense
and I kind of understand how to
structure my code to do something
juniors project i also bought the book
that helped me very much with javascript
javascript patterns it was like 220
pages and i'm like for me I usually only
buy books that are around 200 pages
because I'm they're more they usually
have too much erotic and I want to have
compact and it helped me really to
understand a lot of things that right
now will probably seem trivial for you
like if you if you call new it's
basically nothing else than assigning
you object this formula
okay then I know how to build function
without where I don't have to call you
all the time or it doesn't matter if I
con you and yeah things like self
calling functions and well if you if
you're really thing about it like
obvious and of course the whole scope
and context thing which I hadn't dressed
entirely but mostly so another jess
conference and this time i attended and
i was impressed because there are so
many different kind of people and talks
from game engine over something with
html5 and forms and no SQL solutions and
well this crazy guy iconic javascript
maniac showtek j s and this was a really
creative use of the syntax of JavaScript
and using streams some of you might
still remember I still haven't got my
head around it I looked into the code I
understand the details but I hadn't
clicked yet so this is my challenge to
understand this really like really
uh-huh I see this is how it works all
together I mean kibo told me what it
does a nice understand but I don't see
it in the call yet
and of course it was extremely funny
with hanging out with people but sorry
no photos if you missed that we have
another chance this year so this year we
coming to an end this was a really
exciting year first there was another
villain Jess meet up that was very
impressive and the funny thing for me is
I don't have to move to the meetups
because they are always taking place in
my place in my office not at my place
well and their dad showed 140 bites the
talk that was just downstairs and this
was another great example of creative
use of the language and like show me all
the edges and possibilities that are in
there that are not that obvious and like
documented so I'm happy to do that
because it shows another side of the
language that otherwise would be hidden
if it wouldn't be for this project oh
and I also could spend some money on
another conference this is what may the
european ruby conference that i have
organizing and the great experience
there was that you cojiro matomoto this
is the guy smiling with the glasses is
inventor of ruby and he was talking with
Felix and Josie valima coke meter of
rails and one of the organizers and they
are talking about just talking about
tech stuff and there was no I'm
Unversity and there was so much exchange
and I really like well we're a big
community and it actually doesn't matter
if you do javascript or PHP a ruby
everybody just cared about having fun
and doing something creative so that was
it was a really nice conference for me
followed by another one just a week
later you see the note can be you in
Cologne where I first time saw Ryan down
and actually presenting and he wrote a
web server with C and showed how you you
slippery for that and what impressed me
there was how he does that he did live
coding and when I looked at him he was
like smiling and gleaming eyes and for
me the pieces are like he was a child
he's just playing with the possibilities
so there was no it was just ease there
was nothing in between it was just like
playing with possibilities and and does
in this raw level of see well and I gave
coffee strippers spinning at the same
time and when I looked at it even oh
this looks very much like Ruby so there
was like another closing gap Ruby
JavaScript the lines blur more and more
and fast forward to three days ago
reject yes and there Felix said
something that sums up I should sum up
or a notion of what we actually do and
he said well basically javascript is
just duct tape for the web node is duct
tape for parallelism or not blocking not
pal ism and so now I'm here speaking in
front of you at JS conf and EMS Krypton
is running Ruby Ruby is running
JavaScript to read through v8 and we are
all having fun everybody does what he
likes is creative so for me it's all
like double rainbows
and unicorns thank you very much