I love this quote you know buy the
ticket take the ride almost everyone
here bought a ticket I actually didn't
we'll get to that a minute I'm actually
here to talk to you about how Jays comp
and the people around it literally
changed my life and not just once but
over and over again and we'll get into
that but first hi I'm charlie you might
know me from some places as the internet
or the github or the Twitter's I created
and now help run Empire j/s an empire
node with a bunch of really rad people
many of whom are here today one of them
would have introduced me if I didn't
have a lovely introduction from yawn and
I'm not just talking about co-organizers
but people who have spoken or attended
or helped out obviously none of what
we've done in New York will be possible
without the help of chris and laura and
the community they helped create and
nurture first a special thanks to matt
who took a lot of the photos you're
about to see
like this one of the Williams claim but
now that you know who I am and why I'm
here I want to talk about pirates this
is a photo of chris williams at jazz com
2010 which was for reasons i still have
never asked about pirate themed and it's
kind of a funny story how I ended up
back at jazz con for 2010 even back then
it sold out albeit a bit slower than it
does today and I know this because my
roommate at the time was trying to win a
ticket to go to jazz comp by competing
in scurvy comp which was sort of like
reject Jas in America before reject j/s
existed in Europe because remember back
then this is 2010 way back it was
organized by Kyle Simpson and I think it
only happened that one time so fun fact
speaking of history if you getting
better at the slides I promise if you go
back and look at the lineup for Jays com
2010 you'll notice that although there
are a ton of speakers that are still
around today that gave many amazing
talks there's actually only one piece of
technology that was talked about erin's
giving me the look and as that's that's
used and that's not-- and that's only
five years later i mean think about
things that didn't exist you know five
years ago or will exist five years in
the future and this is both a leading
indicator of the importance of node and
the importance of the fact that in
reality people are greater than software
so back to our story that's me this is a
photo of me from scurvy comp I'm there
in the background I honestly couldn't
find a photo of myself in the foreground
because back then javascript wasn't that
important to me at all I didn't even do
it professionally I was more concerned
with you guessed it dotnet
I was no more interested in things like
types and Silverlight and zamel silly
XML go home you're drunk um and if you
better go backwards and if you ever done
that you might know the community can
sometimes feel like this and that's not
to make a point of being disparaging or
negative but to really describe how I
felt back then I was really really
trying to connect with people i went to
dotnet conferences i wrote open source
because although i wasn't interested in
javascript yet I was still very
interested in open source but there was
still nothing and I promise that this is
true you can go back and scroll to the
very very very very bottom of my github
profile and there's dotnet it's right
there so I tried but there was still
just you know more tumbleweeds that was
more than five years ago so today things
might be different if you do data net
professionally with your JavaScript but
that was my experience I was really
approaching my wit's end because
separately from this sea of tumbleweeds
that was passing over my desktop I was
really in my wit's end with the
technology itself for reasons that we
can talk about later when i'm drunk but
luckily i was going to NYC jazz with my
former roommate or NYC jas doesn't exist
anymore but it was a meetup that was
organized by a guy named by mitchell so
combined with that meet up and Ryan
dolls talk from JS confi you in 2009
javascript had really started to capture
my attention and I started dabbling with
it I was battling with it as part of my
research at Columbia which happened to
take me down to Washington DC quite
frequently to do research at the Museum
of Natural History so that weekend in
April just by chance i was there i
didn't have a master plan I didn't know
it was going to happen so I figured why
the hell not so I'm there I masker
become my roommates trying to win a
ticket
and I met these people and you know
based on my previous experiences the.net
community I wasn't expecting very much
so I was totally blown away like utterly
and completely you know not just because
of that but but it was it was the
feeling of belonging that I had been
looking for so at the end of this quite
frankly you know my feelings about
JavaScript and JS conf were awesome you
know like I went home and I was inspired
and motivated and I eventually had to go
home and I knew that there was something
that I had to do I just didn't really
know what that was and I certainly
didn't think that a domain name that I
would register literally two days later
literally two days later would be
incredibly important to the next you
know five or so years of my life and
that was for anyone who's looked us up
or read my talk description no juicy
calm and so at this point I believe in
JavaScript I believed in node all thanks
to jazz conf so it was off to a pretty
good start and I was also absolutely
taken by the community so that was just
the beginning over the course of the
next year I don't deep into JavaScript
and node writing open source and meeting
everyone I could on the internet and at
NYC Jas and it was during this time that
I met this gentleman Michael Rogers my
mic was too off there we go thank you
Chris at this point in 2011 Chris and
Michael were already working on
something called note cuff and because
of no Jitsu and because of the work I
was doing I happened to be running node
in production at a time when I probably
shouldn't have been which pretty often
ended up like this but whenever you got
it right it totally felt like you know
just the best thing every time you got a
system working in production it was a
huge huge rush for me anyway which is
why I ended up
writing so much open source and because
I think it's important but more on that
later so strangely enough to me anyway I
was invited to speak at node conf and at
node come I did what I think a lot of
people do which is a big reveal and that
software nobody even uses it anymore in
fact it's been formally deprecated like
so many other technologies that get
introduced at conferences they fade into
the background the software wasn't and
isn't important what we were doing was
important and the people we were doing
if it was important and that is again
open source it's about contributing and
with whatever people you share that
interest with and we contributed a lot
to open source identity myself
especially with a ton of other really
amazing people and I did this because
besides the work being compelling I felt
that there was like a moral obligation
to do good things and you can just
totally blame this on pop culture
brainwashing me as a little kid because
for sure my favorite superhero is
spider-man & foreshore this got drilled
into me my whole life and you know I
actually prefer the reboot version of
this which actually is like a thing you
can like take home and feel good about
like if you can do good things for other
people then you have a moral obligation
to do those things plus it's you know so
that's sort of where I ended up
obligation responsibility and that's why
I decided to start an empire jazz
because i saw this community I wanted to
give back to it and I felt that way for
a pretty run-of-the-mill reason I'm from
there I'm a native New Yorker and I
think it's the best city in the world
and you know some other people do
into the 36 chambers I kid but seriously
back in two thousand eleven and two
thousand twelve hearing the same thing
over and over again to everyone I talked
to about JavaScript and no Jitsu they
kept saying the same thing about the
same place so when you're from somewhere
and you love it and everyone keeps
telling you that you can't do what you
love to do in the place that you love
you will get enormously frustrated and
you will do just about anything to make
that place a better place even if it
requires moving mountains for the
community around what you do doing
things like running a conference for the
first time and for anyone who knows
running a conference for the first time
is kind of like this it is complete and
utter confusion you really have no idea
where to start you know you want to do
it but that's about it thankfully I had
the support of Chris and Michael's so
that when I felt like this I could be
like this and then then the day of the
event finally does come and your back to
feeling like this but thankfully I had
the support of jas comp which of course
lastly meant time for the family photo
and then gates a wrap which for most
organisers means time to relax or if you
have any sanity left which this photo
shows we clearly did not then in the end
you feel like this or to put it in
someone else's words I'm gonna let you
read this to yourself because I actually
still can't read it out loud even two
years later I still really can't sort
out my feelings what I do it was about
one of the organizers of the First
Empire j/s Luke and without Luke Empire
j/s 2012 would have never happened and
for those of you who don't know Lou
sometime in 2013 he decided to move to
oakland and some time after that about
two years after we organized empire jazz
together he decided to take his own life
and that is like one of the shittiest
things that you will ever have to deal
with for me especially because i don't
have a lot of experience coping with
loss but i do know how to run a
conference and if that is not both the
best and worst reason to run a really
good event i don't know what is so in
the words of the immortal raekwon i got
with a sick type click and went all out
so Catherine Lopez Juan Vertica Justin
Moses and Adam sonntag are some of the
hardest working people I know despite
all their help deep down I was still
feeling like this because what had
happened only a few months earlier just
increased these almost crushing feelings
of obligation and responsibility I had
as a conference organizer to like the
near breaking point and at times I
really wasn't sure if it was gonna work
but I kept going through my routine
because routine is really important and
attending the local borough jazz meetups
that had it happened just a few months
earlier and it was at one of these that
helped mold my feelings into something
doing good from such a terrible terrible
tragedy it was one of the suggestions of
the Brooklyn jas organizers Brian
Brennan who was also very close to Luke
to make a donation in his name so I
realized at this point that I have a lot
of Brian's to thank in my talk but well
we'll get back to that later all in all
we donated about 3,000 3,500 dollars to
a suicide hotline in New York from both
conference revenue and selling some
t-shirts it still doesn't feel like
enough like I spent a lot of time on the
email chain with Luke's mom because like
I just couldn't couldn't do it for those
who were there like I was just bawling I
wasn't sure if I was going to do that
today and without Jays comp I probably
would not have known
Luke and despite the difficulty I know
that it made me a better person to find
courage to turn bad things into good
things depending on your point of view
of course so after Empire Jas 2014 I was
back to feeling like I was after j s com
2010 I was very inspired and motivated
so I thought how about I start another
conference that sounds like it'll be
easy oh wait a min it I forgot it's a
ton of work so much more quickly than
before inspired and motivated became
completely and utterly overwhelmed so I
went back in my head to some first
principles expanding out and not up
having more events and not just bigger
events is the power of jas comp these
individual J Escom family events are
powered by new and motivated organizers
and so found new people Catherine Lopez
was back from the spring she was the
only co-organizer who had the time to
donate in the fall thankfully Tracy and
Matt and Chris all stepped up to make
Empire node a sweet success I have one
pun one pun and yet the burnout still
lingered it's it still does today even
though I am being more responsible and
helping bring up other organizers to
take over when I knew I couldn't do it
whoa whoa sorry my fault this is the
problem with animations ah there we are
in fact Matt and Chris ran Empire node
2015 just a few months ago with very
little work from myself and Tracy so
kudos to them chris is here you can meet
him so in other words i'm not in this
photo for a good reason but the
lingering burnout that I felt at Empire
node when writing the abstract for this
talk and later when compiling research
for it led me on sort of a journey
journey for a meeting in why every
one who runs a J's conf event does it we
tend to use the word community a lot I
myself have set it at least a few times
in this talk but to me it's it's just a
word a word that's used to a point in
vernacular where it has almost lost
meaning i'm not saying that i don't care
about people because the truth is quite
the opposite but why does everyone do it
so why are these people important why
are they worth all this effort I'm not
saying they're not but I'm asking for
tangible reasons why just this past week
I rewatched talk that Chris gave a temp
rjs 2012 called finding love in a bit it
was a talk that he gave after he had
quit Twitter for like a year after days
calm 2012 he had disconnected himself
from the popularity contest that many of
us including myself fall victim to the
saddest thing about this is that i was
literally in the room when Chris gave
this talk but I was so overwhelmed and
plugged in that I was not truly present
for it or perhaps I was not ready for
the things that he was saying but I am
now and the best two pieces of advice to
me were number one stop taking yourself
so seriously be silly not snarky and I
realized that I am not exactly the right
person to be saying this I realized that
I am perceived as a very intense and
serious person but being serious about
yourself and being serious about your
work are two very different things I
mean what kind of face are you making
right now kind of faces your neighbor
making are you smiling why not we try
like one thing right now smile at your
neighbor like look at the person next to
you and smile at them especially you Tom
make make a funny face d I mean do you
do a mean mug do you feel different
about them now do you feel more
connected I do I mean that's that take
down the wall number to disconnect and
reflect even if it is for one day a week
even if it is just for one hour of one
day a week make it a practice it may not
be easy at first in fact it may be the
most difficult thing you do all week
yoga really helps with that I know
people are not necessarily into that but
it does help a lot try something new
while you're disconnected go for a walk
leave your phone at home read a book
talk to your friends in person build
something new watch a movie with someone
you love following my own advice I put
my focus towards reflecting on Jas conf
and I realized that the community events
that they create is a direct function of
the feeling belonging as actual people
we can create so you can't just say
community it will appear out of thin air
i don't think that it has here that's
not what I'm saying but we just can't
talk about it like it's some giant
living in the hilltops that comes down
to visit the townspeople every now and
then we have to build it ourselves
because if we don't who will yeah you
build it by being kind and helpful and
not getting into fights on Twitter and
not excluding people from events that
you have and having the courage to tell
those around you that it's not okay to
be exclusive because communities are
really fragile and precious and
something that's worth defending so I
promised that my rant is almost over but
this last photo is one that I constantly
come back to whenever I search for
meaning I don't know if folks in the
back and see it but it is the pale blue
dot a photograph taken by the Voyager 1
spacecraft in 1990 about 6 billion
kilometers away from Earth and there is
an amazing quote that goes with it from
of course the immortal Carl Sagan which
I can't do his voice but I can I can try
look again at that dot that's here
that's home
that's us on it everyone you love
everyone you know everyone you have ever
heard of every human being who ever was
lived out their lives the aggregate of
our joy and suffering thousands of
confident religions ideologies and
economic doctrines every hunter and
forager every hero and coward every
creator and destroyer of civilization
every King and peasant every mother and
father hopeful child inventor and
Explorer every teacher of morals every
corrupt politician every superstar every
Supreme Leader every saint and sinner in
the history of our species lives there
on a mote of dust suspended in a star
beam so let's continue to create that
feeling of belonging and let's change
the world let's keep changing the world
don't forget take this feeling home go
do something with it and now Jana and I
have prepared a video montage which will
just really drive at home even more I'm
sorry if I was a bummer but it feels a
lot better now that I said those things
and if you're mad at me we can come talk
it out at the bar
I'm here welcome to gencon Asia maybe
the priest confluences introduced from
underwater for me personally reject is
way more than just a conference it's
it's a very special place with very
special people and they're all gathering
here and it's it's about much more than
just technology it's really about the
people that are here and that's very
very near to my heart so that's where
Cascadia j/s came from it was heavily
inspired by JS com JS con tu l xjs node
comp all of the conference's that you
think of as being the best of what a
developer conference can be and we put
on this event in November of 2012 and it
was just it was a huge success you know
we pulled together just over 200 amazing
people for two days of fun and it was
just one of the most rewarding
experiences I'd ever had
javascript what are you what even is a
class
why should we care about any of this I
give a talk about how I changed careers
in one year from no programming
experience at all to a hired program it
was rough it was hard but my talk is
about how I got so much help from so
many people in the community and how
awesome that was and trying to inspire
other people to help out I don't know
the whole atmosphere is just so friendly
and welcoming and all the talks have
been great and just the people seem
great okay so here's our videos and why
not when I wave thread ever robot after
we take off through this web app well so
the LEDs will flash and it will drive
forward one such as x-ray
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript virtual Dom
javascript is so much more than syntax
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript for those of you
are not familiar is pseudo code with
semi-colons on the end of every
instruction there are a few conferences
i have in my head as my favorites in
europe and this is my first time at jess
convey you and it's right in at number
one what's going to be awesome before I
came here and it's just what I expected
and just a little bit more you topped it
I wouldn't have missed CSS columns the
second edition for anything
HTML had hamill and CSS hats s but Jay
has had just yes that was that last now
CoffeeScript has brought us at ur style
of its own but there's just one little
problem when every stroke
k
number hit in New
and it's enough to make mistake with
JavaScript till source snaps land or
hello
hey jaz can't i'm sorry i'm not there
but i can't be but i'm happy i was all
the times that i was hi Chris and Laura
thank you and also everybody I'm sorry
and I hope the pool is great I'll see
you all next time thanks charlie also by
so fiddle is fuck it do it live this
entire thing this weary moat is bridged
down to an Arduino board spliced today
that's bridged into Johnny 5 which is
running nodejs that's controlling the
Arduino that's reading from the we thing
that talks out to the node copter we
have bound every single button to do
something the start button appropriately
starts it and because we have a windows
person in our group it also ends it go
figure the left goes left the right goes
right the forward goes forward the back
goes back just like a video gas goes up
why goes down B goes something and a
does something else we even programmed
in the konami code that does double
flips so enjoy this is the new style of
gaming that we'd like to interact with
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript what
are you virtual Dom
you may have heard it's not called
es2015 we plan to beat me why I mean
early adopter early as twenty sixteen
features we decided we decided to change
we decided to change the name of es6 yes
2015 and he s 70 s interesting class was
the most requested new feed class was
the most requested new feature invite
even is a class and class was the most
requested new feature in JavaScript and
all of the requests came from Java
programmers but it's really really good
whiskey don't do the accent I'm thinking
of organizing a fun conference in
Ireland and he said don't do I'd love to
go to a fun conference in Ireland oh he
wanted to do it in a hotel Jess conf in
Berlin 2009 was the first summer I
actually felt like I belonged to a group
of people up were into the same things
that I visited know that I didn't I said
well do it I was added in the hotels are
people who came to phone calls when Don
decided they were gonna do their own
conference funk off one was 70 people on
a bus welcome to was 80 people in a
castle funcom 3 was 110 people yeah on
an island Chris was there and ok Chris
wasn't abusing the castle actually have
a video of him going to love the llama
came with the donkey guy owned the
donkey said I have a llama do you want
me to draw him in Chris and Laura's
passion and dedication change the course
of mighty my life and a huge part of F
Delta to Jana lenhart soon why don't why
why why why not see w it's misha poland
mccombie August with me or no snow glia
calling conference a gain of gamma sauna
August finish august cash lon arashi ich
kann future come I wasn't I was
absolutely inspired by a wonderful
weekend in Berlin I met Chris J's conf
Berlin 2010 me to burn the first
somewhere heard iron Queens Knight
eyes like guys are these names are in
Quinn no Erin queen all you would
actually look to see erin quinn to turn
his head into irish food the follow-up
to the pizza book is the potato book
obviously i'll be microphone is picking
all the shit up kirisin laura we love
you thanks for making Jays conf you
probably wouldn't have realized II Men
the lives you touched at the time Laura
and Chris our hearts glad to you you
just wish you all the best huh yeah
there's a la botte and every weekend
here where do love this come from not
not Ireland that's nice balloon if
you're shipping I own an acid and dream
of the box you'll make you think about
going native but X goes a big headache
think of things like PhoneGap or
whatever it's called this week it helps
you to talk a web app without any need
to speak objective-c sometimes you see
Objective C Objective C don't need that
crap for getting the App Store taken
from me
help us run the room just make sure he
sober when you do supposed to be
shipping when you are skipping
objective-c
Wow phonegap sounds really useful thanks
pretty awesome you just the thing is I
mean you think like oh just use phonegap
and will solve my problems but it's
actually it's kind of actually not that
easy there are a few catches okay yeah
yeah I'll tell you about it right now
whew build both sides you can skip IE
you think es5 makes you feel alive
jquery
too bad gingerbreads
still so damn might spread sure it's
still wet kiss but it runs like shit
android 2.3 hi everyone my name is Juan
Pablo erotica i'm here with boolean
Duquette we're both Colombians we are
part of the organizing team for jay's
from Colombia and very thankful for
chris's and Laura's work thanks to their
inspiration we started in event in
Colombia that have been 2013 it also
happened 2015 overall we've run these
two events with about 50 speakers I've
had 700 attendees I've had about 100 of
the bursary scholarships and it has had
a great impact in our community who Liam
what can you tell us about the impact
well we started being the two
communities in the most important cities
in Colombia in both a meta-gene a call
baba 30s and meta gjs and after the
fishiest conflict 2013 there were more
people interested in other cities in
Colombia to start javascript communities
so as the date we have more than 10
seats covered about JavaScript and we
have mota 3,000 people with history in
the community for from Colombia so we
are one of the most important a large
community a lot in America this as being
thankful to the whole days come family
of events and the work that you have
been gone so thank you very much and
keep this magic happening yes keep up
the great work on our other
co-organizers coming Lord lr Catherine
Lopez WWE era thank you very much we
wanted to see save on their behalf um we
know it's not the last event will see
you in huge hugs from Colombia for
everyone bye we love you but it's really
really good
javascript is javascript is javascript
is so much more than syntax why should
we care about I in this
because we'd like challenging now we
want to solve problems or software
engineers
what he didn't use a class and this is a
good point even is a class and this
liquor Kuwait it is a class and it's a
good question and like frankly the
community does not have a good ontology
around what object orientation should be
nor really what classes are at all
there's nothing that works there's
nothing you can read there's nothing to
look at I'm going to tell you what's
going on but that's all there is and no
one has come up the pixel webside aside
'add well fix it
well Victor javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript what
are you virtual Dom javascript
javascript javascript javis javascript
javascript is so much more than syntax
javascript chaves javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript
javascript javascript what are you
virtual not javascript javascript
javascript javascript javascript for
those of you who are not familiar his
pseudo code semicolons on the end of
every instruction i just i just wanted
the browser to be nice like note is nice
we can solve problems by removing
complexity I'll by adding it so at
javascript burnham is your extremely
used to destroying data and we don't
have to do that and we don't have to we
don't have to do that
you don't rewrite your whole application
every five minutes and we don't have to
do that you don't we write to your all
application every five minutes and we
don't have to do that these are not do
you think so did not invent these are
not design of new things I did not
invent them you don't rewrite your all
application every five minutes and we
don't have to do that what's gonna
happen after JavaScript and I I have to
believe what's gonna happen after
JavaScript and I I have to believe that
there is going to be a next language
because if javascript is the last
language that's just going to be really
sad hi I'm Traci Hines I'm one of the
organizers of Cascadia Jas a conference
in the Pacific Northwest for web
developers by web developers we started
in 2012 and we've run for events for
over thirteen hundred awesome people in
Cascadia we've been inspired to push
ourselves in a growing community we want
to see every year ever more inclusive
bigger hearts and pushing rad JavaScript
boundaries cascadia wouldn't exist if
not for Chris and Laura or wish them the
best and were honored to carry on the j
s comp tradition Pacific Northwest hi my
name is trivoli I'm one of the
organizers of variables here in Oslo we
are now working on our 5th edition of
Wales and so far it's been a hugely nice
and great experience I started doing web
development in the mid-90s and the win
immunity for us doing the development
for many many years and then suddenly
Jays comp comes around cup of us went to
Jay's conf in US and in Boyle and it
just felt at home from day one suddenly
there was actually a community for us
and that made us want to do or
own conference and build our own
community herring up slow and so it did
and it's just been an amazing ride so
huge thank you from this award on this
shit happens
we are
german or life in some box I'll be
realistic mr. nobody from foreign women
we might work if I know
Oh
we're in this together we're all in this
together these people that are sitting
in this room with you they're gonna help
you can draw your next job they're gonna
help you you have a bad day and they'll
send you a funny cat just like super
awesome these people are really going to
change your life right here the ones
that are sitting right next to you and
those of you watched falling along at
home come to a conference and let this
like totally transform you my favorite
thing about jasco the conference is
great to get me wrong really really
great coffee and like jumping in the
ocean it's like super fun oh yeah um but
what I love about it is the community
that it spawns cuz like it's not just
jazz comp anymore it's like all the J's
comps in all the countries and then all
of the meetups that are like modeled in
that jazz comp you know kind of culture
which is super super awesome so thank
you Chris thank you thank you my entire
Jess comp team and I want to say let's
say hi from our
oh man we love you guys I record it