okay so we hit through a lot of
technical talks today so I know that
anyway started now so i will make
something less technical more funny or
something like that so i will talk today
what do we why do we need two eyes and
maybe i will start from myself yeah I'm
a JavaScript developer from Poland the
country not so far away from here on
east west yeah on the right and the map
had between Russia and their money and
I'm open web game developer and my main
topic of interests or games but we had
today in a couple of today and yesterday
a couple of game game dev ducks so I
will try to present something different
and I'm an organizer of on being star
that was the first thank you that was
the first html5 game dev conference in
Poland last week thank you and I creator
of some kind of ridiculous and
completely useless web demos like CSS
the end cap
yeah and I'm html5 game dev kappa couch
in w3c as well yeah and that's all yeah
I know that's boring so let's talk about
eyes now uh why we need two eyes first e
okay first of all one sorry one moment I
have so big ears that is hard to me too
no fight with that microphone first of
all one eye is not enough do you ever
heard of any creature animal anything
with only one eye yeah we had something
like a couple of thousand years ago
probably and and it's it's the history
now right so we so one eye is not enough
for us and what about three you ever
heard of any animal with three eyes yeah
what about cats what about cats yeah so
usually gets her only two eyes but there
was one there is uncut in u.s. we've
three of them and maybe i will present
some kind of demo now
it's on the about 30 seconds so so he
has two names he's known as a tennis cat
after the Roman god with two faces and
at 12 years old is the longest-lived cat
of his kind the fact that just earned
him a spot in the Guinness World Records
howdy his own find such an unusual time
he was brought in veterinary school I
used to work there he was brought in at
a day old to be euthanized and I said
I'll take him you know and they let me
take him what was it the truth he was
just so unique but I had he been at just
a normal kid and I probably would have
taken him also if nobody else's too
friendly than it just a normal kid and I
probably did you outside eyes are the
ones that see so okay I think it's
enough
well so I don't know if you heard that
the lady said that the middle I'd is
blind so even if the cat had three eyes
the nature force him to head only two of
them and yeah two is the answer and two
is kind of magic number in our culture
and not only ours because for instance
back in mid 70s the there was some kind
of expedition or how to call it
discovers a village somewhere near yeah
Amazonian River I don't know how to call
it the river in English but that the
biggest one okay cookers and they never
met any other civilization and they go
like ah yeah culture and everything was
based only on three numbers they know
only three numbers 12 and more and yeah
that that makes the number you need okay
so what about our eyes and brain ice
itself are not able to see anything it
it does you know the ice are just like
lance or can kinda tool for our brain to
analyze the images we see and true and
produce the scene we we can remember
after that so for example yeah our eyes
are had about five centimeters space
left between them so basically what we
what we see all the time or two images
in the same time right I think if you're
younger you try to experiments like
putting your fingers on some object
close one eye sea and the finger isn't
the same spot and now oh no is about you
know couple of centimeters on the other
side so yeah and it basically looked
like that so we had the view from the
left I in here view from the right I and
our brain is analyzing the images and
creates the scene we we can see after
that and and okay
analyst what are anaglyphs anaglyphs are
images because yeah basically basically
everything in 3d in game development and
in stuff like that is about cheating
right so we try to cheat our brain so we
try to mmm yeah we try to combine two
images from two separate views into the
one and we use glasses like that word
for this because in here yeah sorry yeah
because in here when we manipulate with
the colors of one image and manipulate
the colors of another image just to
disable the red one in in that one for
their right for the right eye and the
blue and green for another one we can
provide each image to two separate to
separate I just using the glass like
that right so and I think it works like
I made it yesterday during the
conference okay so yeah it's kind of red
stuff right no it's all the scalp and so
basically the anaglyphs are as old as
the photography itself we call that the
science about creating three-dimensional
images stereo stereo stereoscopy yes sir
it's really late now and that is the
first photo ever taken by a human being
barber bite by the human and it's from
back 1826 and yeah I think that one is
better because that is the first the
first photograph weaved up with the
people on there because it tooks really
a long time to you know create something
like that and only the one guy in here
was was playing his shoes that way he
was standing there a couple on hours and
that's why he's on the photo but talking
about anaglyphs in the same year in 1938
in England and France in the same time
there was
discovered that things I was talking
about before that if you provide two
separate images from the different
angles to to your eyes you will see the
Stan light at the scene like a
third-dimensional and first they they
created images like that and use yeah I
don't know the English word for that and
we call it photo plastic on in polish
but i think it's not not the proper one
and because in here you had s one moment
as you can see okay here in that length
you provide the image for one I for
their left one and for the right and one
in here and just couple of years after
that they discovered that anaglyph
techniques I I talked about before and
that was the first anaglyph image taken
ever in it was like 9001 something like
that and just after the people
discovered that we can make photos but
we can also make like moving photos
right we call it movies today they just
create one of the first yeah that's not
the first one but one of the first three
dimensional movie ever and yeah that is
now is the part when you will watch it
and I will drink some water
yeah okay so it was like like
grandfather of avatar okay so how how it
really works let's take two images yeah
it's from some kind of mortal kombat
fine art or something two images for
foreign our eyes that is the image from
our left eye yeah left yeah left and
that is for the right one and we can
manipulate it single pixel of the image
so let's remove all the red channel from
because the colors are construct from
three channels right right red green and
blue so let's remove all the red color
from that one and lived only read one on
another yeah up the opposite okay who
cares and then we have to combine the
images into the one and anyone used
Photoshop in here ever yeah okay so we
had something in Photoshop like blending
modes so you can you can just determine
how one layer is how one layer is you
know interacting with another one with
top layer with the bottom one and yeah
so basically we had it looks like that
in Photoshop but we had the same simple
formula for achieving that in yeah using
pixel manipulation because as I said
before we had three the a scholar is
combined from three different different
channels so we can just manipulate the
the number of values of the of the
pixels and we will construct the image
and it will finally looks like that it
works
okay uh so I know that it was fun right
but it is JavaScript conference so let's
make some live coding maybe and I know
that live coding never works but I will
try so basically hmm I have two images
from my last trip to Mars and and they
were making in the same time from that
funny thing you can see in here because
it has two lens on that like to two
separate photo cameras so it is the same
the same view but from a little bit
different a different angle so yeah I
preferred single document with my own
awesome implementation of jQuery in here
okay and and it is in here so basically
whoa is really okay maybe like that uh
so we have something we called canvas
yeah you heard of them okay and we don't
want to the images to be displayed on
the page so oh no it will be easier at
that
yeah it works nothing is displayed in
here so now let's use our awesome jquery
to take the left image and yeah and
canvas
and let's draw yet we need the context
as well
so let's draw the image like the left
image oh yeah first of all
yeah I know it's ugly but it works right
yeah and we throw it in the same point
and the origin yeah and it works so now
hey come on thank you you can fit about
it and now we have also something like
image data so we can take the image data
from our canvas from whole canvas right
so
and then from the image day in data we
can take the data of each pixel so I
hope it was something like that and yeah
for now yeah okay no one I hope no one
will notice that yeah sure and now we
have an array with the pixels and yeah
and it done should be like that for sure
okay so the first element of the ra is
the red channel the second one is the
green channel then the third one is blue
the fourth one for ya then the next
after the third one is alpha channel and
so on so we want we are not interested
in here in the green or blue channel so
we just want to clear the red color from
from the image ok and after that we want
to put that data that they turn into our
canvas yeah so that is the image without
the red color awesome and now yeah no
one will notice it again
we will yeah we don't need one that one
I don't okay so now we create an array
it's like really big array because each
pixel is represented by four values in
here and we will remember or dead pixels
okay because we needed and we needed
after after that so we had our yeah good
cat I was testing you and now we will
draw another image like the right one
yeah I love jquery it's so easy to use
and just 70 k of code okay uh what's now
sure so we now draw another image the
red the right one okay yeah just just
testing if yeah sure and blah blah yeah
we made place it basically the same
thing in here after after drawing
another image but after that we will
leave the red pixel I don't yeah we
don't need to go
and we will clear that
okay and let's try if it will yeah it
works so now we have two images and we
have to combine them and we have to use
that magic formula from here so the
result coral color is like some thing of
two other colors yes so basically we had
the red pix link you sure and now but
the top color is our well notes like
that sure the top color is in here yeah
and the bottom color is that one
and it works like that for all the
channels
uh yeah I hope it will work and yeah
what I don't heard what do you work yeah
that's good cash in here yeah as I as I
said life coding is never yeah but still
yeah sure okay who cares
well it works
okay so let's back to the slides slides
and that Batman is also anaglyph i made
like i spend like three hours to find
them okay so yeah so basically what we
what we've done now we just clear
completely the red color from one chant
from the 1i view and the green and blue
from another one but not that's not the
only way to produce anaglyphs because we
have other types of anaglyph like
through anaglyph and it that's the
formula in here in which yeah you can
product that that was yeah I don't
really know what what this one was used
for but for example that gray anaglyphs
was used by NASA and to producing
three-dimensional images from that
photos I've I've already show you uh out
but yeah we don't have colors in here
also that is that is an agree if we use
the just with the simple values and that
is the optimized one and probably that
it has the best the best results and i
will show you one one demo after i don't
know 30 seconds so what's more we have
like anaglyphs in our browser so someone
creates a jquery plugin yeah it's not
the plug in its most likely more like a
snippet but
yeah and it looks like three-dimensional
tags but it's really hard to read it
from but but but it works like and they
were thing yeah so I showed you just
during just a couple of seconds ago the
optimized anaglyph and it's used in
WebGL animations so the guy mr. do I
think everyone heard of femur or his
jobs never had all his other projects
and stuff like that so she creates a and
I live demo of renderer for WebGL so
it's completely a calculated on the
shaders so you just make your own WebGL
application as yeah as you drink before
and just put one additional five for the
renderer and it it creates additional
camera and calculate the colors on the
on the on the shaders and yeah pretty
nice isn't it
okay i know that anyone is tired so that
will basically be the end but no I have
one more faintest to present because as
I said before I really like an IRA
enjoyed creating very stupid things in
the way in the web so couple of a couple
of months ago on mozilla the most part
in Helsinki I created CSS nyan cat and
and now it has and now it has a negative
background
okay and that's basically everything I
know
questions for Michael thank you oh no
really yeah I think you had a question
wait a moment because sorry I'm a
complete noob with 2d graphics oh how
much of that can be optimized by the GPU
is it perfectly optimized is it but you
said about that WebGL renderer or know
the composition on canvas the
compositional canvas I think it you know
it's just a pixel manipulation so it's a
way faster than just drawing images and
for example I don't know if you heard of
impact engine by dominic's of let's keep
it creates one of the best html5 game
engines ever and he don't that he never
used draw image function of the canvas
you just you know manipulate each pixel
for rendering des price so i think it's
it's it's quite a good optimized yeah
sorry my english 34 now I'm retired yeah