I'm Matthew I work at Yammer a web
developer I've been working a lot of
different areas of the web stack I guess
for kind of a long time and my home has
always been JavaScript so it's really
exciting to be able to use finally
actually be able to use real JavaScript
on the server and do full stack
development we use a lot of JavaScript
at Yammer in a number of different
environments our desktop app is
JavaScript of course all the web
browsers for our web client we use
JavaScript in an embedded server-side
environment called the Ruby racer which
embeds a v8 process in in Ruby and of
course we've got a fairly new node
service that handles all of our file
uploads so I'm going to try to talk a
little bit about that it's a pretty
short time so I'm going to try to keep
it very high level and just kind of
power through it so the first lesson
this is all stuff that I wish I had
known sort of going into the process
sort of lessons learned and the first
sort of most important thing is is
organizing your code and thinking a
little bit beforehand as you're building
and part of this is sort of the good
problem that we have in JavaScript and
even more specifically with node that
it's really really easy to build
something that's immediately useful it's
very easy to step out a prototype that
does most of what you want almost kind
of too easy because as the
specifications grow and change ppl makes
what seemed to be very small changes to
the code to the specification what
you're what you're actually supposed to
be doing and ends up having a big impact
on the rest of the code base so it
rapidly can devolve into the old school
sort of PHP hairball code especially
because of be asynchronous the callbacks
some of us who've been using javascript
for a very very long
time on the front end are probably
pretty comfortable maybe a little too
comfortable with the the inside out
programming of using callbacks and
events but trying to keep things a
little more clear because it becomes
really really important if you want to
be able to modify your code and make bug
fixes the other small problem is how to
manage third party dependencies in your
code base where to put them how to
organize the code right so with that
said the other fairly significant
problem is dependencies the node
ecosystem is still really really new so
so finding the appropriate library to
use making sure that it does all of what
you want or most of what you want on how
to deal with that twenty percent that
doesn't do that isn't what you want
becomes a bit of a problem so when so
the service that we're running is
something that I started building it's
based on it on some code that I started
writing very very early and NPM was very
very much not there at the time it's
it's the way in p.m. works now is
probably what we would have wanted
installing the dependencies locally
makes a application deployment a lot
easier but at the time npm using NPM
really was an option for us it wasn't
something we could explain to our ops
people that we needed and ask them to
use it the third-party modules that we
needed to use we're also not quite there
and some of that is bugginess because
they're very very new and some of that
is because we're all very very focused
here i think as javascript people on
getting our jobs done and building cool
stuff so everyone is building these
modules with the intent of using it for
whether there's whatever their specific
purpose is so adapting that to something
more general purpose or to your to your
needs becomes a little bit more
difficult so what we're doing right now
we just kind of sidestep the whole thing
we have slurped all of the dependencies
into our code base we're making the
modifications in place
pushing patches back upstream this is
obviously not optimal we don't like copy
paste modify in our own code base and so
doing that with libraries is probably
not the right decision either that's
something that we we hope we can fix and
now that NPM installs the modules
locally it's a lot nicer story
deployment becomes a lot easier you're
not relying on this global like thing
out in the out in the the language
somewhere the language library somewhere
right so this is probably them yes so
sorry if you're offended by strong
language but this is a really important
lesson and it applies not just
operationally deploying all of the
things like this talk bar being spilled
and things not working just assuming
that things are going to go wrong is in
general a good idea but it also applies
more specifically to the asynchronous
programming model right so you do a call
back the interpreter goes along on a tap
anyway and in theory something is good
is going to happen and you'll be back in
the area of code that you care about
sometimes things obviously go wrong and
figuring out how to handle this in this
asynchronous process that's juggling all
of these different requests at once can
get kind of complicated and hairy so
this is a pretty common pattern I think
on the UI side and it seems to work
pretty well on the server as well where
you assume air condition you basically
throw an error or call function that is
an error handler wrap it in a set time
out that you will later on cancel if
things turn out ok so just assume it's
going to be bad and if it comes back and
everything's fine if your unit of work
successfully completes you cancel the
air that's pretty common pattern on the
UI side that doesn't scale well when the
app becomes more more complicated so we
ended up with something like an
in-flight registry where each step in
the process is given an ID we basically
have big object literal with named keys
in it for all the various steps being
processed by all the different
associated with all the different
requests a unit of work goes
off and a lot of times of course it's
something related to I oh it's something
asynchronous with a call back we make an
entry with the basically it's a time
stamp saying when this is when it when
this should be done and we have a
process watcher that looks that pokes
through this list every couple of
seconds to see basically what's overdue
and if something's overdue then we
perform whatever the default error
handling condition is error handling
code is so that in combination with the
uncaught exception means your process
generally stays up and running it's
really really important to log all of
the errors in detail so that you know
exactly why these unexpected things are
happening but even when they're with
this approach even if they're unexpected
errors the request or your control flow
knows that this thing is should be in
flight and should be coming back at some
point and if something goes badly wrong
eventually your process your in-flight
watcher is going to notice and tell that
request you know ship some meaningful
requests back to the browser telling
what to do so that leads right into the
next bit which is visibility into your
app because the code what's that okay
thanks because the code base is pretty
complicated our node app is doing a lot
of different stuff at once streaming
stuff to the file system shipping stuff
off to Amazon thumbnailing it's doing
all of this stuff at once so knowing
when there's some sort of a problem
which piece of the process went wrong is
really really important so measure
everything and build it in from the very
very beginning it's way easier to start
with something small that has a bunch of
metrics built into it then go in and
retrofit your complicated code base with
all the appropriate metrics measure of
hitting log the out of everything
so that you know what's happening and
I'd also like to point out here we're
now using this metrics library which is
a node.js port of coda Hales Scala
metrics library that Mike I be here
wrote so definitely check that out see
what you think
give us give us patches please this is
the last bit and I would actually say
that this might be the most important
piece of all and that's because note is
still very very new and so things still
kind of go wrong a lot and if you rope
in your ops people from the very
beginning and work with them there's a
lot more goodwill and they're a lot more
patient with your bleeding edge node
service if you talk to them first and
make sure that you're sort of being a
good citizen so at Yammer we've got a
bunch of other services written in Java
and Scala and knowing upfront sort of
what is expected of an HTTP service at
Yammer knowing knowing the things that
we should do so the deployment story
restarts metrics reporting all of these
things know knowing what we should be
doing is really really important so
talking to these guys up front and
knowing what's expected knowing what
would make their lives easier means that
there's a lot less bitterness and angst
when your service wakes them up at two
in the morning right they're the guys
who have to deal with that so yes I
think that said I'm MDE on twitter if
you are interested in this javascript
stuff that we're doing a Yammer I can
point you to the other devs at Yammer
who are dealing with whatever different
technologies we also have a developer
center that Michael Rogers has put
together he's been working for us for a
couple of months and really kicking ass
we're really really thrilled to have him
so check out the developer center I
guess that's really it unless there are
questions how big is our no deployment
um right now we have a very small
cluster it's three servers I do not have
statistics on the number of uploads
process per day or anything yet we're
measuring it I just don't know what it
is
that's an interesting question okay yeah
the question was how do we sell ops on
deploying something so new there are a
couple of different good reasons to
deploy this particular thing as a node
service some of it was the dynamics of
the different teams working on it at the
time this was sort of under the umbrella
of the platform team which was very very
javascript heavy I think the Ops guys
also recognize the value of node that
it's an important thing in technology so
getting some operational expertise in
that is I think they understand that
that's important also the fact that the
particular thing that we were doing
which is streaming file uploads its note
is very very well suited to performing
that kind of work and I think they also
recognize the importance of node in the
JavaScript world and so doing
interesting things you know with
javascript in real life and production
is something that you should do if
you're interested in plugging into the
Jazz community it's I mean it is
political but it's also bad ass so you
know anything else okay so he's asking
about storing the data for the in-flight
registry and something like CouchDB
that's not particularly useful for us
because this is processing file uploads
and we're we're tracking basically about
pretty short ephemeral steps so it's
like how long this file should take to
be shipped off to Amazon and once that
uploads done it's done so just keeping
that in memory is a lot a lot more
efficient what's that it's not something
that would be appropriate for what we're
doing but if it's something long-lived
yeah that's mean that would seem
reasonable or if you need to communicate
between nodes in the server excuse me
server nodes in a cluster that might be
a nice suit we're actually using Redis
cluster to communicate between nodes in
the server so if you're interested more
in exactly what we're doing definitely
talk to me because I think I'm about to
get the cane here right so thanks