welcome everybody my name is Bella Lima
I work for regalia as consultants for
notes pane and I'm very glad I was
invited to come here and talk to you
about the wonderful things that we're
doing gnome and related to JavaScript
yeah it's a bit about me I was here and
web developer a few years ago then I
became a genome developer but I kept
doing things related to JavaScript I'm
the weapon in the server side I have
involvement in other products as well
and that's disclaimer i must say that my
genome shall neither GW inspection GES
kohaku myself and just a messenger I
want to bring a message from the genome
community to all of you and try to
resend you the technology we have been
working on for the genome free with the
two purpose one of them is to
communicate the great knowledge that we
have been working non very hard in the
last few years and second try to erase a
rising interest in the wild JavaScript
community about genome and developing
applications using our wonderful stack
of libraries yeah let's start by asking
the question what is going on okay we
numb genome is a group of people it's a
game it truly community-driven break it
has 11 years array almost and yeah it's
also a full featured desktop environment
air I'm going to ask you how many of you
have tried you know or have said of
course it will be easy
yes you can see in this light that's the
genome two in the those and this genome
free maybe you can see a clear
difference ok genome is also collection
of libraries and programs you're not
supposed to result of that an open our
free software there's a bunch of
programs and libraries that has more
than 10 years of evolution and they have
been used in production for a lot of
time already yeah in Apple this year the
non-free was released it was the a very
important milestone for us there was a
lot of people working for a lot of time
on this and a the genome free include a
major breakthrough in several points for
example in this time we just revamped
everything we created a new user
experience we now use the new Howard
capabilities that we have in modern
computers and we really did a lot of
work clean up the stack here there was a
lot of the stuff was very it was very
full of things that we really didn't
need or we could really remove from the
stack make a genome simpler and yeah
also we use the genome shell and I said
we follow you you see experiencing you
know for this version beckenham shell
maybe some of you have seen it already
was just a I'm a full desktop experience
integrating compensating
okay loader or it's fine okay okay yeah
it's a an application launch in Sweet
Chin it allows multiple desktops and
much more in fact two years ago i was
attending gears conf and I had a very
early version of the genome shell
running in my laptop and it really
raised a lot of interest when I was
showing it to the people informally and
I realized that was there was a
miscommunication from the genome
community what we were doing and yeah
you read there that this javascript is
is powering the genome shell it's the
glue that we are using to access their
low level AC libraries of genome and
yeah that's you can see it's almost 30k
lines of JavaScript against also 40 k of
c yeah I realized that we need to
communicate genome in other forums also
because it's very attractive platform
right now for JavaScript developers
after the thing that acknowledges I'm
going to be presenting today so this is
most more or less the genome shell stack
we use OpenGL on the ball we have this
great technology platter and we have the
old metacity wrapped by matter we are
the shell Toki we have also CSS fourth
inning we have this introspection layer
that we're going to be explaining and we
have the JavaScript engine and on top of
this chrome shell maybe i can i can show
you very quickly you know i'm sure maybe
it's not needed raise your hand if you
haven't seen me know Michelle running
before only you
or maybe later I can show you so we're
going to be focusing on these two
technologies that really are the the
technologies that allow us to have
access to the core libraries using
javascript so let's start with the
introspection what is ganamos w
introspection well it's a set of tools
that we have to attract the metadata of
C libraries we attract the API
description in a latinum format of this
very easy to use in a runtime not in the
compile time so we we extracted API a
contract of the library and we put it in
a very well known location on the hard
drive for all forums to access it yeah
we need to realize that the ad it's not
as fully automatic because we need to
annotate the api's we're going to
explain what is it it's very simple
process and also we should design the
the sea ap is in a way that they are an
introspection friendly meaning that
there's no we're citrix on it that make
make it very alien for other languages
to bind so the goals of this technology
are basically to enable us to use the C
libraries in binding the languages like
JavaScript lower parel Python etc and
there's also other uses like API
verification
documentation and yeah this is the most
important thing I think the second one
which is share binding infrastructure
nowadays if you have a library and you
want to make it and respectable sorry if
you want to make it accessible in a
scriptable language you need to write a
binding and it starts the same for every
library that you right I'm going to use
you need to to create the bindings also
and it's a lot of work and this
dublicate the work because the bindings
that we use for accessing in c library
in python it's almost the same code that
you need for javascript or four
languages and what we're trying to
achieve with the other introspections to
concentrate that all that effort in just
one library and make the binding work
but very simple oops sorry about this i
will mention that this technology was
initially created by the start by a
startup called little that they wanted
to create a new user experience for the
vision of the device and they hired a
some of the very good genome hackers
from the genome community and they start
creating this ontology and NASA wrestled
and this ontology was contributed back
to to genome and we were able to use
them for this new experience okay this
this is kind of big I'll try to
wait
nah doesn't matter okay sorry about that
well this is basically a big picture of
what's going on here the only bit
missing is it is the label that says run
time in the other side so this is
compile time this runtime this is our
library and during build time we have a
normal compilation through GCC um we
also have this process which is is this
script called dr scanner creates a kia
and an xml file is the xml
representation of the library api and
then we have a process of compiling this
xml to a binary file and then at the end
we have this to this to input a type
like type Lib file its binary file and
the shirt up to the normal share of the
of the library and during the run time
we have the repository which is the
we're gonna see after but it's a library
that allows us during runtime to access
the symbols I'm the API description and
we also have this library called la lip
ffi which stands for a foreign function
interface is something very low level
that we really don't want to be
discussing much but it's the one that
allows us to access a shared object
library during runtime without knowing
the headers basically so we have we can
know having some information about the
API having the metadata we can actually
use the library with without having
compiler programs with the symbols of
the library and das is the JavaScript
engine that we created is a rapper to
the spider marking a spider spider
monkey engine and it provides the access
to the G repository so das is the one
that combines the metadata that we
obtain from there
introspection process and the shared
object oriented doing during compilation
will allows us to use to make the
automatic reflection the runtime which
is our purpose and spider monkey was the
muscle engine wheel known so this is the
same thing but for four seed and an ad
javascriptcore engine is subtly the same
but I I'm sorry about the the Proteas
problem so what I wanted to point out
with this child was that only changing
the the engine and the wrapper we got
the same thing so the the work that we
need to do to to use this technology is
very limited to what specific JavaScript
engine we work we plan to use and yeah
this is what I explained before the deer
files maximal description of the library
this is an example maybe I can scroll a
bit here it's just an XML file with
description of all symbols Daire
functions arguments classes etc the
caves in the case of classes I'm talking
about the object which is the the object
system of dilip the library that where
genome the genome uses to power oriented
programming in genome so entirely it is
just a binary representation of the
digital file for faster access we don't
really want in at runtime to be parsing
XML we have a very optimizer
presentation of it and we use it during
runtime and this is the only purpose of
the tight-lipped file so the deer files
in the tablet file's health store are
stored in a very well to find locations
so that the geas engine could find them
at one time I'm loaded
when they are needed the G repository
was in its an API for driven library
information from the tight lip during
run time with DES struck the symbols and
use those symbols to access this thing
which it's so so low level that we
really don't want to deal with it is
like science fiction right now 44 in
this context but basically allows us
allows geas to access the introspection
information from one side and be able to
use to actually access the library
runtime using this library which is very
old libraries part of Linux from a long
time so annotations they go in line the
code normally in the form of in the zip
files they complement the API with
information that otherwise wouldn't be
possible to ask to obtain only with the
same text so its semantic information
that's not evident in the source code
and only the programmer of the library
have access for example in the case of
when you have you created a blog you
will allocate the block of memory and
you wanted you want to use it and then
for it but sometimes is the
responsibility of the user of the
library to flip and sometimes is the
library itself but the in the source
code is no no information about this
explicitly and only the programmer of
the library can know about that so this
is one of the cases where do you have to
annotate the code for example this is an
annotation it's just a blog of a comment
block on top of the symbol in this cases
of where I know taking a function I'm
the annotation part is a smart between
parenthesis for example in the case of
file name data they alone on means that
you can personal with you if you don't
put a long long you cannot bus know when
you are in the skin the scriptable
language and also we have something
interesting here oh sorry in the case of
data we annotate there that is not an
array and we specify what other argument
is this the size of this array so this
information could not be obtained
obtained just from analyzing the syntax
of the library so we need to annotate
that to allow the bindable language to
make the magic and to make everything
work as the library designer respect
yeah this is another example in this
case validating the return value this is
a jealous which is a linked list in July
and but it doesn't store any information
or the type is just a pointer containing
this duelist so we need to annotate that
that's what the element type annotation
is for and in this case we annotate we
say that the element type this do list
is a clutter actor it's just a another
symbol of maybe another library which is
not the case but it could be yeah so up
to here we discuss about the early
introspection is is kind of the
foundation to be able to allow
scriptable languages to access the power
of the library the sea libraries that we
have behind and now we're going to talk
about the engines um how they combine
with this GI Joe introspection thing we
have two engines currently in the genome
in economic technologies and ones das
and the other one is C das is rubbing
the Mesilla spider monkey as we saw
before while see this is a JavaScript
core
a spider monkey support some of the
harmonious things this is actually a
problem right now because a lot of code
the Phenom shell code is written using
lab and const and taking advanced
advantage of the features that are
available in the spider monkey engine
already but it but the the seed product
dozen the JavaScript core engine still
doesn't support those so we have right
now have a program compatibility we
cannot run genome shell code in seed
only in GIS and yeah yes small matter
right now powered gnome shell at the
moments in production on millions of the
desktops right now and they have some
other minor differences but both have a
fairly good support for di and we have
this thing that is very recent and very
cool that's a guy called Tim Castle
working in this node G R which is di
score for know and it's an early stage
of development and thus the his reason
for writing this instead of using the
others and I kind of agree with what he
says but I my advice to him would be
first asked to gain on developers go to
the community type I'll try to talk with
with us and try to yeah be advice about
how to do this well because we have a
lot of experience already doing bindings
for this engines and we also have some
ideas like implementing the of course
it's it's meant to be running node as
another extension and it will be the
node way of doing things and we have
some kind of a bit different vision of
for some of the api's that are not
really much exactly and
my advice to this guy I haven't talked
to him already i discovered this bright
very recently not included here but I i
would say go and talk to the genome
community and while you write this and
we are glad that you're writing this
actually so how is writing JavaScript in
a Fergie gnome and i'm going to show you
the demos first to try to getting you
excited about it and then i will show
you how could you start doing so let me
see i was planning to to code the demo
on the fly but maybe oops was that I did
something it's not supposed to be there
wait
okay and yeah we can try to run a to
code a demo in the fly maybe I can
oops
okay have Emmett's here so I have to go
there and we're gonna first import
everything we need for example is do a
very basic gtk application with a button
and with a greeting message so let's
import gtk we're gonna splain everthing
after the demo so right now maybe you
wonder about that some syntax is dead
just don't worry yeah we're gonna we
have gtk we're going to instantiate the
window gtk the window say near window
gtk window type top level so we have the
window this is a constructor judika
window is a constructor and we are
interested in it we have a property name
type is a property of the gtk window and
we pass all the properties in the
constructor using an object and then we
we say show all show all and then we
need a main loop because jalebis is
based on main loop and thus wrapper in
dt coverage salad delete main loop so we
can just do this ok let's save it and
try to run it let's get the console here
or the console small I hope you can see
maybe I can
ah
oops oh sorry I make half
oh yeah sorry this should be uppercase
oh yeah we did with this you need to
initialize everything this is part gtk
thing so we have a duty carry window
running but this is not all we close the
window as you can see the problem keeps
running that's not nice so we're going
to connect the destroy signal of this
window to kill the event loop we're
going to do this way win that connect
destroy we're going to be putting a
function here
ok
and we can say gtk main width knife so
now we run it oops why here come here
now when we close the window we close
also the problem and now let's add some
button here button to decade button
button we need new because it's a
constructor and we can pass label to it
a low GS com Oh some kind of
yeah I think it's right
ok
think it's fine huh and we're going to
have the work the bottom to the window
yeah let's try it ok now the window is
very small because the button is small
let's make it big we have a gtk button
here which does nothing now if we
connect the BTN the signal clicking we
can get
we can print some message to the user
like hello back sample and okay that's
very simple so it's very stupid demo to
show the most basic things that we can
do and i'm going to show you another
demo which is more complex i'm gonna i
have it already written i'm gonna just
run it for you and hope you like it it's
here is GIS demo one thing yeah this is
a webcam this is running this trimmer
and clutter and is Howard accelerated of
course because it's cluttered and this
using just trimmer for capturing it
looks kind of crappy because I just put
a count source and I mean sink and the
texture but I didn't put the other
elements of the pipeline that for
example color space we need to get this
rival I just wanted to show some cool
things
but the thing is that we're gonna check
the code and we're going to see it's 40
lines of code on in JavaScript yes but
it's demo one yeah so it's kind of the
same we have just trimmer which is this
line clutter we have clutter gstreamer
and we have a main loop we call this
teeny tune in solitude streamer we
initialize clutter we created black
color for the for the background we
create a stage the size this is normally
construction we set the color of the
stage we connected to destroy signal of
the stage to close the program we get a
clutter texture we add it to the stage
and we set the size of the texture here
then we get it just through your
pipeline we create a plug-in for the
come the webcam capturing we added to
the pipeline we create a sink element
yeah we create a video sink element and
this where the clutter just swimming
thing goes mixed and we added to the
pipeline and then we will we link the
source which they come webcam source
with the sink which is a cluttered
texture so at this point we created the
pulp the the pipeline we linked it and
this is for the rotation effect because
the birth dates and we specify the
center of the rotation all those are
properties of the normal G objects that
we have we normally use this in C by
here as you can see the the simplex is
very similar and now we do we have a
main loop loop with a time out of 25
seconds and we just modify the angle the
x angle on the cells angle i'm at the
end we just show all the elements of the
stage we set the pipeline to playing and
we run the mile loop is always 52 sorry
so that's it we we can do a fancy just
trim a lot everything only with forty
fifty two lines of JavaScript code and
that's so much more behind to be used
this is only one example two very
popular libraries that we have any venom
start but there are a lot of a lot more
cool things so let's continue
yeah this is this is a special let's say
I am a native JavaScript module that is
built inside jes which is a rapper to
the main loop for convenience a use here
we create a main loop a jelly menu using
a minus ID so we can have several main
loops running and we can refer to them
using this ID so it's something that is
very specific very specific das they
implemented that way for convenience
basically but we could have used normal
jelly main loop here and it would work
the same okay I think we could continue
with this ah maybe I can I have time for
owner cool demo which involves the wet
also and I think it's also kind of cool
wait we have to go
yes let me check something of it
ok GI yes
we're going to round the demo ok now
we're going to open a browser you really
have fun another crumbing instance okay
Nina it's local host
ok we get this image oops
this is a demo of technology is a see
library that isn't respected and do kind
of mix of no GS and socket i/o so we are
going to show all sir let's open our
browser let's say epiphany which is the
oops epiphany doesn't want to run here
in a while let's open eyes whistle which
is five Fox in debian and let's do this
bring it here somewhere wait like this
we also worked in over actually so let's
put opera in the game yeah price here
wait let's bring it here I don't have
room for it but maybe oh wait
oh yeah sorry about that okay so now we
have
this is using web socket fall back to
lump bowling it's full 100% JavaScript
server zion browser side of course it's
kind of the cool things we can do now
that we have a lot of libraries to
access a lot of hardcore things in the
server side to use out of the box yes by
using this analogy okay enough with the
demos I hope you enjoy them let's see
what is this about okay so important
modules is a bit different of what the
comment es a probe has already spread
around all the JavaScript developers
does not require thing the imports
operation is an assignment not a
function called this is actually not
nice because you you can you cannot do a
lot of things that you can do with a
function call like for example
implemented a synchronous loading using
the funk they require function as an
object for all things and we have an
important I think is very limited we
also is them the most serious problem we
have the full modules global scope is
important so you know if you use common
yes or no yes you have the experts
object and you add API to it and that's
the only object gets exported well here
everything goes sported if you have
private symbols there will be a spotted
as well so the DS variable inside the
your module will be exported completely
and i think that's that's a problem and
we need to to improve that that's also
search path similar to require path and
this only synchronous of course is an
assignment this is an example of
importing a normal JavaScript module you
specify the path the module using dots
set of slashes these three examples here
we use const which only works in GIS and
this is the nice way to do it because
module importation should be multiple
and we can get that with cost this is
important a GI module which is a
introspect library that we have in the
repository the J repository and we use
the GI a member of imports which we can
say is a keyword very spot of it's a
multiple and with using GI we have
implicit access to the depository using
the main space when you compile your
library with introspection super you
have to specify a name space for your
library and in this case jalebi is jelly
like this GDK is gtk like that and it's
up to the library developer to create
the name space to be used for the g
repository yeah do you want it to us
yeah it's a weird constrict but it works
like way in the newer versions of yes I
think this you can you can put a equal
equal you can assign two inputs the
identical you are signed a three dot 0
but it does not work in this version the
job of dsm aha that i have running yeah
but it's that's not that works that way
yeah
yeah you for meeting I think it was a it
is already precarious if way of doing it
either another one of the decisions that
the left da but this is the new way of
doing it but I I cannot tell you right
now why it was like that I can try to
find it and tell you after it's like I
think it would be like a symbol of
everything yeah so there is also the
native modules that I was talking before
like a main lib you have the bus rapper
to make it more convenient to use on
JavaScript and the GSA the jes you have
a land some language utilities and the
signals module sir yeah this will be
important native yes-mo they are all
accessible from the reading part so
using the GI api's how to map the
symbols that we have and we know in this
elaborate very well-documented to the
new bindable language we have a set of
what define rules and they are not
actually in hundred percent of the cases
well defined but there's a with practice
and while the documentation for binding
line which is not in place we can kind
of learn how to map the symbols to the
system symbols to javascript this case
and you know it will always work for
most of the cases using the some simple
rules for example functions
functions if you have a normal function
you will use the namespace stop the name
of the function like this for example
detail time out art becomes jelly time
up odd is kind of normal you only need
to identify what is the main space of
that library in this case is G is the AC
namespace of jelly and you replace that
with a with a namespace in the jury
posture which is Galip and you have a
little time out it's kind of a trick a
rule to guess it yeah in the case of the
object methods they they are used like
this you have to map the namespace the
class and then the method so let's say
we have dedicated button new with love
it becomes utk that button using a camel
and then you will level so it's kind of
a very simple rule and in the case of
idioms a it's kind of simple also you
use the namespace then the middle part
symbol and then they the last part in
uppercase
the properties of objects are in in C
and G object in this case we can use
dash for for the properties because they
are strings and we we need to replace
them for underscore to be able to use
them as normal object members in
JavaScript the signals as we saw in the
demo use the Kinect thing and in cities
different they have this signal object
with members where the signal names are
the members of that onion and they often
have a connect a method you pass the
Kaaba and that's in a knife I forgot
about the about I forgot about
constructor but we saw in them we for
constructing lady object which is new
the namespace the clap a class name in
camel case and then you pass a object as
the only argument and object will of the
properties that you want to define and
when to pass the constructor okay so
what about documentation right now
documentation it's for actually for the
binding languages there's no official
documentation we have an official
documentation there and it's kind of
nice but let's remember that also we
could have some Lots in the actual c
library documentation so it's like a
complete thing to do on this very reason
we have been very busy built with
bringing this analogy up today that of
course we are lacking a bit for the
developer story for binding bindable
languages so we need to work on that and
in fact this is a hot topic right now
last month in the desktop summit we have
a DI hackfest and it was the focus of
the harvest was basically documentation
for binding likely to bite and
javascript so the we're really concerned
about this and we want to fix it as soon
as poss
people development tools we don't have
them yet it's too early for us we don't
know what we have lot of discussions
inside the comedian a still whether
we're going to use Python jsk DSC we are
not sure about the developer story yet
we haven't figured out all the details
but I think there's a lot of interesting
having very good development tools and
we want this to succeed and attract
developers attention we'll need to fix
this also okay this is very important
how to synchronize our community with
the rest of the world basically this is
a very delicate issue because there are
some people in favorite there's other
people that are not very interested try
to gather some opinions from the core
developers of distant ologies and well
the basic idea of the basic message will
be that it makes sense it could make
sense for some of the common GS larissa
maybe not for all of them because for
example we have the g i/o library which
is part of g lib and is the the library
we use for input/output and we have
specific ways to do asynchronous
operations we have specific ways of
doing things that integrates well with
the rest of the genome libraries and we
don't want to mix develop a mix code
from comment es api for example for the
HTTP maybe I don't know we really want
to use the g io way because the Python
developers will use that and the Lua
developers the volatile verb
we'll also use that and we really want
to make make a consistent message to the
developers of how the api's should be
used in bindable languages so for some
api's it could make sense synchronize
with them for example I really want to
push for the modules because it's basic
thing and I think we could improve a lot
situation if we have some module
important using modules one on one at
least that's a lot of we need to discuss
a lot and try to reach the communities
and discuss what makes sense what make
not sense and that's the null-gee
private which will in a way bridge the
two API because we are going to be using
live genome libraries in in no context
and this guy is really in I was reading
the heroes about what style to use and
he really wants to implement what makes
sense for in the comic GS context so he
wants to add up even the same text to to
comment yes to the what is familiar to
know at least and this GES comment yes
very new project I just created as an
experiment it's a rubber to G is to
provide community s IV is my purpose
with this is not to to create another
rapper on top of das to have comedy yes
but trying to convince people and try to
move at least create some debate maybe
if the experiment success meaning that
some people do use this rapper instead
of the actor das maybe we can convince
people that to merge this API or baby s
that make sense inside des
so it's not a way to go long-term
foreign experience and this will vary
new I i started writing it like a month
ago and it does modules with one that
one and promises the conditionally
compliant at the moment is there and you
can check it out it's kind of very
superb real thing but anyway so what
current issues we have we have a lot of
challenges like for example the
documentation thing I was talking about
and we still don't have complete support
in all the genome libraries may be in
the coral divers yes but we have a lot
of other libraries that still need to be
inspected authoring and we need to
complete the Super NES official
documentation solve the differences
between GES and seed and try to align
with those some final thoughts we have a
very nice tag it's a very nice
combination of low-level and high-level
we are basing our code in the platform
that has a lot of years of evolution I
will give us robustness and confident
confidence and it's very convenient for
fast prototyping I think I use it a lot
it's something quick and asked me to try
some some magic native code API and of
course it brings jansky to the desktop
this is analysis awesome stack we have
the libraries the genome libraries this
is only the core phenom libraries and
genome 3 stop we have introspection and
we could have a lot of engines and then
our problems running on top and i think
is very awesome i'm very interesting a
platform to develop upon and that's it
sorry for taking more time