do you remember the time when you fell
in love well see ya do you remember the
first feature you were so excited about
well like Marquette which was very
popular some time ago and if you don't
remember it on websites probably you're
very young and do you remember the web
design trends despite you back in the
days
yeah so it's it's very tough to get back
to those feelings and those days and if
you're a long-term marriage with
front-end development is in crisis and
if your love for CSS has burned out it's
time to do something about it and we're
the awesomes I'm Agra India as a short
intro I'm a designer and coder and doing
a front-end developer and we will find
that the awesomes which is an
organization which teaches people how to
create awesome things on the web and
also we do it all not-for-profit and as
a side project after work
yeah just like Kevin said we were based
in in Poland and Warsaw and if you have
any comments or questions we'd be more
than happy to read all of them for
instance in our Twitter you can see our
Twitter handle so we have to make a
small disclaimer right now you might be
disappointed but there will be no code
and no life coding sessions
unfortunately yeah we won't get into any
technical details we won't show you any
brand-new CSS framework or coding
techniques and no fleshie CSS effects
but rather than that we will tell you
true stories about people that we have
met during the last two years so there
is the time in your career when you
realize that coding is cool but you need
two more interact with people a
different ground than your daily job so
this is what happened for us some time
ago and we were lucky because it's
happened at the same
so we can see right now is our chat on
Twitter and we are trying to set arrange
a meeting and do something together for
the community so this was the idea let's
do something and as you said it all
started two years ago in December 2015
yes and the idea was rather humble we
didn't have any fixed plan and
everything went very spontaneously so we
were really overwhelmed with what
happened that this one meeting tour
meeting actually initiated something
very big and it engaged more than 3,000
applicants and 64 awesome participants
who were learning the basic of HTML and
CSS and among them were people from
various professions like philosophers
architects designers photographers etc
etc yes it's good to mention that seven
people and out of them actually became
junior front-end developers and it's
worth adding that we weren't aiming at
like encouraging people to change their
profession what we wanted to do is to
show that coding can be cool no matter
what you do daily it can be a very
useful tool
so we extremely proud of them and also
it included 80 hours of coding 11
mentors who held this and numerous hours
of preparations preparing materials
searching for the venue and planning all
the smallest details and you might be
wondering right now why are we talking
about it while you showing these numbers
because you're on a CSS conference you
would like to see some code but probably
we bad that probably some of you have
ever thought that it would be good to do
something for the community do a slight
project do something what you love that
you can't do at work because you're
doing other things so we hope that
you'll feel inspired and if you already
run your community or around type of
site project or team activity we'll have
some useful tips and tricks and
practicalities which you can apply to
make your community even bigger so it
all started and at the very beginning we
did
and he fixed plaid we just felt that
there is the lack of such initiatives
connected with HTML and CSS in our
neighborhoods
so we decided to do something about it
and it starts yes and we were observing
different initiatives connected with
front-end development coding Ruby on
Rails and we saw that they organized
very long workshops during weekends and
we decided to do something different we
decided to divide our whole course into
smaller and regular meetings so we were
meeting in the afternoon after I will
regular job and we care about good
design so we prepared our own layouts
for our participants and the three
examples are we used on a workshops and
our participants were voting which one
they prefer to call by themselves so
yeah it helps to engage people if you
give them that's it the decision to make
as you probably know that to Harless
things in the web development is cache
invalidation and naming things so we
also have our problem to come up with
some some catchy name for our
initiatives and as you can see most of
them are rather cheesy yeah my firm is
one is fantastic but yeah in the end we
decided to pick worth awesome because
it's awesome and it's connected with
World Wide Web because it has w3 W's and
because we want we wanted to feel like a
big awesome family we finally picked the
awesomes and our tagline is awesome
people just like us who do awesome
things on the web and also there are
lots of communities that encourages
women and join the detect community and
we decided that
rather be open for everyone for people
from different walks of life different
experiences different professions yes
and we really wanted to bring new people
into our industry so we really wanted to
encourage beginners and what is a one of
our goal was to break the nerd
stereotype we really wanted to show that
we were like cheerful people and of
course we love spending time in front
come in front of computer screen but
this is not the only hobby we have it
all started and we set up our own
webpage and also wanted to look
professional so it's required to have on
Facebook fan page and we created an
event and was waiting if anyone would be
interested in learning coding and HTML
and CSS basics but rather we been
overwhelmed about how many applications
we received and we imagine there were
more than 1000 and 800 of them yes it
was a really big number and we had to
read all of them and we had to select 20
final participants it was extremely
tough because people were very
hard-working ambitious talented but that
decision was made and it consisted of
eight classes divided
two hours yeah this is our program yeah
we try to divide our program into like
edible chunks not to make our
participants feel overwhelmed by the
program so we started with the very
beginnings as you can see and started to
getting more advanced things and people
really love building layouts and first
we taught them how to use floats and
later showed how the grid works to show
that the total different approach and we
also engage friends from our industry as
mentors and they were really grateful
for them and they really helped us with
mentoring and tracking progress of our
participants and even if you're an
expert in the industry you can see that
teaching others is a really tough nut to
crack and we have some lesson learned
for example we unintentionally started
to use technical jargon and for example
for people from outsider tech bubbles
slack is just a mysterious words yes and
many people were asking so how they
should actually approach learning HTML
CSS shouldn't be approached just like
foreign languages or maybe should they
learn all HTML tags by heart
so at the time we realize it's so easy
to forget about your own beginnings when
you were struggling with your first line
of code so we're more aware what types
of words we should use what our teaching
methods we should introduce to our
course to make the pruning process much
more easier in these it doesn't matter
how much time do you spend polishing
your slides and giving the lecture the
most important part of the teaching
process is the hands-on experience and
what you can see is the layout coded
totally from scratch by by one of our
participants from the first edition Anya
and we believe that this experience cell
learning from practical examples is more
important than some example taken
completely out of context
and sorry w3schools yes we also paid a
little attention that people could
practice at home so we prepared a
tutorial which is available for free for
everyone unfortunately it's in Polish so
if you'd like to contribute right now
feel free to to come to us we'd be more
than happy to have something someone who
can help us to translate it to English
there are some spooky creatures in CSS
and everyone is afraid of and for our
participants surprise surprise it
appeared to be positioning specificity
yes and specificity sometimes it's even
hard for us for seasoned developers so
there wasn't surprised that that
participants have some problems at the
very beginning to grasp the general
concept how it works and we believe that
asking questions is a crucial part of
the learning process so there are no
stupid questions and we wanted to our
participants to feel as comfortable as
it's possible and when we were seeing
that there are some of them is
struggling along with some hard code
problem we try to approach them we are
our mentors to help them and we also
tried to create a friendly family like
atmosphere so we divided them into
smaller sub groups yes and of course we
have a problem with naming them again we
needed five groups so the first idea was
oh maybe we could use the the Brett
web-browser names but who would like to
join the internet explorer group well
probably not so many people so we did it
we decided to change the concept and we
pick the pantent score names for for the
year it was 2016 and it gave the
artistic vibe to our workshops and
people were really that identifying
themselves with the colors so girls were
in rose quartz and they were very happy
there was David who can see in the
middle he was in
serenity group so it was a lot of fun
and there's some friendship started
among her participants so it was really
worth it to try to act like like big
family and there were some
collaborations between people from
different professions so it became
really interesting to see them all also
after the workshops I guess that even
some ideas for startups were initiated
so we're like a stirrup hop as well and
people love competition so this is why
we wanted to incorporate the l-man into
our work ships as well and after each of
the classes we prepare a quiz on the
Kahoot platform if you don't know it you
should check it out because it's awesome
and there were it's very beneficial
because of two reasons the first one is
that people were revising the moderator
material so they were getting more and
more experience and the second one is
just more engaging fun and we can you
can see right now on the video if you
can see this if not I'm so sorry but it
is the is our Meetup and we're so where
people were playing the the quiz and it
was so exciting as you can see and our
success was to bring more designers
throughout the end well our focus on
aesthetics really paid off and the code
appears to be really good so new tool
it's used for designers and help them
communicate more efficiently with
developers yes and designers started to
like us which was very nice feeling and
thanks to that we were reviving too many
events for designers mainly so this is
the workshops we gave during element
talks this is one of the biggest
conferences in Poland for designers
gathering more than 1500 designers we
were on different conference talking
about collaboration between developers
and designers we did another workshops
for artists and we're mentioning this
not to boast off but to give you the
sense that sometimes it's really good to
step out of your comfort zone and and
check other explore order filled other
areas other environments and it's
extremely inspiring
and it has definitely affected the way
we work and the way we communicate with
people and was also an important part
first was to because the devil is in the
details we also create our branding and
it was really attractive to people they
were hunting for our gadgets on our
events and our meetups
it was really cool and we managed to
produce for example yeah flashy pins and
they fake tattoos it was really a good
integration game when people were like
yeah some people have had attack on
their neck collar for speakers and we
have them with us so if you are not shy
please come after after a lunch break
yeah welcome
and also the also sucks and now so watch
out because we do have one pair of them
with yes and you can film happy owners
just like you know Kravitz so Martha
good luck you don't think to be excited
yeah yeah sorry you can you can give it
to your friend which is a girl out there
or unfortunately it's female sighs so
yeah we were running out of bigger
silence yeah and now we like to focus on
an important topic which became kind of
a buzzword in our industry and actually
we believe that actions have more effect
that works and in fact we haven't
mentioned the diversity words explicitly
not any ones we were promoting our
events people and what's interesting
about 75% of our community are women yes
and we of course observing what's
happening in the industry what's
happening on Twitter they're here
but if you're just open if you respect
other people if you're kind diverse
community should emerge itself so it
shouldn't be something that you push
yourself very hard it should be natural
in our opinion and it happened for us
I'm the coolest thing that happens when
we were running the auctions that apart
from jazzy workshops we create created
something bigger which is a community
and it was really awesome to see that
from an inconspicuous idea it turned out
something really huge yes that you need
to be aware that if you do something
publicly that your initiative will be
exposed for a critic and so friendly
comments so you have to deal with it
because otherwise your enthusiast might
be dumping and your it might cut your
wings so some comments were like a
broken record CSS is not the programming
flag now yeah it doesn't really matter
if this and some people were talking
about 16 hours for learning just such
easy things like HTML and CSS is
insanely long yeah but what is funny on
the opposite there were some people who
saw that well yeah like when you meet
like eight times for two hours is 16
hours it's insanely short to write a
good-quality website so there was some
opposite opinions and also the women in
tech sync appeared and some people saw
that our initiative is created mostly
for women because we are pink and
cheerful social media but in fact it
wasn't true because we were open for
everyone yes and you can imagine that
after all these comments after a whole
year when we were organizing workshops
meetups after I work as an additional
project we're extremely exhausting but
there is actually one thing that can
cheer you up and it's the greatest
reward for all your efforts and these
are sexist stories from our participants
yes mentioned some of them now we're
probably probably wearing a batch of
junior web developers some of them are
successful designers communicating with
developers some of them creating created
really awesome site projects and now you
can hear them speaking by themselves
this is the audio time praying right now
it doesn't work can we try again
No
yes boiler yeah we know Dennis who had
the audio problem as well
is there is there a chance or should we
skip it um once again sorry it works
before yeah it worked now you can see on
your face yeah she called it plenty
there the website she's a designer yeah
she actually graduates from architecture
yeah
okay let's try so she as a designer also
now codes are designed by herself
no it's it should be okay
oops sorry
yeah pictures yeah so should we try to
paraphrase what's happening in the video
or are still having the chance to make
this work
it worked before so maybe
okay let's try again oh why we're
editing till late night yesterday it's
worth to do it please
okay
okay okay so let's give it so we can
tell it no so girls were talking what
they love in CSS and what they hate and
for instance a DA she said that she
loves when you can create spectacular
things not knowing a lot about CSS but
and here's the moment yeah she's talking
about it
spectacular websites the CSS but oh no
this is not the moment whatever yeah
that the spectacular thing is gonna be
at least spectacular for you because the
web sites can be very ugly sometimes
especially when you started how to code
Alena hate naming things in CSS but
instead she thinks that it's a very
useful tool for communicating with
developers because she is a designer we
have Magda and she said that she loves
flexbox but at the same time she hates
that it doesn't work every word and yeah
Anya said that she she she's very
worried sometimes that CSS doesn't work
with her and she doesn't know why
so yeah and ferger's mostly coding it's
a really great new experience something
that opened their eyes and show a new a
new way in their profession so it was
very valuable for them to learn how to
code so yeah as you seen the failures
cut and also failures happen among our
participants it happened some unrequited
love towards CSS life is not as rosy as
it's painted not luxorious
our badges and fortune in socks yes so
some people abandoned coding and
abandoned every classes and it was a
very hard feeling for us because it we
took it very personal but you know you
need to somehow accept the fact and come
to terms with that some people are not
just so keen on coding just like we are
and maybe they didn't have time or just
didn't enjoy coding at all yeah so we
love meeting Queens
pants with people from our community not
in front of computers and not have just
in their chats about technology but also
yeah we have great fun during our
meetups it's it's so called reunions
when we invite people from former
editions of the workshops and our
friends and we just enjoy talking
together and to also love animals and
they are also invited to our workshops
and Freddy started learning flex books
with us but we don't know if he's
already grasped the idea I guess he
abandoned this in the favor for yes is
great because he saw that these are like
contradictory ideas yeah
yeah yes so we're here at CSS confer the
past and CSS con invents in general are
very open and lots of people come from
different parts of the world so we speak
different languages we different food
during our lunch time we have different
hobbies but there is one thing that we
have in common and this is the love for
CSS and we're like a big CSS family and
we're very grateful that we had an
opportunity to share our story with you
here on CSS going to that past so if you
have have ever feel burned out to work
or you feel that you need to do
something these do something different
than your daily job there's something as
a child project or maybe you want to
contribute to your local community and
if you have ever felt lonely in front of
your computer screen this is the height
time to do something about it and
contributes you can do it just like us
for example creating starting founding
the workshops in your local area
yeah or creating local meetups sitting
at the YouTube channel with tutorials or
gave a talk and you don't need to be an
expert just like I was here
today and please remember that time when
you fell in love with CSS and maybe
you'll feel the butterflies in your