okay so um this is about like it's about
relationships the relationships that you
have with your debugger and sometimes
those relationships change I know that a
you know two years ago I was amazingly
into Firebug and now I kind of seen
someone else a little bit but the thing
is that you really want to you know get
in touch you know with your partner and
like know all you know everything
everything you can know about your
partner is good well anyways we're going
to learn a little bit about chrome
devtools firstly about me I work for a
browser I'll give you two guesses I am
the lead developer on moderniser i'm on
the jquery team i create html5
boilerplate there's a bear we'll get
back to that okay right so I'm going to
open up the chrome devtools here on this
page can you guys see this in the back
no ok good let's take this and then
we'll just turn that one and go yeah
that's pretty good better yeah great
yeah so I thought it'd be a little bit
more fun to kind of have the the
devtools kind of be like my slide so I'm
making I'm having some fun here i have
the wait a second tag and the where are
the divs and the Omega tag but we'll go
down to uh we're going to do some
styling stuff first so I'm just going to
show like a bunch of features that the
chrome devtools has you might not know
about some of these are new and in
general the chrome dev channel has these
a lot sooner than everyone else and so
you're going to see features here
they're not available in the regular
chrome stable release yet but some of
them are so first in styling um a while
ago this was like um let me go over here
I wanted to set a background color and
I'd be like background and I hit tab and
you said they didn't we didn't have that
coal in there and so you actually had to
type the colon
really annoying so anyways that's all
better so now we can tab you know tab to
make the next one cool cool no big deal
but where this gets a little bit more
fun is that there's autocomplete right
which is good because sometimes we
forget how background is spelled or
sometimes you want to type the most
delicious color in the history of colors
which is papayawhip so good and on top
of that you might put another color like
one that's particularly difficult to
spell which is fuchsia fuchsia oh I
touch it right the first time terrible
demo fuchsia is like is a really tough
one but the trick is it's fucsia but the
other chick is that it's also magenta so
you could just bypass that entirely but
now that we're here on colors um this
little color swatch you're like oh cool
color swatch great I kind of knew what
color that was but magic you click it
and you iterate through the different
color notations yeah I'm going to go
over like hsl and I like bring down the
yeah bring down the saturation a little
bit you just tweak this a little bit and
then maybe go back to hex and then copy
that back in your style sheet because
that's how it's how you roll so you got
some fun there also let's say that you
want to do some crazy cool patterns and
I'm going to grab my favoritest one this
is a this is it's just CSS gradients
right here and this one is actually a
divyam anyen who I work with on each my
boiler plate and some other stuff
created this it's out of gradients it's
just mind-blowing so anyways I'm gonna
bring this over here I'm going to apply
it to the body yeah buddy whoo looks
pretty good now you'll notice if you've
done CSS gradients before or like
anything where there's a long value and
sometimes you'll be hacking it in the
dev tools and you'll you'll screw it up
and what used to happen is that it would
just disappear and you'd lose your work
and now there's this little arrow e
and he's like yo you mess this up you
should probably fix that so you get a
chance to to UM fix that which which is
good but the other thing that you'll see
is that you'll see like mods prefixed
stuff showing up in the dev tools now
and that might throw you for a loop but
it's actually okay yeah let me uh wow
that pattern is pretty nice i'm going to
move on past it so one of the way that
this gets really cool is so let's say
that I I'm going to add some styles here
to this this guy and I'm going to give
him outline 10 10 picks solid badass
yeah that's pretty good a little bit of
marg maybe okay cool so yeah I just
added it here in the devtools I'm seeing
it live cool this is what we like right
now I'm going to go over to resources
tab and oh this is new we now group the
resources under your like font style
sheet scripts and it's not one huge
lists group now well you'll notice that
there's also this little arrow next to
the style dot CSS and you like what cuz
i click it and it's actually keeping
revisions of all the changes that i'm
making over here it's keeping revisions
and i can like right click and revert
back to an earlier thing if i wanted to
but if it's keeping revisions then that
means that it must be keeping track of
my changes here so all my all my
manipulations over on this side are now
being carried through to the style sheet
with dipping so i can see exactly like
what I change what I removed and so you
know I can tweak whatever I want go over
here and and just right click save as
and save this file back to you know
where I'm at it gets
agreed it gets better so while it is
pretty cool that uh that you know we can
change things over here and go back here
and we have that would be nicer if we
could just kind of do it all operate in
the same place so now if you just double
click and now you can just freeform edit
all you like well that's pretty good
color let's go back to papayawhip yeah
hmm so double click freeform style sheet
editing make your manipulations they
happen completely on the fly slate blue
and you get the live preview and then
you get a chance to save it out just
pretty cool that's ugly Oh clear okay
let's go over the JavaScript side of
things um logging yes okay console.log i
do want to point out this is worthwhile
that well most people when you start
logging you're like oh because i can use
console.log instead of alert and you
forget that console.log takes multiple
arguments and you can send anything that
you want to it so you know take full
advantage of that but in addition to log
there are a lot of things on the console
that help you out so basically all the
debuggers dragonfly IE dev tools Firebug
than the chrome dev tools all support
pretty much most of the console api
which was you know came out of Firebug
basically so things like warren and air
or just basically console logs with
shiny icons but there are more
interesting ones and so here's a test
page made by joke hewitt who created
Firebug and this is just um these are
just calling like console dot time
council about time end just you know
records the amount of time something
took another one that I really like is
console that trace gives you the stack
trace of wherever you are
throws that out to the console so
there's a lot there's a lot on the
console object but then there's actually
cooler stuff there's the command line
API and so there's functions available
to you down in here so for instance like
console dot der is available as der
which is good because you'll have
something like ducking body and if you
do document.body you get like the tree
and you can expand the tree but
sometimes you want like the dom view
Sodor gives you that where you actually
like get it as a Dom object and you can
look into that but there's cooler thing
so let's say say so I have document.body
and actually i have this reference to to
this dom element but i want to inspect
it over in in my elements tab and
document body's pretty easy to find but
sometimes it gets a little bit harder so
you can actually just use the inspect
method and it just jumps you over to
there and throws you onto the body which
is pretty cool other times you'll have a
reference you'll be selecting you know
this guy I've just brought up the
console I hit escape escape brings up
the console on every single one of these
tabs and sometimes like a while ago I
remember I like had it there like go
away just drag it all the way escape pro
tip so I'm selecting this guy right here
I just do dollar zero and dollar zero
refers to whatever element is currently
selected up there and it's just like a
regular Dom element so oh it's just a
regular reference so i can just do a
dollar zero dot inner text or whatever
so in addition to that guy like let's
say I'm going over here and we also have
a copy method and this is pretty cool so
you'll have something like a inner HTML
yeah okay soup and sometimes you'll have
a big string and you want to actually
like copy that somewhere and and while
you could you know select yeah you know
clicking into select is
we pass a so we can just call copy and
copy that to the clipboard go over here
paste it out so there's yeah there's
some pretty cool shortcuts to save you
some time there keys is also another one
it shows you all the the the properties
on an object all the methods and
properties so pass it like document and
it is gives me everything there so keys
and values also yeah so over on the
Firebug wiki is the full list of command
line API oh my god i just found out this
one the other day ryan said in the CSS
ninja showed me this CD so this is not
implemented by chrome but i'm really
we're going to do it because I'm just
it's so rad so you pass it a reference
to a window basically you pass it a
reference to like an iframe and then so
you'll be like CD and then I frame ref
and then after that everything that you
type operates within the context of that
iframe so you don't have to do that
nasty traversal thing absolutely every
time you want to run code you can just
CD into the iframe xeu code inside of
that and then CD top so you know go back
out it's pretty cool so available in
Firebug that's it but it's coming out of
the places soon all right as for do a
little bit of debugging I want to show
off some pretty cool script stuff so i
have this page here and this is just a
list of the developer advocates at at
google and you know I can sort and
that's pretty cool so if I want to
figure out what's going on inside here
I'm going to go into the scripts tab
break it it's cool let's see oh there is
i'm running a developer builds ah great
thank you for sticking with me ok so I'm
over here in the app code for the page I
actually know what line I want to go do
so i can just jump right down to it I'm
in command l which is go to line this
also works over in CSS so I'm going to
jump down there there's a few shortcuts
available you can hit ? right in the dev
tools and get a display of a few of them
so I'm down here in my code and one of
the cool things that you can do now is
edit the script live on the fly so I can
just double-click and then just I don't
know I'm going to like console log out
whatever is coming into here that's
pretty cool so now as I manipulate this
stuff others the argument cuts gets
logged out or maybe I want to do
something a little bit cooler like maybe
do if this guy is feed entry 0 yes
equals Irish yes document
that body style that background equals
something pretty sweet think that I work
I think that work whoo nice definite
improvement so yeah so you can do live
editing right in there and of course I
go over to resources find this script
and the revisions have been saved as
well and I can go and say that out if a
lot pretty cool all right there's a few
more features that i want to show off do
i have three minutes is that what i have
i think of three minutes okay given that
i have three minutes come and talk to me
to see a some crazy breakpoint stuff
that you can do i do want to show this
is really rad there this is very recent
we're just announcing this now we now
have remote debugging ability in the
chrome devtools so if i run something
like this i run chromium with remote
debugging port leaped let's let's try
this out actually okay okay here's
chromium running out and now i'm going
to open up WebKit this is a nightly
WebKit okay so i just opened up so
what's happening is that chrome is
actually running a web server basically
and I can just these are all the tabs
that I have open right and I can just
I'm now this is you know the dev tools
is a web app I'm looking at the dev
tools of chrome with Safari nightly and
you know it just it works just like you
would want it to so this is really cool
right I mean this this is a this work
has been done all at the WebKit level so
that means of course
that all the mobile web kits are getting
this which means also the rim playbook
that just shipped has this feature
available where you just like turn it on
and you can just log in to your tablet
from your desktop machine and it's debug
it like you would want to yes I do all
like I said that the devtools is just a
web app like it's just a bunch of
JavaScript and it's really fun to read
around and one of the things i do want
to point out this is also brand-new over
if you download a chromium chromium
build usually find a page like this and
it's not the most user-friendly thing
but this is new dev tools dot front end
the zip is basically all these files
right here and you can now just run
chrome with this flag point it to that
folder and then just like hack on your
own devtools you know right rewriting
the JavaScript the styling and then just
play around with it and maybe you know
write a patch and and add a feature to
it so that we can make it even cooler
dev tools extensions are about to come
out google i/o is where we're going to
make that announcement that's going to
be really exciting and one last amazing
feature probably read it check this out
it's right over here or bring up the dev
tools well
I'm going to bring up yes this one okay
yeah you have a right you have a bunch
of unmanned flight code and you're like
that sucks right Wow oh that's terrible
so anyways my machine totally just died
a lot okay you can right-click like try
it out get a chromium belt or chrome dev
channel it's in chrome dev channel right
click in the scripts tab and it just
says pretty print and then that minified
code just gets blown out beautiful
indented and lovely even if you refresh
the page that in stay in the session it
stays blown out which is really good
because you're going to what you wanting
to set break points within it right so