popcorn Jas is an html5 video framework
that lets you bring the web into your
videos let's try it this video was shot
in New Orleans this one was shot in Cape
Town here are some clicker photos from
the guy in this video see how the
content of the video can change the web
page this is Will Ferrell dancing to
this exact song and here is what people
are saying about him on Twitter he also
has an article on wikipedia popcorn has
been used to show analysis of a
president speech to add value to a TV
show 2 mashup Donald Duck and glenn beck
and to understand the real justin
bieber's you even started working on a
graphical user interface for popcorn
called butter we have plugins for mini
web services already and popcorn is an
open source project that is evolving
constantly join us and let's make video
and the web play nicely together
you
and this is kind of awkward because this
video is about man standing right over
there so it's like I think you might
have seen it once for who knows but this
actually just shows like us we've got
some plugins going on here we made that
video in at jquery conference in boston
in the fall just projecting some stuff
onto a screen during the party we can
add this wikipedia thing I mean this is
real casual so
it's very surreal it's a quick
demonstration of the declarative popcorn
that was me trying to be just as
controversial as Anton because we had
talks opposing each other at the jQuery
conference hey I can stir it up to trust
me and this everybody is a monkey riding
a dog actually was the demo for showing
how popcorn now supports YouTube and
Vimeo videos just as well as html5
videos so enjoy a monkey a dog yeah so
that was the monkey riding a dog thing
in case you were wondering oh god guys
stop talking to me on IRC it's kind of
funny mmm also this was kind of awesome
we had like a miniature conference in
New York at Tisch and I got paired up
with probably one of like the most
visionary kids I've ever met dude Greg
he had this idea like let's sync html5
video clips you know from like this Star
Trek trailer to wait a second this html5
or nurse from be taking machine I was
like you're nuts it's impossible
ain't no lower Concord
did that let me show you how it works
these keys cute wer you blah blah they
actually match up two instruments here
we can change what's going on but if I
do under you to do better so that's me
pressing buttons on the keyboard in case
you were wondering mhm so let's see here
me actually throw down your like numeric
is going to raise
thinking about he's going to produce
next
under you plenty this is actually going
to the beat that's being produced down
here be fun / totally annoying so you
have a lot of fun with that some of the
other stuff i'll be from from the butter
camp at tisch i'll be showing later on
it's actually just going to sit here and
write some popcorn code using the API
for your entertainment purposes so you
can see basically how simple we have
beaucoup with the help of some teams at
Mozilla made it to control html5 videos
it's fun stuff you see that no kind of
looks what's that oh yeah new to this OS
X things there we go we have that
oops what am i doing I probably could
have used something to make this part
easier but a man hindsight's
twenty-twenty right what's that somebody
giving me more suggestions out there
that we wanted me to do
Shh
you've always had a hard time finding
your place in this world are you talking
to me man you can settle for an ordinary
life yeah alerts are way annoying
you've always had a hard time finding
your place in this world are you talking
about where is it probably would have
been easier if I just you know you flew
OOP
stop whistling that and get it cut in
everybody's head all day long it's gonna
be horrible oh I'm gonna need the whole
package yeah I hear you it's funny I'll
make you watch monkeys riding dogs again
mm-hmm put ya so everything we have run
a distribution with the latest version
at popcorn j/s org slash code / zoom in
so you can see it see that up there
everything brand-new is in that code
dist directory Brett 0.5 minus 0.6 is
gonna be our big docks push exciting so
everybody will be able to figure out I
use it if you don't know already um
actually remember how this works text
yeah there we go
you've always had a hard time finding
your placement what's going on here oh
that would help nope complete oh let's
go see if that even exists yet Oh dash
it's a dash not a silly me sorry about
that
shit fuck are you
bummer we've always in our hard time
finding your place in this world are you
talking with me man you can hmm yeah
I'll skip to the other awesome thing I
was gonna show you sorry should know my
limits mm-hmm Plus this is way funnier
enjoy
do you feel like you're working harder
and harder these days just to stay
financially afloat while fat cats get
richer and richer it's not just a
feeling and you're not alone the income
gap between rich and poor in America is
at an 80 year hi that's the largest
differential since the period
immediately preceding the Great
Depression the halves are getting more
while the have-nots are getting less
meanwhile government isn't helping
decades of rising inequality
you're fired sorry mr. duck that's it
we've just been run out of jobs I'm a
mile and flat
welcome to the program my name is glenn
beck the bad news is just multiplying
our economy is tanking it doesn't show
signs of improving their people losing
jobs our government responds to the
problems with bailouts and when you call
him up and say what are you doing you
don't get any response or not listening
to you Wall Street owns our government
how did we get here I think a lot of
people feel like they're alone and they
just want to give up wow wow I love my
country it is the shining example of a
place where people work together in
peace and friendship and worship God and
make things better together that's why
well the idea is that built America are
being lost and perverted wow wow wow ask
yourself this one question how many
Marxists communists anti-capitalists do
you have around you on a daily basis the
truth is that you are the defender of
Liberty our situation is bad there are
Nazis in America Nazis and communists
you have to think like a German Jew 1934
I'm
Oh
there is a perfect storm formulating and
it is here we are entering a dangerous
and scary time America the country will
be washed with blood these people don't
mess around they are taking you to a
place to be slaughtered death camp what
planet have I landed on its like the
damn planet of the apes did I slip
through a wormhole in the middle of the
night and this looks like a mirror we're
in a dark dark place we've got some dark
dudes coming our way Black Panthers
acorn reparation the welfare Jeremiah
Ryan Jones ama himself al Qaeda Rand
Islamic jihadists Venezuela immigration
xican was refugees from long span across
America legal alien Mexico everyone is
coming the enemy is not only in the
gates they're inside the house million
is BMO scum Aubrey young vessel hola
Maxim Erica it's like a pack of wild
cujo's ripping up the flesh of the
American people drug lords illegal
aliens Mexico
they're going to start getting more and
more violent we have been tossed into
boiling water these people are
cannibalizing random cannibalizing us
that's what Barack Obama is doing to the
American people I'm hoping the guy with
horns doesn't actually show up
everything is about to change to the
extreme the insider extreme we invite
you to join up for 995 a month it's
gonna explain everything that is going
on insider extreme is up and on hello
yes sick twisted freak and welcome to
the extremists who are you isn't that a
name of some stupid Disney curse you can
ask any question
Oh sucks to be you doesn't it when you
bought a house you bet that you could
pay it that nothing would happen it
happened you lost move on what boohoo
cry me a river hey I got an idea listen
to this get a job a lazy slob that
refuses to get off the couch and get a
job
I hope you enjoyed these snacks there
will be more later on so I was actually
going to show a whole bunch of like like
artsy popcorn videos that were made at
butter camp in New York about a month
ago but I'm not gonna show that I'm
gonna save that for tomorrow what I am
going to show is probably the most
amazing thing you've ever seen in your
entire life so I'm not even really sure
how to introduce this aside from get
ready to have your goddamn mind blown up
max Ogden you want to stand up and a
prepare for takeoff all right everybody
this is what happens when you let
programmers play with Arduino 'he's a
potentiometer nodejs socket i/o and
popcorn Jas and YouTube all in the same
sentence uh excuse me just don't worry
about it max you wanna death are you
doing that
oh god man what's up just in case you
guys are wondering he's using a soft
potentiometer over there to slide back
and forth except there was totally way
more awesome when yeah all right pause
know if you guys see that he's actually
doing that
mm-hmm are you doing that I wonder if
it's like trying to catch up with the
instructions this is pretty crazy we
just came up with this like about 45
minutes ago and hacked it together I
mean sorry hacking is so 1998 what I
meant to say was we artistic get
together we paint it we painted it with
our fingers oh and by the way that's
totally a monkey riding a damn goat this
is unbelievable if anybody wants to
actually come in like sit down and see
this afterwards we will most definitely
accommodate yeah if you go see max you
can actually run the potentiometer
yourself
the future of remote control remote
controls will be taped to your keyboard
going to walk around at your level David
want to just come and check out in the
lobby
did you do that tell you it was a long
day with a lot of caffeine you know how
it go how do you do that I don't even
know how that works I didn't hear what
you said so anyway if you actually saw
the code managing this it's pretty
impressive I'll be it messy at the
moment but yeah come check us out we'll
be in lobby for the rest of this
intermission you can ask us questions
about what the hell it is we're talking
about what we did yeah all right okay
come on in I started doing this project
when I was like meeting with graffiti
writers and looking for a way to capture
an archive graffiti in a way that wasn't
just photos and video which is how
graffiti is typically been documented
part of the idea the software is that
like graffiti writers don't see the
software they just write as normal and
it's about passively recording this data
and in the beginning I was just doing
this myself about two years ago I
released the software open source as an
experimental trying to get more people
involved in the software side and then
just the last six months of an
experiment in low Earth opening up the
data and opening up the data has been
much more interesting than opening up
the software essentially I had all these
files from meeting with graffiti writers
I was saving in this format that only my
software was working with and now with
some friends we kind of defined what is
essentially a very simple XML file
standard that it has a header and it has
some other things that are specific to
different software but essentially it's
just points with XY time
and z values there was a team of us that
that met up with this graffiti writer
named tenth one who was a like legendary
Los Angeles graffiti writer from the 90s
and he has ALS which is a like Lou
Gehrig's disease it's like a
degenerative disease that leaves you
paralyzed and so he has no motion except
for his eyes and so this software was
about creating an open source free
software suite that would allow him to
write graffiti with his eyes we were
using a playstation 3 camera mounting
into a pair of glasses to do I tracking
the second version that were going to be
releasing doesn't require it to be head
mounted anymore first iteration was
working with him as an artist to make
this piece for drawing graffiti second
version is hopefully going to be for
everybody else it's in a situation that
might not write graffiti but wants to
write emails I'm also part of the
graffiti research labs we've done the
laser tag project if you seen that one
where as a laser and you can hand it off
to graffiti writers and they write in
real time on buildings and so being a
part of all these different graffiti
related software packages that were open
source but not talking to each other
this graffiti markup language project is
about connecting all those things and so
essentially it's the least sexy part of
the project you know it's just a file
standard so it's actually kind of born
to talk about but it's allowed for all
these interesting things to happen which
is that like 10th for example is now
writing into a format that's the same as
like his friends in the scene that are
riding with a hand or running with the
can or running with a pen and so now the
data is saved in a similar format so we
can go and project temps tags the same
way that we're projecting other tags and
so it was the first step was getting all
the software i was working on connected
into this gml standard but now the next
step is I've been trying to like for
more of a community around this and even
though it's kind of a very niche sort of
a most ridiculous thing I find that it's
in people have sort of an interest in
graffiti there's sort of a pop culture
reference there and so I'm using this as
a way to get people even though even if
they have no interest in graffiti or
they have no interest in open-source
it's a good way of getting people
introduced to these things which I think
are so interesting if you want to get
the software I have it at graffiti
analysis com there's two sides of the
application there's one for capturing
and one for playback and so that so if
you want to do capturing it's this two
point O capture application and this one
runs on all the
various platforms and you don't really
need anything fancier than a laptop with
a built-in webcam to do the capturing
however when you're in situations like
this where you're sitting in semi direct
sunlight you get less control with the
webcam than you do with cameras that
have the ability to change to manually
the light level this is just an external
USB video so now that you've watched a
few minutes of this what you actually
saw there was a mash-up of popcorn j/s
synchronizing with the processing j/s
with GM l which is graffiti markup
language in those tags were actually
being drawn in real time with processing
and gml instructions in sync with the
video of course using popcorn Jas this
was a project that came from the the
mini comp we had in New York about a
month ago called butter camp so I'll be
quiet and turned volume back up and let
you continue watching and the more if
you're really looking for a precise
capture you want the camera really
perpendicular to the page and so this
goes over that capture system as well so
if you're interested in the more
advanced one I have I have a vector file
which I laser cutter you can just laser
cut them but really the parts are there
really simple to cut out just with foam
core the most expensive piece in the
building is capture case is just this
plexiglass which goes on the front this
is like super low tech and everything
but it gives you it gives you a really
nice just blank screen you can take the
page too so that when you're attaching a
light source of the graffiti marker the
lights going through the pages that have
reflected off of it I can show more
about this later I've actually been
using the behind the hand method more
and more lately because you can capture
in the street with like just 5 to 10
seconds setup work in the right scenario
so i'll show the behind the hand capture
method now which is a bit easier what
you're going to see in the upper left is
just the raw video stream that's coming
in from the camera to get a different
camera like right now I'm telling it to
bypass this camera and look for other
cameras but you don't have to worry
about that if you only have one camera
connected the first thing to do is when
this image comes up when you're getting
your raw feed in
this is why these cameras are so nice as
does that can like I can really control
how much lights coming in there's like
some blue and pink lines that are
showing what the software thinks is its
tracking right now the bottom screen is
showing what it thinks the light source
is what we want to see is like a nice
dime size perfect circle and that means
we're getting a good capture any light
source you can get on can probably be
used as a tracking device i like to use
ones that have click button on and off i
usually mount the light source to the
top you want to keep the cameron away so
that the hand doesn't block the light
source so this part is not rocket
science but if there's like a chisel tip
I try to keep this mounted above the
chisel tip and then keep it pulled back
from the page enough that if someone's
using their if they're rotating their
hand they're not going to hit it but
again this is like pretty simple in a
bit of trial and error the brighter the
light of course the more difference of
getting your threshold value between the
ambient light and the light that's being
tracked if you just look at this window
you can see this is obviously not a
clean capture when I have this situation
I can usually adjust this down and just
by using the camera not even using aim
this software you can see I'm already
starting to get a pretty clean capture
right there's not a lot of like fancy
settings in this app but the one that
we're going to really be caring about is
this threshold this is doing a similar
thing to opening up the Lightning camera
but it's just saying how different is
this pixel from the pixels surrounding
it and based on that level it's going to
say use it or don't use it right now I'm
actually pretty close like I'm getting a
pretty decent capture with the way it is
I would call this off work on set you
can click save and then if it crashes
will have the sayings there's two loads
one for capturing behind the hand and
one for capturing through a piece of
glass right now if I move from left to
right on the page I can see that my
track is moving from left to right in
the page also but if I move the camera
two behind I'm going to want that to
reverse and so in the second tab you can
just hit flip x and then if we're set up
in the other mode it'll work from from
the mirrored perspective enter advances
you through the different modes in the
software so if I hit return then i'm
going to start recording so usually I'll
meet with the graffiti writer and I'll
just say ok start writing and I'll start
recording and another enter to stop it
leaves recording mode and it goes into
an edit mode the Z is kind of linear so
it says if you're writing on a page
kind of constantly pulling away it's
kind of about data visualization so it's
about trying to understand more about
how the ink is layering up but also from
an editing standpoint it makes it easier
because you can kind of see where
everything is beginning and ending all
the panning and zooming and tilting all
happens between left click and right
clicking and dragging so by clicking and
dragging these two points that can I can
set what was junk at the beginning what
was junk at the end and you can name the
file here and then when you hit enter
again it will take you into a playback
mode and show you what you've captured
at this point it's also saved the dot
GML file to the the root directory of
the app is running in I'll just get some
data so I'll call this one test GML so f
will pop it back out a full screen under
tags there's a folder with the name that
I just name the file and so here's the
gml file the idea is that you open this
up and it's kind of human readable like
it's meant to be kind of like
introductory like hobbyist hackers
hobbyist programmers to get involved
with this the playback mode has some
functionality that the recording mode
doesn't have the kind of basic way the
visualization is working is besides the
deep Z dimension which is meant to like
give you some more understanding of how
this ink is layering up it's it's not
meant to represent the actual ink that's
on the page it's meant to represent the
motion of the tag that that's one reason
also you're capturing a single line
there's of course other software's that
can capture multiple strokes but for my
interest I like recording all the
movements like when the pen comes up and
moves to the other side graffiti is very
dictated by like riding in a very
specific place at a specific time and so
the ink on the wall is like not just
about someone's vision of what a
graffiti tag should look like it's like
dictated by you know who's walking
around the corner what part of town is
it in like you have like five to ten
seconds to make this form and so for me
capturing all that motion was just an
interest from a research standpoint and
so that's why I'm getting all the
movements so even when the pens up the
thinner the line is the faster the pen
was moving so even when this isn't
playing back you can get some sense of
like the motion and then these the
particles that are getting thrown off
our kind of based on velocities you
round a corner very smoothly for example
you get this even throw of particles
if you had a jagged one you get a spike
the intent is meant to sort of just
amplify that motion it's all about like
trying to see this sort of like dance
that happens when no one's looking right
so that's the basic functionality the
playback mode there's some other things
that you can turn on like there's an
audio setting that'll just take the
audio from the mic and you can get
interaction with so if you're projecting
this outside you can be picking up
ambient things there's also setting more
settings for doing things outside with
it there's an architectural interface so
good graffiti writers aren't just
slapping stuff up anywhere they're very
conscious of like what the architecture
is what the structures are how they're
fitting in and so the software is meant
to work the same way also so if we're
going to project here there's a way
where you can tell the software where
all these corners are like where the
edges are so that when it's when it's
playing back it can interact with that
there's also this warping mode so that
you can if you're projecting at an angle
we're projecting on a surface that isn't
true you can you can set this so that
it's like you can deal with this outside
of the sort of key stoning functionality
the projector so the way the basic way
the architecture settings work is if
you're projecting on something it just
gives me like a simple drawing interface
and I'd outline all these shapes it just
takes about a minute or two and then
when I hit save the software knows that
those angles are to be recognized as a
Ledge so that then when the particles
are interacting with it will start
bouncing off that surface and it's a
little bit of a visual trick and it's
not super high-tech course there's
people doing like much more advanced
stuff with like projection mapping stuff
but it's just a way to like tie in the
graffiti tags to like the environment
and a little bit more graffiti analysis
is kind of the first thing that I made
as an open source software example but
now that so many other people are
building this and trying to point to
what others are making as well that use
the same format because now once you
have that file you can pipe it into all
these different places and so I'm
starting to archive that at graffiti
markup language com and so this is a
place that's pointing to all the
projects that i'm finding on the web
some of them me some of my friends
images so there's uh one more demo that
i want to actually jump to so i'm going
to cut this one short but actually just
discovered yesterday thought it's pretty
cool so give me a second to find it so
so this is actually somebody used
popcorn jss sort of a production tool
and everything is then been synthesized
into and packaged into a single video
which is really interesting or
interesting use of the technology so
enjoy
so you get the idea that's pretty cool
stuff I'm actually going to part ways
with you know and i'll see you guys all
at five o'clock for the last
installation of snacks with popcorn jas
this is a two-part deal for the first
part if you're easily offended by vulgar
words like the S or f words I'd like to
ask you to leave the room for maybe the
next three minutes or earmuffs even so
this is a sorry about the ScreenFlow
demo I didn't make this but this is
totally awesome i found this on twitter
yesterday this is the result of some
pretty fun stuff that somebody took the
time and screencast themselves creating
a popcorn project it's a minute and 20
seconds long let's watch it he left us
oh shit
oh this is daddy why aren't you smiling
oh shit particular by other people
messing with their shit I mean shit you
wouldn't be Vicky yeah I didn't open up
shit shit sweet right there pretty
awesome right all right and for but I
did that again hold on and for the very
last thing this is a pretty tremendous
and I'm totally stoked that I get to
show this off let's go on so everybody
here is familiar with the Khan Academy
ya know maybe whatever so basically this
demonstration was created by David
Humphrey and Bobby rector of Mozilla at
the Seneca College in Toronto and
through the seedot program and what
they've done is they've taken a Khan
Academy one of the one of their
educational videos and they've made it
into an interactive educational
experience so I'm actually going to demo
said experience for you live here which
is pretty awesome this is actually just
published i think hours ago uh or was
yeah yeah hours ago so i'm going to shut
the mic off and jump to this one awesome
all right here we go where we left off
in the last video I think we're getting
a reasonably good appreciation for how
huge the Sun is especially relative to
the earth and how far the earth is away
from the Sun that most of these diagrams
that we see when we in science textbooks
they don't give justice in fact you know
when I showed it this this Sun over here
that was about five or six inches across
I said you would be just this little
speck about that 40 feet the entire
piece this is would be but right to the
left right or would have a radius its
orbit would have a radius of about four
dancing song this you know you wouldn't
even notice it if you were looking at
this thing over here would be this
little speck orbiting at this huge huge
distance if you look at this Sun over
here this Sun over here if I were to
draw the whole Sun it looks like would
have a it looks like i would have a
diameter of about 20 inches so in this
situation in this situation this earth
right here this is drawn to scale this
earth would not be anywhere near this
close it would be it would be about
about 200 feet that way or about the
60-meter so you can imagine if the right
was this size this is all synchronized
to this video down in the corner this
little speck of an earth this little
thing right here would be sitting on
wouldn't even not wouldn't even notice
it this is you you might notice this
from a distance but you wouldn't even
see this thing over here and the other
planets are even further well not all of
the other planets obviously you have
mercury you have mercury here I'll drink
a little bit i'll just list them here
just in case that's mercury if it's not
debated whether it's a planet pluto is
the smallest but some people debate
whether it's really a planet or kind of
just you're a dwarf planet or on any of
those types of things but then you have
Venus probably the closest in size to
the earth or it is the closest in size
of the earth and then you have Mars and
then you have one son then Jupiter is
five times further than Earth so this
would be this if I were to actually do
this the scale distance this would be
300 meters away 300 meters so if I had a
nice big maybe medicine bald sighs son
right over here maybe basketball-sized a
little bit bigger than a basketball this
looks on my screen then I would have I
would put this little this little thing
that's smaller than a ping-pong ball i
would put this three football fields
away that's how far there is and then
Saturn's about twice as far as that
Saturn is about nine times the distance
let me let me make it clear this is the
earth is one after thatl unit away
everything runs synchronized its launch
the video perfectly tire educational
experience is broken out of the corner
binds a prog taken on the whole screen
5s completely interact astronomical unit
so a little bit more than five times the
distance of the Sun to the earth and
Saturn Saturn is approximately nine
astronomical units or nine times the
distance from the Sun to the earth so
once again this would be nine football
fields away or another way to think
about it be essentially a kilometer away
if we had a kind of a medicine ball size
son this little smaller than a pink pong
bald Saturn would be a kilometer away
then I just want it really so you can
see how this could have tremendous
impact and obviously not just education
but any sort of forward thinking
progressive media interaction that might
take the place of a long-standing
juggernaut in the field I don't know
possibly flash a lot of these things can
be achieved and thoroughly believe that
popcorn j/s could be the foundation for
that once again this demonstration was
created by David Humphrey and Bobby
Richter of Mozilla tremendous work these
guys are amazing and with that i'm going
to say goodnight to all of you roads
take me home to the place I belong hold