good my name is Francisco tomas key I am
a co-founder of a company called 280
north I founded that with two of my best
friends from college who are also here
at jay's comp so if you have any
questions you can hit any one of us
we're probably going to be wearing 20
North's shirts so what I'm here to talk
about today is a JavaScript framework we
created called cappuccino just out of
curiosity how many of you have heard of
it just so i know whether i should focus
on okay okay good so something we like
to say a lot and we always try to start
our presentations this way is by
describing exactly what it's for and
what it's not for cappuccino is for what
we call desktop-class applications and
by that we mean kind of the applications
that you used to expect running on the
desktop and a lot of people thought
would never make it to the web but are
more and more going there today so you
know we like to think of the web as this
giant spectrum right and when the web
first started it was had this kind of
web page in mind you know the
traditional restful web something like
New York Times just a bunch of pages
connected by hyperlinks and then over
time they got a little more dynamic
things like amazon com now amazon com
still fits this original vision of the
web really well but you can't deny that
it's not an application right you can
you can put your credit card number and
there thus it's an application so it
does things as well as present things
then you have things like Facebook which
are like exactly in the middle they are
very restful right every single user has
their own page and you know that pages
and change and everything but on the
other hand every single page can have
like 30 different apps running on it so
this is like something that's very
unique to the web and then on the far
right of the spectrum you have things
like Google Maps and Google Maps is
actually a really great example of this
kind of app because Microsoft actually
originally argued against the web
platform by saying they'll never be able
to do something like Maps well they were
wrong and this kind of kicked off the
revolution of doing
incredibly dynamic things things you'd
only expect on the desktop before on the
web so we really wanted to build this
kind of application on the web like
three years ago or something something
like that and the problem was that the
tools for doing it even though the web
was capable of doing it the tools
weren't really there to do it and it's
not because the tools were bad it's that
the tools focused on different things
right the tools were really you know
optimized for building things like new
york times or amazon.com that sort of
thing you know just when Google Maps
first came out no one had already made a
framework for it for anything so we
wanted to make a framework that really
targeted this right hand of the spectrum
what we call desktop-class applications
and you can really tell that this is
necessary because if you go hit view
source on any one of these applications
you know one of the great things of the
web you'll see that all of them have
basically done each other's job over and
over again right meebo is a great
example you know they me bows I use that
instead of ichat a lot and it's a really
great web app yet they have to put so
many resources into drawing windows and
drawing buttons and basically putting
together a windowing system and it
really sucks that for a chat application
there you know strategic advantage to be
we hired 20 people to write a windowing
system that that's not what the web
should be right that should be a solved
problem and you should be able to focus
on what makes your application unique so
I want to give you an example of the
first step we wrote using this framework
it's called 280 slides and I will go
ahead and do that right now
go
so this is Twitty slides it's kind of
like keynote or powerpoint on the web
and it's running in Safari and you can
of course do you expect to be able to do
you know kind of make a title and set
the font or whatever but again we really
wanted that desktop feel so we really
tried to get media right so you know
we've got shapes and you can do whatever
you want with them and this will work in
you know IE or firefox or whatever and
we don't stop there you know we let you
do any arbitrary media so you can do a
search for an image on google images you
can drag that in you know this is just
going to work it's going to be fast and
of course just like on the desktop all
your key bindings should work right so
copy paste should work and that
shouldn't be just bound to text or
images I should be able to do it you
know on slide level if I move things
around undo should just work so all this
and you can undo all the way to the
beginning of your document etc and of
course you can do this with movies as
well so I'm do a quick search here so
when you can quick look this just like
on Mac OS 10 and it's letting up YouTube
there we go so he can kind of preview
your movie for you see it you guys
believe me that this is a real movie not
an animated gif friend I can close this
so then you can drag it on and if you
want so so that's kind of the idea we
wanted something that really felt like a
real application and I want to show you
one more application this one was just
released a couple days ago not by us
it's called mockingbird it's kind of
like balsamic have you guys played
around with balsamic at all so but it's
written completely with web standards
technologies on top of cappuccino and
it's kind of the same thing you can you
know lay out a UI and if you want to
link to another page you can just hear
you have your different pages you can
just kind of drag in the other page and
now it's linked to it there you go so
you guys should just play around with
this I'm go Mockingbird calm we go so
the way we decided to build this is by
taking an existing technology that we
thought already worked really well and
we're all former Mac guys and we used to
write mac software and Coco is the way
you write applications on the mac and we
really like it
you know it's a really great framework
for doing very visual you I driven
things and what really sealed the deal
for us was the fact that Coco has been
around for like 20 years like next step
was running this then Mac started
running it and a few years ago they took
this existing framework and shoved it
into a completely different environment
the iphone and if you look at iphone
apps they look pretty darn good so that
to us kind of proved this framework the
fact that you could take something a 20
year old idea put it on a completely
different platform and revolutionize the
industry well you know maybe they're
doing it because of the framework not in
spite of it right so we said well you
know if you can make great apps on the
mac and the iphone why not the wet so
basically what cappuccino is is a port
of the cocoa frameworks from the mac and
from the iphone onto the web so to do
that we actually created a new language
on top of JavaScript it's called
objective J it just adds a few new
features to JavaScript so if you've ever
wanted to be able to do classical
inheritance or be able to you know
import scripts that sort of thing
objective J handles it the nice thing
about objective J is that it's a strict
superset of JavaScript and that's just a
fancy way of saying any existing
JavaScript will work with objective J so
you can take any existing JavaScript
framework mix it together with objective
J it's just going to work you don't need
to compile it or anything it'll just
work in the browser so what I really
want to focus on today is our new
version that we're going to be launching
soon it's called 0.8 we're in beta right
now so we're calling it 0.79 and we
focused on a lot of different things for
this version but I'm can only hit about
three today and the first big one I want
to hit is common J yes and I'm really
glad that Chris got to kind of give you
guys an introduction to this before me
so i don't have to focus too much but
common chance is really really important
like it's really embarrassing as a
community that anytime we want to do
something on the terminal we have to use
a different language and i could someone
asked earlier you know what's a great
use case for calming j/s well 280 slides
runs javascript in the server and it
sucked having to do it without something
like calm and jas we had to do it on top
of rhino which is you know one of the
few and
competing for the Medal of slowest
implementation I guess I don't know it's
it's it's terrible on top of that any
time you want to do anything you have to
drop down to Java I didn't start
programming java script to program java
so equally terrible and so basically
when it comes to the terminal you can't
really do a lot with JavaScript you can
you can add numbers but the second you
want to print that result no standard
way right the second you want to read
Apollo can't do that so common Jas is
incredibly important to the JavaScript
community and we've invested heavily in
it in the next version of cappuccino so
the way we've invested in it is we built
our entire build process on top of
gobbling jas we've ported all our tools
to come in Jas and we're also going to
handle distribution through common Jas
so let me kind of explain a little
deeper when we first did cappuccino we
didn't need a build system because it's
JavaScript but as it turns out that's
kind of a little lie we tell people oh
it's interpreted you don't need to build
well you do you need to minify you
neither can cat all this stuff so
cappuccinos a pretty big framework and
it requires doing all this and
originally we just wanted something that
I was not make and be could be run cross
platform and so we settled on ant you
know oh you know it's XML must be good
it's not one of the nice things about X
about aunt was that it you can kind of
run JavaScript in it it has a script tag
but you can't really and then the second
you want to do something like if what
can't contain no sorry like you know
conditionals no conditionals guys you
need an external library to do a
conditional on hand so that was that was
pretty terrible so at one point we had
half an aunt and like half in this you
know half javascript stuff in script it
was a complete mess like most our bug
reports were like I don't know how to
build this so then we moved to rake and
I have to say that I like rake a lot
it's the first build system that didn't
want make me want to gouge my eyes out
it's it's a really fantastic tool I
actually learned Ruby through rake so
that should tell you how great it is I
got even know the language and I just
kind of picked it up and we ported
everything in cappuccino from ant to
rake now that being said it still kind
of sucks that it's not
javascript for a number of reasons for
starters it's kind of a you know barrier
to entry if someone wants to fix a build
bug right they come in they're expecting
just JavaScript and then something
doesn't work in the build scripts and
they don't really know what to do and
sure you know learning ruby is easy but
the answer shouldn't be oh just learn
this new language then you can continue
programming in JavaScript no that's not
the right thing additionally it's nice
to be able to use your own idioms when
you're doing other stuff and the last
kind of real deal breaker for us was
that we had written all these great
tools you know for cappuccino and
JavaScript and we couldn't even write
use them in our build system so we ended
up at this point where we had a parallel
set of tools so we would write like you
know something that did something fancy
an objective J and then we'd have to
write it in Ruby to just so we could use
it on you know this on the terminal as
well as on the client-side browser so it
became just a management mess so what we
did was basically take rake and do a
direct port to javascript it's called
Jake and it runs on top of calming j/s
it's really nice because it really is a
direct port so you know we took we build
Atlas on rake and we were able to
translate it to Jake and like you know I
think half an hour to an hour so I'm
just going to quickly show you what
that's like so has anyone here used Rick
do you guys use break for your own
projects okay so it is kind of how you
do things in Reiki you have this build
task and then you can do stuff so this
with Jake just looks like this so it's a
little bit longer because you got that
function keyword but basically oh
there's a syntax error there sorry get
rid of that parentheses so basically if
you want to build something called hello
it'll do whatever is in that function
this is how you set up dependencies in
rake you say well if you want to build
hello you have to you know build
dependency one in dependency to first
and this is how you do it in Jake so
just you know passing on the right as
you can see we obviously have to use
strings instead of symbols or whatever
the other nice thing about rake is that
you can just kind of append dependencies
to an existing task and that still works
the same with Jake and it has this
really nifty file task which basically
says if this if the file on the right is
dirty rebuild a file on the left and
that's exactly the same so again if you
already have rake build scripts is it'll
be really easy to convert them to Jake
and then you can use all your tools and
stuff so we're really happy with that so
we really love Tom and Jas and you know
everyone knows that for a healthier
relationship it's good for the other way
to be true too so what's really cool
about common Jas is that it's fluent an
objective J as well as JavaScript so
this is the way we're going to ship
cappuccino the next version so instead
of this you know go to this website and
click something there's the task which
is kind of like gem it's kind of like
Ruby gems and you'll just be able to
type tusk install cappuccino and you'll
have cappuccino installed on your system
and that solves a really big problem for
us which is you know distribution so
this is one example of one of the many
cappuccino frameworks out there it's
called map kit it allows you to put
google maps into your websites and stuff
and this sucks today it sucks for
JavaScript programmers you have to go
search your mailing list oh here's the
github URL which branch do i download
it's terrible but you know starting with
08 you'll just be able to do this and
you will be able to use it in all your
apps so I'm really excited about that
and this is just kind of the way you
define your little comment je s module
and the only thing I wanted to point out
is that there's these objective J
frameworks and objective jadeybug
frameworks fields which let you say this
is my objective J stuff so you can shape
objective J and JavaScript so I'm really
looking forward to be able being able to
have you know like a nice package
website where people can you know easily
install stuff the other big thing we
wanted to focus on was performance and
the only aspect of that I'm going to
talk about today is spriting so spriting
is not just for images right it's kind
of this abstract concept and the one
form of spriting that I think all
JavaScript frameworks get right is
spriting of actual scripts right you
know you go in and you have a million J
files and if you want something
performing you kind of concatenate them
all together and that's you know poor
man's fighting for that so the one
that's more interesting though and fewer
frameworks get right is images so this
is exactly the same idea right you have
a bunch of images and if you leave them
all separate when you load them up you
get lots of latency because every single
image is a different request and more
importantly it looks really bad if you
don't sprite them right because your
website's loaded and then stuffs kind of
just starts coming in so this is
something that admittedly cappuccino 0.7
did really poorly and by really poorly I
mean not at all so one of the things we
want to do was get this right so the
benefits of spriting again are obvious
right you get less image overhead if you
put a bunch of images together all that
redundant stuff kind of goes away right
with all the headers of an image less
latency right you push one thing instead
of many and again there's this proceed
speed issue right your website feels
faster because everything snaps in but
there are a bunch of problems with
spriting to and I think spriting right
now is still kind of primitive in that
it's not so much an optimization is kind
of a manual task that you have to do
right when we first started spriting
script files together or no no I'm sorry
when we first started doing minimization
of JavaScript it was kind of broken
right like the the very first
minimizer's was sometimes mess up on
your code and then you know you had this
thing that worked when you just shipped
to JavaScript but then you minimized it
and it didn't work and you weren't sure
we weren't quite sure why and then you
went back and it's 0 it doesn't
understand global variable so I have to
do all this stuff and what I'm trying to
say by that is that with minimization
originally we had to do all this work to
work around the minimizer right because
it didn't really understand JavaScript
that well and that's I think the stage
we're at right now with image spriting
because the spider doesn't know if your
things going to repeat horizontally or
vertically we're going to need to be
stretched or if it's going to be drawn
to a canvas so it's it's not as easy
it's just saying take my images and make
them optimized you actually have to
physically go in there and say okay this
one's for horizontal
so once for vertical blah blah blah then
someone goes in changes the code and now
it's broken so that sucks we wanted to
fix that so the solution we came up with
what oh yeah so sorry the result of all
that is that this dream of you know you
take all your images and you get kind of
one shippable image isn't really true
right you end up with you take a bunch
of images and you ship the horizontal
the vertical stretchable and whatever so
it's certainly better than shipping a
bunch of individual images but it's not
that dream of shipping one thing that
just works and on top of that you also
have to ship your code separately so
maybe five downloads instead of 25 it
would still be nice if it could be one
so this kind of solves that problem the
data URL allows you to put image data
right into text what's really nice about
this is that you can make it a hundred
percent automated right you can take all
your images and shove them into a text
file as data URLs not a problem you know
it doesn't matter how you if they're
vertical if they're horizontal if you're
going to draw on the canvas they're just
basically binary data in your txt file
so it just works the other really nice
thing about this is that you always get
one file no matter what for that same
reason you can always shove everything
in one file what are the problems with
data URLs well one of the problems is
that the files get slightly bigger you
know base64 is slightly bigger than the
actual binary representation it's not so
bad when you turn G zipping on since it
handles a lot of the common stuff
anyways but I think the main problem
that most people have on their minds as
I say this right now is but it doesn't
work on aight well it does work in IE as
it turns out and it has since ie6 and
it's called em HTML and this is like
their format for basically shipping any
arbitrary resource so what we've done is
actually built this into cappuccino you
know if you have images it'll
automatically mhtml them or base64 URL
fi them and so your entire app the whole
thing text images everything gets
shipped in one download and we've been
trying this out and it's really amazing
it feels great this is all of cappuccino
this is foundation app kid the default
theme it's just 250k gzipped and what's
really nice is it's everything right its
images everything you're done with one
download yeah so the other nice thing
about this is that we built this into
the build tool so if you have a
cappuccino application will
automatically do this for you so I think
I think this is the way to do spriting
because the other way just doesn't scale
in my opinion the way of hey you know
this guy changes code and all of a
sudden the images show up incorrectly if
you the bigger and bigger your apps get
your going to want something that just
works and I'm really excited about
shipping the feature the other thing
we've been focusing a lot on is one of
our users favorite tools which is nib to
save are you guys familiar with apples
interface builder on the Mac no okay i
will show it to you right now so as I
said we kind of formed cappuccino
because we really like the way you make
applications on the mac and one of the
big differences between the way you make
applications on the mac and the way to
make applications elsewhere is this tool
called interface builder so the way
actually start an application on the mac
is you start up interface builder and
you and you actually edit your interface
and this will take looks like in here so
this is kind of just a mac app right now
if i hit run there's the mac app it's
just as hello world on it and what you
can actually do with cappuccino is take
this interface and convert it so that it
works on the web
so if I double-click this this is
actually like kind of the default way
that you make applications on with
cappuccino so as you can see there's a
tiny bit of difference right this is
kind of full screen instead of a little
individual window the reason for that is
here we just tell the window to get full
screen but if I turn that off it'll look
exactly like the one I just showed you
right so let me show you how you
actually do stuff I'm going to build
kind of a little contrived example you
would never do this in real life I'm
going to build a browser within the
browser but i'll give you an idea of all
the widgets and stuff so if we the first
thing we want is our little browser
window so i'm just going to drag out a
window here this is my new window then
make it a little bigger and now we want
a URL field to actually be able to type
the URL right so i'm going to grab this
URL and I mean this text field and drag
it out make it a little bigger now I'm
going to grab a button this is our back
button type back and I'm going to grab a
web view
so this is where interface builder
really shines because it's kind of with
other UI builders this is where you stop
like okay now I gotta assign an ID and
then I'll go get it into them that's not
what you do an interface builder
interface builder allows you to take the
next step of actually assigning
behaviors to these elements so this is
my browser so what I'm going to do is
control click I'm going to connect this
and say you know what just take the URL
from this text field I'm going to
connect this button let's say well go
back so the last thing we want to do is
actually be able to show this window so
I'm going to open up my main menu and
we'll go to the window here and we'll
just type browser and I'm going to click
here and I'm going to hit command be so
that's another way to open it up and now
again I want to show this window so all
I do is control click from the menu item
to the window and call order front and
the last thing I'm going to do is just
say that this window should not be
visible when we originally launched the
program so I'll save this and I will run
me up to sit once again and I want to
refresh just out of the way we've got
this browser it is i can type in a URL
and it's a little slow but it's loading
it slow
no internet
alright guys stop stop torrenting for a
little bit so I can do my demo here oh
no but I'm ethernet it this should be
you know rock solid alright well sorry
guys this would show apple com but the
other nice thing is I can close this
window and again I can hit command B and
I'll just open up I don't need to worry
about the key presses or key commands or
whatever it's just going to work if you
have an internet connection so I wanted
to show you a real life example right
this is just a demo but sofa just
launched their own cappuccino
application for their new app which is
building stores online and this is it so
you kind of you know set up like how
people can buy sell or whatever it's
just like a management tool for for
setting up a website and this was built
entirely using it to say so every single
piece of you I you see was actually
built on a Mac tested first on a mac and
then converted to the web so that's
pretty exciting and obviously written
with JavaScript and objective J and I'll
show you that in more detail in a second
as well so that's nip to sip it allows
you to use interface builder and this is
all open source of course so you can
download and just use it it makes making
these kind of apps a lot easier so now I
want to talk about the product that
we're going to be releasing pretty soon
which is called 280 Atlas came back to
my presentation just to show that's like
so basically ninja tip is pretty cool
and it got us you know part of the way
there but it's not the full answer right
it's designed for desktop apps you know
the widgets don't look exactly the same
as when we convert them for the web you
know it's not built to talk to web
services that sort of thing so we've
done is actually build our own version
of this called atlas so I'm going to go
ahead and launch that and I'll show it
to you right now so I'm going to make a
new project
so this is the kind of project manager
here's our code you can type your
JavaScript objective J or whatever but
again the kind of what makes us
different is the interface editing
capabilities so I come here and they
should look familiar it's kind of like
interface builder if I double-click this
week the window a little bigger this is
this is kind of like our browser window
right it looks like a little browser
window so I can do just a quick example
here I'll drag this in and I'll drag in
a text field and these guides are really
smart they're not just you know aligned
to something else to actually tell you
you know this should be 10 pixels away
from this guy or whatever so we have the
same connection technologies interface
builder so I can actually connect these
two and just say you know take the flow
value from this and if I save it and hit
run actually let me do one more thing
just that's so it stays centered so now
if I hit run this will launch up Safari
and here we go this is our slider in our
text field and as you see if I how to
move it across it's just going to stay
updated thanks to that connection so all
these built-in connections are nice but
obviously they can only do what the
original widget designer intended them
to do so i want to show you how to build
new kinds of connections so i'm going to
do another kind of simple example the
first thing i'm going to make this just
an ordinary window like we did in
interface builder so I'm just going to
say do not fill the browser window so
now it becomes a normal window and I'm
going to drag out just an ordinary view
that does nothing I got a button will
label this one blue I'll drag out
another button label this one read now
again I want to write code that
interacts with these objects and that's
going to be hard to do because they
exist and you know layout land and not
code land so I'm going to do here is
just come to my code and create an
outlet so i'm going to say at outlet CP
view my view save that and if i come
back now here's that object that i just
edited it understands that this can be a
view so I'm going to connect that now
I've connected that view so anytime I
write in my code my view it's going to
be talking about that object but now I
want to be able to do something from
those buttons so if I show you I try to
make a connection from my button it
doesn't work so I'm going to do is
create an action so I'm going to come
here and type ad action make you read
and I'll do another one for the blue
save that and now if I come back to my
interface I can connect and I can choose
make view read connect here select make
view blue and if I save and run
here's the window I hit read it becomes
rare if I did we become school there you
go so one of the things that cappuccino
gets really right is what we like to
call document based application so
things like marking birds that I showed
you where you make a document or Twitty
slides and you have to save and all that
sort of thing so what I'd like to quit
it so I'd like to do now is show you an
example of making a document based
application so when it come here i'm
going to say new i'm going to choose
document based app and we're going to
make a text editor and all of you are
familiar with best Phineas our friend
Dion over here created so if i go to my
resources i have the main interface just
like before it has my menu and stuff but
i also have another interface file
specifically for my documents so if i
come here right now it just has nothing
so if I I click run just going to load
kind of an empty document based
application and I can make many of them
but obviously they're pretty useless
there you go so alice is really
extensible with plugins so we've decided
to do is just build investment so i can
drag that's been out straub drag and
drop it in i'm just going to make it the
entire size of the window and i will set
the resizing flags here to kind of
stretch with the window so one of the
nice things is you don't have to keep
switching between browser and and atlas
all the time we have this test button or
you can just say test in place so it's
all kind of ambiguous in place so there
you go there's best been so we can make
sure that it works before we actually
committed and trying the whole app and
it seems to be okay so now let's
actually go ahead and try it in the
browser so
there is best bin and I can make you
know lots of them and I can come in here
and I can't i make syntax errors there
we go and eat and these are also very
smart they all have their own individual
on deuce taks as you can see i'm on
doing here and then i can come here and
undo their and everything's just going
to work so the other big problem we
wanted to solve with atlas was you know
you put in all this work and you make
this really great web app but at least
for the time being there's a really big
problem with well what happens when I'm
offline right or what happens when you
know I want to sell to someone who
doesn't really trust aiding my servers
for their information so again cavatina
wasn't necessarily about the web it was
about applications that happened to run
on the web so we've done is you can come
up here to this pop-up button and right
now it's set up to run on the browser
but I can just select native desktop and
instead of hitting run I'm going to hit
build this will take a second as you can
see this is the same exact JavaScript
application this is all running
JavaScript running natively on my mac
and you know i can make new documents or
whatever so this is now a text editor
that runs both on my desktop and on the
web and if you didn't notice before this
is actually how we built atlas you know
when i was editing code this is actually
just a best bin view so we built atlas
in atlas every single line of code that
i showed you today is one hundred
percent JavaScript and objective J and
to give you one additional example of
that I'm going to go ahead and open up
to 80 slides which we wrote a while ago
before we even started all this stuff
this is a tweety slides project and if
you recall here it was running in the
browser so now this is the exact same
code I'm just going to select native
desktop I'm going to hit build this
one's going to take a little longer
because there's actual stuff in there
and sign a demo there we go so it
launches up I can say create new
application I can select this and here
is 280 slides running as a desktop oops
about them so here's 20 slides running
as a desktop application so if you're
not online you can still create and edit
your presentations do whatever here's
that little media panel it becomes a
real deal window so everything just
works the way you'd expect it to work
offline and online so that's atlas
thank computers crashing here we go
yeah okay there we go so that's atlas
we're going to be releasing the beta as
I paid beta for twenty dollars November
15th that's a week from now so you won't
see me online for that whole week as I'm
fixing bugs it's really cool I think
we're going to be seeding stuff out
about once a week you're going to be
able to test it out kind of help us
finish it along and then when we release
the final obviously the twenty dollars
will be removed from that price so
everything I showed you except for Atlas
is a completely open source you can
check it out on twitter north /
cappuccino on github if you go to just
280 north you'll see all our projects
and so include like commonjs we have a
pretty far along implementation of that
called narwhal which tom will be talking
about tomorrow Jake all these tools that
I showed you and yeah you can always hit
cappuccino org it is the first hit for
cappuccino on Google if you spell it
correctly and here are some more length
thanks a lot guys
Thank You Francisco do you guys have any
dealers have any questions for Francisco
while he's up here
no no the Nate oh yes the question was
when an atlas we turn web apps into
desktop apps that they only run on OS 10
and the answer is no when we ship Atlas
it will work both on OS 10 and windows I
mean it's it's just web stuff guys
that's a whole point of who's relying on
standards the the best bin editor plugin
will only run on the browsers that best
in supports all of cappuccino works you
know ie Firefox Safari everything but if
external parties build plugins that only
work on one then the only work there
yeah so when you run I wanted oh yeah so
the question was are there hooks for OS
specific things so the way again I don't
I don't have a lot of time to get into a
lot of detail how this desktop stuff
kind of magically works and you can talk
to the file system and stuff but
basically when you ship a web app you
have the client side component and the
server component right and you do front
end stuff on the client side and then
when you want to save a file or whatever
it gets pushed to the server so we have
that exact same architecture on the
desktop apps so we actually ship your
server code with your client side code
in these desktop apps and the server
code can do whatever it wants it can
write files it can read files it can
start other processes whatever so if you
want to you know from your client side
JavaScript do something you know
platform specific all you have to do is
create a restful request to your own
little private server which can then do
whatever it wants on any operating
system right does that make sense
um way better no um how would we compare
sprout core to cappuccino I mean they're
really two different approaches to a
problem we our approach was Coco is a
really great framework we want to get
that up and running as fast as possible
on the web it's kind of similar to what
we did with Jake right we're not out
here to reinvent build tools like that's
not an interesting problem someone's
already gotten it right you know people
a lot older than me and a lot wiser than
me have like figured out the api's and
gotten it all right there's not that
much difference between the desktop and
the web let's just get it up and running
and that's the reason that we're able to
do things like nib to save with
interface builder the reason we're able
to do Atlas all this stuff we have a
running head start because we're
cheating we're using something that's
already proven to work really well
answer your question well apples using a
lot of frameworks I mean they're using
jQuery on the main apple site and
they're using dojo and other parts of
the site and for some reason the part of
the site that they hired a bunch of
contractors who wrote Spratt for is
using sprout board so cool