don't want you know out there we go
like him - oops
Jessica of Korea presents evap assembly
filled guide easily worth like 70 bottle
caps
welcome to D world 67 three one six one
he has spent your whole life on the
ground always curious and fascinated but
a gently humming machines around young
knowing their jobs sustain your
community for whatever cause a big
calamity that force your ancestors
underground decades ago it was already
receding people are recently starting
wandering outside the heavy vault doors
exploring your desolate surroundings the
reestablish connection to other
settlements definitely came handy when
you managed to port your bulky operating
manual and started discovering the
depths of the technology that is at the
beating heart of your underground
habitat a newly a port as newly
appointed chief wall technician you were
tasked to use this knowledge to improve
the life of your community and you have
every intention in doing so so hi my
name is a spawn smashing ski and now you
know exactly why I just stick with flock
II I'm a freelance developer originally
from Budapest Hungary I live in Estonian
dam I spent quite some time in Asia in
the past few years but this is actually
my first time in Korea
except that one transfer in chat Airport
so I'm really looking forward to seeing
a bitter soul at least after the
conference I'm a missile attack speaker
tech speakers is a program by Mozilla to
support its community members teaching
at speaking a conference is holding
workshops and generally educating people
about open web technologies and the open
web in general I also work vet Mozilla's
devrel team where I help steer their
community efforts including the tech
speakers program itself and evangelizing
open web technologies especially someone
the bleeding get soft like web assembly
service workers or the systems
programming language rust and you know
if you have no idea what can browse the
system programming language do with the
open web will get there so hold that
thought and be following closely the
developments are and web assembly and
related technologies first some time now
and I also participate in the web
assembly community group that is driving
the evolution or the specification and
the expand
showing off Vegas Emily's feature set
and you know you could be too yeah you
don't have to be a compiler engineer or
work at a big influential company to be
able to do this the community group
operates until the w3c but it's open to
participation for anyone who is
interested if you just go to web asami
or click over to community you can
actually see all the many ways and learn
more about the many ways you could
contribute yourself in this talk I will
mention some of the many ways Mozilla
and people working at Mozilla
contributed to the creation and the
evolution of APIs Emily and I haven't
been involved with the work myself
there is now an entire dedicated team at
Mozilla for dedicated for working on the
beginning the leading edge of web
technologies and shaping web assemblies
future occasionally there if I have
positions open so if you would be
interested in being part of that work or
just want to learn more and about it
feel free to reach out to me and I'm
very happy to connect you them with them
before we dive in there is one more
caveat this is not a talk to teach you
about male hub lab assembly looks like
or how to generate web assembly code
there is great documentation a couple of
online paid grounds toriel's
if you decide already that this is
something that interests you this talk
is before that how do you get there how
do you know if you know how do you know
if if you should care about meth
assembly in the first place or why
should you care about web assembly in
the first place I've tried to show some
pointers to that and and if you do
decide to dive in after the talk there
is plenty of resources link later in the
slides due to the nature of technologies
discuss here with them there's always a
fair chance for any factual information
regarding yadda yadda nobody really
needs those disclaimers anyway the gist
of it is really just you know this is
highly volatile working progress stuff
so my change significantly even like any
time so before you push this into
production be sure to do your own
research and now with that
out of the way let's get back to our
favorite what technician who is about to
learn a valuable lesson couple hundred
pages into your newly acquired operating
manual you still seem to be stuck with
historical tropes from the era where
horse-drawn carriages roam the streets
all this time there is not a single bit
of useful information or anything
hands-on to be found on any of you
you've all systems like what a waste of
time in your son in federal raise you
angry toss the manual out onto the
corridor it flying right past one of
your elderly fathers you've apologized
profusely explaining your situation but
the ole mangies losses reply imports a
lifetime of wisdom oh dear
actually history provides the single
most precious kind of knowledge amongst
all there are invaluable lessons to be
learned from the context exposed by past
history and and this is true history
provides context Skepta sister world's
webassembly may often be rooted in the
fact that very few are familiar with the
technologies evolution influences goals
history in short of course we can't
really expect every developer to know
exactly what arduous journey have abbess
only has been through just to get where
it is today follow take a stab at
highlighting some and a few may
moderators some real issues of the web
platform and the solutions Robison aims
to provide
but wait lucky okay okay that map
assembly Decemeber suddenly that what is
web assembly well webassembly allows
code that was written in any of a wide
variety of programming languages to be
run securely on the web you take the
original source or source code of a
supporting programming language it is
compiled while using the web assembly
tool chain into your size and execution
speed efficient binary format that can
be used on the web executed safely at
close to negative speeds inside the web
browser close to native speeds here
refers to the fact that the execution
speed of webassembly compiled binary is
in many cases today are able to approach
the performance of the same source code
when it's compiled to the native
execution format of any given platform
it's fast safe execution on the other
hand means that refers to all the
various ways the during execution even
before execution the web assembly
runtime ensures certain security and
safety guarantees and these are strictly
enforced by the the runtime that runs
the web assembly code which means
running this 4-part occurred on the
user's machine which remains safe robust
and isolated from the rest of the page
while all the same time retaining all
the speed guarantees there is a let me
give you a golden tour of the history
before 2012 that was likely what I call
the primordial period you know dinosaurs
jQuery except JavaScript has been
steadily increasing in speed since like
2008 when v8 was released and and that
kind of like whipped up a browser verb
and like all JavaScript engines were
completing video they were trying to
increase the Indy Java at the speeds
into JavaScript it still wasn't enough
you can never have enough speed so smj
SD booted in 2013 it was created as a
easy to optimize javascript subset that
compiler stand when tools could directly
used to directly target
to generate code that we run in the
browser browser JavaScript engines had
specific optimizations for this kind of
code so they were fast in supporting
browsers it was even possible to compile
entire games and 3d engines with barely
any changes to the original source code
with a SMGs and just run them in the
browser at comfortable speeds it you
know it was a super fast but like it
worked really well it's spiritual you
could call spiritual successor
webassembly was released in 2015
all four major browsers actually shipped
support in a few months by time period
and it continues to be actively
developed now I not really going to
teach you an actual history lesson I
think it's more interesting to actually
take a look at some of them some of
these key features and have a look into
how they came to be so web assembly has
been built on a core principle that
could be summarized as augment not
obsolete this means that it focuses on
CMOS integration really striving to
extend and complement the existing web
platform rather than trying to compete
with it
in fact web asami modules are largely
in-app inert without the Emperor's
cooperation and don't expose any
features beyond those that are already
available to Jas better here means the
host environment so the browser is one
and such but there are quite a few other
Emperor's these days in the case of the
browser JavaScript everyone could save
it some simplification that we Baba
suddenly today you won't be able to do
anything that your JavaScript doesn't do
already but what you could do is you
could be probably put a potentially
faster after the embedder actually
instantiates your web assembly module it
allocates its own memory so your Marisa
module will have its own memory and the
embedding runtime will pass it all other
resources it needs this means dekes
imports an expert's the function calls
of requires and the live model module
after this itself is largely
self-contained and very has very limited
access to its
my man this is also known as the
principle of least privilege you only
want to provide a verse and a module
with access to resources that you you
are pretty sure the exactly needs and
nothing more API calls that need to
access the network or storage still need
to go to the JavaScript runtime or
browser api's and the module might have
hooks into the system api's and other
JavaScript bindings that were passed in
or it may request services such as more
memory by the JavaScript API but
embedding the embedding environment has
the offer to deny any or such requests
and which means wherever suddenly module
is highly dependent on the cooperation
of the embedder itself there are
actually even more implied proposals
that are there are of the web assembly
standard that are working towards
deepening and extending this integration
the cooperative and complementary
relationship actually predates web
assembly and I mentioned a SMGs was a
JavaScript subset and that is still
practically JavaScript but it's true
billions lies in the fact that the
changes required for supporting SMGs
optimizations were so minimal that our
browsers a large browsers wanted in so a
SMGs feature set was soon enough one of
the amount after the other all modern
browsers has shipped support for a SMGs
optimizations in their engines and the
cooperation of browser renders outlived
SMGs following its success the people
who worked on a SMG I started exploring
ways to and the work that is needed to
fix the SMGs inherent shortcomings for a
casual observer rabbits only is often
perceived as simple usually this refers
to the highly constrained features that
after shipping a SMGs it became clear
that some of the shortcomings cannot be
fixed without actually breaking the web
or just reimagining how the architecture
worked and this and this pong a lot of
explorations which eventually converged
into what we call the web assembly MVP
today develop assembly MVP this this
collaboration
made way for the web assembly MVP a
minor might
viable webassembly this was like a
robust extensible and future-proof
foundation that was laid out even in
this like diverse setting like you
Microsoft and Apple collaborating and
more contentious issues so there was a
minimal feature set and the more
contentious issues were set aside to
bake for some additional time or you
know P to be informed by some of the
early adopters this left webOS suddenly
in a constant state of evolution at the
and as the community group the designs
additional and enhancements based on the
implementers feedback but it's not the
only thing that mmm
that webassembly had had access to so
this so this might seem like that it was
not only the specifications resource
constraints that caused web assemblies
simplicity but it was also a deliberate
design choice the entire specification
is around 100 pages the instruction set
or the formal definition on the runtime
fits a single page and you know these
are some some star sentences out of the
specification itself no computation can
crash or otherwise misbehave in way is
not covered by the execution semantics
given in this specification this
robustness stems from the fact that the
web assembly runtime itself is very very
simple very straightforward this
property the safe and secure execution
at consistently fast close to native
speeds on all target platforms is
already hinting towards use cases beyond
the web but let us not get ahead of
ourselves and just talk a little bit
about what creators on the web had to
gain first almost a year have passed
since you first got your hand on your
first operating manual slowly but surely
you have become more handy around the
wall fixed this rebuilt that even gained
some notoriety for some of your
creations and
knowledge you occasionally get visitors
from other vaults seeking your advice or
experience you cannot not formally
remember that one time when you almost
not the poor fellow wall dweller
unconscious with the book and
frustration of being useless he smiles
he put the finishing touches a new piece
of machinery areas that verge to life
will lightly squealing as you push the
big green button why should you Babb
some more often it's not immediately
easy to see the benefit of technology
for once your own use cases but this
doesn't mean that it doesn't have any
industry testimonials finding the idea
use case you often takes time and rarely
happens without export to research and
experimentation industry testimonials
that report significant gains from
making use of FSM they almost never fail
to mention the vending road they have to
embarked on before the true benefits of
the technology started shining through
one of the first and Judah state most
major tools used in the ecosystem is I'm
scripting a c-plus Oz compiler for ASM
GSM web assembly in script is as old as
the entire ecosystem it was born and
then Co evolve alongside a SMGs when we
have assembly rolled around them
scriptum was one of the first tools
there to support it as an old
photographer format and script a made it
possible
easy even to compile large pre-existing
code bases libraries or even entire apps
sometimes millions of lines occurred for
the web not the most prevalent use case
web use case I'll admit but surely not
many of you had ever the sudden urge to
ship a triple-a game title to a vanilla
web browser I guess furthermore one of
these not offering these compiled
bundles you know you input a lot of code
you get out a lot of code and then up
tens or even hundreds of megabytes which
is a very scary figure considering the
ever-increasing bloat of the web today's
web sites all this is to say that this
inner certainly found or even funded
enthusiastic niche or following for
compiling for the browser but stay quite
far from becoming mange
even for those who not writing their own
games and astral class apps Emscripten
was still useful though one could write
a smallish module in a low-level
programming language like C or C++
compiler and use it in one's app to
surgically replace the performance
sensitive parts or use it to target the
web as one of their platforms one would
need to be able to write code in a
low-level language as well as write
JavaScript blue code to discuss two
modules rarely making these their most
reusable most portable pieces of code
ever written but it worked and Tripta is
not the only way though rust was one of
the first level first low-level Lang
systems languages that not only added
built-in support for web assembly target
but it took one sir took it one step
further and even doubled down and
supporting web assembly as a first-class
citizen
high-performance robots memory guarantee
stellar dogs sophisticated tooling an
extensive library of crates which is
third party modules building from the
npm on d on the fret of npm the that
could be imported and reused in an NPM
ish fashion made Russ an ideal choice
for someone who wanted to go deep but
unwilling to deal with C++ shenanigans
and you know if I'm preaching rust
that's because I am a huge fan so I
actually run a Russ conference ourselves
in Europe but if you don't want to go
that far there's a Russ Tokyo conference
happening in October so you should
definitely check that out of course not
everyone can or wants to learn a code
and a low-level language just to get
done assembly script is a provides
a language for this with much familiy
much more familiar semantics to all
JavaScript developers it's like a subset
of typescript and it serves as a much
lower barrier of friendship for creating
web assembly modules bespoke vasami
modules for web developers but to quote
Surma you don't need to understand all
of this to be a good web developer or
even to make good use of web assembly in
the first place Surma here in the
curator post he means that one doesn't
need to be using bespoke tooling just to
be able to create a wrap assembly module
in one project
and surely and Krypton or just using
pre-compiled Watson modules will go a
long way
we tools like assembler script and more
and more languages adding direct support
webOS purpose-built components will also
fry but even so it's hard to imagine
that offering webassembly modules will
become a mainstream task undertaken by
the majority of web developers and
that's perfectly fine it shouldn't be
the good news is one does not need to
know where but some really know about
web assembly to be able to benefit from
the new technologies ecosystem effects
proposals such as interface types
proposal the web I do bindings for the
ongoing
yes module integration currently
underway are working towards integrating
web assembly modules even more
seamlessly into the ecosystem in the
future one you would just import a
module using your favorite package
manager and it could and it could be
using web assembly under the hood
without the use of me even being aware
of the fact in the first place also even
if once production code won't end up
using web assembling one might still
benefit from WebAssign Levi bell tolling
that pack was one of the early
experimenters who had really good
results promising results trying to use
web asana for improving build times with
recent announcement around interface
ties by the muscle of AB assembly team
this already pretty futuristic sounding
paradise might be closer than you would
think
but let us have a glance at a slightly
even more further odd potential of
ramasammy well modern nature certainly
didn't stop coming up with bizarre new
ideas while you and your compatriots
were hiding in your cozy underground and
embrace of your vaults the swirling
display of almost a dozen tales and this
weird-looking animal as you emerge from
the Walt Amana evening this Channing
chills down your spine hard to call it
nightmarish as you're pretty sure you
could never even dream up such a strange
creature was it what is it is it
friendly
or is it hostile yes you will find out
soon enough
and sure enough you know it's tough to
predict the future of a nascent
ecosystem and webassembly is no
different we know if you don't really
know where all of it will end up until
we actually get there someone the
currently discussed post MVP features
garbage collection integration by by DL
integration till calls framing to name a
few
will make it possible for more languages
to target an inter interoperate with the
web this also includes more exotic once
you know languages that look much less
like JavaScript today and this is of
course not you if you live in a beige of
Babel and typescript and element reason
but babbling to make this process even
better and the edges are much faster
this is not only interesting from a
technology standpoint but also
increasing the diversity and
accessibility of developing for the web
allowing people to use whatever language
they feel the most comfortable with
rather than maintaining one particular
man on the web will make their Evette
platform much more resilient in the
future because of every language wanting
to run in the browser now suddenly you
have a common low-level layer they all
support people watch India about quote
something that is frequently observed
the web platforms gravity have given
Babis and the adoption an incredible
boost but not all use cases necessarily
need to involve the browser sure the
verb may be an excellent medium to
popularize the use of Ibis ami but the
same modules could later be adopted for
or in certain cases just ran out of the
box in any verb assembly compatible
right around time and well I would
restrict ourselves to the browser
wherever Semmy seems to have properties
that could come handy in various other
contexts to you wouldn't a would it be
possible to take some of the values of
sake and safe and secure sandboxing into
the in the browser
beyond the web at webassembly would it
be possible to still provide enough
power and flexibility required by all
the other use cases these are the
questions that are being explored in the
sister specification of webassembly the
web assembly system interface or huazi
for short what would it take to take
them assembly into the
restricted environments and providing
more capabilities still retaining most
of the safety guarantees that make the
map so unique what he is another
tremendous effort in reimagining certain
aspects of computing that we simply just
never question and take it as a given
that the proposal initially presented by
Mozilla but there's no word on in in its
own subgroup of the web assembly
community group and has a potential to
XM rebus and his usefulness in a
standardized way across a variety of no
map use cases and you know if you squint
at it the web embedded cloud at the end
of the day you might realize that what
seem based vastly different are actually
closer to each other than if Fang code
size constraints on a web app you know
reducing bytes and food while your may
correspond to requirements on edge
computing servers storage limitations or
sync time as well as microcontrollers
which has very limited memory we can
already see that it's not only that
webassembly is making its way to all of
these other platforms but it motivates
the creation of small self-contained
libraries that is feedback to a
transitive effect into the web ecosystem
and when we have all done done all that
why stop there what if anyone could use
the language of your choice program but
we didn't stop at programming languages
or different paradigms but we went all
the way to liberating programming of the
anglocentric human language what if
learning programming didn't have to
start with learning English or the Latin
alphabet
what if you weren't hindered by knowing
the difference between what and if is or
what a4 is what if you could write the
code entirely in Korean for example
Ramsay Nasir is the rather well-known
creator the first Arabic programming
language it's called Gelb
the phone doesn't support so you will
see the expanded URL on the on the
bottom of the slides he has an
astounding and far provoking talk from
the construct conference earlier that
explored ooh
almost there
a topic in our talk from deconstruct
conference earlier this year they're a
sport how a purely language agnostic
programming language where paradigm
could look like his design prototype
actually builds on web assembly as the
underlying machinery berroco storage
with code fragments living in the
distributed web accessible for anyone
with language specific metadata layered
above to give everyone a chance to write
and reuse code in their own native
tongue I don't have unfortunately any
links for this but as soon as the talks
recording welcome and I will put them
into the slides so it said web
assemblies potentials is seemingly
limitless in this case its properties
are low-level binary format and platform
agnostic disposition made it an ideal
choice for something truly fresh and
unique the only question is what the
only question that remains is what will
you do with that Asami yep thank you
very much I would like to find the
Missoula web assembly team for their
amazing work on the home base and in
general have you Hoffman P Lihue dobro
and gestures for had their help and
support and reviewing their stock Ling
Clark for the amazingly detailed cartoon
deep ties which are laying later on the
inner resources section
Jeff Womack Alexandra Pope and Ling
Clark who influenced in big ways just
the format of this talk and the
organizers and especially Susan for
putting up in me and figma who for their
incredible in browser director editor
built bit was him that uses Moslem
actually many of the graphics for their
stock was actually created almost all
graphics on further stock was created
but figma and but that I think I have
one more thing as you as I can see him
they're big zeros on there I wasn't I'm
bored I was running hurry blow out of
time so I couldn't fit a demo in there
anywhere and I was like but the walkie
you should have fitted demo in there so
I when I decided you is to you know make
the slice the demo itself so if all goes
well
you can see the slides link on the below
talked out flock dot is slash wasn't
such as golf Korea if I exit here you're
gonna see the slide talk it's just a
regular web page the regular web page
with regular images that has regular alt
tags on them so everybody can access it
with a screen reader you can see the
talk you can see all the notes when I
enter presentation mode javascript
imbibe assembly kicks in the online
version doesn't have the experimental
web assembly it has the experiment or
Java Script kit what happens here this
nope this effect that you see on the
stage is generated by webassembly
reinterpreting the webpage which means
you can use the web as you could use to
before and he can use the web assembly
to augment the currently existing
possibilities on the web so with that
thank you very much
and thank you again