hey everybody my name is Carter rabasa
and I'm a developer evangelist for a
company called twilio we're based in San
Francisco the company is based in San
Francisco but actually I hail from
Seattle so I'm incredibly happy to be
here amongst the Sun and the warmth of
florida and i'm here to talk to you
about a subject that is a very near and
dear to my heart and that is what are we
as a community going to do to make more
people around the world interested in
programming you know I I come at this
from a very you know unique perspective
not unique I come from it from my own
perspective you know I'm a father I
think a lot of people who sort of
understand the lack of desire to program
and are working to combat it you know
come at this from lots of different
perspectives you know some of them are
educators you know lots of people have
reasons to care about this issue but I
care about it because I'm a dad I have
two beautiful daughters the first one is
Katherine Katherine is three and a half
years old this photo was taken one year
ago at j/s comp in Scottsdale and she
may look like she's coding but she
really isn't I just it was more of a
photo op but a funny story about about
kids and conferences so hi conferences
have tons of stairs ok
plaintiff everywhere you know that light
stickers in my top so so who here was it
James comp last year awesome so you know
if Katherine wandered up to you and
stole stickers from you I apologize but
it's totally not rapala this is how they
are my other daughter is Emily this is
her she's gonna be two in august and my
why it's amazing my wife knows that I'm
adulterer and I'm an error and all
developers love mustaches for some
reason so she bought Emily this mustache
onesie which is why I'm choosing a
particular picture to show you guys but
but the point is you know I had this
becomes interested in this issue of
people not getting into coding and
become a father and I'm i intensely
think about the future much more than I
used to and I think about their future
and I think about what they like what
they might do or what they might want to
do what they might think that they're
actually capable of doing and you know
I'm a I'm a technical person their
mother is a technical person naturally
you know I think about you know whether
they will be technical people we all get
into the technology industry and
even if they watching with what kind of
barriers Monday days I also had two
daughters and my life are not gonna have
any more tolerant so I now I'm actually
aware the gender issues in our industry
intensely concerned about them and in
somebody that aside sometimes I feel
like I'm very my hands I because you
know I see a lot of people do not to get
bangs trying to dress this but the
numbers ourselves so I'm pull get into a
layer so I look look at the world is
living and I feel like this is this is a
bit of a name you know I apologize if it
feels play out but no software is he in
the world that is a titled an article
written by a guy named Mark Henry's he
published it in Wall Street Journal
couple years ago and it was pretty much
treatise on the fact that every single
industry in the world is being devoured
by software or software companies and
you don't have to look far to see how
great I was just watching that in my
life last Sunday night yeah well guess
who the biggest advertising company in
the world soccer it's google you know
look at think the largest retailer in
the world is standard life you know i
don't want to get caught up on whose
number
maybe there's some of the tables
slightly bigger than amazon by revenue
right now i have every confidence steps
in that place is a great example there's
going to be more video than anybody else
and maybe they're not technically as big
as some of the largest some of the
larger media conglomerates today but i
believe they will be no case our necks
are is both critically acclaimed and one
of the most profitable movie in movies
videos in the world and they're a
software company that are obviously
people that work ethics are that are not
developers but everyone in that company
is a software person they think about
how they can use software create
experiences for people and the list of
industries that's being destructive
today you know goes on and on then you
might say Carter you know that's a
sucker for all industries you know there
are plenty of industries that are
resistant to this disruption you know
whatever your pet industry my 80 or your
friends pet industry and I'm just I just
believe you're wrong you know you can
look at the automobile industry right
you may save yourself hey that's out
there Tesla's not a software company it
just make really sick amazing electric
vehicles they're very expensive and it
will very well designed and that people
love and you don't have to listen to me
and
you can listen to you on right talked to
three interviews deal on loss I'll tell
you the kind of people with Tesla hi
rose our software people the kind of
people who think that software can
enhance experiences for people when you
look at how roaster and model s ur
designed their massive computing
machines they collect gigabytes and
terabytes data send it back to Tesla and
Tesla uses the data to improve the
software for the cars in almost real
time and over longer destructions of
time these assaulted or produce better
designs so you know who is Elon Musk I
guess what he needs he founded paypal
you know he's a software person he's
applying what he knows in the softball
field to other industries and I this is
a pattern you know you're going to see
over and over and other industries this
is the UM this is the CEO of the company
I work for Jeff Lawson coolio was trying
to disrupt the telecom industry I'm
sorry reason or disrupt it's a crappy
word I should have fun without a word
but what is really trying to do this
he's trying to empower software people
to build amazing experiences for people
you know on top of the telecom
infrastructure you know think about the
worst phone you've ever used and some
company you work
god forbid a pay phone like you're as
old as me like you remember these
horrific experiences trying to dial
extensions get rowdy and connected like
those are experiences that are designed
and built and delivered by hardware
people coolio is trying to enable
software people to build much more
elegant user-friendly experiences and
that's incredibly important and you see
this you know not just in telecom
immunity so this with things as simple
as a remote control look at a cable or a
television remote control it's
disgusting but it's a byproduct of
Engineers of hardware engineers and how
they think about user interface and
solving problems look at the apple
remote it's beautiful tell Ian you know
it's multifunctional you can do lots of
things my wife had we recently bought a
house and one of the first purchase even
made the nest you know like why you know
I don't I don't know why write me on
some level I thought that the thermostat
that was there was just ugly and was
right in my dining room right we're
going to be entertaining people is his
ugly disgusting thing but also i think i
didn't know i didn't understand how to
use it was unapproachable to me and then
yes came along and created something
better and it increasingly better
accidentally they create something
better because their software people and
they apply to think about software to
the problem of thermostats and you're
seeing this over and over again so if
you believe what I've said so far
there's this consequence this is another
tired cliché that I happen to believe is
true you know programming is literacy
maybe it's not literacy today but it's
going to be literacy by the time you
know my daughters are older people take
literacy for granted I think people in
the US take literacy for granted I think
there are people who work for nonprofits
and people who are exposed to other
parts of the world that do not take
literacy for granted and understand how
critical literacy is to lifting people
out of poverty in 1440 when Gutenberg
invented the printing press only thirty
percent of continental Europe was
literate and you know now today the the
number is probably in the neo not you
know like you know 99 percent or
something
like that right and literacy isn't just
an abstract thing right literacy
directly translates to better health
greater social equality and increased an
economic prosperity so if that's what
literacy is and you believe that
programming knowing how to code is
becoming a form of literacy then you
should have pause for you know for the
state of the world today and and where
we're going here's another fact that i
find to be incredibly disturbing young
people are not embracing programming now
this is the freakiest thing of them all
right because anybody can look at a
demographic trend and kind of plot out
into the future that's easy I graduated
from high school in 1996 in the mid 90s
if you thought programming was stupid or
you thought email was stupid that was
totally okay like that was a rational
understandable you know opinion to have
about technology at that point because
email was esoteric and the web was brand
new and you could be forgiven for
thinking that you could spend your whole
life and never have to touch email
however the fact that today the fact
that it's 2013 and people still sort of
feel this way about technology and about
being able to wield technology is
unbelievably frightening I mean look at
these numbers you know like you could
other than some blips you know
enrollment in computer science is first
of all pathetic but also fairly flat
right I mean there's mild growth but
nowhere near the kind of growth you
would expect same with engineering like
how is this possible right how is it
possible that intelligent pragmatic you
know educated young people can look at
the world that they live in in the world
that they're likely to live in and
completely reject learning how to
program or learning anything about how
to wield a computer I find this like
baffling an astonishing and scary and
then of course you know the gender
inequality is you know is as dramatic as
well so so the question is you know
what's happening and I don't have
answers you know I'm trust me there are
people who spend more time thinking
about this than me I'm here to say that
we all need to work on fixing this you
know there's you know there are
incredibly smart people like John Resig
you know working at Khan Academy trying
to sort of reinvent education thank god
bless them thank God but I think the
problem is more pervasive than that I
think every single person in this room
can help can help address this problem
and not and more so I want and I want to
say something stronger right we have a
moral imperative to solve this problem
you know this problem is no different
than women suffer it i mean you know i
hate to draw direct comparisons but you
know to me it is in the same ballpark as
women's suffrage and other social issues
that people had to deal with in the past
because of the the fact that being
literate translates into how the quality
of the life that you can live this is a
Reginald Braithwaite I had to look up
his name I know Emma's Ragan Wald on
hacker news he's just a prolific writer
and you know he wrote a blog post
recently called Colin all hackers and he
you know he sees the world that I see
right he sees a world where you know
there's a massive amount of sort of
cultural exclusion of outsiders in the
technology industry and he wonders why
this is the case and what we need to do
to fix this he sees a very uneven
application of programming in the world
right so think of all the places you
could apply programming and software and
it's cool it's very lumpy right and this
is incredibly problematic and
essentially he he wrote a blog post
where he was calling out to hackers and
why was he doing that well hackers
hackers change the world
the way they change the world is that
they wrap around damage right they see
things that are broken and they try to
fix it's a it's just something that's
inside of a person if you if you think
of yourself as a hacker you're the kind
of problem that wants you're the kind of
person that wants to solve problems and
wants to fix things and wants to make
the world better and you sort of put out
this you know this sort of you know this
message asking people to really dive in
who know who here knows who brett victor
is a few of you i watch the video three
weeks ago that was one bleep called
inventing on principle and he informed
his talk quite quite a bit right Victor
is he working lots of places and he did
a lot of innovative you I work at Apple
and he there's this hour long video on
the internet called inventing on
principle where he's giving a talk much
better than this talk by the way where
and you know and I have an appendix of
links and you guys should go check it
out we're basically he says it is
morally wrong for people who build tools
and technology and platforms to build
them in such a poor way that ideas are
allowed to die what he's trying to say
is that we are we are all created we're
all creators in some some sense of that
word right we're no a programmer is no
different than a sculptor or painter or
writer someone who creates something and
there's this human need for creators to
have an immediate connection to like
what they're creating so like a painter
every stroke there see they're getting
feedback like real-time feedback on what
they're doing same with a sculptor
sculptor same with a writer and Brett
looked at the world of being a
programmer and you know looked at the
sort of the process of writing code in
an IDE and then compiling that code and
then maybe deploying that code to a
device and then running the code and in
some cases the Delta is massive right
and you don't find out until five
minutes later that something's wrong or
that you know that you did something
wrong and that that breaks things for
the programmers that are a flawless
never make mistakes or be incredibly
patient
it's not a problem because if you don't
make mistakes you won't make any
mistakes and if you're incredibly
patient you don't care you'll just wait
the problem is that most of the world is
not like that most of the world when you
look at when you when you look at the
dropout rates in computer science and
engineering these people are at least
initially interested in these fields but
then they drop out they quit and why do
they quit well there's lots of reasons
but i think that the state of tool in
today's part of the reason that people
quit they try to do something and they
don't get immediate feedback on on what
they're doing or the result of what
they're doing and it essentially causes
them to give up on it and then their
idea dies right and that is it's wrong
because that person could have an idea
that changes the world but it died
because we didn't give them good enough
tools to use so i think i mentioned that
i don't have you know a definitive
solution for this I don't think anybody
does but I have I have this thought that
um that better api's can help write that
better api's can be a part of this
larger story better tooling can out
there's lots of things that can help I
happen to spend a lot of time thinking
about api's so I'm sort of approaching
this problem from somewhat of a specific
perspective so the question so first
question you'll like what is an API and
I'm not trying to devolve into that
argument you can the truth is actually
everyone has their own specific
definition of what an API is and people
argue about it and it's like you know I
hate these arguments I think we all know
what a languages know we're all
presumably JavaScript developers you
know we understand that languages have
syntax and two met semantics and have a
grammar and to me like an API is just
anything on top of that
a well-defined interface to enabling
somebody to do something that they want
to do above and beyond the language
itself helps you solve problems you know
so let's say we're on a web page and we
want to find the boxes that are checked
on a web page right well there's this
awesome API called the JavaScript Dom
API just kidding it's not awesome at all
sucks and that's what the code looks
like all right that's gross right now it
works and it's logical you know you can
kind of look at it but that's an insane
number amount of code to write to do
something relatively basic it's also
error-prone right because even if you
know JavaScript like did you know that
you can't use for each to iterate
through a node list maybe you know that
from experience like from the terrible
experience of trying it and having to
fail but this is just it's just not a
good API it's not good API design you
know contrast that to the jQuery API
look i'm not i'm not trying to sell
jquery right a lot of people moving away
from jQuery and for totally valid
reasons but that has nothing to do with
the design of its API just has it has to
do with the kind of problems that people
are trying to solve you know this is
what it takes to do this in jQuery once
again I don't find it surprising at all
that John Resig is tackling education I
think if you find an API in the world
that you find to be elegant and easy and
understandable and pleasant to use the
person who designed it probably cares
about your your experience using it and
probably cares about education and
probably wishes that more people would
use that API so then their web AP is you
know we all we all know what web api zar
we're all familiar with them this is
this is roy fielding so Roy fielding
wrote an incredibly famous dissertation
on unrest on rest and that works spawned
a multitude of companies like twilio and
many many others that provide these
restful Web API s and these are these AP
eyes are amazing they're amazing for
lots of reasons and i'm not going to go
into all of them but you know they
a they took something I actually come
from an era kind of prior you know prior
to the the onslaught of restful api is i
come i remember soap does anyone here
remember soap okay oh my god yeah like
shocker that soap didn't catch on right
but there's a there's a reason it didn't
catch on it wasn't accessible it wasn't
understandable it was monolithic it had
all these terrible characteristics that
the big company didn't care about
because they didn't care about the
pervasiveness of soap services you know
they cared about solving their
particular problems and charging you
like a ton of money you know for the
privilege of having that having those
problem solved so I'm not surprised so
there's no surprises so failed it wasn't
democratic you know restful api so very
democratic you know even a novice
developer can understand and interact
with with a restful api the twilio api
is is an example of this so you know we
like to say a twilio you know if you're
if you're a web developer you're
automatically a twilio developer and
there's a means part of that is
marketing but part of that is true you
know this is this is some node some node
code to send an SMS it's it's I mean if
you know in reality is like two lines of
code to send an SMS I was in Vancouver
and I was sitting next to some kids some
sophomores in college that had never
heard of twilio I pulled out my my
computer and I just asked them hey
what's your cell phone number man and i
sent them SMS right in front of them I
couldn't believe I mean why I can
believe it now right but I mean in
writing if you really think about like
they were blown away like I might as
well like started walking on the ceiling
as far as they were concerned because
they simply they did not grasp that that
was something that they were capable of
doing and I think that's true for for
way more people than we realize process
that that's example of sending an SMS
out processing an SMS so twilio makes
makes use of web hooks which means that
every time an SMS comes in to twilio we
send a post request to your web
application and your web application
returns with markup in this case as web
developers you're all familiar with
markup like you're familiar with HTML
the only difference is with Willie oh
you just you generate some XML but
you're still generating mark up every
single tool that you use to generate
markup every part of your tool chain you
can still use it
need to generate a little bit of XML so
this is where you know we kind of come
to the end of this talk and I honestly
believe that every single person sitting
here can help solve this problem right
can at least take a small step towards
solving this problem you do not have to
be the chief architect for some you know
restful api company in order to like
make the world a better in order to
create better api's and make the world a
better and more accessible for place for
people trying to get into programming
you know like first of all think about
think about the industry that you work
in right like I don't care what it is
like try to make the world try to make
more of the world more of the surface
area of the world addressable to
programming you know jeff says you know
if you can if you can turn a problem
into a software problem like you can
solve it right if you can find a way to
like make more things that you work on
addressable to programmers you know
you're going to be able to harness you
know all the program is in the world to
sort of solve some of the problems that
are in your industry improve the
accessibility of your AP is like I'm
talking every API right like if look if
you write a function or method and that
function is going to be called by
someone on your team or someone in your
group or someone at your company or
someone outside of your company like
literally if you're defining a method
signature like think really hard about
it think ten times as hard about it as
you normally do just as an experiment um
you know I you know I I've started doing
this myself right like I have a ton of
crappy code out there and I used to
think it didn't matter because it was
just my problem you know that's not true
you know like the with more more and
more people looking at code on github
you know people are learning like how to
code from you know code snippets that
you would never think that they would
look at and if they're bad code snippet
so they're poorly documented or they
don't make sense or they don't provide
instant feedback then they make it get
to stir discouraged maybe decide you
know screw this I don't want to do this
this is a crazy esoteric field for you
know
masochists and that's terrible right so
you know I think I think we all have a
role to play here and lastly please
commit yourself to helping more people
learn how to code a twilio every single
person who joins the company no matter
what role they have has to write an
application their first week on the job
that salespeople marketers customer
service administrative support it
doesn't matter who you are like you have
to write an application and that's and
you might think that's really daunting
and like holy crap but that's unfair but
it actually isn't because everyone at
the company is part of our culture and
everyone at the company rallies to help
that person define what it is they want
to try to do and help teach them how to
do it like companies should do stuff
like this and it also doesn't have to be
a company thing like find someone in
your life that is curious about
programming and expose them to it and
talk to them about it and learn from
them what is so inaccessible and so
daunting about it and see what we can do
to you know to kind of help make a help
make the world a better place so that's
it thank you very much
you