oh my name is Helene do km from medellin
colombia and malia developer bypass
I'm milli working in education I work
for a company called note source it's
like a main consultant frame of no gsl
around the world and I'm working
creating like education material and
also working mostly with the JavaScript
community in Latin America I'm littering
like a community meta-gene I'm also
doing like my hobby and the passion are
related to JavaScript so I'm a full-time
JavaScript developer and evangelist and
I get paid doing what I love so it's
great whoa javascript is all around the
wall I mean it's at the most important
language on the on the web and right now
it's getting like more more adoption to
other people so it's not only for
creating web application but as I was
talking today in jazz camp and we can
also a program or code revolts
electronics and music video a lot of
interesting topics using javascript so
it has a really bright future right now
we are seeing seeing right now the whole
adoption of JavaScript and I help like
this is a really good at technology to
bed in and to to learn and to get
involved with well I was talking about
no boats and the community of no birds
no boats is a way where you can like
program electronics and robots using
javascript say was talking about the
notebook community all around the world
mainly in Latin America what we are
doing in Latin America bringing more
people into technology and into coding
through hard work or true the maker
philosophy and that's were i was talking
today at jay's come and also did some
demonstration lots of different
experiments and robots I be I've been
working on my free time but this is my
first time in Argentina and I love it so
far it's really nice seria bueno side is
the people are so welcoming and all the
architecture dog and tweaked an
architecture I really love that
we are planning to spend like two weeks
here when Osiris and to help the the
Buenos Aires community and to keep
working on that because this is what we
love to do and we were enjoying the city
and the country very good well Jacob has
been amazing and part of the organizing
group of gays come colombia and we are
organizing the event for next year and
october 2015 and if you put like raise
the bar for us because we need to do
like Maura for the more word to have
like a conference as good and as awesome
as this one so I'm impressed with all
the organization on the whole team
behind it it's amazing congratulations