sunscreen I so I'm Ferrin a director of
engineering and moving world's black
matrix everywhere so on the internet
this is where the slides are it's only
place on my slides I should have put it
in the back so just a little brief
overview I'm going to be discussing
server inject and register server
methods and the happy framework I hope
by the end of the framework you'll know
when and how to use both of them so the
inspiration of this talk came from you
know discovering issues while i was
developing our product for the public
launch too long damn right we used a
server inject as a stopgap so we made a
mistake essentially we found bugs before
we went live I kind of the backstory is
is that you know I wrote a lot of the
API a co-worker was going to work on the
front-end app but then we had some
designer issues and he had to jump on
that so you know I think what it was is
you know I was going through the
documentation of happy and I was like
what can I do to you know do this front
and stuff and I saw seven inject was
like I could do it with that i wish i
would have gone down a little bit first
but if i didn't do that i'm going to be
here talking about it today so so server
inject it uses the shot module for
performing injections without actually
making any network connections so it
takes two arguments options call back so
options you can either send it a string
or not object some of the properties of
the objects are method URL headers
payload credentials simulate I wrote a
bunch of stuff up there I'm going to be
talking about like elsewhere
then there's a callback which gets one
function which is an object and uses
status code headers payload wrap a load
just a raw object and then the results
and I'll talk a little bit about that
later so when and why you should use
server inject great use case testing
here I have some code that kind of just
goes over here you can kind of see like
you you a we're calling the URL to me
and we're looking at the status code see
if it's 200 ok and then we're also
looking at the available property set on
it and we want to make sure it's set to
know and it's basically that so I feel
like I'm talking really really loud
because of things in my bag do things
that server sorry so also it's useful
when you're doing things in your routing
that is very complex and you can't
really abstract it into a method also
you by using server inject you avoid
network stack and potentially you can
also isolate networking issues that way
the credential object is really
interesting too because you can bypass
you know authenticated strategies using
it so when you shouldn't use it anytime
you're not testing I'd oh so I as we
found out and all right some of the
issues we found res results not always
available and I actually found this
issue when i was using seek lies and i
don't remember the details of why so I
had to use res that payload which kind
of sucked because i had to parse it so i
can look at the data and then I had to
reinter to the client and that's a lot
of waste you know memory was also I kind
of kind of thought that there's a little
bit of an implicit assumption that
whatever you're injecting on you're
assuming that it's correct and if it's
not like because you're using server
inject and that's not correct there's so
much overhead and that can cause you
know some debugging issues so yeah as a
result you know once I figured this out
once I I saw some of the issues another
issue we had was because the the the way
it encoded on res dot payload that so
happy is utf-8 when I translate over the
wire its ASCII and awesome because of
that level in the discussion or whatever
it we would see like encoding issues on
our site and so then that's when we were
like how we got a code refactor we need
to use server methods so registered
methods they're awesome because you can
use them to you know share common
functions by attaching them to your
server object this means you don't have
to require common add modules all over
in your plugins you know so makes your
code more dry you can also cash your
methods which is really awesome with the
happiest native caching and you can
change this context within your methods
so you need it of course give your
method a name and you'll be able to
excess it later through server methods
name or if you're in kind of a handler
you'd have to do I think request server
methods name so a neat feature I thought
was that you can register names such as
user dot get and I'll register it as a
nested object and I think this is a
great way to actually kind of create
like a kind of method namespace you know
like here you see that I binded it to
our happiest equalised user model and
then use the sequel eyes finding count
all function
so you also have to give it a function
and it takes this format it's an
arbitrary amount of arguments with your
next call back and then the next is
pretty standard you know error first
your result and then optional TTL for
when you want your cash to expire on
that object you also can give it some
objects objects are buying cash call
back generic key cash is the normal as
river cash so that's pretty
straightforward call back i haven't used
this but apparently you can make your
function method survey method
synchronous and then you're out your
call bak actually takes a little bit of
a different form and then there's the
generate key for when your methods don't
actually return you know a string or
bullying or a number or JSON object so
then you figure out a way to do that and
then you could actually utilize the cash
so how do we do that how do we actually
make a server method there's two two
main ways as a separate parameter so you
define your function and then you
register it that way surfer method foo
foo go okay and then you could do it as
an object which I prefer this method
better because it see the tree just an
object name method and options then of
course you could do it again as an array
of objects so why should you use server
methods you know if you want to use dry
again you avoid having to require all
the common modules everywhere in your
code and just use it on the server
object so and then if you also want to
cash here your items it's a little bit
more difficult and doesn't really work
on sir inject
now when it should be used if it doesn't
fit your use case which means complexity
or if you only perform the operation
once because there's a slight over had
to just call the server methods so just
before I close I did a little bit of
code here like I really wanted to kind
of get into like like what we're looking
at but I couldn't really figure out like
how to get the actual like memory stack
but I could get the latency so this is
what I did with the Linux AV tool and as
you can see like just this coin get
users directly you know takes about gift
gives you about 4.33 requests per second
when you do with the wrapper which I
have directly from this code right here
you know just wrapping that code and its
way much slower it's terrible and then
if you do via method you can see that
it's a little bit less performant than
calling it directly and then when you
actually use the cash it's just insane
ninety-eight percent of the requests are
under 50 minute 150 milliseconds so use
the cash whenever you can oops nevermind
okay so in summary you serve in jax for
your tests in a happy frame work
elsewhere only if and only if your logic
is too complex to be abstracted it is
serving method use server methods if you
need to use the same pieces of code and
multiple locations and bonus points if
you speed up your responses with caching