[Music]
[Applause]
alright this is easy because this is
clearly the most exciting thing that's
happening right now is in here oh I need
bailiff people oh I almost forgot the
most important prop of the talk is of
course the Fox so hi welcome everybody
community lounge and you two go right
into the middle of things so my talk
title supposed air do we have the screen
is supposed to be have cake and eat it
too and I really wanted to talk about
how there are really two communities die
that that I can Frank to be standing
here in the first place and one of those
communities happens to be so I started
speaking four years ago this this
picture is like 2015
I was doing my day job as a front-end
engineer and I discovered meetups I
started going to meetups I was like hey
what about what about speaking at one so
four years ago I did my first talk it
was probably the same length as this one
is going to be but there was really two
communities that that shaped my path
from there on later that year I went to
a event that's called Mozilla festival
kind of Indy the Berlin version of the
same festival missile festival happens
in London a lot of the Mozilla
contributors here you see a picture of
Mozilla reps these are the worldwide
Mozilla contributors who are shaping and
volunteering to to talk about Mozilla
and I got accepted as part of that I
don't even ask me why and I made so many
friends as part of this group some of
these friends yeah I was just hanging
out this past few days hosting me in
their apartment
because why not crushing their couches
just these days so I got to experience
some of these are actually people are
actually here around us today so this
kind of made me I this is this picture
took and and Copenhagen
if you ever beat the castle at it's a
had friends who were photoshopping me
into this Cape of the web being the map
Savior I think this is this is probably
what what makes your heart go when yours
a mozillian but there is another
community not just the Missoula
community there are large community that
shaped my path but that was the
JavaScript community if you have been
here for say it's a scoff you know that
guy
this was web rebels to this date one of
my favorite conferences and to this date
the comp my favorite conferences are
never attended I was sitting at home
watching the livestream tweeting at
people are having the most fun time of
my life
eventually this you like the JavaScript
community and muscle comedic converted
into something that's called missile
attack speakers the Mozilla Tech
speakers community is missile is
supporting some of its developers so
much to deliver contributors and helping
them spread the good word and helping
them grow in speaking about technical
topics teaching people and this is one
of the first picture with me and some of
our Mozilla contributors one from Poland
and one from Tunisia
at the very start of the program this
program actually got me to an obscure
little conference never happened more
than once in Dortmund this very
disparate country got invited after a
lot of troubles and a lot of like sweat
and that excitement and it met even to
this day when I think back to that
conference
it basically shaped the entirety of Who
I am today some of these people I can
affect my my whole on stage presence
these people trusted me these people
trusted me to go onstage and demo
hardware that I barely knew about in the
back of this picture Dan Kelly I'm one
of the developer evangelists at Mozilla
I can call my colleague and friend now
and you know we hold a workshop and this
was the brink of Firefox service
becoming a thing and I was in the big
stage and from that on I cannot like a
five minute talk a 50 minute dot
wouldn't be enough to tell you all the
stories of meeting people in Oslo and
visiting their conference in bonus iris
and making friends all around the world
and making lifelong connections and
friendships along the way and eventually
I got you just confit you not not much
longer later I actually have the same
hoody with me today like the JavaScript
community made a comeback this is this
is from a conference they lost reject
jazz I guess we had their last loss
reject Reyes a few days ago as part of
Berlin joyous but this was the last
region Jay s conference me attack
speaker representing both the Mozilla
community and the JavaScript speaker
budding JavaScript speaker representing
the the JavaScript community so you
might ask yourself okay what is this
arrey have-your-cake- and-eat-it-too
thing and the thing actually goes back
to OTS cough this conference I actually
was visiting family in Cyprus and they
sent this mysterious picture to the
organized
and they are like what is death some of
these organizers to this day like you
can see a renu-it reunion picture for
just a few days ago are my best friends
we organize conferences together with
some of these people just to this date
and this all goes back to a cake that I
actually got in Cyprus I went to a cake
cook a patisserie in Cyprus found one
and ferry the cake in hand luggage into
dis conference to give a guess to the
conference that trusted me with Widger
the gave me their trust and that gave me
a chance so I can stand today here so if
there is anything I could ask you is
give people a chance and lift other
people up because who you are here you
have a privilege of being able to lift
other people up so other people can
stand up these were stages later on
thank you
[Applause]