so my name is Phillip I'm gonna talk to
you about messing around with the
netbook well messing around with
javascript in the Dom to figure out
different network characteristics the
title here is smaller than what's on the
on the website because that wouldn't
actually fit in my slides so I'm gonna
get started everyone here web developer
yeah alright so the web basically runs
on three protocols HTTP at the top
running on tcp and that override be
below that it couldn't really be
anything but we have this dry of
protocols made by three guys over the
course of maybe 20 years starting from
1974 on incidentally they have just one
beard between them so we'll surf bargain
and Tim berners-lee windsurf see anyone
at the beard later on we got JavaScript
and one one guy with one beard and
discovered the good parts so we're gonna
throw all of that out of the window and
play with the nasty parts all right so
number one latency who knows what
network latency is great so I have 30
minutes and I have a lot to cover who
wants to time me 71 I've got six
different topics to go through so let's
hope five minutes per topic right so
let's do latency and let's see if I can
keep it under five minutes so this this
is an image from cable map that info
it's looking at one of the undersea
cables between that goes between Germany
and the u.s. typically it takes light
about 23 milliseconds to go from Berlin
to New York if you put that through
fiber takes 35 milliseconds because
light travels at sixty-six percent of
its speed within 50 now if you actually
need to go send a network signal you
need to send light there send it back
and actually do it two more times
because of losses within different
devices so that 35 milliseconds actually
becomes something like 70 milliseconds
so if we try to ping from one end to the
other that's more or less what you'd see
70 to 80 milliseconds this is fine we
know this because of physics we know
this if we actually see two cities we
know how long it's going to take but
what happens if you're sitting on your
web server you have no idea where your
users coming from all you know where
they're coming from based on the IP
address but you don't know what route
they taking to get to your box so you
want to do some other something else to
measure the actual latency and that's
what we're going to look at so latency
of round trip time which is what we
really care about is the time it takes
to send a packet and get a response back
from the user so we look at an HTTP
request it looks like this the client
sends a get request and the server
handles that request and sends back a
response now if your get request is
small enough it should fit within a
single DCP packet so one HTTP request is
actually one tcp package and if your
response is small enough as well it
should fit within another TCP packet so
you'll get back a response and you'll
get back an acknowledgement as well with
that everyone okay so far so how would
we measure this time any guesses using
only javascript within the browser
bread
right so that's actually exactly what my
code does so I take the start date set a
timer that measures the male's
milliseconds of the current time then
load an image from wherever my server is
and on the onload I measure the end time
take the difference and that should be
the round-trip time right who thinks
that's right anyone else everyone else
thinks it's wrong why do you think it's
wrong
browser needs processing time we so that
the browser's going to file the onload
as soon as the the image is available
this is not being displayed on screen so
it's it's just as long as it's available
there the browser is going to fire the
armlet so it's not a problem with
browser processing time the server could
require some processing time to actually
load that image from disk but let's say
we do this for every single user we do
it more than once that image is going to
be cached in ram so we don't even worry
about that anyone else so that's right
the time it would take to download the
image we can make our image small enough
so I typically use a 1 by 1 GF which is
35 bytes in size 35 by x + ahead of 312
bytes is totally less than thousand 24
bytes which is more or less what a TCP
packet is so even with downloading image
it should still fit in a single TCP
packet and we can't get smaller than
that perfect so a problem is a TCP
handshake right so we're not really
measuring just a round-trip time we are
measuring TCP handshake plus round-trip
time so whenever you make a first
request to a server what happens is your
client sends a syn packet that's one tcp
packet the only thing it has a flag
that's a sin saying synchronized and the
server response saying I acknowledge
your sin and I send you my own sin and
then the client has to respond saying I
acknowledge Austin so now we've come
come pleated this three-way handshake
and our connection is established and
that's when you can start sending data
so we actually sent three packets to and
fro before we send up first get requests
so what we're doing in this case is
actually measuring the time of five
packets right and not two packets so how
do we get around that any guesses
sorry handshake first how do I measure
when my hand shakes dance how do how do
I measure when the handshake is done
alright pretty good keep-alive so let's
keep that in mind keep alive anyone else
fetching two images right so fetch two
images with keep alive so you guys are
actually have you seen my slides before
alright so basically that's what we do
we we rely on the fact that HTTP 1.1 by
default has connection keep-alive so
what that means is when a client makes a
request to a server it'll keep that TCP
connection open for a certain amount of
time typically defined by the default
keep-alive time I think that's between
15 and 30 seconds depending on your web
server so this client makes a connection
to a TCP connection so it does the
handshake and once that handshake is
done it'll keep that connection open for
15 seconds and make as many requests as
are necessary on that same TCP
connection so what we do is we do one
request do I get that that would
initiate the first handshake the onload
would file after the image is downloaded
and then do another request right and
that second request does not need a
handshake because it's going over the
same TCP connection as long as we start
that request after the first image was
downloaded so the code to do that is
slightly more complicated but not too
much we go through two images on the
onload event of the first one we
download the second one is the code
clear to everyone if you have any
questions with the code can ask me but
basically that what it's doing is it
loads an image and the onload event
measures the time and then loads the
image again we throw in some cash
busting code in there because we don't
want the second load to come up from
cash we wanted to always come from
server so now we have to the same image
loaded twice from the same server the
round-trip time is really the or rather
the latency is the time it took the
second image to load and then now that
we know the latency if we subtract that
from the time it took the first image to
load we also know how long it takes the
TCP handshake to happen right any
questions about that so now we can
compare because now we know it takes
three packets to do a TCP handshake and
two packets to download an image
typically that image should be
two-thirds of the so RTP should be
two-thirds of TCP so that makes sense
any questions so far how am i doing on
time nine minutes so i'm good i finished
two parts in nine minutes the third part
is going to be tough so you'll notice
that we ignored dns lookup time here
alright the first connection was
actually it doesn't just do a TCP
handshake it also needs to do a DNS
lookup and we're going to ignore that
for now all right we'll assume DNS has
been cached but we'll deal with that
later assuming a half time so if you
notes on this I use a 1 by 1 jiff 35
bytes in size and experimented with
different types of images the first
thing i tried was just in a 204 head up
back 204 is no content so I don't
actually send any data the problem with
that is it will fire an on error event
and not an onload event does anyone see
a problem with an on-air event I could
still measure the time when the ordinary
files right
exactly I might get a different error
right what happens with me users network
isn't connected the network drops after
he loads my first page so I'm going to
get an on error simply because you
couldn't connect to the server or there
could be a DNS outage or any other
outage that's going to cause that error
which won't actually measure the latency
so I definitely want an onload event I
then tried a PNG with which was zero
bytes in size then also doesn't work it
also fires a non era another interesting
with thing with a 2-0 for is uncertain
mobile devices it doesn't fire any
events so there's no one error no unload
nothing it might it'll actually loads up
but it doesn't doesn't fly any months so
this was the smallest image I could
possibly get that actually fits within a
TCP packet and also fires an onload
event files on all right so third one
I'm gonna do now is network throughput
does everyone know what network
throughput is how does it differ from
bandwidth
after an hour and bites a dog right
right right so you think of it like the
station wagon thing right you can put
hundreds of magnetic tapes or other data
in a station wagon and drive from one
place to another and you'll have really
high bandwidth right because you get so
many petabytes of data across but the
latency is so bad so yeah effective
throughput is not very good if you take
the whole amount of time that it takes
to get the data across what we're
actually going to measure is how much
how much effective use of a network
connection we can use so even if i have
3 mech data connection i might only be
able to use one megabit to actually
download data because of various reasons
so it should be fairly simple to
calculate right download something large
and measure how long it takes to
download that this is everyone okay with
that oh do you see holes in this
approach
alright so looking at that it should be
fairly simple we take the same code that
we used before just use a larger image
and instead of just taking the time we
take the size so we use an image of
known size divided by the time I also
multiply by 1000 here because time is in
milliseconds and I want kilobits
kilobytes per second or kilo bits per
second depending on how I store the size
so does this make sense the do you think
this will work in all cases
tcp or IP packets overhead yeah there is
going to be some overhead do we care is
it who here is a network engineer not a
web developer right so as web developers
we don't care about TCP overhead we care
specifically how long does it take if I
have an image that's 200 kilobytes how
long is it going to take for my user to
download that so I don't really care
about tcp / even though yeah I know it's
going to be there and my throughput for
me as a web developer is how how much
usage my HTTP data is going to make off
the network connection so the problem
with this it works in some cases it
works as long as your image is small
enough so naturally I would have
finished the talk now if it were that
simple the problem is something called
TCP slow start who's familiar with TCP
slow start you want to tell us what it
is yeah start to the lower rate right
the client accepts the highway right
until the client drops again ready these
people we start the connection and
alright so yeah DCP slow start was
basically created to avoid network
congestion let's assume that a server
sends data as fast as it possibly can
now typically servers are way faster
than service network connections are way
faster than a home users network
connections so if they just throw out
data as fast as they possibly can the
network is going to get clogged
somewhere in between and everything else
is going to slow down so what servers do
is they'll send two packets first and
then wait oh well any end of a TCP
connection will send two packets and
then wait for an acknowledgement and
when it gets the acknowledgement it says
if it gets the acknowledgement within a
certain amount of time it says okay this
client can actually handle that speed so
let's try increasing the speed so it'll
double it and keep keep increasing it as
as long as it keeps getting
acknowledgments within the amount of
time now if any acknowledgement actually
doesn't come through in the amount of
time the the other end will assume that
all right the send is congested it's
buffers are full it can accept more data
so I'm going to back down and reduce the
reduce the number of packets i can send
so by default the window size is set to
2 which means i'm going to send two
packets and then wait for an
acknowledgement and when i get the
acknowledgement and then going to send
four packets and wait for an
acknowledgement and so on so the problem
is we have all this dead time right
between sending the second packet and
second sending the third packet we're
doing nothing the network's not being
used at all and so we're not really
measuring how good that network
connection is we are measuring for just
opening a connection at that point of
time how good it is not how how good
it's going to be going forward so we
need to do something else a simple thing
is use a resource that fits within a
window right so something that fits
within two packets is that going to work
any guesses can we use maybe a 2
kilobyte image and say I'll measure the
time it took a two kilobyte image to
download
the problem is we have a wide variety of
network connection types that vary in
the effective bandwidth they provide to
users so you use a 2 kilobyte image on a
3 megabit connection it's going to
download really fast it's not going to
use up any of the bandwidth at all you
want to use a large image for some
network connection that fast but what
happens if you use a net large image and
does that it yeah that's it so try and
use a different image so start off with
a small image that's going to fit within
that to packet size and then once that
is downloaded I'll say ok now my window
size is going to be increased so let's
now put in an image that's going to fit
within 4 packets and once that downloads
then try loading an image that's going
to fit within eight packets and so on
alright so keep increasing it until I
reach a level that I'm comfortable with
so this is more or less the code that
would do that it goes from multiple
images and calculates the time it would
take to download each of them and then
says okay that's my effective bandwidth
looking at the largest image the problem
with this is slow Network really large
image say 100 megabyte image on a 64
kbps connection how long is that going
to take to download even with a full
window size it's going to take a long
time the users just going to be waiting
for you to do your measurement so not a
good idea so what we end up doing is
let's say we we throw in a time out and
say alright I'm going to download it
still download images in ascending or
size but I'm going to set it timeout
value for each of them so if an image
times out if it takes longer than say
point eight seconds or one second to
download I'm going to say ok this
network connection cannot handle an
image larger than the size and that's
where I'm going to stop so we go from we
actually tested with images starting
from 11 kilobytes going all the way up
to six hundred megabytes so we have
images of those sizes and we set a time
upset between 800 milliseconds and
twelve hundred milliseconds
so if an image times out we say that's
the last image we're going to download
measure the time it takes that image to
load and this is what we're doing here
so we have a set time out there when the
time out files we just set say that this
image expired the time out if the images
on load actually files clear the time
outs so that we don't we don't fail it
and then we end the test if any of the
images time up so when an image time's
up we say that's the end of the test
let's go ahead and start measurement at
that point of time so do our
calculations at that point the
calculation code is actually this pretty
much the same as what we saw in the
first case just take the size of the
largest image and the time it took to
download and do either to get the
bandwidth so you think that's good
enough right all right how would we deal
with that checksum the image
how do you check someone image on the
client-side canvas I guess throw it into
canvas get the image data and check some
all right I've never tried that so I've
never tried that so I don't know but
actually thinking about mobile networks
we actually saw a problem not just with
mobile networks but mm different kinds
of networks if you run the same
bandwidth test multiple times you're
going to get different results all
rights simply because there's network
jitter there's other things happening on
the network so you can't really rely
just do a single test and say that's my
users network throughput I'm going to
store it in a cookie and assume that
that's how fast the network is every
time they come to us so I'm not going to
show you the code here but what we end
up doing is statistical sampling we run
it the same test multiple times at
different times and then take the median
of all of them so we don't take the
fastest we don't take the slowest we
take a median and say that's more or
less an order of magnitude of the users
network throughput so typical error
rates we've seen is actually twenty-five
to thirty percent in actually getting
the network throughput whereas in terms
of latency we see an error 4.5 to one
percent so you can see the difference in
mesh in accuracy of the two different
measurements right yeah so the code is
actually fairly big if you do want to
see the code for this it's in boomerang
project which is on github and have a
link to that at the end of my slides
right so number for DNS how am i doing
on time eight minutes to go so we spoke
about DNS briefly in the beginning
anyone know how we're going to calculate
the NS time
no one
right so yeah that's that's more or less
what you do is make to request one with
the post name and the second with the IP
address or the other way around and take
the difference between the two so time
with DNS minus time without DNS which is
the same code again that we've used
except we have different host names
right so this works in many cases except
what happens if the DNS the host name
was already cashed in browsers DNS is
there some way to flush the cache
you can do it is that gonna happen
immediately yeah someone else I have
they Hannah look up an invalid hostname
which will return a non era and you
that'll that'll have written an on-air
oh right and you can't tell the
difference between a non era because DNS
was wrong or because something else
failed yep right so pretty much that's
that's what you do i'm i'm not putting
the code here but dns is already cashed
what you do is set up a wild-card dns
entry on your server say anything dot
hostname com maps to this one IP address
and then generate a random hostname on
the client side just pay 64 encode a a
random number and look up that hostname
so the probability of it being cached is
pretty low right there's still a chance
that that random host name was already
cash but it's fairly low so you do a
lookup for a random host name there's
another problem so we're looking at
hostname and IP address what happens if
we're doing we are assigning IP lookups
based on geolocation so you can't just
use a static hope and static IP address
in that case
any guesses yeah well you may or may not
be controlling the DNS so so okay if you
do control the DNS yeah you know exactly
where they're coming from when they make
the request so you can set the IP at
that point of time again you might be
route around robbing going round robin
between host names with the nursing
between IPS within a single zone so
another way to do that is you do a one
look up with the host name then do
another look up after you finish the
first look up to two lookups in parallel
so do to image loads in parallel right
so the first one is going to do a DNS
lookup plus a TCP handshake the second
one is going to use the connection
that's already open so there's no dns
lookup but it does just as a round-trip
using those two you get dns plus tcp and
then the second one that's running in
third one that's running in parallel
there's a TCP handshake plus a roundtrip
so you take the difference of the first
and a third one and that gives you the
DNS lookup time so I haven't put code
here for that because again it gets way
too complicated but you can look it up
in the DNS plugin in boomerang right so
boomerang has various plugins for doing
Network lookups and this is in DNS
plugin how am i doing on time five
minutes to go two parts to go so ipv6
what we really want to measure with ipv6
well ipv6 is still not very widely
spread so the main thing we really want
to know is is ipv6 supported by this
user or this user's network connection
and if it is supported how fast is it
not just how fast is it but how fast is
it to do a DNS lookup for a qua da for a
record and how fast is it to just load
an image from there so we do two
different things first try to load an
image from an ipv6
so host using the ipv6 address not using
a hostname by using the ipv6 address
itself if that times out and we set a
reasonable time out that either times
out our gives us an on error then we say
ipv6 is not supported by the source so
we'll just stop at that point of time if
it does go through and we do get a
response then we measure the latency of
that and go through the next step which
is try to load the same image using a
hostname so the first test first test
checks of ipv6 is supported the second
test checks if dns lookup of ipv6 hosts
works so it's important that this
hostname only resolved to an ipv6
address and not to an ipv4 address I've
had trouble finding some hosting
providers don't actually let you do that
they'll always give you an ipv4 address
and let you add an ipv6 address to it so
if you have that kind of a provider you
can't really do this test things likely
note will allow you to do that ec2 if
you use there and the load balancer it
allows you to assign only an ipv6
address so using that you can tell
whether DNS lookup works for ipv6 or not
so again the full code for this is in
boomerangs ipv6 plugin it's too big to
fit on a slide so I not put it here does
anyone want to see it I can open it up
in a text editor no all right so finally
network scanning using javascript how
would you go about this in two minutes
so where network scanning is actually
quite a wide topic but what we care
about is a few different things first
find out what kind of network the users
on and secondly do they have anything
interesting running on their private
network right so the interesting thing
about JavaScript running within a
browser that's different from a port
scanner or something running on my host
is that javascript has access to the
users private network so if the users on
a lan connecting by a gateway to the
internet i can get javascript in there
onto their browser that's then going to
run
privileges of their browser so it has
access to the internal network that I
don't have access to from outside so you
can scan the users private land how
would you do that I'll try and load
something from 192.168 point 1 point 1
or 0 point 0.1 or 10 point zero point
zero point one you can hydrate through
these pretty quickly run them all in
parallel and find out what loads once
you find out which network they're on
whether they on 192 or gender or point 0
then you'll start looking for common
look for standard routers so every
single router words and linksys or net
here something they have a logo right
and that logo is not protected by an
admin username and password so try to
low load that logo image if the lower
logo image loads if you get an onload
event firing you know that's the kind of
router they using then you basically try
standard exploits for that particular
router try and gain access to it most
people don't change default user names
and passwords so you can actually try
and login it is assuming they're already
on the private network they can actually
get admin access so they don't allow
admin access from the external interface
but the allow admin access from the
internal interface except Java scripts
going in from the internal interface so
yeah you can get admin access if you're
lucky and they've recently logged in the
cookies are still in their browser and
the Brazil happily log you in without
you having to pass username and password
in using a 401 auth so that's that's one
thing to do and there's actually an
example this guy named Sammy come car
built a script that will actually do all
of this go into your router get your mac
address do a google location look up and
figure out your home address just by you
visiting a website
the other thing you can do is then scan
the internal network so it instils once
you know which network they were which
subnet they're on you start scanning
that for interesting ports so look for
port 80 look for port 22 oh look for 43
3306 you could look for the admin ports
of different database services and
measure how long it takes to respond so
in most cases you'll always get a non
error for these things because let's say
a mysql server is not going to respond
to an HTTP request so you'll get it well
it's not going to respond with HTTP
you're going to get mysql protocol back
so you'll get a non error for most of
them but you'll get some error so if
it's a short time out that means you
make a request there's nothing there you
get a connection refused error that
times out really quickly remember it's
on their local network it's not going
over the internet so it times out
quickly if it takes a little longer time
to time out and you'll actually have to
test this out on your own network to
find out what it is so a little longer
to timeout it means something's
listening there but it's not HTTP and if
it takes a fairly reasonably a long time
to time out it's probably HTTP you've
got a response from an HTTP server but
it's not an image so it timed out
actually you got an error at the at the
passer level within the browser rather
than at the connection level then you
try an iframe so an iframe can load any
HTTP content and it will return an
onload if HTTP loads and then on error
if non HD be loads so those are the
different things you try and that
basically concludes my top two minutes
over right so source code for most of
this stuff is either at the boomerang
project yep or the last one the network
scanning stuff is Sameera PL / map xss
any questions
alright
oh so
so let me repeat the question says by
scanning internal ports can we figure
out what the business of that particular
person is right I don't know anyone just
by knowing what services they're running
internally would you be able to tell
what all right assuming it's running
HTTP because but but would you would you
get that back using javascript that can
only read HTTP well no you can get into
connect so you know that it can connect
but you'll always get an error you won't
get actually get a responsible
like it but you'll always have an HTTP
header other all right all right so i
don't know you can do various things
i've also tried doing a soap so doing
posting to a soap service if you can
send a crafted soap request and find out
what servers running there you can do
interesting things sometimes again if
there's in securely configured services
you can actually get that service to
post a response back to your external
web service so you can get it to do like
an LS or do whatever and send data so
actually post data to your external web
service where you then see what's
running there all right any other
questions
I sorry I can okay all right so we're
not really reading anything we're just
testing to see if something's there or
not you can't you can't really read
what's there because it's cross-domain
although it's running as a script node
within your with in New York or within
your page and it's loading an image so
you can make a cross-domain request your
car just can't read the response okay
anything else any other questions but so
I'm gonna stop here and let the next
speaker Jago right if you have more