my name is Anton Kolev I am front-end
engineer discus I also happen to be a
giant maintainer giant is a fork of
Jesslyn the syntax checker tool and I
gave this similar presentation a few
weeks ago at jQuery conference but that
presentation was more about the use of
Jason how to use it how to integrate it
into your environment but for J's conf I
decided to do something else because I
feel like you people are kind of people
that actually shape the JavaScript
community so this will be more like a
shout out to you for help on this and
other projects so why am I doing this
first I run really passionate about
language tools and code quality tools so
basically every tool that helps us to
write better code to write faster code
I'm really passionate about that and I
also really hate all these fear crap
about JavaScript that's all the
newcomers think that JavaScript is a
very dangerous language and we should
use some subset of this language and
this subject is usually crippled so then
they are just afraid to learn the
language they are afraid to understand
the language they think that prototype
is bad because somebody said so and they
never understand the prototype
inheritance sorry
so initially I forked Justin just
because I needed to I needed for it to
be usable I disgust for our own project
but the feedback was so surprisingly
amazing I mean it really hit the nerve
because people apparently don't like
Rockford's as much as I do so that's why
I decided to expand the project and this
talk will be basically about this
expansion so while language tools are
important first and one of the most
important this important thing is that
they save us time they save us time by
spotting the by obvious box before
actually in runtime for example last
week we merge a big big branch make a
disgust and our build failed because the
jaysene found a leaking global variable
error it was not too horrible it would
probably work on all sides except for
one side and this one side would say hey
I use the same variable i and then
you're me out so that was
spotted it saved us
I know like hours of G bugging and sighs
and the second one is helping syntax
checkers and cut quality tools that help
us to enforce our style rules if you
maintain or if you'll contribute to any
open source project you know that when
somebody sends you a really good patch
they just happen to have it's different
style programming style and you were
thinking yeah I should either tell them
hey please change your style because
your patches get patches goodbye that
I'm not gonna commit it without those
changes then you feel like an asshole or
you're changing that for them before you
actually like commit occur before you
actually merge their pull request and
you still feel like an asshole because
it's not their commit anymore so with
the I will show you example it from
pattern world with the syntax checkers
that actually enforce some kind of style
it's very easy to say if you want this
patch to be accepted just run it through
this tool and if it's all good it's all
good so this is for like experienced
developers for the newcomers code
quality tools they really can help to
guide through the language tricks and
obstacles basically when you write I so
remember when I wrote my first jobs grow
applications like it was really bad
still pretty bad and so when you write
that it's kind of nice to have a tool
that will tell only like obvious
mistakes you made all the styling issues
you have
and when you grow when you learn the
language and you know like how to use
automatic semicolon insertion then you
just turn on the option and you use it
that's fine so they also can guide the
newcomers by providing links to the
useful documentation and thankfully we
have a quite a few syntek shakers and
lenders and all this stuff but some of
them one of them is really mean to the
users so I felt like we should have some
kind of not loss loss is just a
reference to Isaac Asimov blood-like
rules that all projects they're all
linked projects should comply to and the
first rule is the program may not insult
a human being see this is very sad that
I had to put it at the first rule and
you all know what I'm referring to
because the most popular project on the
web and in JavaScript community is like
a giant asshole to developer community
so yeah it's never helps for the project
for the community and for your
contributors when you tell them you're
stupid after every Patrick read full
request so javascript is really flexible
language you can write in different
styles and those styles it's not like
Python or let's say go where you can
write in different styles but they're
all pretty much the same in JavaScript
you can do basically whatever you want
and that's why good lynching tool will
not will confirm to your own style or to
the style of your project if jQuery
people want to put the white space in
between the parentheses that's their
option yeah
and the third Lloyd's again the
reference to this other project so the
program must accept patches because no
matter how smart you are people are
smarter than you and I learned so much
by just running the Jets in progestin
project all those issues and secrets
that people file they explain with like
references to their actual script
specification why it is good and why
they use that and sometimes I was like
whoa I'd never thought I can use that
and yeah so it's very helpful for
everybody when you're good with your
community so yeah let's see other
languages I have two examples from
Python and go because I really love both
languages and so in Python Python has
their linters they're very popular by
lenient by flakes they check the probe
they've just like jslint except for
except that Filene actually runs the
code so it can detect if your imports
are like incorrect or if you have messed
up paths and keep 8pi check the programs
to get the program against the official
Python style guide they have the style
guide that if you want to contribute to
Python standard library or to Python or
something in fact in there so you have
to run your code through the PPA that
file which is what which works for them
that will not work for JavaScript
because of different styles but we can
do something like that but better and
flexible so it's good for the discusses
a Python shop so and we use those tools
the PI flakes as our parts of our build
project and I know a lot of other big
Python shops that actually use it as a
part of build projects and in JavaScript
people well they don't use that they
don't use neither jslint or Jason or
JavaScript Lane I I know why but I don't
have time to joke around Crawfords
anymore so go go has the
awesome oh sorry yeah so uh this better
so go has this amazing go format utility
that ships with the actual compiler and
it's not only checks your code it's
actually fixes your code it's prettify
set according to their rules again the
go is more like python so it's very it's
very hard to be to have some unique
style it's pretty much the same so this
way ships with a compiler and I'm pretty
sure all three go projects in the world
use that so now back to JavaScript it's
everything is not too horrible in
JavaScript we have those linters jail in
JavaScript lane closure compiler closure
compiler linker is really good and we
have nice documentation now we have this
better j/s project that actually that is
actually hmm moved good articles to the
first page of google search either that
or I have really good Google
personalization because all those good
and I was like MDC and extra specs are
now in my first page near the top so we
have that but it all can be better
first of all as I said about tp8 we need
our tools to enforce style guides after
the my jQuery contour I got approached
by jQuery team they said that hey we
would like to use Jayceon but we need a
way to enforce our style guide for the
pull request we're having because we're
they spend too much time dealing with
that I put this white space here white
space there so we need this we need
something that is flexible enough to
support custom style guides because I'm
pretty sure we have like 150 people here
and we have like 48 different styles of
writing JavaScript and we can and people
try to
in force one style and make everybody to
rewrite all their code but as you can
see that totally failed
so next index checkers yeah they must
have plug-in architecture plug-in
architecture is important for every good
project that wants to be expanded by the
community let's say you're writing some
Yui widget or yeah and you know you
don't only want to check that your
JavaScript is correct and valid and
doesn't have obvious mistakes let's say
you want to check the namespace that the
namespace is according to your rules we
will never incorporate that in Jayceon
because well it's your project it's your
problem but if there with the plug-in
architecture you can actually do it
yourself and it will work
hopefully just fine also we have all
those nice languages like spin-offs like
CoffeeScript and the future version of
JavaScript harmony and at some point we
will need to support them because well
people use them and especially
CoffeeScript people apparently liked the
language so why not and here we come to
the Jason project and the project part
is the important because based on the
feedback I decided to expand Jesse from
Jesse syntax checker utility more to a
learning project so today I removed HTML
CSS linters from Jason because nobody
uses that so now it's just JavaScript
with JSON syntax checker the latest
release that I made during the jQuery
conference is now stable release it has
all the options are fully tested they
covered by tests but unfortunately it's
still the fork of courgettes lint which
means first for a it uses pratt parser
to parse the search tree b it uses one
letter variables every where
like everywhere and it's very
frustrating to maintain that code base
so but people use the
people use Jason in the scoured version
it's very stable I know at least six
pretty big companies that use it as a
part of their build process and so
that's why I decided to expand it so now
Jason's will be will soon be a syntax
checker and documentation project every
warning every error every option in J's
hint will reference to the number of
links to the other resources like NBC or
the blogs like where as yes or
JavaScript JavaScript network press they
will explain why like for example if you
have a option to turn on automatic
semicolon insertion that will have the
full documentation of what F dramatic
semicolon insertion is why would you
need to use that what don't you want to
use that and all this stuff also a plan
to make it change the architectures to
be more extendable so that you generate
you will have yoga basic hair will have
a hooks for every lucky band and you
will have a source tree at any point so
it's any point you'll be able to hook
into some event and say hey if this
function is named like differently break
the bill at some point in future we will
add more languages support but it's more
like future and the most important the
most important part of these over the
next release of the next version will be
the ability to create your own style
guides basically because I promised that
to jQuery same so you I have no clue
what the syntax is gonna be I don't know
how it's gonna work now because I just
started to work on that and well
basically this why I'm here I want to
ask all your help and you can help by
sending tickets and patches that's
always helpful pull requests I am
literally dancing around every sample
request comes in so
you can write documentation which is a
long shot because you will never write
documentation so have to suck it up and
send me links to your very favorite
blogs and sites that's that that's
really easy to do because everybody has
like a lot of good JavaScript articles
bookmarked in their browsers or
delicious if it's still around and yeah
just send those links and we will put
that into the appropriate sections of
the J mu J s king.com
when it'll be out if you know not a lot
if you know something about the how to
parse about the JavaScript lectures like
narcissus or whatever uglify j SS uses
uses I'm basically doing a branch and
experiment on writing J's hint with the
new elixir and if you want to join me on
this project if you want to want to work
together to collaborate feel free to
approach me after they talk because it's
it's kind of fun like even with the
Jason giant current code base it's still
fun to maintain it and now you can
create your own project which I
encourage everybody to do if you don't
like me my Russian accent or Jason black
in general go ahead create another
project I love competition I would love
to see what your ideas are if you want
to create another since exchequer but
some other utility like we saw today
zero Angeles which is an amazing tool
and I think I will incorporate it in
into Jason calm so anything any language
to let you plan to create basically I
can help you with my time on creating
them and or I can like just link you to
these celebrity people here that will
help you with the promotion but there's
problem what if you want to help but
your company doesn't like open-source
and does encourage a person so you can
always work for
company that encourages open source and
actually pays money to work on open
source projects sorry about that I know
that's everybody hates that much yeah
and we're hiring like a couple front-end
engineers so yeah so um thanks hopefully
it was not very boring and sorry for the
delay
and yeah talk to me if you want to help
with the project or if you want my help
with your project or if you want just to
meet celebrities yeah and go to
github.com Jesse and J's hint and open a
pull request and I will make it will
make me very happy