I have a lot of energy because I
literally have been typing into these
slides like three seconds ago so I'm
hyped about how this is gonna go so this
talk is about creating add-ons for node
how many people know what add-ons for
node are okay cool cool that's people
so essentially add-ons are the node
version of C extension so you can take C
C code C libraries and expose them as
JavaScript API is I'm kind of going out
of order here so we'll see Who am I
first of all I'm Marco Rogers very newly
minted started working at at Yammer in
San Francisco so I'm also like one of
the node guys from very early days I was
like lurking on the mailing list when it
first showed up and like you know
remember 0.133 which really kind of felt
like it was a node and that you could
use it for something useful and they
stayed three three for a long time so
I've been around for a while I kind of
fell into doing node add-ons it's kind
of a story but we don't have a lot of
time I have a tremendous amount of
slides and I don't even we're not gonna
make it through those because I want to
do something else too so so let's keep
it moving I'm also the maintainer of Lib
xml j s one of the biggest node add-ons
easily one of the most complex it is
bindings to lib xml - which is the giant
like you know super compliant c library
for dealing with xml and HTML people
familiar with that pretty much so okay
and just to shout out to to Jeff's make
who actually started the project I
handed her over to me at a certain point
so I'm the primary maintainer now but I
just want to I wanted to give him a
shout out real quick so let's go through
the kind of boilerplate e stuff and then
we'll
get what kind of an atom looks like and
then I really want to kind of pull up
some code and look at it because the
reason I'm doing this talk let me kind
of just take a segue the reason I'm
doing this talk is because no one else
was doing this talk and note add-ons are
actually I think stream ly important
there's not a lot of community around
them yet and we we need to make more of
them so I'm the guy that's not afraid to
stand up here and look stupid while I
talk to you about it and like because
you know I don't have all the knowledge
that I need so I need to bring you guys
in so that's what I'm trying to do right
okay so an add-on is just simply a way
to bind C C++ classes or functions into
JavaScript okay a better definition a
way to enable new j/s ap is based on
existing code and that's a simple
distinction but it's important because
we'll see in a little bit you can create
you can and you should create your
JavaScript API the way that you want it
to be rather than looking at the library
and say what does this do
let me map this straight into JavaScript
right and most importantly I think just
for the purposes of organization a node
add-on when you create a node add-on you
get a you get one file and it's like
something dot node that's the extension
and node sees that as a module that it's
going to require and it's gonna have
exports hanging off of it just like any
other node module that you guys are
familiar with so that's also important
and we'll come back to that okay so why
would anyone want to do this I just
thought that this was something that I
wanted to throw out there C++ code is
really fast everybody likes that writing
it makes you feel kind of like a badass
especially if you are you know just
strictly a front-end guy like having
done C since college I'm describing
myself and then I jumped into it and I
was like alright I can do this right but
it it's hard and the people who know see
here are gonna be like well you can
leave I'm sorry cuz it sucks
and it's frustrating and but it's
awesome because when you get into it
when you get back into it and you feel
you see stuff working and you run a test
of a JavaScript module versus a C module
and you get like you know
orders of magnitude speed-up you feel
like a badass right so the third point I
think is the most important which is C
in C++ code actually exists and runs and
works right now whereas we're working
with JavaScript which doesn't have any
libraries right so the reason I'm giving
this talk and the reason that you guys
keep writing writing add-ons is to make
libraries for node right instead of
writing them in JavaScript which is
really fun and really cool use the ones
that are already there and network and
our battle-tested
and they're way fast right so and
finally you can speak intelligently
about why you hate to write C and C++
which I do all the time so so for the
for the majority of these examples I'm
gonna be using bcrypt people familiar
with bcrypt
pretty much so essentially it allows you
to encrypt data using Blowfish encoding
algorithms right and it's really simple
the the the signature should be crib
kind of look like this these are the two
major functions right you can generate a
salt by passing it a number and you can
call B crypt which is going to take a
the first string which is the the thing
that you want to encrypt the second
string which is the salt the second
string which is the salt and it's gonna
return you the encrypted version I'm
using s five for slides here so it's
gonna give me crap by now quick
shout-out to Nick Campbell who's a
friend of mine I wanted to use B crypt
for one because it's pretty simple the
API is simple but it's also very useful
and we can focus on the add-on rather
than the library itself because this is
the signature that's it we can move on
to the next thing and talk about how
we're gonna expose it in node and also
Nick Campbell is a good friend of mine
and I'm gonna if we have time kind of
tear into his version of B crypt and how
we might be able to improve it and he'd
be good-natured about that so I thought
that was a good idea and if you want to
learn more about bcrypt
click on this link where Koda Hale who
actually also works at Yammer I thought
it'd be cool I threw his link up there
it's from like years ago before I know
who he was and that's how I learned
about bcrypt so that's cool
all right so we're gonna write an add-on
and essentially it's gonna work like
this we're gonna require bcrypt
and that's gonna be our add-on module
it's gonna have a you know a class
hanging off of it that is bcrypt we're
gonna skip the salt stuff I just have my
own salt here create a bcrypt object and
then call encrypt one function that's
not gonna work
one function you call and you get you
pass it a password you get a salt and
you're good to go right that's that's
85% of what you need out of out of this
module right so pretty simple and we
should be able to get it done
how's it work so like I said when you
create a module you when you when you
successfully get your module to compile
you're gonna get one file that says
bcrypt node or whatever you decided to
name it be crypt that node when you
require modules in node it searches
through the past it finds them and it
tries to load them up when it sees dot
node it immediately treats that as an
add-on and calls DL open if you're
jumping into C you'll find out about DL
open I'm not gonna talk about it because
it makes my head hurt and then inside
your add-on will see this there's an
init function right and that's your
entry point into C into loading up your
C module as an add-on and we'll see that
and it basically it essentially behaves
like a module except you get you and it
you pass in an exports object and you
enhance that exports object and pass it
back from C right so it's essentially
you you get a module like like you
expect a node with an object that has
methods and properties hanging off of it
so it should be pretty familiar C so
let's let's kind of jump kind of jump in
I want to look at some code in in a
second but I want to go through the kind
of basic stuff right so this is
JavaScript and it's running in v8 and
it's a simple function it says encrypt
this is bound to whatever the context is
if there is one there's some arguments
you can check the arguments object and
you can pull them out and then you
return something very simple 101 right
here's what that looks like in v8
this is C++ if every time I look at it I
try to like I have to encourage myself
to keep doing it but it looks like this
right so bcrypt here is a C++ class and
encrypt is the function that's hanging
off of it and this is the part that
looks funky right this is the this is
essentially the crux of the v8 API which
is you call C++ functions and they have
this method signature and there's this
arguments object and that's in v8 and
this is their encapsulation of what we
just saw right which is we've got this
argument object that that represents the
the variable number of arguments that
we're passing to this function and then
we do something with them and we don't
return something
so this arguments object has some some
methods off of it that let you do
essentially the same thing because of
the way C++ works and because javascript
is so dynamic and the the context is
gonna change you can't use the regular
C++ this so the v8 guys they hung it off
of the arguments object so that's how
you can always get to this which is a
handle and we're gonna talk about that
in a minute I'm creating the same kind
of variable here with an Argus one I
missed a step but you can check the
length you can pull arguments out of the
args object because it acts as an array
right so you can index it you have to
worry about types a lot in v8 right
JavaScript types are really simple C and
C++ types are not and that's gonna be a
big deal and that's something that I
really want to kind of get you guys
feedback on if again if we have this
time so you know you can set you set
some some parameters you create some
variable set some parameters and then
how we added these two strings together
here really simply we need to use a
function for that and C so they're
string
string ducking cat and you pass it to vh
string objects we can create a new one
on the fly and then we pass our variable
whether it's defaulted or whether it was
passed in so they make sense to
everybody
is that mapping go for it uh yes that
that's a problem that's the type of
sorry like I said three seconds ago I
was doing this yes this should be args
here is what he said
so we're gonna see real working code in
a little bit so hopefully they'll be
better let's go all right let's talk
about some concepts that we're that
we're seeing here right the type of this
variable is a handle and it should
actually have a template parameter on it
this is not a C++ tutorial so I'm not
even going to go into how that works but
you'll learn the kind of boilerplate
stuff and eventually it'll make sense
but so essentially it kind of works like
this v8 is running a JavaScript you know
environment on a heap all JavaScript
values are on a heap right so when
you're dealing with them in your C++
functions you deal with handles and
handle is a local reference to
JavaScript values on the heap right so
everything that you deal with that is a
javascript value is gonna go through
handles and you essentially unwrap them
to get at the C types underneath them
we'll see a little bit of that hopefully
but like I said I really want to get to
the kind of the meat of things right
this is kind of what I exactly what I
just said about handles you need to
unwrap handles to get to the data
there's also handle scopes the reason
that v8 went with this and if you know
anything about SpiderMonkey they don't
have any kind of concept like this
the reason v8 went with this is that
they want to make it easy for you to
clean up your references so that they
don't leak and the way that they do that
is to have everything in a handle and a
handle is a handle make sure that you're
going through the right you know I mean
it's a name named appropriately it's a
handle to whatever you're dealing with
and you always
through the handle and they can track
handles and the way that they do that is
through this handle scope object you
create a handle scope and every time you
get a handle this object is gonna track
it and when it goes out of scope by
popping off you know pot this function
pops off the stack it's gonna clean out
all those handles right so it keeps you
from having a lot of memory leaks it
also creates a lot of headaches and will
maybe talk about that in a little bit
right if I'm going too fast please let
me know but you know I really want to
kind of blaze and then see if we can see
some code right there's two types of
handles there's local handles which like
I said are really important for cleaning
up your temporary objects that you're
dealing with in JavaScript
those get collected as usual by you know
by a a sea stack popping off and then
there are persistent handles because you
want to you want to have you know when
you get to your final destination of
your you know your return value you want
to have that persist so it can go back
into the JavaScript environment and
doesn't get collected right because it's
it's gonna get collected unless there is
a JavaScript reference to it so you need
to use persistent handles to make sure
that you know if you're dealing with
stuff in JavaScript you jump into C++
land and start doing something meanwhile
the v8 garbage collector decides to run
and it says oh you're not using this
I'll just clean it up then you're effed
right you're kind of screwed so all
right so the way that you deal with that
handle scopes and handles is like this
and this this slide may made more sense
earlier but you create a handle scope by
just you know doing a local
initialization of it and as soon as you
do this this is the only line that you
need your tracking handles within this
function right every handle you create
within this function is gonna get
tracked and it's gonna get cleaned up
when the function ends so this is
actually the way this worked out is kind
of a patch file because what I had
before I before I knew better what I had
was just okay I'm just gonna return a v8
array right like so created new arrays
basically like the empty brackets that
we all know from JavaScript and return
it and it was working fine 80% of the
time until the garbage collector
got to it and then it was gone and I was
SEC faulting right so that's what
happens like it's gonna let you drag
these handles around all the time until
you try to use them and the data
underneath has been collected and it
craps out that's what happens so what
you have to do is create scopes make
sure things get cleaned up and then you
have to close the scope it's miss named
I think but essentially what it means is
this is a local handle but I'm gonna
pass it to the calling scope because I
know that it's my return value right so
you take this scope and you say okay for
this handle I know you have it tracked
and you're gonna try to screw me on this
close it pass it back right so this is
very important there are a lot of
patches in live XML Jas just doing this
right and if you forget it you will have
problems so okay next kind of concept I
want to talk about really quick is how
do you deal with objects right you you
have your C library it might be a C++
library and they have classes and you're
going to want to hang some state off of
those classes and you're gonna get to
them when you when your extension calls
your C methods right the way that you do
that or at least the the node way that
we're providing to do that is through
node object wrap and you know to kind of
keep things simple all this does is take
a C++ class and wrap it in a v8 handle
right so you can pass that handle around
and it'll act like an object when it's
in jeaious jeaious land when you call
and when you call into a c function you
take that handle and you unwrap it and
you get your C++ object back it's really
convenient it there's there's a lot of
like tricky C magic going on in there if
you're if you're not faint of heart jump
in there and take a look but it's it's
it's grimy so just you know do what it
says so
all right and I mean basically it has
two functions on it right
it has rap and has unwrapped so object
wrapped out unwrapped basically is gonna
take this the this the this context
that's coming in with this function and
that's a v8 handle write unwrap says
okay unwrap this and give me back my C++
object which is a B crypt and again
and I've left the template ization off
of here you have to tell it what you're
in right unwrapping and we'll see that
in real code in a little bit but as soon
as you do this you're you're back in
Sealand and you can do whatever you want
with this corner - you'd be crypt object
so alright there are a lot of classes
and utilities that node gives you to be
able to approximate what you expect a
node in the C in C and C++ land things
like event emitters are there so you can
subclass an event emitter on your C++
class and make it act like an event
emitter and and see you're calling emit
and you're giving it you know the the
name clothes and the callback thing is a
little a little a little different
that's on the other side of emit but
we're not gonna get to that because
there's a lot and we only have have a
half-hour and I'm already about 20
minutes in so but on the other side this
is JavaScript and I didn't you know I
didn't these slides are super new so
this is a new connection in JavaScript
this represents your connection in C++
class you're making a new one and you're
treating it just like an event emitter
right so it's gonna go through C code
it's gonna admit whatever you want it to
admit and it behaved when once it comes
out of the module it behaves like node
and it's awesome right so if you if you
learn the the kind of paradigms and the
the techniques to you know write your
modules such that they behave like node
you're white right way better add-ons
and people will be really happy there's
lots of other stuff I'm gonna start like
breeze in just a little bit like yeah
okay I'm so I'm a thing and there's lots
to cover here I didn't go through
throwing exceptions right you need to do
that object wrap also has a ref you know
it's kind of a reference counting thing
where you can when you have to do a
synchronous actions and you're
essentially off of the v8 thread to keep
your to keep your to keep the garbage
collector from collecting your your
objects like it's supposed to do you
have to tell it that it's referenced and
ref is the way that you do that there's
code around that to I really want to
just point you guys at a lot of examples
and have you kind of go in refer to
these slides and maybe it'll make more
sense but half hour so let's keep going
signatures are the way that you
make sure that the object that you're
calling methods on goes with your module
right because there's a disconnect
between the C++ classes and the
functions because javascript is so
dynamic I could I can take you know a
function and detach it from this object
and call it right and JavaScript is not
gonna know that it goes with that that
object because there's a C++ class under
it and if I try to reference it it's
gonna crash doesn't know that so there's
so signatures are really important also
but the thing is you can get really far
without doing any of this stuff and you
feel awesome about it and it's working
until it doesn't and so you have to
start finding all of these techniques to
to shore up your code and make it more
robust so I'm throwing this stuff in
here
but as you guys dig in like you know I'm
trying to get the conversation started
here so I know about this stuff when you
run into it like please let's starts
talking about it
so all right there's lots more slides
but let's let's stop and kind of look at
some code here and see if we can get
through at least a little bit right all
right so I've got I've got bcrypt here
right
there's several files here there is
there's a there's a dot H file which is
the headers for Blowfish and bcrypt
there's bcrypt CC which is the actual
implementation of bcrypt it has those
two that gin salt and that encrypt
function and see that I showed before
and there's Blowfish here so this is the
that's the the best extent of the C
library that's it right and then these
two files are your node add-on so these
five files if you put the right things
in them you get this little module that
will do B crypt for you and I think
that's really cool
so let's see how far I can get hang on
just a second
hello can hear alright cool cool uh
those are my slides let's get rid of
those this is Emacs oh god help me if I
can't get through this but yeah I'm
gonna blow them up um let me just find
what I need first let's look at the H
file which I don't have open this week
alright so source the Crypt node H
alright so here's our here's our header
file right here's what we want our
module to do it's gonna have a class
it's gonna be called bcrypt oh yeah
sorry there we go yeah all right I do I
do use Emacs I don't have to blow it up
very often so so here we go you've got
your bcrypt object and you've got uu
subclassing object wraps so that it will
behave sanely when you want it to stick
around right and there's there's three
there's three functions here right
there's there's a static version of
initialize which we'll see in just a
second that's how you're going to
essentially initialize your module and
populate it with methods there's a new
function which is your constructor for
this bcrypt object and javascript when
you call new bcrypt it's gonna call this
new function okay and there's encrypt
which is the the v8 version of this
encrypt function that you're gonna call
so these are if you remember the slides
that's the extent of what this module
does you get an object create one called
encrypt that's it right so this is the
extent of what we need for this now
let's look at the C file
okay I'm gonna I'm gonna go pretty fast
there's not a lot to look at here oh if
this is the wrong file sorry all right
here's what the C code looks like couple
headers don't worry about that using
namespace so you don't have to type v8
colon colon everywhere note colon colon
everywhere
here's your initialize function let me
start let me start with an it actually
here's an it way at the bottom it has an
extern it's called it in it and it gets
a handle object which is your target
this maps directly to module dot exports
it's the it's the JavaScript version of
that or is the C++ version of that so
we're gonna hang methods off of here and
when you do require bcrypt this is the
object that you're going to get and all
we do in this init function like I said
this is just a portal in is we
initialize it by passing it in to
initialize right here's where we get in
this - v8 I'm you know I can't do too
much to explain this because I have five
minutes but here the here are the things
that are happening here right we're
making a function template and what this
says is we're making a new function
template and what we're passing it in is
our function new that's this we're
telling it we're making a new JavaScript
function template that's going to be
mapped directly to this c++ new function
okay so when we when we call new bcrypt
it's going to call this we have to do
some some v8 stuff like set some
internal fields you'll learn about that
there's some other this is our Jen salt
function which I commented out and note
set prototype method is a one of those
handy macros that node gives you to do
these types of things easily so it's
going to take our function template it's
going to create a new property call
encrypt and encrypt is going to match
map directly to our encrypt function
that we're going to look at in just a
second so when you call encrypt on this
object it's going to map to this C++
function so so there's that and then
finally so what we have now what we have
now is
a new a new constructor essentially
right when we do new bcrypt
that's this this is a function template
right we've mapped it to encrypt so
we've got a function called encrypt and
then what we what we're creating now is
a new symbol called bcrypt
mapping it to our constructor and then
we're good to go
we've got our constructor here we've got
our encrypt function here
we hooked them up and then we've
attached that off of this target target
that set B Cribs get function cool
pretty much sweet all right
so new is really simple we create our
handle scope we always need those we
create a new bcrypt C++ object and then
we wrap it so this is a function that
comes off of object wrap and it says
take the C++ function and wrap this
handle around it and the handle that we
want is the context of this new function
okay so our thought this is going to
return our handle we're gonna pass it
into wrap and now we have a JavaScript
handle with our C object underneath and
they're gonna go together until they get
collected okay and then we return our
object you have to do this in you don't
have to do this explicitly in JavaScript
you have to do this in C++ to return
your object when you do constructors
encrypt this is the meat of it this is
the only thing that this this module
does handle scope unwrap our bcrypt
object because this we're calling bcrypt
dot encrypt unwrap it by calling unwrap
and we got we have to tell it it's a
bcrypt object right you've seen this now
we have our c++ object now we're gonna
pull the arguments out the first one is
our password second one is our salt all
of this is dealing with c conversion
from j s to C types all of this okay
turn it into a string because it's of
type handle value value is the highest
you know the highest level in the
hierarchy of values and v8 so it's a
value turn it into a string we know it's
a string because we're you know
we built this and we're writing the code
for it if you don't know what it is this
gets way harder but we know what it is
do data and you salt I'm turning into
utf-8 values and then I'm pulling those
out into char stars you have to go
through these steps usually right you
can write a macro around it but
essentially we went from JavaScript
strings to be a to C char stars now we
have we have our data right and then
this is the library call B Krypton those
two things and get back a char star
sorry um so I think the rest of this
makes a lot of sense right we're
creating a new string with our new b
cryptid value and we're returning it
that's it like you just you just created
a module right I didn't get to how to
build this and I don't think that's bad
because that part sucks but definitely
come talk to me let's look at this stuff
I'm gonna post all the slides which have
way more information about all the stuff
that I did not get to but if do we have
any time for questions at all what's
that oh yes it is going to be at it is
not up yet it is going to be at it is
going to be on github yes
it's in one of these slides where it
will be the repositories there is just
empty I'm gonna put the slides up what's
that
polo tech it's on the first slide that's
me everywhere Twitter github IRC
whatever so come talk to me we need to