you
hello Berlin it's good to see you guys
it's good to be here
I'd like to start with a huge thanks to
the conference organizers for this like
beautiful event and really nice space
that I'm speaking in today and
especially to Yann over there who lunged
me to apply to speak at this because I
probably wouldn't have otherwise and I
also wouldn't be experiencing this
really warm and friendly community that
you all are it's really lovely
secondly I've got quite a lot of
material to run through so I don't think
we'll have time for Q&A and even if we
did I realized that I'm one of the last
things that's standing between you and a
cold beer so I'll be standing or had a
parent at the stage at 7:00 p.m. after
the final talk is done if you want to
come up and say hi right so my name is
Hannah Donovan or at hand on the
internet that's another way you can ask
me questions and I'm based in London
where everybody looks like this
obviously and I'm what I call a full
stack designer so I do everything from
like UX and user research through to
interactions and interfaces and then
like graphic design and icons and some
CSS that kind of thing and I combine all
of these skills together daily to make
products and I mainly make products in
the digital music space so you may know
me from some serious things like last.fm
where I helped shape the product early
on and led design there or you may know
me from some not so serious things like
drinketh I this was sort of an
accidental hack day success if you
haven't tried it out be careful it might
kill you with the quantities and lastly
my current project this is my jam where
I'm co-founder and design director so if
you don't know about this is my jam it's
a place to put your favorite song right
now and it's not just any song it's like
the song that you can't get out of your
head right now the one that you've got
on repeat on your phone and you only get
one you can put it on your profile and
you can sort of change up your profile
it customize it to really tell the world
how you feel about this particular piece
of music and what you get is a playlist
of
songs from your friends and it's sort of
like this ever-changing hand-picked
radio station by people whose music
tastes you trust and it's a slow music
service we don't really encourage you to
post that often which is kind of an
unusual thing I suppose we focus on the
quality rather than the quantity of the
posting but despite all that we just
recently had 1.3 million jams posted
which is pretty cool so I'm excited to
share that with you music and design are
my passion and my life's work other
highly important things that you might
want to know about me I recently
purchased a reindeer pelt I'm not joking
it's the softest thing that I've ever
touched and I wrote most of this talk
sitting on it I play orchestra with a
real Orchestra here we play music like
that we rehearse in spaces that look
like that and I also play with a comedy
orchestra which plays music like that
and our rehearsal spaces look like this
and my favorite film is Monsters Inc I'm
about six years old up here so just keep
that in mind during the course of this
presentation today okay and my favorite
image on the Internet are you guys ready
for this my absolute favorite image
makes me laugh every time is these guys
I'm modeling all my haircuts on them I'm
working on the one on the top right
right now I think right okay let's get
down to business so today in case you
didn't read the blurb on the side or
whatever I'm mostly going to be talking
about feels yeah let's just get this out
right away at the beginning of this
presentation so if you want to like run
for the door now is your chance okay in
2011 I quit my job at last.fm and I was
sort of clinging to what was left of my
ability to make things which at the time
was not a whole hell of a lot okay and
since then I've been working on this as
a design problem as makers burnout is
something that we all face it's not a
very nice thing it might be big it might
be small
mine was mine was pretty big yeah and
that's the story that I'm going to tell
you about today so let's get started
all right well back up to 1999 so I went
to design school it's kind of like art
school was very traditional graphic
design sort of focus thing did a lot of
art classes as well I fell in love with
the web while I was there you guys can
probably guess the rest of that story
and you know like art school and owl
says there was a lot of this going on
there definitely but there were also
some other things that I learned that
was sort of the beginning of a lifetime
of learning about the things that I'm
going to address today like the value of
good critique or you know create a block
or things like this like what it what's
required to make good work and I
graduated which was cool and I got my
first design job which was great I think
much to my parents surprise I wasn't
doing that and I got an even better
design job in a better city so that was
cool
and then I got like a super awesome
design job in a really awesome City and
that was great too I felt like I was
sort of living the dream and then wait a
minute this is nothing that's not how
it's supposed to go right this is not
the right trajectory for that but I was
totally totally burnt out completely
broken depressed frustrated exhausted I
couldn't even pick up a pencil and
sketch anything so like you do I left my
job in February of that year
packed a suitcase and ran away from it
all right so two months later I'm
somewhere in Hong Kong
I'm still pretty miserable at this point
I thought I might never be able to
design anything ever again I thought
maybe I had completely forgotten how
whatever tap of creativity I used to
just be able to turn on and things would
come out of it now like wouldn't even
drip and this tap of creativity is also
the only way that I have to make a
living to write so huge problem there
and then I get this text from my
longtime friend and colleague Matthew
gall and he's sort of like hey I know
you're off the grid and like running
around the world and like where are you
but I'm really desperate for a designer
could you please help me with something
on this project and I thought about it
for a bit and then I texted him back yes
and it was in that moment when I did
this that I realized that this is the
commitment to a creative life no matter
how you might be there is only
one way out and that way out is to keep
making so enough of me why does this
matter to you guys well first of all
it's because of this how many people
here have dealt with something similar
maybe on a less drastic scale okay just
raise your hand okay so it's like almost
half of you and you know if it hasn't
happened to you yet there's a very good
chance that it might so this is a real
issue guys we all make our money this
way right and you know there's there's
ways to get around this you're probably
familiar with some of these ways there's
ways like this and this and you know
that and I like those things those
things are cool don't get me wrong but
they're not super effective in the long
term and that's what I want to talk
about a bit more and you'd also think
that like the most important thing is
that we all understand and are able to
take care of what keeps us creative
right but from my conversations with
peers in the tech
I'm not totally convinced that that
actually happens for instance if you did
a CS degree you might not have even had
that sort of like first brush with like
the personal creativity bla that I was
forced to have to deal with in design
school you know early on and and that's
that's crazy because it doesn't matter
what you call yourself or what tools you
make things with or how you make them
what matters is that we're all makers
and that we all need to take care of
this and because we don't talk about
this problem it's really self
reinforcing especially in the in the
startup community I find that we really
really focus on tools we talk about the
efficiency of things it's all like lean
this and Minimum Viable bla that and we
treat ourselves like a tool that can be
optimized for even higher performance we
separate the making from the maker how's
the company doing we ask each other well
the company will be doing fine if people
are making things and people will only
be making things if they're in a space
where they feel like they can make good
things right as a quick aside I think
it's really interesting that recently
people have been talking about failure a
lot in the tech community but I think
it's really only the tip of the iceberg
in sort of talking about people and I
hope that as a community we dig deeper
there but you know it's hard because of
this right so hopefully we can cuz we
need to learn from each other you all
right
I think it's like time for a little owl
break that was a lot so far yep
this is did you guys like owls I love
owls they there's so many you love owls
- there's so many fascinating things
about owls like did you know that they
can basically like hear with their face
it's amazing it's it's super cool hit me
up for more a love facts afterwards so
that's my hungover owl this is
definitely what I'm gonna look like
tomorrow morning I don't know about you
guys okay let's get back to business
so we're in Hong Kong it's 2011 you know
I feel really shitty
how do I dig myself out of this big hole
right two and a half years later these
are some of the methods that worked for
me to overcome my maker's block and have
continued to work for me actually so
what works for me might not work for you
you know this is not some kind of like
five-step self-help guide Oh God
but an opportunity for you to add
something to your toolkit if you think
it might be useful right so the first
thing here is learning when to stop we
come from a world of things that don't
have an end instead of like the physical
end to a record when the music stops
playing we have like a pause button on
our phones and we craft digital things
where we can sort of tweak and update
and revert as often as we would like to
and I think the lesson here is that it's
much easier to learn where the end of
something is actually if you work with
physical stuff early on in one of my
first painting classes in uni I remember
you know really harshly learning this
horrible lesson about over painting
which is basically when the painting was
better yesterday night then it is today
and now you have to throw it out and
start a whole new one and finish it at
exactly the same point before your
critique tomorrow it's not a good place
to be in encoding this manifests itself
as over optimising or over architecting
and it's applicable whether you're
working on like a really small part of a
system just one tiny feature or the big
picture right and I had to learn the
hard way in the big picture category
when to stop working at Loftus last.fm
because I was still tweaking things that
really didn't need to be tweaked anymore
but the other reason that this is really
important is I think that you need to
finish working on things to allow other
ideas to come in so my six-year-old
brain it's like it's like a small box
and I can like put one idea in one side
and then it rattles around in there for
a while but then I have to like push it
out the other side to make space for
more ideas to come in otherwise it just
all gets blocked up and
and there's no more space for new inputs
and we need new inputs to keep making
new things that's what keeps this cycle
virtuous and keep going secondly start
with something yep
when we feel like we can't make things
we're on a very steep and slippery slide
to feeling like everything we make is
I'm sure you've been there at least
once before in your life and worrying
about it being is even harder at
the very beginning of a project because
at the beginning of a project we have
this extra barrier to overcome which is
like oh my god I'm staring at a blank
canvas how am I ever gonna make
something out of this or staring at a
blank whatever in fact I hate this
feeling so much that to this day I do
something that I call ruining my
sketchbooks which is like when I get a
brand-new sketchbook I'm just like too
afraid to start making something in
there because it's all pristine and
looks so nice and how could I ever
possibly fill it up with great stuff etc
etc so I take the first page and I
always write book of sketch and like
really sloppy writing and just like
doodle something stupid in there and
then flip the page over and then on the
next page I get down to business and
it's all fine after that
but I sort of ruin it first to like
lower the bar for myself that I can get
it done so don't worry about making
something because the first thing
that you make you know it probably will
be it's just about getting that
thing out faster making that stupid
doodle in like five seconds so that you
can get on to iterating something good
out of that and there's so many good
examples of this and LaMotte who wrote
bird by bird which is a really great
book on writing she calls upon writers
to write shitty first drafts that's what
she calls it and Fred Brooks the author
of the mythical man-month whom I'm sure
you have heard of says about first
systems plan to throw one away because
you will anyway
in fact since you know I'm just up here
sort of like exposing all these really
embarrassing things to you I'm going to
show you the very first version of Jem I
mean link this is really really bad you
know this was just sort of like one of
my first sketches of
but it it stuck a couple of things
together you know we knew we wanted the
jam itself to be really big which is
something that like at the time no one
on the internet was really doing like a
song was always like a little row or a
little button it wasn't like a big thing
we knew we wanted like some space and
for heard you know some writing about it
and today it looks like this and I look
at this and I still see a lot of
imperfections with it of course but it's
a hell of a lot better than it was at
the beginning it's just about getting
that shitty first thing done really
quickly and getting it over with third
here taking that small first step making
the prototype will actually help
motivate you do more and I think there's
this big commons miss common
misconception about making things that
it's like some kind of magical process
where like a lightning bolt comes down
and like hits you and your head explodes
you've got this amazing idea all of a
sudden in fact I often experience this
when people ask me oh how did you and
Matt come up with the idea for this as
my jam
tell me all about it and I'm like oh
well you know it was like five years of
really hard work working together very
closely you know working on social music
and the internet and understanding the
whole crazy ecosystem of like writes and
labels and their eyes glaze over right
and they're like wait what it wasn't
just like you woke up one morning and
you had this brilliant idea that's what
they always want me to tell them right
and I'm like no not how it works first
you have to take an action and then from
that you're motivated and and then
something happens you know you need to
let the sky get dark and stormy and
interesting first before there's a
lightning bolt a related concept to this
is one that Julia Cameron talks about in
her book the artists way which is that
we are like you know like sharks that
need to keep swimming to stay alive we
sort of need to keep making things to
stay true to ourselves to our integrity
and it really doesn't matter I don't
think how small or insignificant that
thing is that you make as long as you
keep making it so when I felt like I
couldn't design anything what I did is I
actually started making a garden and
this is what it looks like
some plants actually turned out pretty
well and it wasn't bad garden you know
and this felt a little bit similar to
design for me because it was kind of
creatives kind of technical you make
things grow right I mean sure it's like
a totally crazy old lady habit you know
it's bonkers but whatever it was like
something that just helped the creative
shark inside of me you know feel
satisfied and it helped me see the light
at the end of the tunnel right this kind
of a big one I want to talk about habits
for a bit
so rightly so our industry places a lot
of importance on habits for getting
things done processes you know sort of
state of the art stuff a good example of
this is agile right it helps you get
things done and then there's like a
second kind of habit too that's really
important Twyla Tharp talks about this
in her book the creative habit she's a
choreographer she talks about the
importance of personal habits to keep
yourself sort of sharp and ready to be
able to make things so for her this is
like getting up super early in the
morning and this ritual of like hailing
a cab in Manhattan and going to the gym
where she does this insane workout
routine because that's how she keeps
herself ready for us it might be
something like you know reading a blog
every day that we or whatever something
to keep our knowledge up-to-date right
but there's a third a third and more
elusive habit that I need to tell you
guys about this habit is the one of
creating patterns for personal
serendipity because making things
requires unusual inputs we need the
unexpected in our life and that means
making space for the unexpected to
happen which is difficult when we're
following routines and sort of doing
things daily so an example of this is
this year actually team Jam and a couple
of people are a few people rather from
our co-working space hired this house in
Spain
just south of Barcelona it was really
cheap because we got it right before the
tourist season started nice six bedroom
house and we went there and did a bunch
of work and it was amazing we got so
much done like we had all these really
incredible ideas it was just a wonderful
experience and we're all like how did
this happen and I really think it was
just down to the fact that it was an
unusual environment there were different
inputs we had to think of things
differently it really helped us get
things done but it doesn't even need to
be that extravagant in fact it can be
really small and simple and cheap
another example of this is I use 750
words every day to journal and that's a
way for me to write down things
unexpectedly tidbits of ideas whatever
it's just like stuff but it's giving
myself the space and time for that
unexpected to happen I sometimes think
of this there's this this Tom Waits
interview that I saw once on video it's
it's really really good and he talks
about like someone asked him like how do
you write songs and he talks about the
songs as like because you know he's
crazy like butterflies and he's got a
butterfly net and he has to like catch
the songs right but there's an element
of truth to that which is like without
the butterfly net in the first place you
know you don't even know if you're going
to you won't don't even know if you
might be able to catch it and that's
what sort of creating these patterns for
personal serendipity is all about it's
kind of a you know it feels like a funny
thing to do because you don't know if
that serendipity is going to happen you
don't know if you're going to be able to
catch a butterfly but without even
creating the space to do that in the
first place you're never gonna get one
right another silly thing I do is
another freeze the only thing I do I
can't believe I'm telling you guys this
why did I why did I write this talk is
sometimes I walk around the neighborhood
and I look at moss and I I like textures
a lot so I like touching the moss and
occasionally I steal it and take it home
to my garden yep okay we're on the fifth
one I don't know how we're doing on time
there's like there's no timer up here
I hope we're all right okay I'm just
gonna keep on going by far the most
important technique is to do something
different this really helps me get
unstuck so one of my old painting
teachers used to say that that he would
always have two canvases going at the
same time usually one in oils and one in
acrylics and he'd like paint on one and
whenever
got stuck and it's like ah this isn't
working he just like turned his stool
around and he'd paint on the other
canvas until he realized oh that's how I
need to solve this one then he flipped
back around again and work on this
canvas and having something else like
that to help you get unstuck I find
really really cool works really well and
it's about taking the skills you have in
one category and just sort of shifting
them a little bit so try working in a
different medium or a different paradigm
or a different idiom or language so even
through this entire period while I was
actually working full time as an
interaction designer what I decided to
do was take on a bunch of side projects
of print work for friends this was
something that I hadn't done in like
seven years print work it's like a
completely different sort of technical
skill but I think it was really this
these side projects that helped me turn
my creative tap back on these side
projects with a deadline especially are
a really great way to sort of fake it
until you make it and I'm quite happy to
say that I'm not taking on any more side
projects because I now have so many
ideas of my own that I want to execute I
don't have time to be working on stuff
for other people I actually haven't
shown these too many people yet so I
thought you know like I'd show them to
you guys like why not you know might as
well say this is what I did so I made
these like silly cards for Matthew ogle
when he left last FM they had like
drawings of the web team members on them
they were planning poker cards for scum
and I collaborated with Jamie McKelvie
on a backup for an issue of Ironman I
did all of the infographics this is sort
of like Tony Stark's posthuman
understanding of the world because he
can do that kind of stuff we also
collaborated together on an album for
art brut where Jamie did the
illustrations and I did all the design
and the layout that year also my
grandmother turned 80 years old so my
sisters and I decided to make a cookbook
of all of her recipes because she's an
amazing cook and this included like
photographing everything like making it
photographing everything making these
illustrations and and all sorts of stuff
for that it was a pretty fun project we
made it into like a hardback really
beautiful object I did some identity
design for a friend of mine who runs a
speakeasy called
Manhattan's project that Orchestra that
I was telling you about that I play with
I redesigned their logo for them this
year because it was their 50th
anniversary why not
and more recently actually I just
finished working on the logo for a brand
new comic that's coming out it's gonna
be out next month actually called 3
which is written by Karen Gillan if
you're into that kind of stuff and it's
about Sparta so once you find your
methods that work for you because these
are my methods they might not work for
you it's really important that you
codify them you need to work them into
your life so this doesn't happen again
and you also need to talk about them
with your colleagues too this will help
each other critique the methods behind
your work not just the work itself and I
think especially you know if some of
your methods are a little bit quirky
like you like to go pick moths out of
people's yards or whatever you know or
different to other people in your work
space like you need 15 minutes at the
beginning of each day to write your
journal or whatever then talk to your
colleagues about them so that they
understand that these quirky habits are
not just like weird and wacky but it's
actually what makes you a creative
person every single day so that you can
come into work and do that great work
all right so we're nearly at the end and
I still haven't told you what's up with
the animals you guys wondering what's up
with the animals yeah you're wondering
yeah so in 2011 I I sketched this little
guy for fun and I really had a lot of
fun doing it and then later on
owls right I got to hold duster who is
this like amazing African spotted eagle
owl he was 12 years old when I held him
so he was pretty old dude I really hope
he's still alive
and then I got this magic pen I call it
it's a Wacom inkling that records pen
strokes to vector which is pretty neat
and I needed a project to motivate me to
help learn how to learn how to use it
right because kind of different method
of drawing so when I was applying to
speak at Jay s conf I knew that I wanted
to talk about makers block I knew that I
wanted to like tell this story and share
it with the community but I also knew
that I am needed to get energy
from somewhere to do it I need an action
to get the motivation rolling and I also
needed some kind of unusual element for
personal serendipity and I needed to do
something different which is why
sometimes you need to draw animals thank
you very much