so my name is a ray Morgan I'm not sure
if who knows me and who doesn't i was
actually here last year and I I spoke in
the bee track but probably no one knew
that because in the a track Brendan Eich
was talking so I think I had four people
five people and most of them were there
just like talking about the previous
talk so alright so today I'm going to
talk about app versus web but before I
do I want to lay down a couple
definitions of what I'm talking about
when I'm saying app and web just so that
we're all in the same page here and we
can all understand each other so when
I'm speaking about apps I'm talking
about native apps written and usually a
compiled language and these are things
like objective-c apps or Java apps for
Android and when I'm talking about web
i'm talking about applications or web
pages that are written in HTML CSS and
JavaScript I'm not so I'm not talking
about web is a protocol for native apps
but actual web applications so here's
the two camps and I thought this was
interesting because this is one of those
things that people are going to look
back on us and we're going to be known
for killing terrorists and World of
Warcraft so I think that's awesome but
so the two camps here this is actually
on the on your left we have a native app
this is the YouTube app obviously and on
the right we have the web application so
there's two different ideas when it
comes to what this what we should be
doing and you usually fall in either one
of the other camps the native app guys
they're like oh the web sucks and you
can't really do anything with it it's
limited we can't get all the cool
features of native stuff and then on the
other side the web guys we claim that we
can do anything you guys can do but
better faster and we don't have to learn
crazy languages and ID's so once upon a
time I was a front-end developer my work
for zappos com and i've been doing
front-end development there for about
four years now and really have a strong
passion for web technologies so when
when I first started we were still using
tables and stuff like that and
throughout the the years we've moved
over to you know semantic stuff and I
actually got a opportunity last year to
start working on native apps so I kind
of was tinkering with Objective C stuff
and so last August I was approached to
it's like hey you want to work on a on
the iPad app we're going to work on the
iPad app and I said sure so I kind of
have an interesting background I think
I've been working a lot of front-end
development but I also do native app
development so I'm not I'm not fully on
one side or the other I think that
there's a strong balance that we should
be striking between the two and so the
the first app we worked on was the ipad
app and i had been tinkering with
Objective C for probably about three
weeks maybe four weeks prior to that I
don't no idea why they let me do this so
it was me and one other guy that had
some experience so we kind of just start
hacking on it and we we release the
first version eight weeks later and this
is a full shopping app where you can
browse search view products choose your
size with color check out everything
like that and it was a native app on for
the iphone and at the same time I just
want to give a shout out to the are our
one API developer at the same time we
would do it we were making our Zappos
API so this whole thing was kind of a
crazy rush to get it out eight weeks we
made a native app and a full API so just
if you ever make it an API for anyone I
highly recommend making a real app or
real something with it and don't just
kind of think you know what you get what
your users are going to want so the the
point of that story is that native apps
aren't hard that aren't that hard to
write and this is kind of I think a hot
topic where you know as web developers
we think that this native platform is
impossible that we shouldn't even try
because why when we can just do web
stuff i have i've had people come up to
me saying that they
been working on like these iphone apps
and that was their first programming
language that was a first introduction
to programming was these iOS and Android
apps and one of the reasons that makes
it really really easy is all the
documentation the documentation I don't
know if anyone's ever googled anything
for like objective-c it's it's
phenomenal there's probably like
hundreds of hours of videos I'm just the
WWDC talks from last year and then also
the Stanford classes and you google
anything and you get probably 27 or 30
Stack Overflow questions and answers and
it's it's it's great and to demonstrate
this I'm actually gonna try something
I've never done before and it's probably
going to crash and burn so I have a
back-up plan if it does but I'm actually
going to live code a objective-c app a
really simple one so let's see how this
works that's not what I wanted yeah
we'll figure that out later okay so how
many here have actually written any kind
of native apps so objective-c apps with
Objective C first awesome awesome so
maybe 40 people what about like a native
android apps java about the same number
what about windows mobile apps too okay
we're good all right so if you haven't
if you've never done this don't worry
it's not what too scary so I'm just
gonna create a new project xcode is a
weird tool that is good and bad at a you
hate it you love it it's one of the
things so I'm just going to choose this
a creative you base of you base is just
a very kind of doesn't really give you
much by default but alright i guess i
can't change use the same name there we
go all right
so it's going to stay up a little
structure a little project structure for
me I don't have to really do that so I
got kind of two files here which is the
main kind of entry to the application
echo to view controller hmm and then i
have this xib file or a nib is what they
use to be called so if you've ever done
see development this is very similar you
have the header file and then the actual
implementation file oh right right oh
man I have no idea how to do that here
we'll just dude this way how about that
I'll just code like this yeah it didn't
yeah neither those that's what I'm used
to yupo you know I ex good see this is
what I'm talking about they do things a
little different I'm gonna go do fonts
oh wow look at that they have a theme
just for this hey nice that's awesome
alright so here we go we're just gonna
let's do an IB I'll kind of explain what
some of this means as i go and some i
won't so an iboutlet IBTimes for
interface builder which will explore in
a little bit i be outlet is just a way
to hook into something that you build
with interface builder so um so I be
outlet let's just UI label so we're
gonna make it we're going to use a label
i'm going to call it label will make two
of these but this one's going to be a UI
text field not that there we go and this
one's just going to be called Chi field
alright and then just copy this so these
so i'm doing here is i'm just defining
properties on this class so the class is
to find with the at interface a
directive and i'm just defining
properties that are in that class so
this one will have a label and a a text
field these are
two variables and then you also have to
do this weird thing to kind of tell
objective-c to give you gathers and
setters so you can properly use these
things so i'ma do not Tom 'ok retain
copy this so non-atomic is just a
keyword to whenever you change the
property of label anything about it
it'll make sure it's or non-atomic will
make sure it's not thread-safe atomic
will make it thread-safe atomic slower
you don't really use it too much of iOS
development may be in Mac development
may be in very specific places and then
one more thing I want to do is I want to
do I want to add one function and this
you the same thing I'd be action it's
kind of like outlets it's a I think it
is a going to event listener it allows
you hook up events so this is going to
be when a button espresso lon button
press and then uh you have been yeah
whatever okay so what i'm doing here is
to kind of defining the header of it i
know i did that wrong backwards boom
okay so I'm just defining that I will
have a function called on button press
and it returns the type Ib action which
is actually null but it's like a fancy
key word and I'm gonna get one argument
to that function and it's going to be
the button that was pressed and that's
all I need to do in this file so I'm
going to switch over to the
implementation file this is where your
all your actual code is you'll see a
bunch of stuff in there that doesn't
that apple auto generates and mostly
doesn't matter for us today so I'm a
synthesized synthesized is this stupid
thing you have to do that lets you it
like actually creates the getters and
setters I don't know why I do both at
property and at synthesized dumb see so
label and tea fields so this is just
saying those from these guys these
properties here is label and text fields
I
actually do want to use them so do that
and one more thing whenever you do an
iboutlet you also have to set them to
new on viewed it and unload for memory
management and these are just kind of
things that you just you pick up really
quick there these are kind of tedious
little little things setting up
variables i wish it was just VAR but
piled languages stack p type what can
you do all right so um the last thing my
doing this file my do i'm just going to
take this guy i'm going to copy it over
to wherever so the class definition is
kind of hard to see but it's from this
implementation down to this at end they
don't like it's like weird C syntax
mixed with Objective C syntax so the at
signs or like this are like that block
right there so the ad implementation and
yeah so I'm going to define this this uh
this action right here and all I want to
do is whatever is in the text box I want
to put into the label so I'm just gonna
do self dot label dot txt so that's the
actual text property so when i change
that the view will change and the view
is kind of like the element and i want
to set that equal to soft t field text
simple enough so take the text from the
text fields and put it into the text of
the label alright so if we run it right
now everything is not done because we
don't have any view all we have is the
code for the view it'll actually compile
run everything like that we just don't
have anything I put the simulator down
here later so yeah we have an empty gray
barring projective see up so let's just
jump into this nib and I'm going to add
just loads all right a label I'm going
to add a button I'm gonna add a button
there it is and i'm going to add that
text fields ok and alice is going so
slow
alright alright so now we have the the
elements on the screen just it types
really slow and so now all we need to do
is kind of connect the pieces so we have
the elements but they're not connected
to those references so when you push
this button it's not going to do
anything it's like if as if you put a
button element on an HTML page into any
JavaScript it's just going to be a
button they can press it's not very
exciting so hook up the this stuff all
we have to do is magic clicking so
control dragging from what's called
files owner which is this weird name for
the class that that view that we made
the data echo to view controller so I'm
gonna drag this down to the label and it
says hey here's an outlet barely see it
it lists out all the outlets that those
ib outlets that we made and it already
filters down to the only the UI label
outlets because you can't connect a text
outlet to a label outlet and things like
that because that would be weird I'm
gonna do the same thing for text field
and then also for the button press go
this way so that when you press the
button we want to send the event the
event of on button press so we set all
that up already we're just connecting it
and now if the if everything went
according to plan we should
we should have a really really slow
loading application um out there yeah
ojs calm and we press it and there's the
text you'll notice it just did something
weird there it made it small and ellipse
ellipse don't know how sad word so let's
make that a little bigger so when you
run again it'll actually work as
expected so now if we do ljs calm boom
hello Jas conf thank you thank you Apple
so that that's kind of a really basic
intro to objective c programming it
weird syntax crazy weird syntax but all
together it's not that hard it takes it
may be a little bit of ramp up but
there's a lot of good documentation on
it and a lot of a lot of people that are
interested in this so you can probably
find people to help you out and teach
you some stuff I highly recommend it on
one of my big passions besides a front
end dev and like mobile dev is just kind
of looking into languages and i highly
recommend looking into some languages if
javascript is like your primary language
or if you've been using javascript and
say Ruby I would look into some other
languages just to kind of see what else
is out there and how they do things I
think it will really help the community
as a whole to see how other communities
and other languages and frameworks work
and how people have been doing these
things so it's like objective seat on a
Mac development they've been doing this
forever so we can probably learn a lot
from them all right so that's a that's
that demo let's go back to here see if I
can so yeah native apps they're not not
that hard you can figure it out it takes
a little bit tom a little bit overhead
but i think most people could figure it
out and the second point on that one is
native apps are easy to get performant
and i think this is something we take
for granted is that
when you're developing these native apps
they do so much for you for free when it
comes to performance when it comes to
rendering speed actions like how long
the things take to like run and this
might not this isn't is isn't as big of
a deal i think in the in the mobile web
community and it should be a lot bigger
of a deal so like one of the things like
i'm sure everyone's seen the objectives
like like a native app where it scrolls
i'm not sure if android does this or if
they're working on another working on a
bunch of like GPU stuff in a 23 and 30
but Apple does some really crazy stuff
where they they actually so if the if
you're scrolling if you if you flick up
in the in a Cell moves off screen they
actually take it out of the out of the
rendering path and they give you a
chance to reuse it so you can actually
get a real ik handle to it and push it
and it'll push it onto the bottom of it
and so it's like it's like the cycle
that they do and it's so that they don't
have to do any kind of new object
allocation it's it's really and you
don't have to worry about it's all under
the hood and it's actually kind of hard
especially with these newer phones and
the new iPad it's hard to make an appt
not get high frame rate and what I'm
saying high frame rate i'm talking 60
frames a second i'm not talking you know
30 frames a second i'm talking 60 frames
a second so this is something that is
really big um so this lasts this last
year after working we released the ipad
app the iphone app and android app all
within five months of each other there's
there was three of us work this three of
us working on it and so at the end of
the the the android cycle we were
working on a mobile website our design
resource at the time was kind of
consumed by the android platform and
working on that so you know as being a
high and mighty web dev i decided that i
would just you know copy some of the
stuff we don't from the apps we can do
this it's a the mobile web is awesome we
can make this happen so I start writing
another yet another micro framework that
was more perfectly suited for mine
situations and I liked reinventing
wheels so we
I work on this and about a month or not
a month two weeks into it two or three I
kind of have this breakdown because the
this mobile site you know you're
flipping through it you're using it's
cool there's some stuff but it's just
wrong it just feels it feels like a
crappy version of our iPhone app and I
don't want a crappy version of our
iphone app I want a sweet mobile website
and so this this brings me to the next
point and I want to really ask this
question should mobile web really be
trying to emulate native apps and I
think this is a very interesting topic
and something that I think not everyone
is really asking themselves like why are
we trying to emulate everything native
apps are trying to do is that right does
it feel right when you go to a website a
mobile on your mobile phone and you end
up going and it looks kind of like a
native app but not really like how many
you have that experience where you get
to a page and it's just it's confusing
or it's just frustrating because they
tried so hard to make it native that it
just doesn't work and that could be
anything from performance to just
strange scrolling to just awkward design
and then the other thing is it takes a
lot of code to do that the I was so I
was writing this little micro framework
but it was still a lot of code it was
probably getting around eight eight
hundred lines of code to do some of this
stuff and I just like SAT back and I was
like this is not the right path it just
is something as simple as a back button
you know we take a backbone for granted
in the browser and sometimes we think
that the backbone is just to get you to
the previous page but it's not just to
get you to the previous page it does a
lot more than that if you if you really
take note of it it one thing is if
you're strolling if you scroll down and
you hit back you'll get back to that
that part of the page where you scroll
to this is very important and we
actually had a I'm gonna call it a bug
went live on the zappos a year or two
ago and it in Firefox who kind of busted
that mentality and it's scroll people at
the top so they be scrolling through
searches I click something they hit back
and they be
top we got tons of complaints and this
is something that you might not think
about but it's a huge deal and we don't
get a lot of a lot of complaints when it
comes to technical things and that was
really eye-opening and another thing is
it doesn't just bring you back to the
previous point in the page because if
that was all if that was all it was we
can solve this but it also brings you
back to the previous point of the page
with the current state of that page so
if you ever use a like a mobile website
no take note of JavaScript that ran on
that page go to the next page hit the
back button and see what the state of
the page is like it actually captures a
lot of like what the current state is
and so this is something that's very
hard and you'd have to write a lot of
custom code for your app this is
something a framework cannot handle
because it have to run it have to run
very specific code for your app to get
it back in the same state and I just
think it leads to a lot of broken
expectation expectations you know what
are you designed just as simple as what
are you designing for are you designing
for an iphone are you designing for an
Android Windows Mobile which is even
more different than both of them they
you know where do you put the back
button do you put at the top do you not
put a back button because Android users
don't like back buttons I have a
background on the phone do you put the
tab bar at the bottom you put it at the
top you know all these things are very
the each of these devices are very
specific you I kind of mentalities and
how they do things and I think that's
that's important that we try not to
break these expectations of what these
of these things and if we're trying to
emulate native apps this is hard because
they do things certain ways and if we're
trying to emulate all that it's just not
going to work so this leads me to my my
main point here is let's get back to the
basics of the web a lot of times as
developers we really want to try to do
something awesome right we really want
to push the envelope and I think there's
a place for that I think there's a place
for a lot of these tools I'm there was a
few talks yesterday on then they're
absolutely have like the world of
respect for these guys because
I've been doing web mobile web
development for the last month and man I
want to pull my hair out it's it's
ridiculous some of these bugs that you
have to deal with and and so they try
their don't try and do these things and
I think if we just get back to the
basics of what the web was all about and
what was that what did it used to be
semantic HTML like what ever happened to
that like where's the notion that we
should be still be building semantic
HTML websites I think there is also a
place for some of these crazy things and
uh I'm glad that Google and some other
guys are stepping up with some of these
like crazy like hash bang specs um I
don't know what you're standing on that
but I think it's at the very least it
allows us to do certain things that we
weren't able to do before so I think
there's a place for than that but some
of these things they just you know you
write JavaScript it just generates all
your HTML and while there's a place for
that and as you saw in the objective-c
that's kind of how it is it's just it's
it just feels wrong and you have to
learn a lot to be able to write in those
frameworks and I'd argue why not just
learn native app development if you're
trying to make a native app I understand
you have to make 18 different devices
but you don't really just the next one
is a progressive enhancement this is
another one those sites that run like
that they're only going to run on the
newest platforms and with this one I'm
not saying you have to support
everything I don't I don't think you do
you have to know your user base so let's
a pose we actually kind of lucky because
we really only have two types of devices
shopping on the mobile website which is
iphone and android i think we had six
blackberry request last week and i think
i know the guy that was doing that
because he bugs me about it every day so
you don't have to support everything you
just gotta support you have to support
your users but not all your iPhone users
are on iphone 4s you know not all your
your Android users have the latest and
greatest droid x2 or whatever that it's
it's a very it's we as developers we
usually have some of these latest
technologies
if you don't test it on these older ones
I I would you would see that things
aren't what all peachy and nice so if
when you're using some if you are
thinking about using some of these these
all-in-one apps things I would really
highly recommend actually finding
someone with like an old iphone iphone
to iphone 3 an android that's not the
latest one maybe it's maybe there's a
latest one but it's just a low-cost one
and really try some of those those
things out on them because it's it's not
always as performing is you would like
and sometimes it's it's borderline
unusable and that brings me to usability
I think this is a very very important
point so when you're designing these
things what do you design for as i said
iphone or android but i think if we kind
of abstract away from that and we kind
we did this with a kind of when kind of
web two point O was all catching on and
everyone was going on that we kind of
started making these really heavily
desktop like apps and I think we've
realized that that is not what the web
should be we stopped doing that and you
get a lot of much simpler applications
come out of that and people are more
used to certain mindsets when they're
browsing on the mobile devices and when
they're using the web and so I think
usability is an important point that we
need to really keep this in mind user
bill is designed around making a usable
app and also simplicity I really really
really love simple things complicated
things frustrate me a lot and so if we
go back to what the web was all about
it's all about some simple ideas you
know links should be links they should
take you to pages they we shouldn't be
trying to wrap this concept of the
native app around this web model and
other things things such as a be testing
and Google Analytics i'm sure most
places want analytics on your pages how
do you do this with those type of things
you can probably do it but you would
have to write custom code for all of
that stuff you can't just drop it in
like you used to be able to so
um yeah that's that was that point so
that's kind of that part now I want to
go into a quick demo of some of the
stuff we've been doing some other sites
and then jump into some kind of weird
tricks and hacks and things that a I've
kind of learned doing some of this
development um so let me go up here I
don't need you anymore all right so I'm
gonna go to the browser here I wish I
can bump the size of this one up I don't
think there is a way alright so it's
going to browser so i want to show you a
couple of sites first off before i show
you kind of like the new what we're
working on zappos but flickr is a very
interesting one where i think they did
that they captured this this notion of
the web really well it still uses some
some fancier tricks such as like the
hash bang or hash minus the bang but it
still kind of captures what the web is
about and it allows the user to interact
like it is a website so I'm just going
to go to me so if you haven't used this
it's it's really really nice so I'll go
to this picture here so if you can find
that guy and give them a bear hug like
that you can win a zappos fun bag that's
what I heard so this is ian c myers he
was leaving we opened up a dev dev
office and SF and so that was John bunch
the tallest guy is a pose giving in a
hug so yeah I mean this is it's it's
super simple it kind of interacts like
you would think it would it's it doesn't
it doesn't do a lot of crazy things now
I do have a lot of problems with this
one as well especially when it comes to
the back button they kind of break that
model whereas like if I go here I scroll
down I click on this guy or here and
then I'll hit back and I'm at the top
it's I guess it's not as bad for them
because there's not that many but it's
it's still not right it flush
rates people it's just not what they're
used to another example is a facebook
they do some cool touch stuff they also
do a lot of newer stuff and so they you
know it's it's it's simple it's you know
it's not they're not trying to emulate
everything in native app is um they just
kind of you know I have a drop down here
it's it's pretty simple stuff i like it
i don't actually use facebook but not
much so now i want to show you kind of
what we've been working on and it's
going to be kind of slope is running on
a dev builds going through a VPN and to
like layers of complexity so this is the
this is what we're working on if you've
seen the current mobile website and i
hope you and think that was what this
talk is about was that thing is i kind
of hacked it together real quick so this
is the the new mobile website here and
so I'm just going to do I'm sure to
search here so you'll notice that we
kind of keep the the idea behind of of
Zappos and kind of just pulled it over
we did some really good to have an
awesome designer we're can I think
that's a huge thing is we should have
good designers helping us so we have you
know the search results here and these
buttons up here which actually pull up a
select box so they're actually just
select boxes kind of massed in this
button form and it works absolutely
beautifully because they get like this
kind of what they're used to and we
don't have to implement that because
that would be a lot of work and it would
make it a lot of code and we're you know
lazy developers are how it should be so
you know filtering this is installed yet
I apologize and then stop paginate
encoder page for here and go to product
so you can see it's it's very very
simple like a like a like a website it
doesn't feel like a mobile app but we do
things where that where the browsers
allow us we do things that are
interesting such as the swiping you know
we you can swipe through product images
like you expect and people actually
expect
at like if you give them this site and
we've done some user testing and if you
give them this this page like this
they'll flip through it automatically
it's not a strange concept to them and
so and another thing is pinching and
zooming so we wanted to we have large
images on Zappos and we wanted to really
bring pinching and zooming to the device
and we could have implemented this in
JavaScript with some crazy complexity
but you know it was actually the
designers idea because he didn't think
like we could implement it in JavaScript
and we kind of bought a heads on that
for a second but he actually came up
with hey why don't we just go to the
image so we just linked to the image
here and you know you get native zooming
native scrolling and it it's actually
brilliantly simple and you could do that
in them and other ways to do by just
like going to a web page that's not
constrained by the scrolling of the zoom
if you wanted more features on that page
so yeah that's kind of I want to show
you one more thing that I thought was
pretty pretty sweet so I'm going to show
you a little bit of code here let me
bump this up and change the running out
of time but let me go to good what's the
best one for that ah that's not too bad
that's popped up
alright this block right here if you
don't know if you've seen these app
media queries and CSS but they're
actually really cool so you could you
can actually specify like hey this is
going to be only for specific devices or
not even specific devices but specific
qualities of a device so in this case
the max with the min with has to be 480
pixels so as to be 480 pixels before
it's going to run that block and the
cool part is if the page changes so that
it is 400 pixels at some foreign JT
pictures at some point it will then
apply that part of the style sheet and
480 pixels is the rotation of an iPhone
and in most androids are at least that
but the whole idea here is so we had
this on the cart we have this this area
we have three bonds on the bottom in the
the subtotal of that item but when you
rotated it we wanted to kind of lay out
slightly different it's it looks very
similar but it's different because of
how it has to be laid out and though
it's it's hard to explain because it you
usually it really makes it a lot more
sense on an Android device so it's the
way that the buttons were spaced before
are different and it's just so that we
can get this like grid line in the
middle so yeah so this this this block
runs only when it's that size I think
that's really cool some other neat
things if you ever working on the on
mobile web stuff there's these like some
of these like CSS properties such as
WebKit appearance we probably probably
haven't seen it or maybe you have I kind
of stumbled upon it by accident it was
one of the greatest things that happened
to me basically what it does is any kind
of Native feel of a UI element sew a
button a select box it basically just
removes it all and makes it like this
white boring button but it's awesome
because then you can just style it up as
however you want so we on all selection
all buttons we just kill all the native
styling and then later down below we had
gradients and other background images to
them to kind of give them the effect of
an actual button they
other thing is WebKit text size adjust
it's a mouthful but so when you rotate
an iPhone or an Android the browser
automatically kind of images the size of
the text to kind of scale it to fit the
page more but when you're making a very
specific app where you know the sizes
and your kind of relying on that the you
don't want that effect or things will
break at weird points and yeah so that
turns that just turns it off also
fantastic there's one more in here that
I wanted to which one was it it was so
I'm grabbing notes here it was 0 users
WebKit users select I don't know where I
use that whip Kate oops user up there's
I'm so users select this is so that like
you know that copy and paste dialog that
pops up when you're clicking around you
can actually disable that with CSS I
wouldn't I wouldn't that Apple gives a
big warning on that page of don't do
this on like the body because I would
make people angry if I did want to copy
and paste something but for specific
elements it's actually really cool so
like you know a button sometimes you
press and you're thinking about you want
to hold it for a second and a copy and
paste dialog pops up it's it's strange
so that's also a really cool one and
lastly box sizing which puts the you can
make it so like ghosts like I e6
rendering mode for an element which
sounds crazy but it'll actually put the
border and the padding inside the
element when it's laid out and it allows
you to do like fifty percent with with a
border which is awesome you could do
that with the flexbox tough but it's not
supported fully in everything yet so yes
so that's a that's pretty much all i had
there so i don't know if i have time for
questions oh yeah we're hiring it's my i
have to say that I think we're hiring
for a lot of stuff so pretty much if
you're into anything from front-end
development back
development mobile stuff cysts
engineering call center whatever yeah so
if i have time for questions I'd like to
kind of field a couple questions so the
quite the question I'll repeat it
Christian here is like for media queries
there's a lot of discussion on that and
should we use some of the mobile stuff
it works out but should be using it on
our main site to make the main site so
if you go to this site it will just use
media queries to make it a mobile site
and I think that really depends on your
what you're going for the the zappos
mobile website is very different than
the website so it wouldn't have worked
out the some of the information is
different we don't put ever we don't
push everything down some of the
features that aren't really required for
the mobile experience so when it worked
out for us but if you have certain
things I think like a good example would
be like any kind of content side like a
blog or anything to that I think it's a
perfect idea I don't you actually don't
know all the debating the debates on
that and so it works it's cool I guess
that's all I care about so yeah in so
the quote the comment was on why limit
this discussion of app versus or the app
the native app feel to mobile why not
also desktop browser and I think that's
an excellent an excellent point I went
in I think that's a great argument to be
made on the desktop platform as well I
think it's been something we've been
struggling with for a while I I just
don't have the qualifications I guess to
argue that so I'm going to argue what
I've been working on and but yeah I
think that's an awesome point and I
fully support that anyone else
alright well thank you roads take me
home to the place I belong hold the door