welcome to today's guess we have Rick
Waldron Cassandra perch and Francis
colada and i am your host Raquel villas
all right ok so I think we're running
behind because whatever and so I just
kind of wanted to start off let's just
kind of chit chat a little bit you know
we're running this kind of like a
podcast but it's live get it yeah all
right um so Cassandra how did you get
into no BOTS how did this happen um you
did that but yeah you know God up steer
and a JS cog I i went to note bots
during the the thursday and i'd heard of
Johnny Five but I hadn't like done
anything and so then they handed me an
arduino uno with the with the with the
swag bag and you were just so excited
about everything and and I was hooked I
built something I built an RGB LED that
you could control with with Wi-Fi or
with a web page and that was it that
that's how I got started so who's you
actually Oh God okay I totally did not
hear if it is your hand if you've got a
spark or in fact raise your spark court
you have your sparkle raise your hand if
you got one of these at home I want to
see some blue legs oh my god those are
the cool kids sorry Oh so-so
yeah who hears use Johnny Five before or
any other node bought stuff at all all
right that's awesome thank you you're in
the right place yeah how many of you are
signed up for four node bots or IRL
tomorrow so Charles it snowed bot snowed
copters node Rockets node boats okay all
right so its most of you those of you
who are going kayaking all right we're
doing the Segway whatever signals if you
have fun this is fun for a lifetime yeah
I mean once in a lifetime experience Shh
lifetime experience so first get started
so it was I I like these things and they
were fun but I'm really bad at see who
hears bad at sea so knows any see it all
raise your hand if you know any see at
all so you're all badass see I got it I
don't think so and that was me I was bad
at yeah but javascript was fun and oddly
enough parsing midi was fun and uh
that's what they owed is fine and no
doubt a fun trip is sniff and so these
this brought my worlds together and it
was great yay what about you what about
me she got started hi um so so I to do
robots once upon a time uh and then I
left because I see very well um and
actually also yeah it just got
complicated and then this guy decided to
go on stage with like his little little
cute little robot for the like like ran
around on a on a stage I was like whoa
but it's dumb like dum dum in a sense I
didn't have any actual like knowledge of
its environment so I was like okay time
to bring in some real robot like
knowledge into this yeah you can see
where we're was looking it could see
where it should not go yeah
so so yeah so I that's that's how i got
into node bots specifically but I've
always done the bots she's so humble it
turns out Raquel is what actually
legitimizes this entire movement she's
the sole purpose that there's any
legitimacy here what was it the NASA JPL
yeah yep yes high-five up here I got
started because of Chris Williams cuz he
wrote notes serial port and I was like
that looks like fun i could control real
world things with javascript know and
now I I laugh at the scoffing see that's
a circle laughter and then I created
Johnny Five sometime after that and then
we build things and I don't want to take
all the credit for that anymore because
so many people are I have their arts I
believe like 59 contributors to the
Johnny Five repo now like how a lot of
them are here actually if you've ever
had a commit landed in Johnny fly of
raise your hand yeah wait where y'all
are they all have rooms they're all like
napkins great fantastic I want to snack
well you get a snack later so how about
we do some demos yeah let's demo all
right so who wants to see some demos you
hate demos you don't want to see demos
we're gonna force you to watch demos I'm
a service cassandra has i think ok so
you ok demo let's also remember she
started a year ago right and and and
this is what this is what happens when
you go to the j sirl thing tomorrow and
then keep playing around UT to this so
um thanks what this is is a it's
controlled by NS burrito which was a
microcontroller that was kick-started
last year and it's running a modified
JavaScript interpreter
so this whole entire dress is in
JavaScript um yeah no um there are 56
RGB LEDs they are Adafruit neopixels
version 2 there's an accelerometer in
the bottom of the skirt so hold on
they're basically on a set time out to
add new lights and when I when the
accelerometer moves that timeout
decreases so basically more of them
light up when I move around there's also
a photocell on my on my collar I noticed
when the lights got dark this is
blindingly bright so what I did was I I
told the photocell okay when it's when
it's darker make the lights a little
dimmer so it's not you know blinding
yeah that's that's my demo so oh yeah
don't trip over something oh so it turns
off if there's too much there's too much
light yes they actually got the writer
if it's lighter because then you can see
the lights Oh stay away from that thing
that almost tripping Christ Oh anything
that is not encouraged oh I'm wearing
like flat shoes because I tried to twirl
in my hotel room in heels and it turns
out can't do it oh good thing I tried
that um but yeah that's that's my demo I
think all right awesome all right uh do
you have a demo hi I have a beginning of
a demo so you might notice your spark or
doing this so the Wi-Fi over here in the
main hall is actually I find out not the
same Wi-Fi we have over the robot room
tomorrow over there they took the they
thought a lot of things they thought of
all these little Wi-Fi devices so we
should have better luck over there but i
recommend you play with it in your hotel
room later well yes okay play with
eating your hotel room oh that thing
yeah it was your fault sorry about that
um so get him get him online get him
talking budu spark loaded we're gonna
have some instructions for you guys
later but if specially if you're coming
tomorrow and also you know if you have
you know want to play with it you know
to not now you know that's that's the
best way to go about it and because this
isn't connected because we're over here
I gonna come back to me later okay
that's fine cool Rick sure you're not
going to call this
and that was my demo yeah you in the
front rows oh yeah are we gonna we're
gonna do the thingy with the the what
should we call it yeah let's uh uh yeah
I guess we'll denied thinking with a
watchamacallit I got it so it's cool
take it from its gonna I was gonna sue
wait you want a quick time this thing
sure you could hold this I don't need
this I'll just talk really loudly this
is the project I've been working on for
several months uh no signal way home it
says know what's computer say no how do
computers work wait what well the I
don't know how to do that
contact do your thing this is totally
normal node bot see things by the way
controlling eat controlling both feet
there we go sometimes up down on the
floor like what angle a certain thing is
it and you know like a little notepad
you know like as I'm taking measurements
so in order to figure that out I got
sick of looking up at the laptop what's
going on controlling both feet left foot
is at the agrees right foot is that
degrees but it just says degrees hold on
a second hold on a second hold on he's
fainting it can't take the pressure Oh
robots they're not that smart they're
only as smart is and this is why the
robot revolution will never happen yeah
laughed hip roll is a degrees right hip
roll is that degrees it just says
degrees there's no actual number there
roll back your git commit yeah
so what I don't know okay o0 planning so
one second I told you we were doing this
yeah I know but just skip to the fun
thing let's get to the geez just do your
move this table is not not leveled wow
that's a bummer anyway if it was a level
table it would have done an arabesque on
its own and balanced can everybody see
what's actually going on here do you see
I mean the table is at least enough
level in the front there that this is
holding itself up the amount of power
required is it's significantly more than
any that you guys would be working with
over you know tomorrow or probably any
time soon but also what goes into this
is a whole lot of immaculate it's dead
is a lot of they're ready for this
javascript animation so i give this
whole talk at empire j/s a couple weeks
ago where I basically drew the I
basically brought out the similarities
and showed a couple of examples of
JavaScript animations and all this is is
is animating but we're just animating up
the properties of a servo of a thing
physical space right we're just saying
well I want to move the where it's
pointing from 0 to 180 which is
literally no different from moving a div
across the screen from like left 02 left
180 in animating so I actually want to
introduce where is he Donovan where are
ya this gentleman right here has been
diligently working on a whole new
feature for Johnny Five specifically for
the servo class it's going to be a
built-in animation system so you can
actually apply like you know animation
algorithms like easing ease out sort of
things to the motion and move
of the servo which allow you to
basically control any kind of motion or
movement Donovan actually is doing this
while working on a Quadra pet I don't
know if we have time for you to you can
hold it up or something you got it over
there so he's programming this also with
Johnny Five just these are all built
with just Johnny Five and JavaScript and
it snowed this this can be Wireless it's
got on board support for XP radios we've
got it wired so you know so I don't have
demo fail you see how well that worked
out you guys could probably harass him
over the next day or two to show you in
more detail I'm really excited because
he's abstracted the whole notion of like
timing and and calculating frames per
second and everything you need to
actually get really really smooth servo
animations it's all like baked ins or
it's still continuing down Johnny fives
a long-term goal of just providing the
best possible primitives for you to
build amazing things whatever your heart
desires hopefully with in addition to
that is not the monster board the moment
except I do have a Intel Galileo with me
Johnny Five can now control any board
you want it to control the introduction
of the IO plug-in system I was gonna get
one on boards you can run on a Raspberry
Pi on a BeagleBone on anything that has
an IO plugin written for it if you have
a board that you want to control and use
the Johnny Five API come see me will
build an IO plugin together why not
it'll be awesome i'm told very soon the
Pinocchio Pinocchio already has one
there yep no key oh yes spark there's
one for that too got it all awesome
that's all I'd say okay alright so okay
thank you I'll to our demos
you go okay did you want to do you want
to demo your sharkman I was gonna live
demo a shark fish I made this during the
talk earlier because I saw shark and I
just wanted to show how easy was to
throw together a sure hopefully by the
end we'll have a robot shark that maybe
node boats or node rockets to deal with
some gnarly terrorize there are sharks
here they do swim in the ocean and they
are aware of amelia island alright
alright alright so so okay this isn't
for question it's time for questions so
okay I went ahead and asked a bunch of
people on the internet what questions
you might have for this I have some of
those questions here I think y'all might
have some also really interesting
questions but I want to get like past a
couple of the more common ones I like I
want interesting questions so the
question like how do I get started and
go online there are lots of options
bubble blah like get a spark from the
vendor's kit and just start playing with
johnny five documented yes um yes also
asked us um let's see how many know
about Stu I need to take over the world
just one forty to forty two servos 42
sir yes 42 robots each having 42 servos
I'm not gonna answer this question yeah
you need that to a self-replicating
robot with have a good as many printers
repairing 3d printers in the other room
we're close yeah so that's cool uh
somebody asked questions for the robots
well so somebody wanted to know if if
their caretakers take good care of them
what's it like doing a lot of work for
people and how are you feeling overall
so one of the first rules of node boxes
don't build evil robots yeah
she peppery you have no actual last name
good talk robots cough last year we're
basically if we don't build evil robots
there won't be evil robots seems like a
pretty solid well if you think maybe I
can feel then don't be and and they
won't want to overthrow you and they'll
just want to help us and so also to be
fair there's there's kind of an
application for this question of like
how to travel with robots because
there's something I've got the law is
how do how do you travel with like
especially with like this um obviously a
TSA agent may look at this and think
what is going on um so one way you can
take care of your robots especially if
you're checking your bag put a copy of
make magazine in your checked bag with
your stuff apparently this kind of makes
it see a TSA agent if they inspect your
bag kind of go Oh maker got it the other
thing I did I left a letter in my bag
saying hello TSA agent here's everything
in my bag it's clearly labeled please
don't cut anything please don't take
anything and I actually did get a letter
when I got here saying that they had
gone through my bag and luckily
everything was okay I nearly had like a
heart attack when I opened my bag and
saw the inspection letters but yeah when
you're traveling take care of your
robots by labeling them clearly and
being very careful in packing them
excellent I always carry printouts of
the T essays various what can go and
carry on and what can go and check
luggage so the check luggage list goes
in the check luggage so it says all of
these things you might find in here it's
possible that's like tools put tools in
your check luggage or else they'll take
them away from you trust me they will
take them away from you
sounds like it is indeed um with the
carry-on stuff you actually I've never
had a problem they've looked at it
they've opened it up kind of poked
around and they're like oh I see it's
just hardware interesting electronics
great whatever on your way um I actually
had problems with batteries yes that's
what I was about to get 20 there are
interesting rules about batteries
batteries that are are active like
lithium polymer you know like it's a gel
inside right you got to bring that and
carry on because it's pressurized in the
cabin it's not pressurized where your
luggage goes right see what could happen
their problems you can put regular nicad
and and I what's the other one nine volt
yeah nickel metal hydride batteries in
your checked but why Polly goes in your
carry-on always yes yep home depot yep
that too yeah so let's see what else um
once I'm done burning up LEDs and
spinning motors what are some
approachable resources for learning the
rest of electrical theory without having
to pick up discrete algebra and Greek
along the way I think that's actually a
really good question uh you could just
go and get a masters in robotics um
don't have to you don't have to though
there are lots there are lots of good
beginner books sure there's a circuits
for dummies it yes yeah getting started
in electronics which was made the first
edition was like 1970 they used to sell
out at every radio shack electricity
doesn't change yeah you know most of
these components that we're using today
are the same as they've been for many
many years and it's pretty good the one
from the one from make the the magazine
company they haven't getting started
with electronics with lots of pictures
great for people like me and yeah so
their book is actually also really good
and it doesn't get too deep into the
math or Greek letters or anything like
that there's like two formulas you're
going to need for tomorrow and they're
both very there they're like three
letters so there's a question on here
that I'm going to ask it i'm going to
ask raquel to answer it what makes it a
robot not just some programmed hardware
oh that's an excellent question yeah um
so what's the difference between a robot
and just some programmed hardware to me
a robot depending on it like so you ask
five roboticists what the definition of
robot is and you'll get five different
answers I personally like the if it if
it understands instructions and acts on
them then it is a robot which means that
some programmed hardware is still a
robot but to me the coolest robots are
ones that make interesting decisions by
themselves given certain types of input
I like autonomous robots because they
can say oh what's going on in the world
around me based on that information what
am I going to do next that's a cool
robot otherwise program harbor yeah
that's cool too i do that we all do that
well program Tyler's question as well
okay I just say the definition of what a
node bot is is any program hardware that
runs nodejs so so note bots is sort of
the big old kachel for all of us
learning experimenting and doing
whatever the hell you want with it so
don't don't sweat it yeah absolutely so
um okay I think we're just about done
but if anybody has a really interesting
question and i'm talking like cool like
not not like oh where do i go get
something to buy on the internet that
way yeah you can ask those later but
like I mean like a really interesting
question no no yes in the back I know
what I want to do I wants worms I want
the mesh I just learned about the
Pinocchio it's a little power mesh
network it's not Wi-Fi it's everything
and their self healing and they talk in
addressing it just everything I want out
of a mesh network and I won't lost them
I want to know where they all are and I
want them to all do cool things that's
whether they're flying or walking or
crawling or just happen to be on people
look I think I think with the things we
could do with a low power mesh is just
and and you know you don't need to build
a server for freaking everything also
and I what I wouldn't see built in three
years isn't just robots at the stronger
community so I try to I try to kind of
say this everywhere I go with robots um
document your builds all of them like we
definitely wanna see what you're making
um if you build something awesome in
three years that's cool but we want to
see it so document your builds and I
want to see a stronger community and
tons of documentation in three years
about mesh networks in Pinocchio and
that's really scary actually to me like
the Met the best Pinocchio like I just
yeah yeah I think I really want to see
more computer vision type stuff and
right now there is a port for open CD in
in JavaScript it's really
counterintuitive and difficult like I
want it I want to just press play I just
want to NPM install blah and have it
like in my computer everything done I
don't want to have to build things on
top of it
and then start playing with opencv and
really making cool like making the
robots figure out how to like if I could
make my own rumba with with JavaScript
like proper with slam which is
simultaneous localization and mapping
and that would be awesome they wouldn't
run into you exactly and clean my house
I don't know three years you want a
robot clean your house we don't really
get it there runs java script yeah I've
the whole point of robots is for them to
do things for me that I don't want the
do myself that's the whole point I can
do that don't tempt me dangerous don't
what do you wanted you in three yeah
what do you want to see robots in three
years I want an apology from the
scoffers that's all hahaha all right
first I think that's a that's all the
time we have uh but thank you q outgoing