hi can you hear me yeah hi I'm Mary I'm
going to talk about Isla which is a
programming language I've been making
for young children so I'm going to talk
about designing a language for children
I'm going to talk about the compiler
that I wrote that runs the language I'm
going to talk about teaching my
girlfriend and my dad to program and I'm
gonna speak about modes of expression
but first I'll take you through your
first program written in ila code so
either as a drummer his years hopefully
yep that's my niece she's called ila she
likes the Yankees she's 2 years old and
her favorite lunch is jelly tots which
is a type of English sweetie here's some
more people mary is a guitarist and Emma
is a singer and Sophie is a pianist and
he's a list of eyelas auntie's so we'll
had Mary to that list Emma and Sophie so
let's review islets a drummer she's 2
years old
she loves jelly tots and she's got three
aunties a guitarist a singer and a
pianist so designing a programming
language for children well first of all
can children program I feel like a age 5
which is the lower bound of the age
range I'm aiming at for this language
then at age 5 then children can learning
to read learning to write which mean to
me means they can input code at the
keyboard and read it off the screen and
they can also reason as well they've got
the Faculty of reasoning so I've had
some humiliating defeats at the hands of
my niece when debating whether she
should be allowed to have another jelly
tot or so and then should children
program well computers are being used to
make more and more stuff and that's only
going to increase as time goes on and
also I think program
is the best way to control the computer
and so and I think a person makes
something to try and show what is inside
their head and I think it's a really
good thing for people to show each other
the insides of their heads and so should
children program well if computers are
being used to make more and more stuff
and programming is the best way to
control a computer then to me
programming is becoming like a core
skill the way we view reading and
writing and doing maths at the moment
and so I think programming should be
learned at the same time as all those
skills are you from about age four or
five what are the opinions that I use to
guide the development of the language
well number one programming is typing so
programming is not clipping together
little jigsaw pieces that have code
written on them it's not manipulating
blocks with a GUI it's not using any
kind of GUI it's it's it's typing words
into a computer and the reason this is
important is number one language is the
best way that humans have come up with
for expressing ideas in a powerful and
subtle way and number two there's this
notion of indirection which is the
reason that I think programming so fun
so I type in something into the computer
here and then something happens over
here and in between there's magic and
that magic is fun but I'll come back to
that idea in a bit number two the second
opinion I took was that you should have
an application for a programming
language it should be useful for
something so I didn't want kids just or
anyone just typing in random code to
instantiate variables or print out the
numbers between one and a hundred
because that's really dull they should
be able to make something with it
because that's the whole point of
programming to me is to express yourself
to actually make something and so the
application that I chose to start with
was a old school text adventure writing
environment so you can type Eila code
and you define your own old school text
adventure you know kind of like Zork or
adventure or whatever and then you can
play through it so it's interactive
but at the same time different heads
contain different things so I didn't
want to tie the core language to the
particular application that I chose the
storytelling environment and so I've
tried to make it general so that it
could be conceivably used for anything
and number four the fourth principle
that I've used to guide the development
is to use baby talk so what I mean by
that is to try and make the language
similar to how children actually speak
so that that means there's a few
ramifications of that so number one
there's no punctuation except for the
apostrophes that go around strings and
that's because punctuation is hard to
distinguish it's hard to distinguish
pieces of punctuation from each other
and it's also hard to type punctuation
because you often need to use the shift
key number two is that most programming
languages use programming jargon like
for or if a while or then and I mean
what the hell do they mean so all of the
keywords in either of words that a child
would actually use in the context that
they're used and the number three is the
language is somewhat natural language
ish and my aim there is to try and make
it so that even if you don't know much
code even if you don't know how to code
you'll be able to read the language and
basically read a piece of code and
basically understand what's going on but
at the same time I'm trying to avoid
that trap that say Apple script falls
into where it looks like English and it
gives you the impression that you can
just type any random thing that comes
into your head that's in English you
know the computer will magically
understand because of course it won't
and so there's only one way to do
everything and it's very consistent and
it's a much closer to a sort of pidgin
English so I'm trying to avoid that
impression that you can just type any
random stuff that comes into your head
so the ILA compiler this is the thing
that the piece of code that goes from a
piece of violet code like this so right
Eila to actually printing out either at
the console so how do we get from
a piece of code - the result well the
compiler that I wrote takes a two-stage
process does a two-stage process number
one parsing number two interpreting so
let's start with parsing parsing is
taking that piece of code which starts
out as a completely unstructured string
so just a list of characters and turning
it into a much more detailed recipe
called an abstract syntax tree which can
be used to actually run the code so here
is the abstract syntax tree for that
piece of code that we just saw a moment
ago right
Eila so this is going to print out
islets of the console nothing else so
let's go through it so at the top level
the whole thing is a tree then you have
an expression so the whole piece of code
is an expression and then you can
subcategorize that expression as an
invocation which means you're running a
function and then that invocation splits
down into two components the identifier
which is the name of the function you
want to work to run right WRI T and then
the parameter or the value which is the
parameter being passed to the function
which is either in quotation marks and
then the value can be sub categorized as
a literal as opposed to a variable and
then the literal can be sub categorized
as a string as opposed to a number so
this is the end result of parsing so how
do we get there we I used something
called a parsing expression grammar or
also known as a peg for short and a
party expression grammar it's a list of
rules which basically says on one side
I've got this thing and I can decompose
it as this list of things here so let's
take an example here's one of the
parsing expression grammar rules known
as a production rule and it says that an
invocation can be decomposed into an
identifier followed which is the name of
the function you're going to run right
followed by space followed by a value
which is the name of the which is the
parameter you're passing to the function
followed by a new line character so
let's look at the parsing expression
grammar for to pause this piece of code
so on the Left we've got
the grammar and on the right we've got
the abstract syntax tree that comes out
which is the end of the passing stage so
we have to start with an expression
that's what the parsing expression
grammar says okay let's pop that into
the abstract syntax tree then the next
rule says that an expression must be an
invocation okay easy let's pop that into
to the abstract syntax tree then the
parsing expression grammars says that an
invocation must be composed of an
identifier followed by space followed by
value followed by a new line character
as we saw a moment ago so let's take
those pieces one at a time an identifier
the parsing expression grammar says must
be a list of lowercase letters more than
one lowercase letter so that is write
the name of the function we're trying to
run and then the value the second part
of the invocation the parsing expression
grammar says that that must be a literal
okay let's pop that in and then the
pausing expression grammar says that the
literal must be a string and then it
says that a string is an apostrophe
followed by zero or more lowercase
letters followed by another ' and so we
can pop that into the abstract syntax
tree so we've passed that piece of code
we've done the first stage of the
compilation process so how does the
pause function actually work well we've
done the hard work now
because if you're using a pausing
expression grammar you're probably using
a pausing expression grammar library I
used one it's called page s it's really
nice I highly recommend it and all you
do is you give your list of production
rules your parsing expression grammar to
the library and then it gives you back a
parser and then you shovel code into
your parser and it gives you back the
abstract syntax tree so the pass
function is trivial next stage final
stage is interpreting so this is taking
the recipe that we've produced the
abstract syntax tree and essentially
following the instructions which means
running JavaScript code in my case that
is commensurate with the instructions in
the in the recipe so here's the abstract
syntax tree is JSON
let's look at it in a bit of detail line
two is the first node the expression
which is remember the overarching node
of the whole tree the tag attribute says
that it's of type expression as opposed
to an invocation or an identifier or
value or whatever and then the content
is every sub node under it in the tree
so the expression node has a whole of
the rest of the tree underneath it now a
quick aside the way the interpret
function works is that essentially what
you want to do is you want to run
different code depending on what type of
node you're dealing with so you want to
do something different if you're running
an X if you're dealing with an
expression node in the abstract syntax
tree so if you're dealing with a string
node in the abstract syntax tree now you
could do this by eye defining a bunch of
classes and then defining a specific
version of the interpret function on
each class and that would totally work
so you'd have a class for an expression
node and a class for an identify node
and so forth that would totally work but
it's a bunch of boilerplate and it's a
waste of time another technique you can
use is multi methods which is a
functional programming technique where
you just define the functions that you
care about so let's look at an example
again we're in JavaScript here I used a
library called multi message s it's
really nice so it starts out on line one
with instantiating the interpret
function which is just a multi method
now the way the multi master decides
which version of itself to run it
decides based upon what the arguments
are that are passed into the function so
let's look at an example so this is the
piece of code that decides which version
of the multi method to run so remember
we've got a version for an expression
node and a version for an identifier
node and so forth we need to figure out
which type of node we're dealing with so
we just look at the node that gets
passed in on line 3 look at the tag
which will be a string like expression
or identifier and return it so that's
the dispatch function so then this is us
defining the actual interpret functions
that we're going to run so on line 6 in
the case of an expression we do
something on line 10 in the case of
inuvik
Kayson node we do something else so
let's look at the real interpret
function same idea we've got a dispatch
function which tells us which version of
the function we want to run and here's
our first customer line six the actual
function that we run for an expression
node so it's pretty simple line seven we
look at the node grab the content which
and remember in the case of expression
node is going to be the whole of the
rest of the tree and then just call
interpret again so we recurse which will
result in running dysfunction the
invocation function so this is the
invocation version of the interpret
function and this is where the real
stuff happens so in line two we need to
figure out what the name of the function
is we want to run so we need to figure
out right WRI te how do we do that well
it's pretty trivial we just look at the
node online to look at the content and
then grab the first element of the
content which is going to be the right
identifier and then call interpret on it
which calls this version of the
interpret function for an identifier
which just returns the content of the
node which is just going to be the
string right so bingo line two we've got
our function name next line three we
need to get the actual function we want
to run so I've defined the write
function which just writes out the
string you pass it to the console in
JavaScript so we need to go and grab
that javascript function how does that
happen
what's what's going on here we can see
something about an environment now the
environment is the general context that
you're running all of your ila code in
and it includes the actual context which
is waste or all of the variables and
functions that are in scope currently
now that's where the right function
belongs the WR ite function and because
that's a built-in it's a function that's
built right into Euler it's available in
at all times so we need to go and grab
the right function from the execution
context so that we just get the
environment which gets passed into every
invocation of the interpret function get
the context off the environment look up
the function name and bingo we've got
the actual JavaScript function we need
to run
on the home stretch now we just need to
grab the parameter which was going to
pass to the right function which is just
remember it's ila in apostrophes that's
the thing we're going to print out so
it's the second element of the content
of the invocation node so we call
interpret again that calls the value
version of interpret which same same
pattern look at the content call
interpret that calls the literal version
of interpret same again look at the
content call interpret finally here at
last we've got the actual thing we're
looking for where this is the string
version of the interpret function and we
look at the content of the node which
will just be a low in apostrophes and
pass that back so now on line four we've
got the parameter work we're trying to
print out then long last line five we
could actually run the function so you
can see that we just invoke FN and
passing the parameter and that will
print out Euler to the console then it
returns a return value which in the case
of the write function is undefined and
then finally a bit of tidying up because
every every expression can modify the
environment we need to return the new
environment that resulted from this from
this node being run now in our case
there's no changes actually so the
context just stays as environment
context which is what got passed in and
then we specify a return value because
expressions in ila can return values but
obviously in this case it's going to be
undefined
so that's basically in at the end of the
code teaching my girlfriend and my dad
to program this was really fun i as I
said the eventual goal for ila is for it
to be usable by five-year-olds but
that's a long way in the future at the
moment as a stepping-stone I'm using non
programmers who are non-technical people
and which includes Elian my dad to try
the language out on so I sat each of
them down separately at an islet repple
where you can just type in pieces of
viola code and we worked through it so
this is Ellie she typed right my name is
Ellie in apostrophes which of course
prints out my name is Ellie
that was all good totally worked
understood what was going on first
problem was when I suggested that she
write out a number instead and when she
wrote this
she wrote write 26 but she put
apostrophes around 26 and I said that's
cool that totally works
but you don't need the apostrophes and
she said well why and I sort of thought
about it and thought well that's a good
question
and I thought about talking about the
historical reasons for why you don't all
the computational reasons why you don't
need apostrophes around numbers in many
programming languages but that was far
too much detail and so I asked her a bit
more about what she was thinking and it
it turned out that this apostrophe
notion was something that she clung on
to to understand what was going on in
the code so to her and my dad
apostrophes meant inert or inactive or
literal whereas no apostrophes meant
active something like a variable or a
function name and so the fact that there
were no apostrophes around the number 26
was really confusing because it seemed
like it was going to be active when
actually it was a literal so I've
changed that in the language and now you
have to put apostrophes around every
literal this is my dad now he's
instantiating the name variable and
assigning it to Richard and then he's
typing write name and of course that
prints out Richard when this happened it
was kind of profound that she was a sort
of beautiful moment because he said oh
this is fun and you know I mean he'd
never done any programming before he's
67 and it seemed like he understood why
it was fun and that I think brings in
this idea of indirection again where
again as I say you you do something here
and something happens over here and
there's magic in between and that's why
it's fun and so it's kind of like
setting up a long line of dominoes all
sat all stood on their ends where you
flick one and you watch the whole of the
rest of them go and I think that's why
programming is fun now finally for this
section metaphors when I was working
through the code working through
teaching Euler to Ellie and my dad then
I found myself using metaphors or
analogies a lot so to explain fair
variables then I used metaphors and I
found that they both responded to
different types of metaphors so Ellie
liked this notion of aliases where the
alias is like the variable name and then
the actual person is the piece of data
whereas my dad preferred this notion of
bags where you've got a bag and it's got
the variable name written on it and then
you put the data in the bag and that's
like a variable now the problem here is
that these are awful analogies that's
not the way variables work at all but I
couldn't come up with didn't think
better and then things got a little
worse when I try to explain references
to my dad so in I li can let's say you
instantiate two objects Mary as a person
and Isla as a person and then you say
Mary friend I'll a friend is Mary so
friend the attribute of Isla is a
reference so I explain this to my dad
with this notion of maps where map says
in treasure maps not hash maps and so I
said reference is kind of like a map
where you follow it to its location and
it might produce another another
reference another map and then you
follow that one to where it goes and
maybe you get the actual piece of data
and that's all good you know that works
he understood what I was talking about
but it took like five minutes and a
proper backwards and forwards
conversation and a diagram and so I'm
really unclear on how I'm going to teach
this stuff when I'm not there to talk it
through with the person being taught so
that's totally an open question at the
moment there's a lot of open questions
with eyelet really which leads me to
modes of expression final final topic
your mode of expression is the medium in
which you choose to make the thing
you're making so a mode of expression is
as a film or as a novel or as a piece of
prose or as a poem and you have to
choose your mode of expression extremely
carefully because your mode of
expression dictates your abstractions
now your abstractions are the building
blocks that you use to express your idea
so they're the sort of base materials
that you can combine in some interesting
way
to produce the thing you're trying to
make you know be a novel or Microsoft
Word or whatever and so his programmers
are abstractions of things like
variables or functions or continuations
or closures or libraries of code but the
most powerful abstraction that we have
is the programming language we choose to
use and it's a programming language is
kind of a matter of stretching really
and the reason for this is syntax
programming languages are really the
only way that you can control the syntax
that you use it's the only way you can
decide what type of syntax you want to
use and the reason syntax is important
is because it allows you to arrange your
other abstractions so you've got your
abstractions and they're all well
anchored but you use syntax to order
them and thus produce what you're making
so to explain what I mean I'm gonna talk
about freeze frames in film so the
freeze frame is being been being used
for pretty much since the feature films
were started being made and so by freeze
frame I mean the film the you know
you're watching a some film and the
film's moving and then it stops and
you've got a still image in front of you
for a number of seconds so if you go
back to 1947 when Frank Capra made It's
a Wonderful Life then near the beginning
of the film there's a freeze frame of
George Bailey the protagonist who's
played by Jimmy Stewart and he's talking
about the breadth of his ambitions and
he does this gesture like this but when
he's speaking then he side onto the
camera as iron to you and in this
gesture there's a tiny microcosm of the
whole film so what this idea expresses
is that George Bailey has these grand
Empress ambitions to build bridges and
to see the world but he in the end
forsakes them all in in exchange for a
life of great death so he stays in
Bedford Falls he marries the woman he's
in love with he raises some children and
he builds an altruistic business so his
life is not wide at all not not not wide
at all it's actually very deep and so
Frank Capra expressed a single idea with
this freeze-frame um it's
quite beautiful and subtle idea I think
but nonetheless it's a single idea if
you come forward to 1992 when Martin
Scorsese made Goodfellas then you find
freeze frames being used in a far more
subtle fashion
so there's freeze frames throughout
Goodfellas and what Scorsese uses freeze
French for is that's a piece of syntax
as opposed to a piece of vocabulary and
this is the key difference and the fact
that uses the freeze frame of syntax
makes it a far more powerful tool at his
disposal so to give you an example as a
freeze frame and he uses that as a piece
of syntax to arrange his vocabulary his
building blocks which are character
points of view so for example the film
freezes and you've got the narrator
speaking which is one point of view
you've got what the characters are
saying before the freeze frame and after
the freeze frame which is two more
points of view and then finally you've
got the actual what's going on in the
freeze frame and see he's using the
freeze frame to arrange these pieces of
vocabulary into a far more complex
construction and so Scorsese took the
freeze frame much further and this is
why syntax is important because more
powerful abstractions give you more
control over what you built and
abstractions suited to your work give
you even more control over what you
build and so to me there's just an
inevitable conclusion here which is that
you should invent your own programming
language
or to put it another way this is this is
the pharmacy I'm gonna say the value of
Greek prose composition he said was not
that it gave one any particular facility
in the language that could not be gained
as easily by the methods but they've
done properly off the top of one's head
it taught one to think in Greek when
stock patterns become different he said
when forced into the confines of a rigid
and unfamiliar tongue certain common
ideas become inexpressible other
previously undreamt of ones spring to
life finding miraculous new articulation
I will now take questions
awesome yes okay alright bring you the
mic Tiffany was this the first language
that you wrote and was your your
motivation to to write a language
specifically for your niece and have it
ready when she's 5 or was it really
about this idea and then you were like
what language I thought for my
development as a programmer it would be
good to write a language I think
everyone should write a language just
for the learning experience I thought it
was my first programming language and
I'm stupid
then maybe I should start easy with a
programming language for children big
mistake
it's I think it's far harder so yes one
question was sorry can you wave you are
yeah what is the next step I mean what
is the purpose for the language right
now you want to move into some schools
and also or what's the idea
the idea is to did the whole language is
completely in flux at the moment so I've
got some syntax and you can do useful
stuff with it but everything is up for
debate at the moment so I'm quite wary
of showing it to too many people yeah I
mean it's available on today I love
language dogs but I don't want to show
it's too many people because it's so
unfinished but so my next step is to try
it on as many people preferably
non-programmers and young children as
possible to try and tune it okay we have
another question way back here hi there
I really like your ideas especially
about kind of visual trickery and
programming environments what do you
think of scratch is that which ones that
is that there I mean the scratch
programming environment for kids sure i
I've looked at a number of languages
that are for children and I sort of I
think I said it in my in the talk that I
feel like many of them are taking the
wrong approach with starting with a GUI
because I think that's not programming
and I don't think you get the magic
feeling of programming manipulating a
GUI and also I don't think you can
produce nearly as subtle constructions
so I'm trying to steer away from from
all of those approaches essentially
any other questions a couple here okay
sorry all the time is we said yeah we're
doing okay for time so this is in
English I mean might be one of the most
common languages but do you think it
should be in in the native language of
the children I mean it's more difficult
for a German child to understand the
English language definitely
so the my idea is for this is that the
keywords can be translated into other
spoken languages trivially obviously but
the word ordering of different language
is different but nonetheless up because
there's only one way to do everything
that I feel like the syntax won't be a
problem there and so you could just
change the word ordering of each type of
statement you can make and change the
keywords and you'd have either in German
or any other language you choose what
are you what are you dead years to bring
the more complex constructs of the
JavaScript or whatever programming
language to a children for example think
about recursions or loops or whatever I
mean is an imperative language the right
way to teach that to children or do we
have to think more about a functional
what are you my idea is that at the
moment isla is purely a data definition
language so there's no control
statements there's no conditionals and
I'm trying to start with that core and
then build up adding things as I figure
out how to do them in what I hope is an
intuitive way so my ideas are a complete
muddle on the things that you suggested
at the moment um so you talked about how
eventually you want to teach it too or
you want to be teaching programming to
five-year-olds it seems like one of the
the biggest hurdles at that age and
teaching them with this rather than with
a GUI is just gonna be like reading like
at 5:00 a lot of kids can't read that
well and can't write that well what are
your thoughts on that
definitely so I feel like if children
are learning to read at that age then
they could learn to program in tandem
with it and so I hope that there
ability would build to increase with
their reading and writing ability I
haven't actually tried it with any
five-year-olds yet because it's not
nearly good enough for that yet so don't
know yet so you mentioned that you would
like to like write language that is
similar to natural language but not
quite because it might be dangerous to
actually make it feel like natural
language so where do you actually find
the balance where what's the kind of
dividing point where decides that's kind
of the way it should be the the rule
I've taken is that there's only one way
to do everything so there's only one way
to construct every piece of syntax which
I think hopefully is enough to give the
impression that you can't type whatever
you want but still totally under that I
don't know whether I've made the correct
assumption there yet but that's my sort
of dividing line that I hope will keep
it from going into AppleScript territory
where which is just a mess there's only
one way to write correct
isn't that curbing the imagination of
children or um sorry could you repeat
the question yeah so I thought you said
there's only one way to write a correct
syntax for your programming language
isn't that curbing the imagination of
children I don't know
and quite obvious obvious question why
do you choose JavaScript I was actually
a bit of a confession
the original compiler is written in
closure i ported it to JavaScript so
that I could submit it for a talk to
Jess