designer who am I my name is Carlos
Perez I am the director of design at bat
hound I am a designer but i also like to
build a lot with the web and i made my
first website in 1995 and i use tables
to do the layout and i use a phone line
to transmit the data so dating myself a
little bit but yeah I've been at this
for a while so I design I code I use vim
and I lie I love working with developers
I don't just like working with
developers I know sometimes that's an
odd sentiment from designers I wish it
wasn't but sometimes it is you can
follow myself forbid hound where who I
work with at carlos perez r at bid hound
io on Twitter and yeah it how it is
sponsoring this which is awesome I'm
happy to be here this is my first time I
guess it'll be my last time
unfortunately but really excited to be
here so what am I talking about when my
boss Dan came to me he said we want you
to do the talk at JS comp for us this
year and I said okay that's that's a
little it's intimidating it's a bit
awkward because what do I have to
contribute to a room of developers and I
kind of figured you know what actually I
have a lot to contribute we work
together a lot we can work together even
better a lot of the times so I really
did see this as an opportunity it took
me exactly one week to do to get to that
point but I figured yeah let's go for it
so what I'm going to run through is kind
of a little bit as you're going to share
a bit of the process that we have a bit
hound and how we mesh design a
development together I wouldn't say it's
necessarily unique but it feels good so
I'm kind of excited to be able to share
that any time I have the opportunity to
so I'm going to talk about where design
goes kind of seems like a silly question
but it's it's one I think a lot of
people struggle with what's our process
how do we accomplish these things what
tools we use to improve collaboration is
there too much about good things
sometimes and I'll share some some
downfalls why javascript is the best to
help bridge design and development
and why this all matters so just to
preface this this isn't the agile
manifesto I this is just my opinion and
we we pride ourselves in changing our
process a lot if you know we might have
a few sprint plantings we're just like
you know what this isn't working anymore
and we things up so this is kind of like
the culmination of of what we've
experienced over the past couple years
some of my experiences working at other
organizations so again just my opinion
so to answer that first question where
does design go it's a tough question
product managers designers developers we
all struggle with it where does it go a
lot of deb shops you now use agile of
course and it's usually a developer
introduced process and it usually winds
up living in development so as an
outsider the designer coming in it's
kind of hard to find that sweet spot of
like so where do I fit in on this so I'm
going to hopefully answer that a little
bit better we know it shouldn't go at
the end I think we've been beaten the
over the head with that enough where if
you're leading designed to be that
little like little bit of lipstick at
the end a little bit of Polish that you
want to pretty things up ah it doesn't
really work so I'm not going to dwell on
that too much so that can only say the
beginning right and it feels good I'm
going to start off with design we're
doing you're right we're thinking about
the problem first we're going to do the
mock-ups and then we're going to hand it
off and we're going to build it but this
is actually kind of where I see the
process fell apart a lot because the
expectation generally is designer and
the product manager go off look at the
research do interviews with users do
some wire frames makeup to mock ups then
that got to hand it off the developers
create some stories get those assigned
and it gets built and it's usually about
this time when the designer stops that
on that feature and goes works on the
next one something that I had struggled
with a lot was the idea of having to
keep one sprint ahead of the developers
and that was really really challenging a
because it expected that that work could
be done
you know in a sprint right ahead but
then it didn't really give that
opportunity to continue working on that
initial feature so yeah so what's what's
the problem with I won't i kind of just
explained that sorry but the i think
that what what generally happens with
this is the designers original intent
might not carry through to the end
product and that's not the developers
fault at all everything is done with a
series of best guesses right designers
will do mock-ups based on the
information they have at the time to
give it to the developers developers
have different information they have
technical reasons why something can or
can't happen they run into other Road
bloxorz other bugs there's other
priorities that come up so to make the
assumption that we can figure out the
design at the beginning and then it gets
just you know the perfect product comes
out at the end well it's it's a
challenging one so all right where does
it go might not like where this is
leading but it's kind of everywhere and
that's easy for me to say and the
designers standing up here saying design
should be everywhere well development
should be everywhere too I think it's
really a product building Express it's
not a dev process it's not a design
process so I've been home we really try
to make this about the product
development starts at the beginning
design starts at the beginning and we
work our way through it so let me
explain how we actually go about doing
this so how do we put design everywhere
for starters we assign our features to a
designer and developer pair board our
CTO just pointed out to me it's like
yeah we actually have two designers and
one developer we're not counting you of
course we have another one so but that's
that's actually kind of an interesting
thing and we're building a tool that
looks at your code it's kind of neat
though so we we assign the feature and
the expectation is we don't really go
dive deep into what that feature is
supposed to do at the time we let the
pair figure that out and that what that
kind of means is just from the get-go
there aren't necessarily too many
assumptions about what it
look like we start by looking at the
data so a lot of our features will
actually start with a route that outputs
JSON or you know not even maybe it's
just something we we throw in slack and
that's where we start discussing it and
what this does is gets rid of that
paradigm of the designer using perfect
data to do these perfect mock-ups and
everything looks beautiful but once you
start plugging in real data you realize
that falls apart really quickly so we
start with the data so that anything
that we do from a design perspective is
already looking at real world
circumstances and that really that
really helps out a lot we don't define a
handoff stage where you know once
designs done developers take over of
course it happens but it's never it's
never the same for for any given feature
so and like I said there there would the
handoff might actually happen multiple
times designed to Deb back the design
and it's a iterative process another
little trick up our sleeves is we we
like designers who code so where we code
enough to be dangerous so you can really
probably call us front-end developers
that's probably what we would be called
in a lot of organizations but we
definitely lean towards the aesthetic
the experience side so weird that first
run at second but given how closely we
work with our developers that's a very
nice compliment what this also helps
with which you might appreciate is those
pixel perfect mind-numbing alterations
that the designer wants to do well we do
that ourselves so hopefully that leaves
the the more interesting and more
complicated dev work available so you're
not getting annoyed by us all the time
so developers help with design problems
that's that's how we do it designers
help with Deb problems and we we do do a
lot of pair programming but it's often
with the designer and the developer
which is really neat and we both learn
so much
from that process oh so that's top tools
and i don't mean the designers i mean
like apps and stuff the ones that we use
to help us do this process better so to
start i want to say break down the
barriers of these are design tools and
these are developer tools because that
already been just silos the the process
like well i'm not supposed to use that
so i'm not going to bother learning
about it so we we try to find as many
many ways to level that playing field we
we use pull requests kind of like how
github I don't know if they still do but
this is what they used to do there's
presentation called how github uses
github to build github and we kind of
modeled our process around that and that
is you open a PO request the moment you
start on a future versus it's just the
thing that you do at the end to review
the code and what that lets us do is is
embed discussion into the pull request
we have this thread of comments we put
mock-ups in there we put all sorts of
things we use it to review code of
course and it gives us kind of a
historical backlog of how a feature got
developed and we tend to work very
closely in office together but whenever
travel does happen this is a perfect way
for us to stay on top of things but the
fact that design is in those pull
requests from the beginning also means
that towards the end of the review
process design is also involved and they
know everybody is on the same page about
what's going on your issue tracker I
included this because I i went to a
design meetup months ago and I asked to
designers about what issue tracker they
use that at their companies and they
kind of just grumbled and said oh I
don't know the developers use pivotal we
don't usually touch that which I kind of
found found interesting is like why not
that's perfect way for you guys to
collaborate with development put new
ideas down initiate discussion so I
actually see the issue tracker is just
as much as design tool as a development
and it's great for great for that
conversation so for designers who are
just dangerous enough with
ode get is a very daunting roadblock a
involves the command line so it's
already you kind of lost most designers
and so once you're you know you want to
play around with code but then get kind
of gets in the way so you must have I'm
sure there's a onboarding process to
share your your best practices with new
hires when it comes to your get process
and i encourage you to include designers
in that as well there's a there's a GUI
app called tower for the mac that is
brilliant for this that's how i got to
understand get i now use it on the
command line but i still use tower for
certain things because just does it
better Oh at least I feel it does better
so get them comfortable and get your
local dev environment should be friendly
and this is obviously could be said for
both designers and developers the moment
again any barrier that might prevent
somebody from pittle fiddling around
with with code from prototyping
something it's just an excuse to say you
know what hey not really my job I guess
I'm going to stick to doing some
mock-ups and sketch or Photoshop so a
bit helm i love i love our local dev
environment it takes those commands to
get running board did a talk about how
we how we get from zero deploy request
and by noon or buy lunch something like
that and it's totally doable so the the
easier it is to get up and running the
less of a barrier of course it is to
start fiddling with some code this this
kind of seems like a like a simple idea
use old-school tools and but it's
actually quite powerful when you think
about use a chalkboard or you use a
whiteboard or paper whatever and there's
no pretenses behind well that's a design
tool or that's a developer tool no it's
it's just that it's a thing it's a tool
and we use them extensively we use them
for our sprint planning we you we do our
to-do lists on there we do our mock-ups
on there and it's very common to see
will
have a design element mocked up and
right next to it the data structure of
the data that's going to populate those
elements so that discussion happens from
the get-go javascript is the best I
don't have to tell you this you're here
for a reason but i'll give you the
designers perspective of why javascript
is awesome for this this includes jquery
and I know I've and I've heard it
firsthand where it's like we want
developers who do javascript and no not
jquery and it's like well hold on a
minute jquery is I think the best
language to orb language sorry framework
that bridges what's happening in the
browser to code and it's something as
designers it's really easy to understand
and I've tried PHP I looked at
objective-c million zillion times and
gave up on that those never took jquery
it was very easy to grasp very easy to
start prototyping in it which brings me
to prototyping I mean that's great again
you know this designers might not open
up the Dom inspector I mean I've I know
how many times I've done this too it
doesn't look as designer and said like
even if you just wanted to change text
you can do it like this and then their
eyes just light up and never mind the
things you can actually do with with
actual animation and they're all that
kind of stuff so javascript is it's
perfect for prototyping a lot of our
features start as hockey prototypes like
this and they that's they get cleaned up
but that's eventually what gets chipped
and it's even better when you're using
nodes so for my personal experience I
knew a little bit of jQuery I got better
at just vanilla JavaScript and then I
started to understand the backend a lot
better it's one language I got it and
again that's just a powerful thing to
arm somebody with when when it usually
it's just a very daunting task so can
you have too much of a good thing is
there too much crossover that happens
between design of development and there
it's absolutely there is something that
the designers that at Midtown often
struggle with is getting caught up in
the challenge of trying to figure
something out so after about the sixth
hour trying to scour stackoverflow for
an answer I asked a developer and I get
it solved in five minutes so it's
something we just have to kind of keep
on top up and say this is this is great
we're all about the pursuit of knowledge
and and learning about this but at the
end of the day we got to ship something
so it's just something to be cognizant
of we also find developers using doing
too much design actually we don't it's
it's I didn't have a screenshot of the
table thing that you did other day but
and this isn't a slight honestly what
what is what is awesome and I never get
tired of is when when we're talking
about features or we talk about planning
and the developers are saying hold on a
minute we can't do it like this that
would be a bad experience that wouldn't
look right it wouldn't fit well with the
product and that that happens a lot
which is really really awesome the
biggest concern is when is a feature
done so you're working with design
development very much entrenched and you
start getting those problems and you're
starting to any and you need to solve
them and that couldn't spiral sometimes
out of control but at the same time it's
kind of a good thing so I mean we call
the scope creep right but the scope is
rarely right so when it one's a better
time to do it well right in the middle
of it when you're when you're building
the product so it is good but of course
at the end of the day you need to you
need to ship something so we still need
we still struggle with it and we just
need to plan a bit better at ahead to
know you know what this looks like one
of those features that just it's going
to grow will will often ship things into
production behind a feature flag will
play around with it for a while
or we before we expose it to the to the
rest of our users and sometimes
sometimes this happens and maybe on more
than one occasion but I don't really
want to dwell on that yeah I've ruined a
good couple morning by force pushing to
master I really like the new protected
branch feature on github and I do have
some pre push or commit tools a command
line to prevent that but that's good I
hopefully will never hopefully will
never make that mistake again so so what
why why does this matter why why should
you try to get designers developers
working together and honestly think it
makes for more thoughtful products you
start you start thinking everybody
starts thinking about the experience
about the user you're all working
towards the same goal it and it
translates to to your users kind of like
a mentioned before there's a constant
level of Polish going on because both
designers and developers are all of a
sudden comfortable to fix those little
nitpicky things that are in production
that never quite get assigned in it in a
sprint because yeah they're never top of
mind right everybody's armed with the
right tool set to make the changes
themselves so we will often just fix it
rather than open up an issue because
usually it's just a couple more minutes
of time so designers think more about
code structure and implementation which
I strongly believe makes you a better
designer it reinforces the process
aspect of it and developers think more
about design experience and of course
you guys already do I get it we are we
always try to understand the process the
development process as well I think this
just makes it a little bit stronger but
what this really all kind of boils down
to is that it's all about empathy
once you start to understand your
co-workers challenges once they start to
understand yours you can actually help
each other and this speaks volumes to
what the product starts to feel like and
what the users wind up seeing with this
so it's empathy between your co-workers
is empathy with your users which is
really powerful and the onus isn't on
developers this isn't hey how come
you're not letting designers in that's
not the problem designers have to be
just as willing to participate I've seen
with plenty of designers who don't want
to participate so I think it's it
obviously takes both sides to get that
process figure it out and that's that's
it keep in touch again my twitter handle
it hound I really urge you guys to go
check that out I love to hear some
feedback on it and yeah thank you very
much if you have any questions come see