hey everybody I'm fought a wolf before
we get started this is all this is
pretty similar to my absolute last slide
with all this info so yeah get out your
cameras or really quickly type the notes
if you write down nothing else just get
that top link which is bit dot Lee slash
Fatih - Cascadia je s - 2018
that's bit dot Lee slash Fatih -
Cascadia je s - 2018 that's all these
slides sans that one link in PDF format
if you want to follow along alright I
want to do I do that because I noticed
we're all speaking really fast because
we're trying to cram everything we can
into 25 minutes I will try and do the
same all right so my talk is called
teaching decided to touch and feel a bit
more or a bit more empathy the react
native Braille 6 key input NPM package
that our team at the circus Inc created
for PSU Department called Universal
Design lab and for an app they want to
create it called unify ueb prep which a
ue b stands for unified english braille
which I'll get into and that's a picture
of the package in action right up there
in the top center so about me my name is
Fatih wolf that is my legal name I'm a
web and mobile app developer in
JavaScript at the circus Inc that's the
circus comm in Portland Oregon
that's the polish spelling by the way
because the owners of our building are a
Polish descent and they call the
building circ so we're the circus and I
ran away and joined the circus
and I am a totally stable genius if any
of you have a problem with my saying
that I would just say I'm as much of a
totally stable genius as anyone else who
feels the need to constantly claim that
they're a totally stable genius however
I'm not necessarily a react native or
NPM genius I had played a bit with react
native and I
some react stuff prior to joining the
circus I love that sing I joined the
circus and I knew I've known an npn I
done some express stuff and such and I
downloaded and used NPM packages great
but I'd never done an NPM package myself
before these are all the ways you can
get in touch with me and a bit about me
I tend to be on my off hours a streaming
binge junkie that's why the picture of
the doctor Jodie Whittaker up is up
there I am Brad Baker I have my own
sourdough starter home I bake bread with
oh I thinking I need to feed that
starter and I'm a bicyclist that bottom
thing is me at the end of the Seattle to
Portland ride three years ago and I am a
beer snob no PBR for me thank you so
before we get into the main part of the
talk I want to ask you guys to
participate in a little experiment with
me you don't have to participate folks
if you don't want to but if you do I'm
going to ask you to get out your smart
device be it a iPhone or Android or a
tablet or an iPad or whatever and I'm
going to ask you to lock the screen so
it goes blank and then close your eyes
with your eyes closed just by touch
unlock the screen now if you have one of
those fingerprint sensors that should be
easy if you've got like the modern it
checks your face you can just turn it
toward your face with your eyes closed
if you want then once you think you have
it open try and do a simple task open a
message an SMS message and try to start
typing in an SMS message or a notepad or
open your mail find the icon that opens
your mail and begin to try and touch and
see where messages are how's that going
for everybody
I thought so so what's this all about
I'm here to describe to you a new NPM
package for react native that we made
because we created the app and react
native it for a keyboard for Braille six
key input I'm going to talk about how we
get got here or why we created this in
particular I'm going to talk about the
road to getting there which is as Sir
Paul said a long and winding road many
twists and turns and now with even more
crushing to fit defeats yet triumphant
via victories and I'm also going to talk
about the future of it and how you folks
can contribute to this open source NPM
package before I go any further
Marcy mentioned accessibility and I'm
very much especially since working on
this before this me and knowing
accessibility and Al Evan why not much
and in fact I haven't worked very much
on that part of this product that we're
working on and so it when people said
well as you're talking to me about
accessibility in a 11y my first reaction
was to go no because I just didn't know
that much about it
except there has been a person he's an
intern working on that part on the app
and I will talk about it a bit later
also I didn't want to talk about it much
because it's kind of known that react
native is very what or used to be very
limited in how it handled accessibility
in a 11y it was extremely limited and
people weren't happy about it but then I
I did a little bit more searching I
thought well maybe we can incorporate
some of that in here I wanted to call
everyone's attention to an article I
recently read it's on LinkedIn it's
written by a MS Zeki Chen she's a
computer science and business major at
UC Berkeley and for a few months she was
an intern at Facebook working on react
native particularly on the accessibility
API for react native and she talks about
in this that's the link to the article
right up there so feel free to look it
up it's a very good article she talks
about what the original limitations were
that people were complaining about she
talked about the
sighing decisions when she was an intern
that the team made and how they
implemented them and how you can begin
to use them now so I highly recommend
this article and I think we're gonna be
going over it and implementing a lot
into our app so how did we get here well
first before I ran off and joined the
circus as I said mid 2017 to late 2017
dr. Samuelson OTT and dr. Holly Lawson
their PhDs at Portland State University
they Sam runs the universal design lab
that's the links for all that and they
wanted to create an app to help families
and allies and friends of people who are
sight impaired learn Braille right at
least beginning that was what our goal
was with this app and this is the little
website that we created for them that
last link on the last slide goes to this
site is sort of announcing the app hope
we've got Sam has gotten his enterprise
accounts for Google Play and iOS now and
as soon as he gets the marketing
materials this app should be released on
the App Store's in the next few weeks
and so we were going to create this app
for them and this was created based on
mock-ups by the owner of our agency Juan
Fernandez he's a amazing graphic artist
and he and so we were going to begin
work on this and then I was hired in
February of this year 2018 to do some
web work with them but mostly to really
laser focus on this react native app for
PSU so of course I was just getting my
feet wet in react native and such so I
couldn't do this alone that's my CTO and
boss and he's also a co-owner and senior
partner at the circus that's Ryan
Anderson I hope next year in the next
couple of years he does a call for a
proposal here because the guy's a
freaking genius he really is I rely on
him for so much and I really admire him
also that's the intern I was talking
about from PSU
dr. Senate Sam he he found him he's a
computer science major PSU and he's
helping us and he's the one who began to
incorporate a lot of the accessibility
so some of the commands within the app
could be spoken and then there's me
working diligently every day in on the
app so what were some of the
requirements of this app well it needed
to run on smartphones and tablets on
Apple iOS and Google Android now I'm
running out of everywhere on you know
tablets iPads everywhere
send so of course Ryan the CTO and the
rest of the screen well let's do react
native it right once runs on both iOS
and Android forever right right we'll
talk more about that in a minute it
needs to be responsive on all sizes of
screens and phones and tablets it needs
to have interactive exercises that can
be logged and people get awards or the
the admin on the backend can see what
exercises and courses people have
completed and that included a keyboard
to input six dot Braille characters
which is what you see in the universal
English Braille there have been two
grades of that by the way there's been
grade one and now we're on grade two of
ueb the Braille input should not cover
over parts of the screen in the app with
which the user is tried interact just
like when you bring up a keyboard in
notepad as you'll see me do in a moment
it should not cover the whole screen you
should be able to see what you're typing
and you should be able to touch all the
buttons in the Braille cell at once and
make any Braille character in the six
dots that is possible using multi-touch
and it should all be a seamless
experience right and I know some of you
who know accessibility and a11y much
better than I are going wait fada does
an apple iOS and Google Android have
similar accessibility controls for the
site impaired
well yeah
Google Android has this thing called
Braille back it's not part of the OS
it's a separate free app you can
download and the problem with that is it
expects you to have your own external
Braille keyboard they make these
accessibility keyboards for people who
are cycling pared who want to type
Braille maybe you've seen some people
use them I will say they are kind of
expensive Android also has a thing
called G board which is their
internationalization the ability to type
in many different languages using the
Android G board and someone in a forearm
or in some Stack Overflow post I read
said and it can do Braille I said really
and I started going through and looking
up everything I could find Google
searches and Stack Overflow about G
board and I could not find a Braille
library for it I could be wrong I don't
I'm a fully admit that I don't know that
much about it so if someone knows if
there's an ability to do Braille through
G board please let me know Apple iOS
it's built baked into the system with
the accessibility controls through the
general control panel and with voiceover
so I'm going to give you an example of
this now I'm gonna unplug here and plug
this into my phone so you'll see my
phone screen they're gonna need to turn
this off for a second so because I don't
want to cause seizures in the audience
from the screen flashing alright and let
me get to the app I want so I haven't
set up I I haven't set it up already so
three clicks on the power button brings
up voiceover and then using the rotor
which you can set in those accessibility
Croke controls and general settings you
can switch to a keyboard so just like a
regular keyboard you have these things
any but you can still see your screen
above etc but now I'm going to turn
voice over on I'm going to hold this up
so you guys can hear it
voiceover on notes no text field is
editing character mode
let's do new one there we go
and now here's the voiceover on no no
bring off-screen input or escape there's
a bubble to the left table top mode
contract a b c d alright voiceover off
that's a good example of that and i am
now going to switch back so that you can
continue and if you're not a sight
impaired person who's had to get used to
using a device with sort of okay Google
or Alexa or a Siri barking back at you
constantly that can be a bit
disconcerting and annoying right and we
want something that was a little bit
more seamless so I said let's make it an
NPM package and open source it and they
said yeah and we're all excited because
we're now I'm making my first
MTM package and they're gonna help me
and this is gonna be great right and so
there it is the NPM package that's the
link if you want to go take a look at it
it's up there it's got to read me for it
and here is the related github
repository now the github repository has
one thing that the package does and
that's if you see at the top there's a
little app thing that's an expo app that
allows you to test and see the thing
working and I'm gonna unplug this again
and plug it into the phone and we're
gonna see the expo app working this is
silent because the app itself doesn't
have any I mean the package itself
doesn't have accessibility but you can
add that into what other app you put it
in so here it is working hopefully there
it is alright so there you go the
Braille six key input in action there's
a name there's a B there's a see there's
a D there's an e alright you can delete
or you can clear the whole thing you
know
and that's doing just standard Braille
all right I'm gonna switch back now so
there we go that was working great so
far and we got the interface and the
touch working fairly well and we were
testing it in expo on iOS and it was
looking and we figured out be the same
on Android and so everything's ready
right but not quite there is as you go
between platforms like I said many
twists and turns initial tests on Apple
iOS said eh okay ready so we were kind
of feeling yeah let's go
MVP ship at until we began to test on
Android not so much
some of the problems we initially had
Braille fonts those who know Braille you
that's let me see a be a see us that's
the word abacus right there I have
learned a bit since February I wanted to
show you that over here what we did was
I did a kind of test in code pen and
kind of shown all sorts of different
fonts working we have source sans sim
Braille which comes from the American
publishing house for the blind with
their Braille blaster program they have
for translating Braille we tried source
sans and Apple Gothic and other things
that had Braille in them and what Holly
dr. Holly Lawson wanted was these
wonderful little things called ghost
dots and she wanted the Braille large
enough of course on phone screens and
tablets that people could read it
especially if they weren't fully sight
impaired but mostly sight impaired so
okay we we we did some testing through
this and even though these all look
great here what we found is some of them
just don't show up with the ghost bot
dots even if we do react native
link of the font once we import it even
if we do that some just don't show the
goats box dots the one that worked on
both Apple iOS and Android Apple Braille
once you react native link it it worked
great so let's go back here so that
problem solved then we had the
responsiveness in portrait versus
landscape and different screen sizes for
different screen sizes if it wasn't
doing well with the react native style
sheets no matter what we did we had to
make certain helper functions to check
is this an iPhone 10 which is a much
larger dots per inch screen is this is
this an iPad we did a little helper
functions and then we would redo redo
the style sheets based on that and I
also found this wonderful package react
native responsive style sheet to show
you in our app that working here is like
the style sheets down here first you
import it once it's in your package JSON
you import it using the important
statement up here and then down here at
the very bottom we have the style sheet
there's there's the regular normal
styles using the responsive style sheet
create and then below there are the
responsive styles if your normal styles
are what you want in portrait you can
just leave the Portland port the
portrait is empty objects and then any
variations in landscape you can put in
there that will register and I'm going
to unplug and plug back in again just to
show you real quick so with this in you
can see it working like that and that's
the react native spot a style sheet
unplugging again thank you oh you didn't
see it I'm apologize
quick let's wait till they it's plugged
back in there we go alright so here
there you go everyone see that all right
thanks for keeping me honest and unplug
again I have to tell them that so they
you don't see a whole bunch of flicker
screen alright I'm plugged back into
this area so that problem solved so then
there was the question of you know being
able to touch all the buttons at once to
make all the Braille characters and of
course we all know that as lordy poss no
multi-touch so there are two choices
here a couple the first was and I'll
show this to you the react native
gesture responders system API here it is
and it starts out pretty good and yeah
I'm reading through it and my boss Ryan
the genius saying you should use gesture
responder system for multi-touch and I
kept reading through and I saw these
props that you attach to the view in
react native I'm going yeah but there's
not many examples in fact there's no
examples and oh and I got to learn
location Y and location X and geometry
math and I started to get scared and I
said there's got to be an easy way to do
easier way to do this so I came back
here and I did some searching in Google
and Stack Overflow and I found
oh well JavaScript itself has touched
things there's the touchstart touchmove
touch n that you can add to an add event
listener with a callback function of
what you want it to do or in modern
JavaScript you can do on touch start on
touch move on touch end and I tried
those and in the expo app and on iOS
working great and we're like yes ok
don't have to deal with that just your
responders stuff at all yeah I did it
and then we tried testing on Android and
it's not react natives in the face
folk or Android swans just Android
handles touch gestures and multi-touch
gestures in a different way and
different heuristics than iOS does to
which my boss Ryan went duh and he said
remember when I said you should maybe
try the gesture responder system so we
so I party jumping ahead so we did and
I'm just gonna really quick show you the
gesture responders system as part of
this it's so in the view here this is
the enclosing view around all these
little Braille input components we made
here we have the in the six key input as
part of the package we have the view
views have layout and you can do a call
back function on layout which allows you
to get locations of everything on the
screen I'll show you that in a sec and
here are the gesture responder stuff
it's on on start should set responder on
respond or move on respond or release
just props on view doesn't have to be a
touchable view or a touchable opacity or
anything like that it can be just a
regular view that's now set to respond
to multi touches here are the functions
I was telling you about here's the on
layout that we call the on layout gets a
native event which contains a layout
that has all sorts of stuff and then we
use a layout measure method that react
native supplies and we do a call back to
that and say take that stuff in the
native object it's going to have the X&Y
of the component itself where it starts
it's going to have its width and height
and it's going to have the absolute page
X and page Y on the screen where it's
located and then we put that in two
state variables just what we need the
page X goes to X page Y goes to Y width
and height and and you can see that's
our state variable right there so down
here in the move callback this is what
happened we take a native event there
that records the change touches we say
get
to get that the that X Y width and
height we put into the state variable of
layout create a test array and if
there's anything already in the test
array put it in there
and then we say change touches based on
their position in the as we loop through
in the array go into page X and page Y
and a constant here we create these
variables and set them to zero and then
this is something my genius CTO came up
with he bases this is the he helped me
out doing the Y and X math so if this
this is the Y up and down so if it's
this much it's the third button if it
it's the third set of row of third
buttons if it's this much
it's the row of second buttons if it's
this much it's the row of first buttons
and down here this is the X so if it's
this it's three if it's this one it's
the ones on the left one the ones and
then we put all that into a thing we
call button touch array and then we do a
switch on it and say if it's one one
that's the one button on the left is if
it's one two that's the two button the
right except etc all the way down to six
and that's how we did the multi-touch
and so I was very excited to learn that
and very grateful that he made me do the
hard work and go all the way through
that all right
there is one thing left that we ran into
most human beings not all but most human
beings are born with how many fingers on
each hand five right and so what is a
limitation on both iOS and Android of
the total number of fingers that can
touch a screen at once for phones five
that's all it'll take on phones tablets
and iPads we'll take more but the phones
that's it
and that really ticked us off because in
Universal English Braille grade 2 there
is an all 6 character that you need to
do as a modifier to describe other
characters in the contracted Braille and
but
I'm gonna unplug and show you really
quick we found a workaround thanks to
Ryan insisting that I do the hard work
and do the gesture responder Swift
system plugged in and what we can do
because we're using just your responder
we do one two three four five right but
not won't take anymore I'm hitting six
nothing happened but then I can lift off
of five if five is still part of the
array that we're building I touch six
with that finger release there's the
full thing so we did find a good
workaround for it gonna unplug again all
right
so finishing up so I think we've all
learned something here today don't you
oh there it goes
there we go
wait that slide doesn't look quite right
that's better
all right so there's this open-source
package for 6ki braille ueb input in
react native it's an alternative
solution to the OS platform
accessibility in apps as I said the road
to making things work the same in both
react native and Apple iOS and Google
Android is not the happy rainbow sparkle
Playland you'd think and it's open
source so we're saying please four can
contribute if you're going to contribute
directly to this project email is on the
github and the and the NPM repository
and we ask you write us first to make
sure as as maintained as we want to make
sure it's the direction we want the
package to go but if you want a fork and
use it for something else that's what
you could do for instance we made this
react native maybe you want a fork and
refactor the code for just regular react
for the web maybe you want to reef just
read it and go over it and do something
similar for angular for view hey Yahoo
de was here yesterday for ember you know
we you know there's all sorts of things
that one of my next projects after we do
the release for like 1:1 or 1/5 is in
landscape on tablets we want to have the
fingers buttons at an angle because
that's the way most people will be
touching the screen so we want to make
it easier for them but wait there's more
that app itself ueb prep we want to make
it into an open-source framework for any
sort of education training handbook etc
its experience it's got a from the front
end react native app and it has a
back-end admin which has a front-end for
the web that's in react native web and
we use storybook to check the components
there and the backend of it is using AWS
lambda with with server list which is a
node.js implementation it kim and that's
what we write our api sin is a node on
service can be configured to contain
training exercises and meteor rich video
and audio experiences i could also
say if you're like if you're like with
tree house and you want to do an app
where people finish and then if they
want to take the next course they have
to pay for it you can incorporate
ecommerce into it also
Universal Design lab as you can see on
the far right has already got a new skin
on it for other accessibility stuff
they're going to do and one of our big
clients at the circus Inc is also Hood
to Coast we do all their websites they
don't just do the one who'd to Coast
race they do races all over the world
all right including in China and other
places and we made the app for them
using this framework weary skinned it we
gave them their own back-end they put in
all sorts of information for their
handbook and we help them by going out
with a drone team and we photographed
some of the major legs that they had
video of with drones and that's all in
that app that app was done in a little
over three weeks just using this
framework and the skins it's amazing so
thanks that's about this and I want to
say I about three or four years ago is
at the Portland one I'm wearing the
Portland hoody I got back then I'm a
very happy Cascadia jeaious but this is
my first time speaking at Cascadia just
je s I'm very happy and very honored to
be here thank you very much