today I'm going to talk about react GS
and unfortunately you can't see the
picture but this is a picture of a bunch
of turtles sitting on top of each other
and I've tried to use the the subtitle
JavaScript Turtles all the way down and
I hope you'll see what I mean as we go
forward so we're experiencing this
progression of JavaScript adoption in
lots of places you wouldn't expect it so
this is a typical web stack you know
you've got the browser layer you've got
the server layer you've got a dad base
layer and the typical stack kind of
looks like this or at least the
traditional one does you've got
javascript in your browser the powers of
you I you know shows your countdown
whatever and you've got some kind of
server-side language like Java Ruby PHP
Python the list goes on and then inside
your database you have SQL well so now
we have no GS right so we can build
great server applications in JavaScript
which is totally awesome but you notice
that that a little section there the DB
hasn't changed yet so what can we do to
bring JavaScript to the database so like
all these turtles that are marching
toward the sea and I hope you can see
that we're on a path and that path is
adoption of JavaScript in all places all
right so you're probably saying what
about CouchDB couch TV has javascript
and couch TV is great I like couchdb a
lot and I'm going to apologize advance
for this straw man argument so no
offense to any of the couch GBI guys
there in the that are in the room it has
been my experience even long before i
started at ba show that the types of
applications people want to build with
CouchDB are not the types of
applications that people would want to
have
I'm sorry not the same types of
applications that you would write for
nodejs and so in a sense you don't want
to end up like this turtle and if you
can't see it there's a car on the road
way behind him you know you want to
rather be like these turtles right you
want to be no GS ninjas so I'm going to
tell you a bit about rioc and why you
should use Frank's awesome rioc GS
driver so say hi to Frank later so what
is react react is a distributed fault
tolerant replicated data store so if you
think of like a lot of people are
familiar with CouchDB a lot of people
familiar with Redis in the room I'm
assuming it's a key value store but the
big difference is that all of your data
is replicated a bunch of among a bunch
of machines so we like to say your data
is safe with us you can lose a machine
your data is still available the next
thing is that it scales out linearly so
you know a lot of people say lots of
things about scalability and what we say
is just add more machines so this is not
that every machine has all your data but
every machine can serve any requests for
any client and react also has a flexible
data model which means it's essentially
key value but you have a couple extras
which I'll talk about in the course of
this talk and you have MapReduce and we
also have a pretty recently released
react search now of course with a
flexible data model great power comes
great responsibility so in your app
you're going to have to take a little
bit more ownership of how you structure
and manipulate your data now I've
glossed over a lot of the the high level
features of react but Matthias who's
taking some awesome pictures today made
this awesome animated gif and I think it
explains better than what I could do in
words how rioc works so in this little
animated gif you've got eight nodes in
your cluster you sent a request to one
it goes out to three
and then if you lose one the data goes
to some other node that might have a
copy or store copy when that other node
node that was lost comes back the data
goes back where it belongs oh yeah and
it has javascript so let's talk about
rioc GS I pointed out Frank earlier it's
also react is also has this beautiful
website which has some pretty awesome
documentation on it how to get started
but let's talk a little bit more detail
about that so to get started with react
GS you want to download react or react
search download stop basho calm has all
the binary packages and also if you want
to bother building it yourself there's
source package available then you'll mpm
stall rioc GS and i like the latest
because you know the the production
releases are kind of erratic but the
latest stuff is always awesome works
with node node 0 40 or you can clone it
beyond the bleeding edge so let's see
what I also i got in here ok so let's
look at the basic client operations
isn't that a cute little turtle ok so
the operations for the client are really
simple you're required react GSU call
get client on the the module that's
exported and that gives you your basic
client like you would expect with any
other node library and then so if you
want to fetch an object out of rioc you
give it a bucketing key all of your keys
in react or namespace within a bucket
you don't have to create them ahead of
time but they provide a nice way to
organize your data and just like most
node drivers you send it a call back so
your data actually doesn't return from
that function call it's passed to the
callback and the callback like you're
used to as the very first argument is
going to be an error object if there was
on and the next one is going to be the
actual data you got back from react so
in this case we're logging to the
console that we found that object if you
want to store an object you do a very
similar thing and you can pass it Jason
to store the object automatically
marchal that and ship it off to react
and when you request it back it will
also come back in in JSON so just fair
warning from now on i alighted the cop
the callback because it just kind of
adds some extra noise but you'll want to
be using that callback to get get
information about your your your request
okay so obviously you can you can fetch
objects you can store them you can also
remove them you can check they exists
and looks like my my flipping is messed
up this is a cool new feature that Frank
just pushed out yesterday right yeah so
rioc has the ability to stream lists of
keys that you have stored so you can
pass it this keys stream if you want to
find out what keys are in the framework
bucket and and then it returns an event
emitter so you can listen for the keys
event on that and then start the request
yeah event mentors are awesome use them
so you can get all the the objects from
that bucket if you want and I'm sorry I
use objects loosely it's kind of a
terminology we have inside bash oh but
it basically means the key that you
store plus all the metadata around it so
if that gets confusing i'm not talking
about javascript objects you can also
count the keys if you want to find out
how many keys are in the in the bucket
so that's the basic you know really
simple key value a couple extra things
but there's an interesting thing about
the rioc GS driver which is a metal
object and we've got a stack of turtles
there on the right side sorry if you
can't see it so if you want to modify
things about the request to react if you
want to find out some more information
about what the response was you have
this meta object and it always comes as
the penultimate or the ultimate in the
case the callback argument to your
function so let's look at what you can
do on requests so with the meta object
on requests you're sending request time
metadata and these are important things
like your content type now unlike
CouchDB
or Redis rioc doesn't care what you
store in it it doesn't have any idea of
what it is so it's the responsibility
the application to tell what kind of
content you're storing and that
basically corresponds to the HTTP header
content type now rioc GS also does some
things nicely for you short circuits
that if you're just passing a JSON
object you can also pass the client ID
this is important if you have an
application like many node applications
will be that have heavy right load and
the client ID helps us disambiguate
concurrent rights in the in rioc there's
also links in user meadow which are some
sort of useful metadata that will look
at later and of course rioc has is a
dynamo like system I'm sorry this is not
like really database crowd so I'm kind
of a loss here on this but you can tell
it how many nodes you want to return a
successful response when you submit a
write or read and once those are
satisfied then it will return response
to the client so you can tell it how
much consistency you want which is
pretty awesome and then return body just
basically lets you on a right get back
the resulting value that was sent to the
server okay so let's look at what the
meta does in callbacks so again response
time metadata and this will include
information like the bucket in the key
that we're stored so you can choose to
store something without a key and react
will pick a key for you in that case you
want to read that key in your callback
and also the vector clock which is just
a crazy distributed systems thing that
like the key helps us keep track of who
wrote what when and that's all you
really need to know about it just make
sure that you pass it along again the
links in the user matter will come back
so if you request you fetched this
object from react you'll get information
about what other
it's linked to and any specific
application metadata and then typical
you know HTTP like things like the last
modified date that you tagged the status
code from the request so under the
covers rioc GS uses the node HTTP
library to do most of its communication
okay so if we want to take advantage of
this meta we might do something like in
this case when we're fetching the object
will get it back in the data and the
call back here and then we'll add a link
to that object and store it back so in
this case we've taken that meta that
came from the response we call a special
function on it add link that makes the
note GS object point to the vm v eight
and then we're storing that back in
react or you might do something like set
the content type when you're saving for
the first time excuse me I you know I
said before that rioc GS will do a lot
of things for you to make it really
short that the kind of you know
developer-friendly API that you're
looking for in this case what it says is
you only have to tell HTML it knows
you're talking about text HTML so that's
great now we have key value access you
can get you can store but you definitely
want to go beyond querying adjust key
value and I'm sorry this this turtle
doesn't have any relevance to the slide
but I thought it's pretty cool eating a
strawberry so I mentioned links before
links are away a lightweight way to
relate objects to one another inside
react and you can follow those links
automatically and so here's a turtle
with two heads that are linked together
so if I wanted to find all of my friends
and this is the typical social network
example I would start at the object that
is in the bucket people the keyshawn and
then i sent it this specification which
is how to match links that are on that
object in this case i don't care the
very first argument is the bucket I
don't care what bucket it's in but I
want to follow the tag that's friends
and that I'll return a bunch of objects
to your your node.js application
that are all of those things that are
linked from from people Sean and then
there's people Matthias in this case
we're going to follow his friends but
we're also going to follow anybody who
are linked from his friends so you can
do this sort of fan-out type of query
where if things are linked up right you
can get lots of interesting information
about how things are related and this
has been a core future rioc for a long
time but wait a minute you said that
rioc had javascript in it right I did
right okay so I'm going to explain how
JavaScript is down inside rioc as well
and that's with MapReduce we do a lot of
stuff with MapReduce when we're
developing apps for react and this is
basically how it works it's a little bit
different than what you might have seen
in couch if you any of you use Hadoop
anybody used to do yeah just a few
people it's very different from how you
use Hadoop too so basically the the idea
of MapReduce is a functional idea you
start with a list of keys rioc will
fetch those keys and run a map function
across all of them and that's
distributed around the cluster so the
map function runs where the data is
stored in your rioc cluster which makes
it really efficient to load that from
disk etc and then once all those map
functions have run and they can return
any number of results from 0 to however
many there they can be sent to a reduced
function which will coalesce a single
value or a list of values and return
that to the client okay that's great
where's the JavaScript you're saying
well the job the list of keys and all of
the functions that you want to compute
are submitted as Jason which is pretty
cool all of those map functions can be
JavaScript that reduce function can be
JavaScript and then when it's returned
to you it's in Jason okay we got
JavaScript so let's look at how you run
it so in this case I am executing a
MapReduce query and all you have to do
is on that that client object that you
initialized at the beginning is add the
frameworks bucket so this basically says
give
all the keys in the bucket and perform
this job across them and we're going to
use a built-in function to map across
all those which is called map values
Jason and then when you call run that
actually sends a query as a JSON object
over to rioc and it will execute it and
return some results so this case of
course we're just logging to the console
the data we get back a little bit more
complicated example and I think this is
actually the standout feature of what
makes rioc GS really tightly integrated
with rioc and that's that you can define
a function inside your node.js
application and it'll be turned into a
string and sent over to rioc and execute
it over there so if you don't want to
break out of JavaScript and start
writing strings for all your functions
or calling built-ins you can just write
them in line with your code it's pretty
awesome so in this case I just described
what this MapReduce queries doing we're
going to start with a specific key just
the nodejs key inside the frameworks
bucket and then we're going to follow
links on that to vm saying remember
earlier in my examples I linked to the
v8 vm so we should get that object
coming out and on all those things that
it's linked to that have there in that
vm bucket we're going to just parse the
contents of that object as jason and
return the name property from the the
object that was that was parsed and then
in the reduce function we're just going
to sort the list of results and return
those to the client and I know this is
like you know Matthias rude a couple
blog posts a while back about why
MapReduce is hard and why MapReduce is
easy and I'm sorry I have to gloss over
this right now but those are pretty
awesome ways to learn how to understand
this programming model okay just one
more example in this case we're using a
new feature of rioc 0-14 which is called
key filters and what we try to encourage
people to do with rioc is to use keys
that are meaningful to your application
they may have some embedded in
mation about the object that's being
stored in them and in that case that
makes it actually a lot easier to query
them because you can even say I know
exactly what the key is going to be
that's the ideal case where you can say
I know the key is going to contain this
and so key filters let you take a whole
bucket listing all the keys you've
stored in that bucket and filter them
with various predicates in this case I'm
taking all the emails in in the email
bucket and saying these are the ones
that ends with basho calm returned only
those now the difference between that
and just running a map function that
might have you know and if else in it is
that you're not actually loading that
data off of disk so it's much much
faster in this case we're you also using
another built-in called Matt by fields
this is a kind of a cool feature in that
you can create generic map and reduce
functions in JavaScript that take a
trailing argument and so you can
parameterize those generic functions to
perform specific tasks in this case I'm
saying okay they need to be joined on
2010 January first ok and we run that so
there's also search I mentioned that at
the beginning react search is a full
text search engine very similar at least
from the outside to solar but on the
inside it's totally different and it
uses all the distributed stuff that riac
does but rioc GS has special support for
it so if you want to have all your Jason
documents that you're storing
automatically index in react search you
can se debe tener un able index and then
the bucket name and that'll put on a
pre-commit hook to the storage
operations to index that in react search
you can also just perform a flat search
like you would expect with solar you
send it you know leucine style query
string say give me all the documents
that have the title scalable in them
and you can use search to feed a
MapReduce query so if you know a full
text query that will satisfy the set of
keys you want to fetch then you can use
that to to feed a MapReduce query and
just add your map and reduce functions
on there and whatever combinations you
need okay so there's some other things
that's the main features of react GS
there's some other things that are
included there's a connect session store
in fact I've just got a pull request
applied to it today it's pretty cool
there's a miniature rioc so we were on
the right test for applications right
but sometimes those tests need to hit
the data store in this case it's
actually pretty awesome what it does is
it fires up a rioc that's a subprocess
of your node test process and tells it
to delete all the data in it at the end
of each run so you'll definitely want to
look into that also there's multiple
ways to talk to react the default is
HTTP but there's also a binary protocol
which is based on Google protocol
buffers and react GS has some
experimental support for that and
there's also a a luoc which is I'm sorry
kind of a weird name but if you wanted
to store large files in your react
cluster luoc will split them up into
chunks for you and no GSA I'm sorry no
GS via react Jas has support for that so
no presentation would be good without a
demo so this application is available on
github I'm going to talk through a
little bit of it and it's also hosted on
joints node server a node service and so
you'll be able to see that ok so what
reactant is is a very simple syslog
server so it receives UDP syslog
messages it stores them a react search
and then it serves them up in a nice
little web interface which is also
powered by node and and then you can
search through all of your logs so
miniature log lead type of thing
interesting thing of that we discovered
when we were writing this and this
should come as no surprise to any of you
but don't block the reactor okay we
actually found that we were dropping a
bunch of UDP messages because we weren't
deferring our rights to rioc that was
that was kind of interesting so instead
what we did is we set up a queue we push
messages into the queue and then
periodically check to see if it's over a
certain threshold and then drain them
which actually worked really well and we
didn't really lose any messages so we
parse the message we create a hash of it
to use for the key and then we push it
into the queue ok it's C go down here so
this callback this process next key
message is what actually pushes it in to
rioc and we do use the typical tail call
type of call back to pop something off
the queue and then stick it in to rioc
ok and that's breasts for that spoiler
plate and then there's the web server
which we actually use the react j/s
session store to with express to have a
simple login and that's set up right
here this Express create server stuff so
we've required rioc GS up here we've
required the session store which
actually those fixes that we did in this
project have been moved into the prod
into react yes now so you shouldn't
shouldnt have to see that anymore and so
we created a session store stores its
its stuff in syslog web sessions bucket
and uses the same client that we use for
for the the web app ok and then there's
some stuff related to MapReduce in
filtering those queries and I don't want
to spend too much time doing a code
review because I know how boring that is
so we're going to look at the
application this is pretty simple
demonstrating using the session store
and if you go here it's okay if you go
here i'm sure it'll hold up its fasho
dot noge and the username is react and
the password is awesomesauce okay so now
we've got pretty blank screen but if we
type so we actually fabricated some
syslog messages to feed into react
search and so some of them have this
connection closed message so if we click
that in search and we get back a bunch
of text messages on the side that are
you know syslog format you may be
familiar with and all of these you know
things have their connection closed
unexpectedly so you can make it filter
that so let's say we wanted and those
are all happening at the same time the
times not going to be useful so I'm
Justin just searching you know typical
leucine type of search you can actually
feed that to MapReduce like I mentioned
before and then we made a selector down
here you can select which map function
you want so if we just want the host
names out of all those results click
search again and my apologies for the
the interface here it's kind of rural
but here's all these results so every
one of these things that was a search
result got passages map function that
just returns the host name and account
for that now that doesn't seem very
useful until you look at the reduce
function you say well let's group x
values and when you do that you can see
well web to bachelor com that's probably
a bit tiny web to bachelor com had 87 of
these messages and apple on and so on so
in contrast to the way that Hadoop does
MapReduce and the way that couch gb does
MapReduce you can build these things on
the fly you're not building views you're
not stuck into a fixed job you can
submit them whenever you want and then
you might also want to do something like
let's see let's fetch the date an hour
and these all happen in nineteen o clock
383 messages so that's a little demo and
let's flip back here I'd be happy to
take questions that's how to contact me
check out the jas comp basher com site
yes how hard is it to replicate the
server the react server it's built in so
you start with one node and you have
three copies of everything when you go
to three nodes there's a copy on every
machine you grow two more and it's
spread out even more thinly so
replication is automatic did that answer
your question yeah okay way in the back
yeah the question was why would you want
to use a key streaming and an
interesting thing about the way
streaming keys or I'm sorry key listing
works in rioc is that when you submit a
request for a list of keys it goes out
to one-third of all of the nodes in the
in the system and says give me your key
list for this bucket and so as you can
imagine with a big bucket that's going
to take a long time to smash into a JSON
array and send back to the client that's
going to take up a lot of memory if
you've got a lot of keys Sookie
streaming sidesteps that and actually
start sending back results as soon as
they get there so this is actually nice
fit with the way that node does things
and that you can receive events
asynchronously showing thanks very much