well hello and well thank you guys for
being here especially after just a tea
party you're not the only one with the
sexy boo is using it was a great party
thank you i'm talking and start talking
about the open wed device that is the
first iphone is going to be delivered
with the shiny I'm fantastic 54 sauce so
let's start with a bit of introduction
that's me Francisco Spanish guy here
those are some bits of my digital life
okay so you can find Miller in Twitter
github and i'm working for telephonic a
digital and you are going to sing okay
why it's a guy from telefonica critical
digital talking about farfus first so
let's start with a bit of history okay
and i will explain your why and talking
about this so in early 2011 and we are
telefonica digital started to realize
that the mobile landscape was already
dominated by two mainly brand and we
didn't like the way that it was that it
was working at all because the problem
was that or either do you have our real
expensive device or you have a phone
that is not going to be updated at all
and talking about buying a iphone or
super nice android device that is like
500 600 pounds or either you buy a cheap
android phone let me show you the error
so we didn't like that at all because
especially we are really being that in
south america so we said okay we want to
do something we want to create a device
that is cheap that anyone can buy is
able to deliver the same experience that
you have in in your iphones and super
900 so in order to do that we decided to
to go for with quite technologies by the
time we thought okay what technologies
are mature enough to deliver these kind
of things we are going to create this
phone and we are going to be biased
missing in this web technologies so we
were thinking about it we were
prototyping and so on and you know what
happened and in two thousand june june
july a theme past year Mazel already
announced today about to make a project
and it was like
do the same idea the same principles is
amazing in the other part of the world
there were other people having this
thing idea what we're going to do are we
going to compete with them go away we
call them we called Mozilla and say hey
guys we really love your idea within the
distinct level can we work together and
the answer was yes come on let's go and
that's what today I'm here ok so we
started working together I don't know
you guys see in the motorway Congress
you teach her prototype that we were
coming with two different new eyes using
the same back end we were already
collaborating band then we realize that
it was a waste of time and resources to
create in two separate you guys so we
said okay no stop it let's try to work
together and what we are doing so far is
the photo fast telefonica and gosh
Mozilla we are trying to achieve that
it's great fire sauce android loading
remember I said that we want to create a
cheap phone that is going to be able to
deliver that that experience okay so the
open where device is going to be this
first film is going to be launched in
Brazil in q1 next year okay so if you
count the number of moles that means
them Mozilla will be able to deliver a
completely new and shiny operating
system in less than one year and a half
that's blow minding is incredible I mean
who is able to say that you can deliver
a new operating system in that that time
so remember what I want to do to realize
about the open where device is going to
be a cheap phone really really cheap
whoa where you going to deliver that
kind of super nice experience and now
it's enough talking about open with
device Alyssa still talking about
Firefox OS okay so okay it's chip that
means that the resources that we are
going to have in the four are not like
the best one memory is not going to be
infinite the screen maybe is not the
best one but experience is going to be
amazing on how we're going to deliver
that okay so five or six I want 50 sauce
is the one who is going to deliver that
experience all that is a prototype okay
think that that's a nice Firefox's I'm
going to explain you what are the
principles I went to there are going to
make fascist or becoming that I'm
theme from so we are going to have like
three layers in the up in the in the
whole phone and I go to explain the
three of em okay the first one is the
one that we call Gong Gong is a solid
linux okay stripers is a kernel is a
linux running on the phone I'm here
Mozilla were really really smart instead
of saying okay let's reinvent the wheel
let's create our own version of lino
studies going to be able to run here no
no no no I this already are open source
project that does this is called Android
ok we have android this open-source
pretty cool let's remove the part i will
live from it java ok we're through java
and what we have is that solid a linux
kernel on toast relations oh and this is
pretty good is pretty nice which means
that Firefox OS is going to be quite
easy to port platforms are already
running on Android that's pretty
important ok that means that so far you
have like fastest horse running in
samsung galaxy s2 in galaxy nexus nexus
one prototype is and some LG phones and
so on and even things like raspberry pi
can you imagine you know it's like if
you are able to run android maybe well
you will be able to run at some point
fortunate fire forces I think that is
particular idea ok now we had this
colonel we have these drivers what else
we have another layer it's called gecko
I'm sure that this name is familiar for
you all ok this is the magic engine that
is powering the Firefox in your laptops
and your bro in your list of browsers is
the same one that is forwarding the fire
phone sauce ok and the good things about
it is like this is talking directly to
the that kernel and O's driver there is
not any other layer of operating system
behind it which means that we are saving
like a lot of resources you see here we
are just saving resources instead of
having needing like a lot of memory to
running an operating system and then
putting a brush during the top do is the
browser or they prostrate you've already
running here that's incredible but we
will need more things extra AP is in
order to
being able to run a phone because at the
end of the day I phone needs to make
calls isn't it not it's like that ice
cream it's pretty cool but we need to be
close we need to send SMS and things
like that so later we will talk about
all those new API is ok we will talk
about what Mozilla is doing for
providing us with those aps in order to
create the phone and the last layer is
Gaia okay guy is just on you I but we
put in top of that process arranging and
we create the experience the user
experience for for the firefox sauce
it's called Gaia but at the other day
you just a set of web AP day web apps
you can create your own later I want to
show you that we can create whatever you
want so this is amazing and this is what
what today I will try to to show you
that is not just an operating system
that is a philosophy it's much more sour
things so let's stop talking about those
those api's so Mozilla is doing a
greater for its incredible is life okay
we don't have all the we need more
things we want to create a phone no we
need like making calls we need a
telephone API we need to make the phone
vibrate we will have a our vision API
but the most important thing for me is
not just that they are creating the
api's that they need they are trying to
standardize them that's quite important
okay that means that it's not okay i'm
going to create this no no no they're
going to the process talking with the
industry to talking with the standard
organizations in order to standardize
those those api's that's amazing that's
a really great year from them that means
that anyone can participate in defining
those api's discussing and things like
that and that's very important guys that
you can go and start discussing what
what would you like to do to be working
on the SMS api all still like that so
please take a look to that wiki page and
you will realize that there is a lot of
new api's they're incredible sorry also
an important thing is some of those KPIs
are not just going to live in the phone
itself know all those ideas are going to
jump to the browser actually to in fact
the latest version of the browser
professionally already contains some of
those AP ice so that's an another great
effort and that's opening as well our
new possibilities okay so now what I
would like to do is show you a bit of
code allowed to say p is what they are
doing and you will realize that at the
holiday this is just JavaScript so
that's an example of the delay phone the
API okay it's quite simple you can read
it it's not a problem you can understand
it is I've been oriented so whenever you
receive a call you have you have a cold
wet that to handle that call
synchronously you can do stuff so any
one of you can read that perfectly it
can understand it there's no like a
black magic there it's like quite simple
the same thing for sending SMS or
receiving SMS the code is quite simple
for you you all can understand perfectly
we don't mean having to explain it what
it's doing that's one of the great
things of this also more examples api's
the open web apps api this is one of my
favorite ones i would like to spend some
time explaining here open with us is
just a definition outside okay i have
this application the web application is
an application what I'm going to defying
is a manifest file very suggestion file
that contains things like name
description icons where's my lunch but I
things like that and also the API
provides a set of methods to installing
an application and installing it or even
querying all the applications are
installed this is an example of to say p
is that I told you that they are jumping
not just they are not just about to wake
oh okay they are also as well in the
Firefox nightly already so that means
you can install a web application in
whatever is running the gecko ng what it
means that the same applies in that you
are going to run in the phone is the one
that you can run in a browser your
desktop is the same code is in render
the same thing so that's pretty cool
open with us or something that is
fantastic and you will think okay well
but this is just by Mozilla no just no
again until s doing therefore of
standardizing please I think that's
quite important okay
is not just one thing that they're
someone created this is something that
is going to is trying to become a
standard another example Web API is no
it's like this is for Android developers
is quite quite familiar okay this is
like hey please system there is an
application that is able to do some
tests for me like sending sms yes please
this is the phone number i want to send
an SMS someone take take the task of
sending an SMS for me this is quite
similar for for android and things like
that and also a good example of
standardization there is already
something like web intents from google
okay machine on google are working
together trying to have the same way of
auto in this country stuff so maybe in
just three months time this becomes a
standard again again an example with
your Wi-Fi eph okay i could be talking
about VBS forever okay because there's a
lot of them we have web Bluetooth API we
have settings API that we have wet FM
API is incredible the new set of AP ice
that has been created for this all they
need javascript and all of them quite
easy to use for you so please take a
look I mean for example you had a
contacts API Gregor come on with your
hand raised here he created that API you
know it's incredible I mean there's so
many things I'm what I want to do to
show and share with us I'd go there take
a look and you realize that you can
start doing incredible things with
JavaScript okay well I know also another
in here would like to talk about the
connection connectivity API please this
is not just for using bout to waco you
can detect when a user doesn't have
connections right now please use it okay
because we we are used to people having
connection having kabul cables having
with you and so on but in a mobile phone
people go offline quite often so please
turn into account okay not just for
Portugal for anything okay so we had a
set of API is incredible and I don't
know how big is the list is quite big I
can tell you what we created with those
api's what we created with those api's
is the last part of the ice cream that
you saw before
is the Gaia is the UX is the UX for this
firefox operating system but what I
Gallia is just a set of apps of open web
apps that once that I defined if you're
the ones that I said before so those are
screenshot taken from the phone I mean
those are not designs and things like
that that actually the implementation
okay so what you have on your on your
left is an example of the system
application is an open web app you can
go check it and you will realize that is
pure HTML Javascript and CSS nothing
else using those new API but at the
other day is whatever you're doing you
are able to do I mean it's not black
magic go check it you have things like I
screen locker settings you have a lot of
applications for example that one that
you have on your right is the home
screen application in the first app that
you see when you when you open the
engine on stuff own this home screen
application what is doing is something's
really really simple is going and using
the open web apps API asking how many
applications you have installed going
through them and showing and present in
the icons for its application in a grid
format but think about this this is an
HTML Adam that you can modify and you
can do whatever you want in this case we
are showing a grid okay by you it's up
to you I mean you can decide to show
wherever you want if you have a new idea
and want to do it on 3d or wherever is
there okay that's important thing that
you can do whatever you want you have a
white canvas here to do a staff so more
things native why what means negative
here is quite funny native this lady
with the web is the native here the open
web is this thing that you don't need
anything else firefox sauce is was made
for am by the web so remember i love
that trace that said the web is the
platform yes it is okay so these are
examples are the native dialer and the
native contacts are just web
applications that can run in the Firefox
browser for example the only thing that
you will need at this set of ApS that we
say
before for example just think about it I
learn what the tire is doing so far it's
quite simple we had the settings API
okay so we are going to store a we have
the vibration API for example so we are
going to store if we need to vibrate and
we need to ring also in settings when we
store we can store the ringtone for the
phone so what we do is just check the
settings API when we receive an incoming
call check we need to vibrate or make a
sound we have a node and I will do note
in the dome where we change the source
pointing it to the audio file that we
want to make the song and we start
playing whenever we get the call we stop
playing this like that you know it's
like it's not really complicated I mean
of course it has her for a bit more of
science here but what I mean is I using
your hands to modify the way that this
does this work so how do we create it
this application is open web apps so far
I didn't mention anything about an SDK
you know when you are trying to working
on your platform the first thing that
you think about is like which the SDK
how I can work on it there is no SDK why
because this is the open web lass anyone
tells you how you had to create your
website no one why should Mozilla tell
you how you have to create web apps for
the phone remember the phone 53 sauce is
made for the open web so no one is going
to tell you how you have to create your
of your webs so there's the reason why
there is no like SDK there is not
something like that also take into
account that we said that the phone has
a really limited number of resources so
instead of using a standard on generic
libraries we decided to create a
specific vanilla plain JavaScript just
to save in memory and things like that
okay but what we did is like okay once
all of the old UX people get together
and and they decided how they look and
feel the phone was looking
for the developers like like me what we
did is like okay we need to kind of use
have the same look and feel at least for
the applications that we are going to
ship at the beginning and what we have
is lie so it's a guideline this
guideline is what we call building
blocks building blocks is another open
source project ok just to define the
markup and the CSS that the application
shall have that's just a recommendation
doesn't mean that you need to use it for
us or developers working right now in
the project is a way of creating
applications in a faster way so there
were we have issues just the markup and
the CSS no javascript cuz remember these
are the things that we can do so far
without JavaScript transitions an
emergency like that we don't need to to
go and modify the Dom for doing that
it's better that we let the CSS ng into
to do this thing for us so the building
blocks you will have a list of common
companies that we are using we are
repeating across the applications that
we're going to lunch okay so yeah that's
the building blocks go there take a look
at you will realize so now is the time
for trying it I told you this is running
in several devices already but I'm sure
that you want to try it now you can do
it I was telling you this is the open
web you don't need the physic physically
default for trying it so here is like
there are like three metal three ways of
of trying it first is Firefox nightly as
I said it's like they are sharing the
same a magical engine because we go it's
the same one you won't have somewhat
open API so you already have in bought
you a go but basically if you want to
test the look and feel on everything
wherever renders preferably in Firefox
nightly will render perfectly in Firefox
OS okay so that's pretty cool you can go
download it it's pretty nice then you
have BTW but to gecko yes it's
cross-platform and you can compile it
for your own and architecture not just
for the phone itself this is like a pure
emulator this contains all the aps is
exactly the same software is running in
the device but you can have it on your
you can have it on your on your machine
okay oh and also mozilla is is providing
us nightly builds for this
so you don't have to compile it you can
click just go there under load it for
your for your operating system it's
pretty cool is the same thing that you
have in the in the form but you have it
on your key architecture this week or
one week ago this new thing that is
called r2d2 v2g that actually stands for
ready to deliver to boot to gecko is a
political extension you need to install
in your in your Firefox nightly ok what
it does is like it as it adds an extra
menu and if you are browsing our web
page you can click and install it and
what it will do it will launch a BG
emulator with that application already
installer and you can check it you don't
have to configure it or things like that
so i will highly recommend to you i
would highly recommend to you guys to
try to using this this new sniffing and
once that you try hopefully you will
feel what I'm feeling when I working on
this project for me is a predator is
basically means freedom the freedom of
creating anything that is on my mind
firefall sauce is the chance that we
have for first participating in a
project being able to collaborate and
decide how things are working but also
Mozilla is giving us the chance or
creating these things in this white
canvas what right now we are running
gaya you can create wherever you want ok
whatever you want even when I say
whatever you want means whatever you
want right now we are creating a phone
but you can decide this to create any
other thing is an open web app you
create web apps so you can put something
on the phone that the first thing that
it does when he runs whatever you decide
ok an example of this is is this this is
a considered a colleague on me that is
working next to me it's had in mind okay
he's not working in the project but he
sit next to me and I always telling him
this is amazing this is amazing try I
try and he he can with this idea i'm
going to create a phone for other people
the littler the phone is going to do is
just too much has some for quick dials
or so i'm going to the files
zones and I'm going to track the people
with the GPS if the people get out of
the safe zone i'm going to send a signal
and things like that he came with this
design and literally just in two weeks
that was running on the phone and that's
not just a simple application that's why
you have when you turn on the phone that
device what he's doing is just doing
that okay what it means and you can
create whatever you want in this case
it's a phone that what it does is just
having these four quick dials but again
this is a blank canvas what you have in
your hand is a phone that's actually a
computer will extremely good
communication capabilities and a lot of
sensors so imagine the amount of things
that you can do is incredible so it's
not just a phone is a chance or creating
new incredible staff so please start
thinking about it start thinking all the
new ideas are you can start creating
with these um yes it will blow your mind
I missing kreyol each day I wake up it's
like yes I go to do this one way you had
to fix max okay but you can do it you
know like it's in your hands please
please do it also you yesterday I saw
they actually the presenters measuring
their time and I'm really bad with
timing conferences so I decided to
create an application that measures the
time ok so is here I used to spend 15
minutes creating that web application
and if you think about it it is a timer
and you're updating each second just to
show the time there it took me 15
minutes guys for you it will taper all
the time ok so what what with this what
I can what I want to tell you is like
this is the open web mozilla is bringing
your hands a super powerful tool and I
really would like to use the open source
when I saw yesterday but the things that
I cannot use it and I quite happy that I
cannot use it I cannot use it because
this is open source d who was born open
source is incredible so please go there
check it collaborate learn from the
people on the RSC go and dive into the
into the mailing list okay so just check
and have that chance that you have for
being participate of creating an
operating system that's so big that's
incredible and just the feeling of being
part of that movement is incredible I
really would like you to feel that and
that's what i wanted to share with you
please go ahead check it participate and
help more syllable a better group web
and the top thank you
I have one question I've been a palm
user for a long time I had every rep OS
device possible and it's open web breath
this is the same thing why the hell do
we need this well because we didn't have
webos hope until this week and this has
been open source since I know it like
one year ago maybe now it's taina work
together and I think that the two
projects have to learn a lot from each
other but so far Weber's wasn't open
till literally this move this tuesday i
think so this another chance this is the
open web we have several changes several
options to go for them could you detail
steps i would have to take two runners
on my phone yeah if you want to running
in your phone actually what you had to
check is not the guy a project is the BG
project and there there is a list of
steps that you have to follow so
basically the loader repo connect your
phone and execute configure and execute
make it will download some wineries
there are proprietary that's why we
cannot distribute distribute images of
the phone because it contains
proprietary firmware but during the
build process that firmware is
downloaded and then put it back to their
to the device it's quite simple so i can
run firefox on my android phone will
avail to run chrome on this I'm chrome
uh I server you a question I I never try
well I try but there are some things
that are that are not looking completely
ok because as you know they still there
are some differences between the two
engines so Chrome's a nice if C C++ app
so it's not actually impossible to run a
c++ I upon this hey know what's far as I
know maybe they people from Mozilla can
tell you know yesterday but as far as I
know what you are running on the phone
are pure web apps
so its web what you run any more
questions nothing cool I just want to
say just one thing sorry it's like I
have a couple of devices please stop me
okay let's just shake me and tell me
show me the phone let's play with it i
want to check my web page on it also
there are a lot of mysterion peoples
here pls wave your hands there's a lot
of millions that they had their phones
or the you so maybe they can they can
show you how the phone looks like okay