so the talk today is in three parts kind
of stealing a stylistic take on that
John did yesterday i'll do some slides
I'll do some demos and then I'll do kind
of a second set of demos it's the middle
set of demos actual kind of software
stuff the third one is more kind of a
the way I would like to see the future
you know the way the world should be
kind of some movie demos of that so so
like Chris said I'm Jason Huggins i work
at sauce labs and selenium is open
source testing tool its website is
selenium HQ org and then I registered
this other domain it's a forwards to my
company's address p 13 wide com so i'll
try to not make this a sleazy sales
pitch but there will be some subliminal
advertising so first of all why would
someone ever use selenium well the first
thing is the browser wars are back when
selenium was actually created ie had
ninety-five percent of the market share
of sorts but the cranky developers that
I worked with that we're in that five
percent they were using Mozilla and I
needed to test in both browsers and now
that IE does not have ninety five
percent of the market you know all these
browsers keep on coming so that's good
it's it's a complicated problem to solve
as John Resig window yesterday so
selenium is a robot library that will
act as a user would going through a
website you would open a browser link
type text Winfield click buttons things
like that so the mission for selenium is
anything that a user can do selenium
should be able to do and specifically
it's how it's kind of risen above all
the other functional testing tools in
the market is that it's really good for
Ajax II kind of apps this is kind of the
canonical very simple Ajax app that
Google suggests where as you're typing
your search string it's doing Ajax
requests behind the scenes and you can
emulate the
tapping of the down arrow to select a
particular particular value the other
thing that selenium is good for but it's
functional testing tools in general is
end-to-end workflows so this is a
screenshot of Google Doc so let's say
you've got a workflow where you want to
create a document then you want to click
on the sharing tab then you want to
share it with two of your friends let's
say Larry and Sergey and then you want
to click on invite collaborator
collaborators and just that general
workflow you want to make sure that
works in all the browsers and generally
you would call these kinds of things
large tests when you are talking to the
network you're talking to the database
you're you're obviously launching the
browser it's everything and to end
that's what a functional testing tools
for and that's what selenium is for so
what what we try to do with the selonian
project it's kind of ambitious but we
want to be able to test any browser on
any platform and with the other caveat
is that we want to be able to make it so
you can drive it from any programming
language so regardless of the web
framework that you're doing on the
server side so we support Perl Python
Ruby Java C sharp and then other members
that's officially the members the
community of committed client libraries
and lots of other languages so it's it's
a yeah you're supposed to keep it simple
but we have lots of simple parts and
this become this big thing so selenium
also this is its downloads to date
cumulative to life of the project
probably came out in 2004 I think we
really started tracking stuff in 2006 I
guess so we've got even though quantity
does not guarantee quality the quantity
actually is pretty good we have over one
and a half million downloads life to
date and so the bottom line is is
monthly totals and then the big line is
cumulative and if you look at the other
tools that are kind of in competition
with selenium its selenium is one if I
could be not so humble for a second this
also we did reverse dns lookups on that
download traffic and this is just a
representative of the companies that
have at least 100 downloads and so and
also this doesn't not count the people
who just check out the code this is
actually downloading the binary at night
so now that we've proven that beyond a
shadow of doubt that selenium is awesome
why would you not use selenium well
first of all functional testing in
general is slow by nature subliminal
advertising that's what my startup is
specifically focused on solving is the
speed issue but compared to the better
thing to do if your developers to write
lots of fast tight small unit tests that
don't touch the database don't touch the
network don't touch the GUI just
thinking of an isolation so it's better
to do small unit tests but when you have
to you have to use selenium but knowing
that selenium is is and functional
testing in general is slow also because
selenium originally just started out as
a JavaScript library and everyone has
this problem as a JavaScript developer
you can't touch the all the black box
widgets that are in the web page the
flash and applet flash and java applets
and now Silverlight also the adobe
reader all those things unless there's a
JavaScript bridge to talk to those
widgets from JavaScript than I mean then
you then you can do it if there's a
bridge but if not slim can't do it that
confuses some people when you think like
oh well a user should be able to click
into the YouTube player and click play
why can't selenium well you have to know
that it's it was implemented in
JavaScript and so it's limited to that
also the as we all know JavaScript lives
in a security sandbox and it feels like
that sandbox is pretty big when flooding
was created five years ago but it's
getting smaller and smaller you have
things like mashups and where you've got
data coming from two different sites and
you have things like I google or
facebook where you just have lots of
different data coming from lots of
different domains and what doesn't trip
up a user oh one other example is the
specific instance of this is the same
origin policy your javascript is not
allowed to go to any
their site and that's just not how
people are doing apps these days and
again from a point of view of a
functional testing tool a user can go
from site to site the testing tool
should too so but constantly come up in
into the boundaries of the sandbox when
it comes to testing so obviously
selenium is not for small tests for big
tests so a brief history of Suwanee and
this is kind of the untold story so I'll
just kind of fly through these things so
originally started when I was at
ThoughtWorks five years ago I was in
charge of a writing in house replacement
for our time and expense system so if
you can look right kind of at the bottom
here like there's a couple of buttons
they're kind of fuzzy but this was ajax
before it was Ajax I just call it fast
JavaScript or fast apps in the sense
where if you got a five-line expense
report you want to add one row because
you're doing a lot you have lots of
expenses instead of making what was
stated a state of the art at the time a
request response I just would clone the
last row blank out the lines and you
know add a new one increment the counter
and this was awesome I didn't think to
come up with an acronym for these things
but what we did notice though is because
we did have a user base using Mozilla
and ie what was happening is we would
check in that feature and every other
week it would be working and you know
one of those browsers so we would launch
the bug oh hey open a bug it's broken in
IE we'd fix in IE of course to be broken
in missoula very frustrating but I did
not want to go back to the days of
request response so I wanted to keep
this fast functionality fast JavaScript
but had a figure way to test it so we
would go on and on like have to keep
this feature we dad we had several
failed attempts at basically selenium is
like the fifth thing that we tried or
fourth or fifth the first thing we tried
was J web unit first problem is that we
were a Python project and we're trying
to use a Java technology so that's right
off the bat silly and stupid but the
other thing was at the time for
functional testing the state of the art
was something like j web unit where it
was an HTTP protocol driver where you
would do like regex assertions on the
HTTP text traffic going over the wire
and everyone just and especially since
you were doing request response anyway
everything that you needed to know
was supposed to be on the wire right
it's all this text but because I browser
specific bugs just looking at the HTTP
traffic was pointless so that was
quickly abandoned the second thing we
tried was something called driftwood a
co-worker of mine Andrew mcCormick he's
in Chicago I was in Chicago to with him
anyway see he he created this prototype
and it was Mozilla specific so it didn't
help us for solving the IE problems but
it did kind of do at least prove the
point that you could drive the browser
ins from inside the browser and using
javascript so that was pretty cool the
third thing we tried was a project that
was around for maybe about a year at
that point was jay s unit that was
written is written by edward hyatt thing
he's at pivotal labs in california and
the thing that didn't work with this is
that jay s unit is meant for unit
testing i kind of need something
functional testing but specifically that
was wrong with it is i need to be able
to see the user interface and see all
the widgets being exercised but the
other kind of very specific thing that
it could not do that everyone knows that
cilenia javascript is load and go the
second that script gets loaded from the
server it executes s'right but with a
workflow you have to do everything kind
of asynchronously where you have to load
a page and then kind of hang out for a
while stop wait till the page is loaded
then continue and that asynchronous kind
of call back scheme which is not
supported by jay s unit so I we couldn't
we tried to shoehorn it in there and
just couldn't make it work so another
attempt I really said like me and I
really need a functional testing tool or
something with you know the emphasis on
actually seeing what the browsers are
doing and so Ward Cunningham created
around that time created this framework
called fit I think it fit is the acronym
is framework for integrated testing he's
also the creator of wiki and lots of
other things but so he created this
thing called fit and it was implemented
in lots of different languages but there
was no
for the JavaScript platform if you will
at the time so I kind of emailed him say
hey did anyone done this yet I said no
let go ahead so I tried to implement it
and he had a specific thing if you know
fit i'm not going to go into it but
they've got these things called fixtures
and it's good for data driven
development but one of the things they
had this thing called action fixture and
they've got four he has four API
commands i don't know if i can zoom in
here so you can see this you've got
starts enter press and click and she
says on his website if you deviate from
this api you forked the project and you
know you're no longer can call yourself
fit and also it's like okay also the
other thing is kind of silly if i want
to check a checkbox that's not the
command you would want to use that
actually is a check is the command for
verifying field but that doesn't make
any sense and you know i'm going to
check a checkbox but then check the
value in too much naming classic so I
didn't like the API it was too limiting
so he kind of I guess said at the time
go for yourself you're very pleasant guy
he didn't actually say those words but
we had were forced to fork fit and so
out of all the things that we weren't
learns originally it was Jay sft when we
kind of rebranded it to be a selenium so
you know on that side note what's with
the name selenium all the company
mercury interactive they were required
by HP last year they are like the 400
pound gorilla in the testing and the
corporate evil proprietary testing tools
market and so I was just playing around
was googling around for play on words
with mercury mercury poisoning antidote
for mercury poisoning found this kind of
quack doctor who's you know talks about
like removing mercury amalgam dental
fillings and how selenium supplements
can be a cure for mercury talk poisoning
so like a ha that's it so now that I've
said this out loud it used to be the
inside joke of the project and now it's
on now it's live for the world to know
that we are suspicions were specifically
mooning the ogre of mercury interactive
so now I'll briefly kind of fly through
the projects that are kind of in the
selenium family originally started with
this JavaScript oh sorry for Saul there
any questions I'm flying through all
right I'll go faster the first thing
it's lame started out as is a just a
JavaScript library and if you've seen
selenium it kind of looks like this
where you can recognize that the the
inspiration from fit where forget all of
the left side and the right side just
focus on the center whoa so fuggin wrong
button here there you go the center
you've got the three column field where
the command the first column is the
command the second column is kind of
like the field that you want to do
something too and the third thing is
like the variable so this this line
right here it would be I would want to
type the letter X into the username
field just kind of lifted straight from
from fit and then the web app that
you're testing the load in an iframe
down below so when you click the play
button it will be kind of a player piano
or it's actually kind of it will show
each line yeah here it you can't really
see it but as each line gets passed
it'll go from grey to green and if that
test line failed it'll go red so it was
very visual visually interesting and
finally got what I wanted and it worked
across browser back tears tears on
chinya in Tokyo he's also this creator
of the pocket guitar iPhone app it's
like number 7 on the all-time top iphone
app things but he also before he was
famous on the iphone stuff he created
selenium ide which is effectively
selenium core but pulled out as a as a
browser extension for firefox and the
cool thing about this is it is no longer
susceptible to the security sandbox so
you can go from site to site and go to
ssl protected websites and it was pretty
cool it also has a record playback
feature so if you want to test that you
know scenario going to google com
testing some values you know it can
record
this for you the other cool thing about
this is that in the options menu you can
select to translate the source of the
test that you just recorded to Java or
any of the languages that we support I
hate Java so I would report it to the
Python and then we can use that drive
that from the next tool that we have is
something called selenium remote control
if you find a lot of people who hate
selenium they probably specifically hate
selenium remote control the IDE has a
lot of fans but remote control is kind
of this hairy beast so imagine a that
robot that I showed you at the beginning
this is the remote control for that like
I think like asimo I guess and it's like
what selenium server is selenium remote
control it's the server that sits in the
middle between your application code
your perl python ruby whatever code and
your browsers on one side or actually
doing it that way and it will proxy all
the commands for you but also handle
starting the browsers stopping them if
the windmill guys looked at this and
there they kind of felt like selenium
server was just too much too much code
and they felt you know arm's distance
from the browsers so they one of the
things they did with windmill has got a
rid of the selenium server thing and
just went straight from Python to the
browser's lots of other you know
competitors to selenium if you will kind
of skip that middleman of and just do
straight language to straight browsers
like the water project web application
testing and Ruby they now have Firefox
support for a long time it was just the
Ruby and ie show and that's what you'd
see a lot it's a common thing selenium
puts this thing in the middle but that
gives us the ability to do all languages
and all browsers and the last part of
the selenium family is something called
selenium grid and that's I won't really
go too much into the specifics of this
it's kind of an advanced use also kind
of very applicable to my startup but the
very simple quiz is what is faster you
know doing for things serially on one
machine or doing four things in parallel
and four machines so obviously
this is faster and grid selenium grid is
the open source component of selenium to
do that you still have to do some
configuration on your machines but the
capability is there and then the
shameless plug is Mike startup does a
selenium grid like thing on on the cloud
and you see two so if I can get out of
this application I can let's see there
you go okay so that's the slide
component I'll show you some some things
that will to the title of my talk will
drive you bonkers when you do functional
testing one specific example is alert
alert confirm prompts firefox 30 the
stupid self signed certificate prompt
where you have to like click 20 times to
actually let you you know except that
certificate those other things like
basic authentication prompts all these
kind of popups the problem with those is
that once that pop-up goes up to the
screen again because that security
sandbox JavaScript can't click on the ok
button once it's there a human or some
kind of native operating system code
actually has to click on that ok
selenium projects to date we fake it out
by overriding the wind the the alerts
all the things that we can when you when
you call to alert it's actually a
function called window alert and we
replace that with our own code that it
just says you know return true and when
we put it in a log hash of alerts that
have been accumulated so you can do
assertions on that but it's kind of it's
just a hack that's worked for a couple
of years but it's getting harder what's
pasilla team specifically does is when
it loads the page it injects that hack
into all the stuff that you did but when
you have lots of dynamic pages up so
crazy widgets on the screen we can't be
everywhere all the time hacking all the
pages that come in and so occasionally a
little alerts fly up and when that alert
comes up the combination problem of the
JavaScript thread itself is it's frozen
at that point which is a nice debugging
trick but if you have a code execution
running in the browser you can't even
call back to the server saying I'm stuck
because you're you really are stuck so
the one thing i want to show you there's
a snippet of code that at least in
firefox can guarantee any pop-up that
comes up it'll actually it can show it
and then click on it and this is going
to done it in javascript but the key of
this is that it's actually running kind
of as a browser extension so that in as
bratton browser extension land you have
a second execution thread so even if the
primary thing where the alert comes up
is stuck your extensions have a second
thread that actually can kind of go fix
the problem so Aaron buban he is at
Google he wrote grease monkey and he's
also on the gears team he gave me a of
code and I can't it really too boring
for me to go through all of this but
i'll just briefly kind of do the code
summary this firefox and firefox
specifically as a harp it's a wonderful
browser to test because infinitely
anything is configurable but it's also
its own little operating system so what
would work what is easy for Safari it's
just use all of you Apple events and you
just do all kinds of just same stuff you
do in any application on the Apple side
and I IE and Windows you can use windows
automation and all kinds of stuff but
firefox is its own thing so you guys had
to come up with some crazy things so he
has this crazy bit of code that lets me
listen to firefox's internal eventing
system which is kind of a superset of
all the events that just plain old
JavaScript protected or a security
protected JavaScript and get to
specifically there's an event called Dom
window opened that I can hook to and if
I can make this a little bit bigger the
magic is I can see if I can find the
right along here magic is this line of
code I can set a time out i don't think
i have that version running on the
machine but if you can see it maybe not
for the video but i can catch it i can
catch it and then in a timeout close it
so if my selenium test is actually
running this snippet of code is kind of
like we're running as like a watchdog
and actually can catch it so the brief
demo of this is I've got
see I've got Firebug running and I could
do the before and after but in the
interest of time I'll just show the you
the after and hopefully no demo gremlins
show up but this is something that's
been previously impossible to handle in
selenium so you see the alert comes down
and then my timer kind of kicks in and
gets it to go away so the future of the
project is going down this path of
finding either browser extensions or
actually native operating system code to
get out of that security sandbox and do
things to the browser this is
specifically a Firefox hack for ie I'll
have to do something similar i created
it's it's open on code google com
something called selenium ice it's a
hello world browser extension it's also
really hard to Google for information on
how to write browser extensions for IE
so that it's kind of like a just if you
wanted to write browser extensions in
general for IE go check out selenium
eyes but it's you want to be able to
inject yourself into the as IE is about
to show an alert to the screen you want
to get your media hooks into it so you
can you know get in a reference to that
and then close it in a second so slutty
mice was kind of my first attempt at at
doing that one of the other things you
have to do in in protected a browser
extension land is stuff like the file
upload fields it's the same kind of
thing you have to use kind of a browser
extension to do that yes that's like the
extension itself is written in C sharp
but also you can do it through Microsoft
automation library stuff that that's
kind of external but really you need a
browser extension to write when the when
the alert pops up so that's the
frustrating the the good thing and bad
thing about the selenium project we did
kind of the worst is better approach we
saw about eighty percent of the problem
by doing everything in JavaScript but
now we're five years in we're the only
thing left for us to do is that twenty
percent and we have to architectural e
you know do something
do something different so so on that
note though it's not just a pie in this
guy rewrite that'll take forever there's
a project that already exists called
webdriver that actually does it hat it
does implement the things the way you
should do with these browser extensions
or just native operating system hooks
and selenium 2.0 and lake over the next
year will be merging with them so we'll
have that capability for word what
webdriver that's also a hosted code
google com so that this that's kind of
one example of being able to get rid of
these alerts that's been kind of driving
me crazy and also I think John if I
think might be is he here I think he's
on the other I think he noticed he noted
that yeah tests warm if you throw an
alert there it might kill that session
so it's it plagues every automation
tester so that's now gotten to go away
the other thing that people complain
about selenium is the syntax of those
tables I have some I guess some
incongruity in the sense that I hate XML
yet I supported a responsible for those
selenium test tables where you've got it
just it's ugly to hack code inside HTML
tables or XML it's the same thing so
what people would love to do is be able
to write their tests it's just plain old
JavaScript like I said before it's
tricky because JavaScript by itself is
just load and go and I need this
asynchronous way to do it and what I
wanted to briefly touch on today is
there's two ways that you can kind of
hack supporting plain old JavaScript as
your tests knowing that you have to kind
of do this continuation engine of sorts
of like do one line of code and hang out
wait to be called back and then restart
again so one thing I found is this this
library called narcissus written by
Brendan Eich at Mozilla who created
JavaScript he was prototyping the next
version of javascript javascript to I
guess what she was like four and the
cool thing he did is he wrote a compiler
parser in JavaScript so you could play
with two features but it compiles down
and runs in JavaScript 15 so
similar in that sense to objective J
where you kind of writing a parser and
you have the same kind of issues of you
can now run through your code the way we
want it but debugging is a little bit
trickier but I did kind of Jack this
into selenium to see if I could get it
to work and so I kind of have three
tests of course as a testing to a
testing tool I have to have tests for
everything before I do it sorry for the
resolution here see if I can make this
bigger so i'll just run so the brief
test is creating functions testing if
then loop if then else or and also doing
a loop as well so if I so if I can
reload this page what it does is parse
it parses it and actually I also
swaggins run it let's walk through it if
you can see it at the bottom I'm kind of
faking out a read eval print loop here
by actually opening a page and setting
the I frame down here to a new page but
with a text message as its variable if I
do if then else you can kind of look
that it's going to create a variable you
know if things are true will you know
put hello world sorry for the small text
and the next one yeah show some more
text also again so we can run this so
one of the interesting things about this
is this this parser that's implemented
in JavaScript probably can't tell it so
much at the bottom but this is the live
stack when you people talk about stack
based languages or register based
languages this effectively you're
compiling JavaScript down to JavaScript
self but you're creating this data
structure and because these selenium
tables are executing the threads I
already have all this other smarts to do
these things I'm compiling down
javascript to these little tables you
actually can see the stack be animated
and as it evaluates a particular command
you can see it commands being inserted
into the stack let's actually a better
example is the formatted the do loops so
as it gets to a new loop it's injecting
new stuff all the stuff at the bottom is
the remaining end of the stack but it's
smart enough to inject into that loop
right in the middle this has actually
been interesting to kind of just
understand how interpreters work how it
adds things to the stack right and
there's one other thing that I thought
it was interesting about this is that if
I change one LLC so if i look at this
source code is parsed it parsed the test
if i go and change so if i can get to
the source code here where's the window
i'm going to uncomment this code here go
back to that screen if i can find my
browser window ever reload it of course
it's not going to work yes i reloaded it
and now you're looking at a you know
printed representation of the abstract
syntax tree this is crazy like we're
doing it all in JavaScript land and so
usually if you want to understand how an
interpreter works you know you're you
have to go down to the C code to figure
out how things are are implemented but
because narcissus is met a circular
interpreter you can kind of stay all in
JavaScript land and actually you know
mess around with things so specifically
like to make sense of this if we look at
the exists the first test of course I to
go undo the 10 second let's bring back
the source control the first line was of
setting a variable called URL to just a
string but if I look at the syntax tree
there it is some setting a variable the
name of the variable is URL and I'm
setting it to the string here yeah sorry
about that setting it to the this value
so it's really great way just if you're
mucking around with wanting to implement
your own language narcissus actually is
a pretty least for me Oh as a not being
a language creator it was a way to
understand this stuff so if anything the
takeaway from this is go around with a
narcissist now there's a couple of
projects that have taken narcissist and
actually fix a lot of bugs in it so
there's something called narrative j/s
and another thing called strands those
are two other projects that have needed
that asynchronous needed to add
asynchronous call backs or making it
easier to do that stuff in JavaScript so
if we really put this into selanne and
we'll probably not use narcissus
directly will probably use narrative j/s
or strands and that's so those are the
two kind of a geeky demos that i want to
show you how much how much time 55 all
right so I'll leave you on a this is my
kind of a soapbox rant for how I want
the future to be if you want to show you
a demo the one thing if everyone go if
you go back in time to that magical year
between when the iphone was just
vaporware and all we had were these
videos on apple com and i look at this
and like this is test automation this is
a functional test of their product and
the amazing thing is about Apple is like
this isn't just some geeky thing that QA
engineer does these are freaking
commercials but I look at this like this
is what I want the people when they
think of tests is to not write something
with a really boring report that goes to
your QA manager you should be thinking
in terms of kind of like a Hollywood
screenwriter like you should be writing
screenplays that show off how awesome
your application is I mean Apple let's
all they do is just show their app and
this is kind of what a functional
testing tool should do open and
something
and exercise the application and show it
off so what I'm trying to do with
selenium i call it like the missing the
Hollywood feature set slowing it down
animating the mouse maybe doing
text-to-speech narration all kinds of
things so i look at iphone videos is
kind of the gold standard for what i
want to do there are some actual code
like bringing that back to the reality
this is a project called casta not and
this is a automated screencast he does
text to speech is recorded on a mac and
showing off this application so this is
like a CMS he's using a mouse poze is
the thing that makes it highlighting and
it's this Ruby liable regulator yeah we
should have more to create a simple sign
structure I mean this is pretty sick
because if you do this automated instead
of screencasting by drinking and driving
all that finish Lewbert has many types
of pages
okay I'm running out of time here so
sing along it's a blog right so this is
a library you can go google it casta not
is the library and the thing is from a
test automation point of view it's
ghetto its 1970s bad old way to not do
testing there's like hard-coded values
like go to this absolute screen
coordinate terrible so from it from a
Hollywood screenwriting point of view a
plus or maybe like a minus iphone gets
the a plus but from test automation
point of view they get an F because they
just do it wrong but if you can get some
kind of test automation tool combined
with the screencasting Hollywood feature
set smart so you got something I think
and one other thing is to kind of put my
money where my mouth is is this is some
of the stuff that I actually was trying
to trying to do again subliminal
advertising we have before we had a user
interface we had an API we were actually
sitting very lightly on top of CouchDB
so if you want to give uploaded script
to us and then run that script on our
code on our on our servers first you up
and create a script object and CouchDB
and then you'll create a job object and
what I did here is this is an automated
screencast kind of taken from you
actually just I've got my stuff that
would otherwise type at the terminal or
the interactive prompt and instead of
just running it silently behind the
scenes and is giving a pass/fail I'm
actually slowing it down I'm launching a
terminal window in this case I'm using
the Python dog tail library to drive
everything do it kind of slowly so I
actually can see the results and because
it's also got testing hooks in there if
anything fails I'll get that pass fail
at the end but I also now could
potentially post this on my website as
okay you want to use our REST API well
you know this is how you would do it and
I'll use as my pass fail for you know
whether this is useful like actually can
show this to people and that this isn't
that interesting I could kind of spice
it up with some text to speech or some
music or make it more iphone commercial
ish but this is kind of where that I
want the future to be is like when you
do functional testing try to make it
look like an iphone commercial
everything else make it really boring
fast unit tests but really try to aspire
to do that
so i think i'm at a time and that is my
talk thanks