yeah hi how is everyone CSS I look yes
it's these date on chairs everybody's
way too comfortable you need like
plastic chairs we were send out on
belief that's what's happening thanks
everyone for coming out today
thank you for Karolina for organizing
and the rest of the jss crew really
excited to be here this is the first
time we've given a tandem talk together
manjar has given most of this talk
before but not without me here to hassle
him and take over half of it so let us
know how it goes by heckling us
throughout please heed there we go there
we go all right
cueing it this is us we're Connors and
MBO on Twitter and github I'm just
kidding I'm not gonna use that's how you
can find as Alex said we both work at
github I've been there for just over two
years Connor a little over a year and a
half we work on github calm basically
but a couple of different product
features around there which we'll talked
about talked about a little bit later
before that we both worked at Twitter I
worked there for two and a half years
Connor about the same amount as well I
was pretty good time together
we've actually been together for about
six years now it's the second longest
relationship I've ever had in addition
to work in a cool product companies we
we really like open source I created
bootstrap which is the be and Connor
created ratchet which is the are both of
them are front-end frameworks ratchet is
for if you ever heard a ratchet ratchet
is for basically if you want to build
mobile applications in HTML CSS that's
what that does for you bootstrap then is
mobile to desktop bottom line was point
of mentioning this is that we've spent a
lot of time writing HTML and CSS Adam
mentioned he's been writing CSS for 10
years I don't mean to one-up him but as
a good friend of him I will he does by
15 years and it's awesome but anyway
here's gonna take it away now with his
talk all right
all right you can sit down it's fine um
cool so yeah thanks for letting us be
here
so we're designers right so this
conference is really interesting I've
been to a number of them one other one I
don't know I exaggerated anyways up in
Australia once but anyways what's really
cool about this is that we've got like
designers and developers right like we
got a mix of people and you know even
though we're product designers that's
sort of what we identify as like when
people say what do you do I'm a designer
right but we write a lot of code and and
we work with a lot of engineers every
day and you know fancy to say we've
written some Ruby before and JavaScript
so I mean a lot of these principles even
though we're talking about design a
little bit you know it applies to
everybody so we're gonna step back and
just talk a little bit about like design
in general like what do we actually mean
because I think it's important so yeah
design is a process I'm not gonna read
just every slide by the way I now keep
I'm looking up there yeah design is a
process and it's getting to a solution
you got a problem you trying to solve it
and a lot of times design kind of looks
something like this and hopefully you
can see the circles they look little dim
but anyways you know you do a lot of
sketching and do a lot of wireframe
getting Photoshop you get in the code
and it's like this whole big ordeal it's
exhausting design gosh it's supposed to
be this uppity like thing right we're
all designers and we realize that like
really just solving the same problems
like over and over again in different
fidelity right were you sketching and
I'm not saying anything I mean this is
bad like this is a good good step but
when you're sketching like you're trying
to solve the problem then you get the
wireframes you get a little bit more
context and like you get a little more
handle on the problem you realize that
all those decisions you made are
probably wrong or like half of them
wrong so start making them again and
then you get the Photoshop and you spend
a lot of time in Photoshop and you're
doing that and and then you get into
code and you realize all of those
decisions were stupid you wasted all
your time you have to read make all
those decisions as soon as you do things
like what Adam was talking about in here
you know you have people using the thing
and it's a real tangible piece of
software that you build and really what
it boils down to for us at least and
based on our you know the six years
we've been together as mark says it
boils down to just working through ideas
and no matter what we do and then moving
into CODIS
quickly as we can because that's
actually where you know we think the
best part of design is made and and yeah
so I mean this is the point sort of what
we're thinking about is that practice
I'm greatly improves when you move into
code the design process becomes way more
clear and focused your decisions become
quicker they become clearer and we think
they just make for better products and
that's why we like HTML and CSS we spend
obviously bootstrap we spend a lot of
time working with CSS so so why why this
code make it better
well I think the first thing is that it
actually elevates the conversation so I
don't know about you guys but I've been
in like a lot you know I spent some time
doing like contracting work and stuff
back in the day or old graphic design
boutique firms and things like that and
you spent a lot of time like biessing
everyone you know like hey look at you
know this is the theme and the metaphor
we're working with no that's bad I don't
mean to like downplay it but a lot of
times you end up like looking at a
picture of software and that's not very
helpful like oh you know design is the
thing we're building it's not the file
that goes into the trashcan after we're
done and and so this conversation we've
time and time again and meetings like
you're looking at this piece of paper
and you're trying to make decisions and
what that boils down to is arguments
over box-shadow or I guess drop shadow
if you're talking in Photoshop terms
like whatever like these conversations
kind of get stupid so when you're
dealing with like code and you can get
real data in there and real feels it
feels real you know it all sudden your
conversation becomes way more focus so
that's one reason why you should move in
the code quicker your decisions get
faster and hopefully your product
development cycle is is faster code
inherently promotes or ideally promotes
systemic design and by systemic design
we just mean like design patterns I you
know as you're designing things you find
that you're building the same thing over
and over again well maybe you should
simplify that we just got done talking
about a a talk that does is talking
about this exact same thing but even
like on a higher level than just CSS
attributes we're talking about like
modules on the side like
a user card on say a social media site
or something like that like we ended up
making those user cards like 15,000
times and they're all different it ends
up being like 5,000 lines of code and
that's no good
and that 5,000 lines of code is off
oftentimes like a very good indicator of
maybe you need to simplify make it one
module that works everywhere and so much
simpler amount of code so code allows
you to figure that stuff out way easier
than a Photoshop document or maybe 50
Photoshop documents up on this wall and
we'll go over that and a little bit but
lastly and I think most importantly and
I think this conference is a testament
to this is that it lets you speak the
same language we're all here and we can
all talk to each other and we have a
commonality no matter if you are like a
hardcore visual designer that works with
CSS or a hardcore you know engineer and
it's working mainly with JavaScript or
whatever you know go down the list we
all can look at this stuff and it's blue
down to text that we can all speak the
same language and we call with software
like github shameless plug we can all
work together and I think that's really
important because it's really hard you
know Marc and I tried to like
collaborate over you know this document
this keynote document it went horrible
it was terrible I just didn't make any
change there's terrible but code like
this is all just a code which I guess we
could have done that I don't know
realization right now um wouldn't let us
speak the same language work better
together so I think that's another
benefit of the design process in code so
anyways so putting that into perspective
a little bit though one of the the
biggest projects that Connor and I the I
guess the privilege to work on was nunu
Twitter and if you're not familiar this
hashtag nunu Twitter
refers to the version of Twitter comm
and then the mobile clients that came
out exactly three years in one day ago
which was when they went from the
sliding drawer to the expanding
collapsing tweets on Twitter com we
worked on that we worked on for that for
six months in early 2000 or mid 2011 all
the way to early December so the gist of
this talk should be stuff that hopefully
we all realized and at least know or
I've heard people talk about which is
that code is better let's get the code
faster because that's where everything
is going to be anyway so why don't you
move there very quick
so hopefully this shouldn't be anything
too profound we just want to explain
some some cool stories I think from this
so this is new new Twitter this is what
it looked like it's kind of pretty
similar still except they've changed the
header and a couple of things they've
doesn't some new type and whatnot but so
Jack Dorsey came back and Bennett
mid-2011 he's like I'm gonna put my mark
on this this product again and so he
pulled a bunch of designers there about
a dozen of us or so into a conference
room and we basically stayed there for
four weeks it was a four-week design
sprint and the idea was to basically
whiteboard and then go to photoshop and
mock up the iPhone clients and the the
desktop web clients of how this brand
new reimagining of his product would
look and so it wasn't very pretty to
start there's a lot of sketches here
that's a lot like there's a nav mental
model I don't remember what it was but
there was three circles above and I
think that's what we're getting at we
just need three things but I was like we
couldn't figure in that out by just
whiteboarding and doing tons of
Photoshop mock-ups and I can tell you
why we didn't figure it out by doing
tons of Photoshop mock-ups so we did a
ton of Photoshop mock-ups for every
single view and it's a little grainy
it's actually horrible to look at I'm
sorry but we had these monster documents
and these are literally every single one
of these phones and screens is a PSD and
when we updated one we had to update
about 4,000 more which was awesome at
the time but not really and we did the
same for desktop and then we did the
same for our m5 client html5 client
they'd be the same for our Android
client and so that was the first four
weeks it was awesome we just
photoshopped all the things and then
then our boss pulls us aside and he
tells us this scope prototype it but
don't write prototype code this is gonna
write production cuz we're not time to
write prototype code and we're like cool
look at this we got this do this and
then let me start think about cuz we're
gonna write we write twitter calm that's
so that's unbelievably awesome and then
it's oh no what are we gonna do how do
we do that this is range of emotions in
this couple of weeks while we try to do
this and so myself Connor and one of the
guy are on this we're tasked with
rewriting all of Twitter comms
HTML and CSS and we're like let's just
start programming let's just get right
to it
shout-out to Jessica Dillon for the
photo here she tweeted it a couple
months ago
I think it's fantastic so we just
started coding and the first this is the
first time we actually realized this
which is that PSD s don't mean squat
when you're building things on the web
because you'll have this pixel perfect
design but once you actually start to
code it you realize all these different
things and a lot of madama brought up as
well and is that you're gonna have all
these different people accessing this
content from different devices and you
don't know their situation you just have
to do your best to accommodate for all
those unknowns and so when we started
coding this we cut it up and maybe like
a week of real basic prototype here of
it and then we loaded it 97 it just
promptly crashed the entire computer fun
fact this is because we were using HTML
semantic elements and the html5 shim
which apparently just didn't work for IE
7 welcome that's that version or
something so we had to scrap all those
plans and we rewrote that entirely but
we didn't we would not have realized
that if we just stuck in Photoshop for
even longer while we try to figure out
design decisions one of those design
decisions for example was consolidating
all these similar things into one
component one instance of this component
one do one thing have one thing do one
thing really really well and an example
of that is like an avatar full name
username or two lines of text next to it
we had about six of those in those four
thousand mock-ups and Photoshop that we
had done and so when we got them and
we're starting to code this for the
engineers with the engineers we're
seeing stuff like this where it's like
this is the same thing but slightly
different and we'd be into lazy people
that we are we don't want to code the
same thing multiple times so we said no
no we're doing one thing and this is
what it's going to be and so we become
like we became like an intermediary
between the rest of design and the
people that actually know engineering
where that are writing all the
JavaScript and then the the rails code
to actually power this stuff one
component one piece of data it pushed
the product forward because instead of
having six different things that users
would see that are slightly the same
there was either gonna see just one
thing and that's how they know they're
actually looking at Twitter they've seen
the same thing what's actually
interesting about this is it Maps really
well up to today's frameworks and style
guides if you go to a company they have
a style guide this is how we do this
this how we do buttons and forms and how
we lay out our pages and things like
that it's a lot of that shared knowledge
but a lot of its also unique
lastly three years ago we didn't really
know this like this is still thing
people are talking about today is like
it's at github it's not it's not shipped
until it's fast and at Twitter when
we're crashing things that 500 million
monthly uniques I think we're trying to
access that's not a good thing so speed
becomes the future that we talk about so
instead of having the conversation about
what size box yet oh we're gonna use we
said no no no no box shadow because
browsers three years ago couldn't do it
especially ie9 at the time just one of
the amount of box shows we wanted to do
and if remember twitter.com it's
infinite scroll you just getting more
and more tweets more and more box
shadows it's just just bringing the page
to a crawl so it answered all those
stylistic questions and allowed us to
focus on the actual interactions and the
speed and the overall picture of the
product and it was immensely useful and
I think I can speak for the both of us
want to say it was by far the most
illuminated an awesome product we've
ever worked on
you're not allowed to speak for me but
it's carried forward in the three years
since then that we released that and two
more projects we worked on at Twitter
and even practice worked on github so
see what that looks like yeah so I mean
we talked a little bit about Twitter we
joke around like it's been like two and
a half almost three years since we're at
Twitter we should probably stop talking
about Twitter for a while all right it's
it's in the past mark anyways so let's
talk about Twitter a little bit we did
twitter.com your new Twitter and then we
had to iterate on it so I mean one of
the first projects we sort of picked up
after that was the profile redesign so
you kind of have me to blame for like
this well not really I can't really take
credit for the center to avatar somebody
centered an avatar before I did but
anyways we started doing this project
and you know we started falling into the
same traps like alright let's start
doing Photoshop documents for a thousand
different iterate or like every you know
permutation of this profile everything
that could happen so yeah we did that
for about a day I was like oh Wayne I
remember we already figured out what not
to do in this project so we started
coding it again right and this is just a
mobile prototype you know we mentioned
that a lot of bootstrap and ratchet are
open source projects came out of our
work at Twitter well this is a perfect
example this is like sort of what
ratchet started which was a mobile Iowa
prototyping tool originally came out of
and so we started building this stuff
and it you know it did a couple of
things obviously we already talked about
letting us figure out you know real data
even if it's just JSON dumps that we
were able to plug in it let us do user
testing let us get in front of users and
actually hand it to them but one of the
biggest things this particular project
actually taught us was they allowed a
small group of people to get a lot of
momentum around a very simple idea and a
big company I don't know about you guys
like obviously you know I hadn't
mentioned Salesforce that's a pretty big
company
well little bigger some medium-sized
would you say anyways yeah we some of us
may work at big companies it's really
hard to get momentum going well I think
code and our experience is it's proven
that it's like really easy to get
momentum when you're actually to have
something that feels real so in this
particular case like we're running a
bunch of red blocks I won't name names
but anyways I'm just kidding I will name
names it was Marc Jacobs I was able to
take you know the phone and say alright
here's this profile here's something
cool we could do really quickly and just
go up to the CEO go up to dick and say
hey man can we build this they could be
really cool if we could build this and
of course he's like it looks done why
isn't it shipped right because you know
he's not trying to figure out this low
level organizational crap he just wants
to ship product and get stuff done and
so like you know you get that momentum
going and yeah it's really cool so I
mean this is just one example so again
not to talk about Twitter forever
I went over to github and you know we've
been talking a lot about big projects
like new Twitter and profiles that's
pretty cool but this really just applies
to everything so this is a really small
project first project I worked on it I
get up I just sort of grabbed you know I
looked at the site and I was like what
sucks on github.com that I could fix
really simply and it was our Senate page
our joint page and I sort of was able to
open up a pull request and of course
this is what github is based around open
up a poll or Kratz cut a branch and
start working on it so it's really cool
to be able to like get in there and
start designing some stuff but just
roping back to like that design process
it's not saying this isn't a design in
the browser talk like we're not trying
to say like old design philosophies and
old design techniques are antiquated and
throw them out and you're a loser if use
them cuz I sketch all day long like this
is sort of like what I think is you know
one of the things that allows you to
even code faster is getting your ideas
really quickly going back to that
simplified process just get your idea
out as quickly as possible whether it's
a sharpie or a pin and then move it
through to code as quickly as possible
so I mean this is just a quick flow but
it's another example of how we were able
to get momentum around in just a new
company I didn't know anybody but mark
and be able to get something ship really
quickly and obviously that it's gonna
vary you're gonna get different mileage
from company company but in general
whether there's a lot of bureaucracy or
none at all like it's proven to be like
a really good technique and of the many
right ways of doing something this is
one that's worked out for us the other
one for me has been split this which
until very recently was probably the
most requested feature in all of github
history how many people use split this
side by side this yes nobody like half
the room at least half the room Connor
come on you guys check so in addition to
Pawnee bridge names we jump right into
polar coasts because we can actually
show people these things I bought a year
and a half ago I did a quick mock-up and
then tweedle Twitter with some code and
tried to make side-by-side this happen I
just couldn't because the code was so
convoluted in that case I got shut down
I'm gonna shut myself down by trying to
do even more mock-ups with it and then I
got a little more momentum behind me and
I was able to do it after some brief
refactoring to our diffing code and we
made it happen by opening the polar
quest and exactly two months later we
had it shipped to the entire user base
and so went about two and a half weeks
of like in this code in this in this
pull request here and it includes
screenshots from the stuff that I'd
worked on you see today's split this
actually collapsed the additions and
deletions onto us combined rows whereas
the original prototype didn't so that
was a product decision we made after we
started feeling it out in the browser
after we start actually using it
ourselves because do you imagine trying
design like dips in Photoshop or sketch
that sounds horrendous I'd have to copy
and paste code a bunch of times and then
by the way we just shipped syntax
highlighting on tips today we'd have to
do that to you because that was going on
at the same time and trying to recreate
all this stuff which is horrible so we
figure out the basics jumped into code
open up a branch or start a branch open
a pull request and we got this cool
thing at the top my top comment you can
actually play with it on a staging
environment cuz I have a cool thing
called branch labs we just push code out
there and I got some vulgar commits and
some really shitty commits there too and
we just kept iterating on this branch
and we actually got to play with it and
that's the point is that you get to did
you get to those real fields of like oh
click this button all the sudden I have
a split diff and I'm writing these
comments on one side and these comments
on another side I'm telling Conor how
awesome or how bad his code is and
that's awesome that's how we should be
doing these things as close to the end
goal as possible and that's what we
basically want to reiterate today is
just that get to code real fast and no
matter if you're a designer or developer
by title you will be an awesome product
designer because you're building it
where it's gonna end up and that's
what's most exciting about what we do
why we write all the HTML CSS that we do
and that I think about wraps it up for
us thanks so much for coming out