I'm going to talk about cecchetti oh
it's a open source project for enabling
WebSocket and making real time
applications easy to make on every
browser and every mobile device and we
can make it work on so my name is
Guillermo ouch and the CTO and
co-founder of an education startup in
San Francisco we have a big commitment
to open source and I spent part of my
time developing this technology having
heavily involved with no Jas since it
appeared I originally developed a
standalone WebSocket server that of
course would only work with WebSocket
clients and then I saw the opportunity
of making WebSocket work on more than
just cutting edge browsers i'm also a
core modules developer I've been working
on client side JavaScript for a while
and those are my if you want to reach
out or fork any of my projects you can
go to github or follow me on Twitter or
find me on freenode so Sokka do is
actually two projects there's a socket
i/o client that of course runs on the
browser uses feature detection to decide
what how to establish a real-time
communication to the server depending on
the user agent capabilities and an
officially supported socket i/o noth web
server there some projects are trying to
make socket i/o work also on other
stacks such as air leg python with
tornado twisted even google go so you
can go to the socket a website to learn
more about those so the client-side API
looks
I know if you guys are familiar with
WebSocket but i'm going to go into it
later the api that you instantiate from
the client looks pretty much like
WebSocket it does it does more than web
socket which is necessary for creating
real world real time applications the
premise is that it works in every
browser so you're not concerned about
compatibility and it's lightweight it's
only 10 kilobytes when compressed I'm
going to talk a little bit about about
the real time web and what I mean when I
talk about real time web applications
there when you when we talk about real
time web applications there are many
terms that come to mind and that have
been popularized over the years such as
the Bayeux prodigal comet this this
premise of server push so we're sending
data to the client which is reversing
the request response model now there's
web socket and all other protocols like
XMPP so what is which I'm going to start
by describing a real simple real time
application at Twitter client that
fetches know Jas tweets as they are
pushed by Twitter's and you might wish
to display the tweets on your website so
the first approach that would come to
mind for most people is just making
agents requests every five seconds right
so you could use set interval and with a
light jquery call you can get data from
server to the client in pseudo real time
of course the problem is that you're
only getting data five seconds at a time
and whatever happens in the middle
you're not showing instantly or you're
not sure
wing to the user as frequently as you
could wish so the next approach that
would come to mind was would be making a
nation skull and that as the server is
there any data ordinary tweets for me
and if there is show them if there is
not initiate another Asians request but
that approach has two major flaws one is
that taken into consideration the HTTP
latency and download time the best-case
scenario for that is that it might take
500 milliseconds between Asia's requests
where the client is basically
disconnected and another problems that
we're increasing network traffic but the
server might not have any tweets for us
might not have any data so we're
basically asking the server a law
generating a lot of calls for and we're
not sure if there is going to be data
there so they're the first solution to
this problem is called long polling it
it's not actual server push but it
that's a pretty good job for most of the
use cases because what it does is it
opens the connection and if there is no
data for us it keeps it open for a
number of seconds like 20 seconds it
effectively decreases latency and or
traffic and another advantage of this
approach is that it pretty much works in
every browser if you're using jQuery to
make the call or and any other
JavaScript framework you're you're
enabling your application to make a
real-time call without any overhead or
incompatibilities of course it also has
witnesses if there's a lot of data for
us then the long polling loop will be
would be effectively closing and opening
connections all the time so we're back
at our second approach which was calling
the HS create another HS code when when
when finished so again we're hitting
latency and network traffic problems so
the solution that makes the most sense
would be keeping the connection open and
there are transports there are solutions
for this too pretty common ones are
opening an iframe in not closing it and
get a script tags that are executed when
there's data and another one a little
bit less known but supported by Firefox
is the multi-part x-mix replace content
type essentially it's a normal
xmlhttprequest object that is created by
passing the multi-part flag and it
senses messages with boundaries so the
server has to say okay here's a message
the boundary some some delimiter message
and the connection is open and we're
getting data all the time the hidden
iframe also has implementation
differences we have to make sure we send
the connection keep-alive header
transfer encoding chunked those are HTTP
headers that we have to send and as a
new experience problem what happens when
you just open an iframe that is injected
into the DOM is that many browsers
browsers are going to show the progress
bar as if the page never loaded so the
user will be met with a progress bar
that it's like he's not sure what's
going on really there is a solution for
this which is implemented by cerca de
enero explorer discovered and
popularized by the gmail team when they
created gmail chat which is hiding this
iframe injecting it into a pseudo
document which is an activex HTML file
component that effectively hides the
spinners and progress bars so these are
to transport that transports that we can
leverage to make real-time communication
possible of course for certain browsers
and the server has to behave differently
depending on which transport is used so
the this technique are there they vary
by user agent they're only for incoming
data so when you open that iframe
and you need to send data to a server in
order to have bi-directional
communication you still have to use
regular Ajax so the solution by the web
standards people is called WebSocket so
you shouldn't be needing to struggle
with all these limitations we need the
prodigal that enables bi-directional
communication out of the box with a
simple API if you guys read the spec
it's it's this is the way the
description and simplicity is one of the
core goals of this protocol the way that
it works at an HTTP level is that it
updates the connection HTTP 1.1 supports
this upgrade header that basically says
at this point we're not doing a normal
HTTP communication we're upgrading it to
a new protocol in this case the
WebSocket protocol again the server has
to behave react to this response by
doing several things during the
handshake process draft 76 linear draft
of WebSocket introduced a security
mechanism it has a fairly unique
pregnancy framing system it does utf-8
for the encoding know binary support and
of course it's only supported by
cutting-edge browsers and it's still
ongoing constant changes it's pretty
much a work in progress but again one of
the advantages is a WebSocket is really
simple basically we declare we connect
to the server with the WSS schema and we
have three event handlers actually for
there is an error when that notifies us
when the connection is open when a
message is received and when the
connection is gratefully closed
so considering the state of WebSocket
today let's think about cross browser
support when we do latex today like I
described earlier we were used to using
some obstruction of xml httprequest
which also gives us compatibility for
example with ie6 by leveraging the
ActiveX object that microsoft created
back in the day they say this kind of
API make it simpler to achieve the goal
of making an asynchronous request to the
server and they also have new features
in the case of jquery we all say we now
have support for timeouts caching
filters depending on the content type of
the response and again the entire goal
is that were making age it's simple to
use and so ko has a really similar goal
so we're abstracting away all these
transports it's not just WebSocket we
can also use flash if available we can
use long polling we can use multi-part
HX iframes and it all depends on what
user agent is trying to connect to a
server so far Sokka do has been tested
on I 5.5 with different transports like
flash and HTML file safari 3 chrome
opera and mobile devices it again adds
new features so for example well when
you open a WebSocket connection they the
closed event will only be fired if the
connection is closed appropriately if if
the server dies or the client internet
connection is has issues that closed
event will never fire so even though the
API is simple we still have limitations
when we really need to create a
functional real world application
we were trying to do what all these
frameworks did for Ajax we're trying to
do for real-time communication so so far
the the project has been successfully
deployed to production in many cases if
you guys follow the node knockout
competition many people have created
real ten games and other kinds of
real-time applications with it and there
is a lot of community interest on github
but one thing to keep in mind that sucka
day was just a building block it's okay
is protocol agnostic saga de oh you can
send Jason and on the client side
interpret it and do something or you can
connect and implement the IRC protocol
for example and you can create an IRC
client and speak the IRC idioms again
Sokka do is just a building block
creating real-time applications is not
trivial there's many different protocols
in many different ways to do it and
again is significantly significantly
different from making certain things in
your regular web application real time
so i created this project that leverages
socket AO called no stream the goal of
no stream is being the protocol for the
most common use cases for your web
applications as an example i created a
really simple to the list application on
nodejs
so again this is a regular web
application that interfaces with the
database and displays the two Lewis
items that you have the complete and it
allows you to have new items every time
we have something the page is refreshed
and we can edit right so even though
this is a really simple application it
still has many flaws for the users the
first one is that what happens when you
open two tabs of two instances of your
application and you decide to delete an
item all of a sudden this page has two
items this page has three it ends up
hurting the user experience in this
particular case but what happens if more
than one person are trying to use this
this application so I'm going to quickly
show what the code looks like to create
this application for those not familiar
with no Jas I'm defining a model I'm
using Express web framework to defined
to define some routes like edit as
delete and I call the database and I
remove the items to have the items
respectively and then what I sent to the
client is a redirect and this is this is
what we're trying to change with no
string so i'm going to show you what the
real time version of this to do list
looks like
this in this case we're attaching socket
i/o to the web server so and it has two
new features first we're displaying who
is editing and now we're making all the
interactions that I described through
the routes we're making them real time
so what happens when I open a new tab is
that all of a sudden they're all the
same and we can take it to a new level
and we can try out different browsers
it's interesting to see that so far I
five of course is connecting to socket
i/o through WebSocket because it's the
best transporter socket i/o can find
what happens when I go to Firefox is
that it's going to use multi-part like I
describe this process is complete
transparent to the developer and and
again it we are in effectively enabling
real-time collaboration across users if
I close one tab the counter will stop
will change now the real interesting
part about no stream is that we're all
these features have been created by only
doing two things one is firing events
when certain actions happen which it's a
great fit for no Jas of course and the
other thing is that i'm only using I'm
only telling the template language what
things to update so this is what a
template language looks like this is
similar to Hamill it's called Jade this
is the page for our old to do
application the traditional one I get
the items I go through them and I show a
piece of template now in the real 10
version
all I do is declare a part of the
template that's real time I tell it this
piece of disputes of template it's real
time and it it will repaint whenever the
connections event is fire and the
variable will be called connections
sayin oh oh I'm sorry
nope
and not quite
any suggestions lazy always good no pun
intended again I simply replace that 4-h
loop with this real time filter and I'm
indicating it that it will append new
items when the new event is fired it'll
repaint with edits fired and remove when
the removal and is fired and all i have
to do from my application its fire those
events so instead of resurrecting the
user I'm just sending a 200 response and
emitting this event so what happens is
that the user the you as a developer I
are simply making a nation's call that
triggers that event and through the
real-time socket we fired the we fire
the changes so not only has the need
effective way of making your application
real time it also has it also makes the
client-side code simpler because we're
no longer making a nation's request that
returns some HTML and then we decided to
inject it somewhere you don't have it's
transparently from the client-side point
of view so that's a no stream again uses
salga do as a building block to enable
it to work on every browser including
mobile devices and
you can find this particular example
oops at my github page JS conf to the
demo that's it thank you
any questions
so yeah those the differences between
transports including the ones related to
message length are taken care of by
cerca de oso at you when you're
leveraging it you're not concerned at
all with with how the limitation had
limitations of limitations of the
transport so Sokka dave has a very thin
prodigal that is of course hidden from
the user which is required for example
for long polling so in one polling the
client is opening and closing
connections but the server might want to
send messages during that disconnection
period so we need a protocol that says
okay this long polling client has a
session ID and will buffer messages from
for him on server side and when he
recollects we're saying that protocol is
saying okay you have ten messages so you
have to fire ten message events and each
the transfer also takes care of saying
okay the message length is this and if
it if the client can check okay is the
entire message here otherwise it will
wait for more data
correct I'm gonna open source it right
away
no stream is entirely based on no Jas
technologies so right now it works with
a specific template language created for
node but it wouldn't be too difficult to
make it work with more and again the
server side part of ocotillo itself the
protocol is documented and it can be
implemented on any back-end and again
the client side part of no stream can
also be leveraged for any implementation
that speaks the no stream protocol yeah
so connect is a framework that is geared
towards request-response cycles so
making it making Sokka a middleware in
that regard would be extremely difficult
and we would have to actually change how
connect middleware is defined but what
I'm working on is a session connect and
the ability for easy identification of
Sokka do clients to the session of your
website so if connect if you're
leveraging this session component in
connect you probably have some like
database data associated to that session
because the user might be logged in and
making that easy to retrieve from socket
i/o is certainly one of my goals but
also make it compatible with any other
session mechanisms that you might be
using not just connect and the session
middleware yep
nope
correct yeah any sugg and a wood would
totally support that yep