[Music]
thank you and yeah it's nice to see all
of you here to want to listen to my
story about gratitude and I'm gonna tell
you about a day and evening in July 2015
that changed my perspective of Who I am
and what I'm gonna be and I'm still very
very grateful for that moment but the
story starts a little bit earlier about
six months earlier when I came to Berlin
as a biologist to start a PhD on
honeybees and I stayed there for three
months notice academia really wasn't the
place for me
and I decided to become a developer so I
learned how to code I wrote lots and
lots of applications and three months
later I actually had my first developer
job so then that was awesome right but
it was also super scary you go in there
you don't know anything and right there
was so much stuff than over my hat but
also in my first days on that job
something really weird happened to me
suddenly I was introduced everywhere as
the female developer and I never
considered myself female I was just
sissy I never thought about this and it
kept on happening like I I was lucky my
team was really nice they were trying to
make me feel good and they were teaching
me a lot of things but I was constantly
the only woman in the room and I didn't
even notice but it it was just straining
so now we come to delight three months
later I still come home really tired
because of all the stuff that I learned
every day right but also because of this
weird feeling of not fitting in like
everybody is kind of speaking a
different language from me and so I'm
new to Berlin so I go to meetups to meet
people and one of these meetups that I
found was women who code Berlin and on
that night it was the very first meetup
I didn't expect anything one of my first
tech meetups and I walk into a room and
this room in this room they are like 50
female developers and I almost cried it
like I still can't describe the feeling
and yeah all I can say like sometimes
you have to go away to notice your home
it like the way these meetups work is
they have a couple of talks and a lot of
community time it's open to everybody
also males can attend only people who
consider themselves female can speak and
all the technical to like it's over all
languages all topics so the technical
talks totally went over my hat I didn't
understand anything but the thing that I
really remember is the amazing Alexander
like a veal Oscar she's one of the
organizers and as senior iOS developer
at SoundCloud and she gave a talk about
something iOS II I didn't understand at
all but seeing her up on stage there
showed me that these people who are
somewhat like me who can be coding
rockstars and that was the first moment
where I actually felt like I could
belong into this industry that there
could be a place for me in there and
this really has opened up for me the
opportunity to go to a lot of other
meetups and now I'm this is four years
ago right so now I speak at a lot of
meters I tutor I there's a lot of
communities that I can call home now but
it all started on that that evening and
I'm super super grateful for that so
thank you
[Applause]