Okay if you think they are doing badly you stand up you can believe they are making
I stand here talking about the entire presentation!
Hello everyone, my tame is Tara.
Today I will ask you to use your imagination to think about the web in a way you never thought
Before.
What I ask you to imagine is a web without a server.
If your immediate response is chaos or skepticism, it's okay because it doesn't
It has a lot to do with how the Internet works today.
If I tell my background and my work now, they will start to come together.
My name is Tara Vancil and I am a web developer.
For me, this means that I spend most of my time thinking about networking or building things
Online.
I'm really interested in peer-to-peer protocols. I like anything about nails.
If you are interested in polish or nail polish, we will definitely talk about it later.
The Internet is now a very important part of my life, but this is not always the case.
I didn't actually grow up online.
My family does not have a computer and we live in a rural area with a little internet.
The only computer I have access to is the school. We mainly use them to learn how
Enter.
I did enter Facebook, MySpace and Sparknotes in my teens, but my object line experience
It's mainly about consumption.
I'm almost watching my photos crush and catch up with books I don't have
Reading English lessons.
It was not until a long time ago that I learned about the existence of HTML, JavaScript and
CSS I realized I can build stuff online.
It's just something I never considered before.
I think building a website is reserved for super talented programmers.
This is a very, very exciting time for me.
Because it completely changed my perception of what the web is and how I participate
On it.
But after studying, I finally realized how to write a web page in HTML.
I need an important question to answer: how do I share these things
I'm building?
Thankfully, the answer to this question is really simple.
You just need to install webpack using MPM and you can set up your local web server and SSH to the server
You have set it up on AWS.
OK, it's actually not that simple.
Now, to be clear, I'm joking.
I do n’t think tools are complicated and bad, I think tools are great because they help
We build things, it doesn't matter which tool you choose, as long as it helps you
Build what the browser can understand.
Whether you are writing a simple HTML file or building something more complex, your options are valid.
The point is that writing web pages is flexible and forgive
Initial beginners have space and most experts-experts in building something
What makes sense is what makes the web such a great toolset.
When I was a beginner, it was actually a kind burden to build something and share
The internet.
I can tell you that this is not a tool to make. I feel that way.
This is the server.
Now, I mean the best way, but the server is terrible.
I feel like this because I started building things online in this sweet place
The period when GeoCities was closed but tools like Netlify and Glitch did not
Still exists.
GitHub pages are everywhere, but I don't feel comfortable using git at that point.
As far as I know, the best option I share is the website I am making
Set up the server.
This is frustrating because I don't have the time, expertise or money to do this.
Really, who?
Like a human super sliver, who knows how to set up a server,
And, let alone enjoy it.
I can set up the server now, for a few days, when I have the mood to play Engine X
But most of the time this is the last thing I want to do.
I believe some people in this room are running the server very well, but I don't think it is
Fairly expect the rest of the world.
With 3 billion people on the Internet today, that number will only grow.
They are using tools like Facebook, Instagram and WeChat welcome.
awesome.
We saw on a scale that the connection between people was once unimaginable.
But I think it's fair to say that most of these people will never go
Engage these tools beyond the boundaries of the network.
Post tweets, share life updates on Facebook, or show photos of Berlin Street
Cats on Instagram, but they will never make an HTML page, and never for their fan site
Favorite band.
They can never experience the joy of creative building something online
It really is theirs.
I think we have to sit down and think about whether this is really appropriate.
maybe.
Maybe not everyone wants to learn how to build a website.
But I think we should be sure that the network itself will not hinder those
Who does it.
Personally, I worry about it.
I'm afraid that publishing online is a bottleneck.
It's as simple as sending HTML files to friends. It's too complicated.
I mean, think about it: if you know the web, you can spend months and months packing
Latest on how to write HTML pages, vertical center divs or navigation
JavaScript framework.
After all, you have your own support, you have some confidence, maybe it was built
You are proud of something.
You still need to figure out the server.
I just think the web can do better.
In fact, I think it's vital that the web do better.
Because barriers to entry remain-if barriers to entry remain high, I
Hate thinking about the web for ten or two decades.
Keep in mind that the web has been around since 1990, and we have seen early
What happens when most people use a few platforms is involved.
So how does this work for a long time?
If 28 years from today, what it will look like, most people are still using tools like Facebook,
Or WeChat, or Instagram.
Is it still the web or does the provider shape it into something completely different?
I do n’t know, but it seems to make sense, but I do n’t think this is a risk we should be willing to take
take.
The network is too precious.
This is a weird social experiment that establishes a global language for building things.
How cool?
At least, I think a network like this looks boring to me.
If you were here last year, you may remember one of our hosts, Rachel White, made a statement
Called Keep the Web Weird.
When I interpreted it as that kind of love letter community, the internet inspired creativity
Well, the tools are accessible.
She returned to GeoCities and Angel Fire with several tools at the time
People can jump into the browser, write HTML, and publish the website for free.
But you probably know that GeoCities was closed down in 2009 and took 38 million websites
it.
Archives provide a courageous effort to save those websites and save precious gifts
From the age of GeoCities, but failed to save all 38 million websites.
They are gone.
I think GeoCities come and go and the rise of Neocities and Glitch tells us
What we have about the internet and what is missing from it.
I think it tells us that setting up the server is out of reach for most people
They simply can't do it. Instead, they have the tools to rely on it.
Now, I like Neocities, I like Glitch, and in fact, I think they do the most
Now important network work.
We came here before 3 Neocities and Glitch to help us circumvent the fact of publishing
Difficult online, but I think we should ask why it is so uncomfortable
First place?
What can we do to make it easier for the kind of longevity we expect
network platform?
I think we can make it easier, and I want to share with you my views on this possible
looks like.
I would like to ask if the server shares a website if we don't need it?
What if we can press the button in the browser and, with one click, create a new web page?
That would be great but how can we pull it down the world?
We have these very powerful devices.
We have mobile phones, laptops, right?
Maybe we can turn them into servers?
Sadly, this is not easy.
There are many problems with this idea, but in short, our personal devices
It's just not the server.
First, we sometimes close them, is it because we are asleep
Or the battery is broken.
They do not always have dedicated IP addresses, and they are not built at all for processing
The kind of traffic the server does.
Imagine publishing a video computer from your personal to make it viral.
Your computer will be overwhelmed by millions of requests, and your home network may
He fell down after a few minutes.
Well, if this one-click publishing idea is to work, we have to think outside
Server box, because, again, our personal device is just not a server.
Fortunately, some smart people have solved this problem on its head and have found a regular way
A device doesn't need to be a server to do various things of the server.
BitTorrent was created in the early 2000s and you call it a peer-to-peer network.
The key innovation is asking if instead one computer, one server, handles all
What is the responsibility of hosting files if we share this responsibility
A network of a bunch of different computers so that any device can jump to the network
And contribute some bandwidth?
Maybe some of these devices are similar to those that the server undoubtedly exists in the cloud
Sometimes some devices go offline, but the big idea is that regular devices can help
Contribute a network of resources to hosted files?
This is really a big problem.
Now, I believe most people know BitTorrent because of its shame.
It is mainly used for downloading movies and illegal music and other media, but I
I want to point out that it is incredible with a lot of legal and other innovations
Legal use case.
The most important thing is that it makes it possible for ordinary people with regular equipment
Being able to host files, I just thought it was pretty cool.
So what if we take this approach and we apply it online?
Websites are just files after all.
If the website is just a collection of files, then if we can use peer-to-peer
To get a website from one computer to another?
It turns out you can, I'm really excited to tell you more about it.
I work with these two guys-P Frazee and Macintosh.
They are all here today.
The three of us worked together on a project called Beaker Browser.
Beaker is an experimental browser, meaning we don't always follow web standards.
But this is not because we don't think they are important, we have only performed some experiments
Remember we want to run, we think they are worth running, even if they are
Does not meet the standard.
What the core experiment we are running happens when you take one of these peer-to-peer
Web, do you put it in your browser?
So we want to keep the web roughly the same, keep the browser very familiar, but make
It's peer.
We are in a very lucky position to do this experiment.
Because Macintosh is a peer-to-peer protocol for core developers called Dat
Similar to BitTorrent, but there are important improvements that make it perfect for this type
What we do online.
We took it to the browser, then put it in. It went into Beaker and found something really
Interesting things happen, such as enabling one-click publishing, giving the view source cool
New features and made it possible to provide developers with new Web APIs.
Why don't I show you?
Ok.
This is the beaker.
My apologies for the tags and URL bar are small.
I will try to point out what is important.
At first glance, it looks spectacular to any browser you are familiar with.
So it is not significant in this regard.
Before I show you anything exciting, I tell you what a peer-to-peer website looks like.
like.
This is my website, you may notice that instead of HTTPS, the protocol in the URL
It's DAT.
It's really small but that's what it says.
It looks like the website you expect looks like-the links work like you
I hope that the images work the same way they do in other browsers
CSS.
This is our intention choice.
We do n’t want to end the web, we want to see what happens if we put
One of the peer-to-peer networks.
[Distorted sound input].
We do treat this device like a server but it is not.
So I want to jump to Beaker's main menu and click the "Create New" button.
I will click on the website template.
You can create an empty project or import an existing one.
For this, I will import this template time.
What happened here was Beaker forging a brand new website.
It has information on how to get started, change the background color here, nothing
It's too fancy.
I think it's exciting that this site has its own URL.
I can share this URL with anyone of you.
If you want to open it in Beaker, because we are the only one who supports it, you can
Download the website from my computer.
No server is involved here.
Right now, this URL is not very pretty.
do not you remember.
Just like IP addresses are hard to remember.
How does a URL like this use the Domain Name System? It turned out to work great.
I built a website to show you how it works.
This is the JSConf EU subdomain on my website.
By using, I was able to get a txt record of this wonderful time.
I set it up through my domain registrar-Google-I pointed the subdomain to long
Ugly URL, that's all it needs.
I don't have any server fuss to get that good URL.
I promised you, I will tell you to observe the source, let's take a look at Beak Beck.
What we see here is all the files that make up the site we just looked at
in.
You can see favicon here we can take a look at the style and of course we can
See the HTML we just saw.
These files exist on my computer.
Shouldn't I be able to edit them if they live on my computer?
Yes, you can.
We can actually edit the file in the view source so I can click the button
Right here.
I want to add some exclamation marks to this title.
When I save and return the label, we see those changes.
[applause].
OK, this is cool, but we are all developers and we may have a preference for us
Editing environment?
Some of us like Sublime, and some of us like DS Code.
Again, these files are all on my computer, so I can open them in my favorite editor.
Before I do this, I want to open a cool one we have a small feature-library loading
-I want to jump over-I want to jump to the view source tool
once again.
I want to copy the path to those local files on my computer.
And open those files.
I want to open the index.html file, I just want to say "Hello, from Sublime".
Once I click on save and go to the tab, we can see the changes without the need
Refresh.
[applause].
This is an interesting gadget.
So i show you one click release
You see some new stuff sources we enabled but i didn't tell you about the new
Network API is not yet available.
Before I do this, I want to give a backstory why we think this is necessary.
When we first started building Beaker, we were happy with the facts we could do
Launched one-click publishing but we realized that the web is not a static collection
Website, though it might be a better place if it is.
We think there is any way to reconstruct the behavior used by applications on the web
Pee network?
Can we solve problems with user profiles, databases, or something like that?
The answer is yes.
If you consider it, the database or user profile is usually represented by just
Documents, right?
And, if the site is just files, then maybe we can represent user data and users
Personal information on the website.
This is what we and others mean. Building on these toolsets is experimentation.
use.
This is a profile.json file.
This is the profile social media site I use on peer-to-peer.
You can see these attributes are my name, bio, and avatar.
I think it would be easier for me to sink it later if I said that.
If we want to make it possible for developers to build peer-to-peer applications to use user data,
We need to make sure they can read and write rye data.
The new Web API looks a bit like this.
Again, it would be easier if I just told you.
I plan to jump to the console site here.
Let's see.
I want to launch this Dat website on behalf of us by getting an object
on.
I will use it to do this using Dat to archive the API and Beaker we have.
Do window.location.
We have this object now and we can do many things with it.
I want to tell you something we can write about this site's new HTML file.
We will have a website written by ourselves.
Ok, so website.writefile and call it api.html and write simple markup for it.
We wrote this file, now if we go to api.ptml we can see that we have created
A new HTML file.
[applause].
This may not be completely intuitive at first, but it can be done a lot.
We have a complete social media application with these APIs for writing user profiles.
It looks a bit like Twitter, and you may have noticed that it was intentional.
We want to see if we can replicate a lot of the behavior Twitter provides, so
We have a feed, we can look at people's posts, and of course we can post replies.
I think I would say "Hello from JSConf", anyone who follows me will sync
These changes come from my profile
-Synchronize these changes. "
I want-I want to show you what I mean by putting
User data from user profile to website.
These are my posts.
The objects that represent my posts are beautiful and simple: text and timestamps.
If this is a response, it will also contain information about the person I responded to.
I think it's cool.
Interesting things happen when separated from user data at the application layer.
In this case, the application layer is a point of view above my profile.
# 1 in the profiles of all my friends.
This means that neither the application nor the data is bundled longer, so I can actually customize
The application has no consequences, so let's do it and let's see what happens
jobs.
I will open it in ViewSource.
I'm not just this site, so I can't just edit them.
I have to make a copy.
I want to continue making copies.
I don't like that kind of churros.
This app has round buttons.
I want to make it square.
I'm going to jump to the CSS file here and search for the button class.
This is the border radius I want to get rid of.
We will save it.
We will see a brand new social media application.
We can see that the buttons are now square.
[applause].
I didn't give this specific example application permissions write to my profile
That's why it looks a little different, but if I choose my profile and load everything
Get up, I won't lose any friends.
I will not lose my network or content or anything.
Even though this change I made is a bit trivial, you can imagine being in a situation
On social media, it's not trivial to want to change production.
Maybe you want to have some say how the color scheme works because you are
Color blindness, or you want better control tools.
You have the right to do this with this model, and I think it's great.
Right now, I will not make any promises of this type of model, a peer-to-peer network
To solve all wrong network problems, I will not promise
Apps like Friter will always be as popular as Facebook or Twitter because
They are already very popular, but I can guarantee a peer-to-peer network
To make such an application possible, I can say it's full of confidence because I use Friter
Every day, my friends do the same.
If you want to know more about Beaker, please talk to me later, I am happy to share
about it.
You can visit these links to learn more.
I want to end this and fundamentally, the peer-to-peer network is a more interesting network,
No matter what your technical expertise is, this is one you can contribute, build and
share it.
I think this makes it a valuable experiment to run not only in Beaker, but also on each one individually
Browser.
Thank you so much for imagining me.
[applause].