[Music]
hey everyone so I'm back again for a
quick lightening talk after I saw Tim's
talk on CSS I couldn't resist
and I wanted to add in a JavaScript
pranks demo for you guys so if you can
prank and CSS when I prank and
JavaScript as well so there's this
website here I made I'm gonna go over
some of the code with you guys really
quickly we can see how to troll in
JavaScript okay so this is very ad hoc
so apologies for the informality of this
okay so one thing you can do is some
websites on the internet they actually
lets you log out the site with a get
request so if you visit this you are
these URLs here you'll be logged out of
those sites well guess what any website
on the Internet can make get requests by
putting those URLs into an image tag and
that will log you out so let's go ahead
and iterate over this and just log you
out of everything when you visit this
site why not right
let's see what else let's see okay
here's a good one so no sorry it's down
here yes okay this is this one is
amazing so when you link to a website
and you add the target equals a blank
underscore blank to the link that opens
the link up in a new tab but it also
sets a property called window opener on
that child window and that property is a
reference back to the parent window that
opened you and using that reference you
can set window opener dot location and
to navigate to the window that linked to
you so for example you send a link to
this site to your friends and met in
facebook Messenger and the site you land
on navigates the facebook messenger
window to the same troll site so it
takes over the other tab pretty cool
this is a standard troll trick so this
one lets you confirm that the user
really wants to leave the website that
there
they're on so and they try to close the
tab they have to see another prompt
window here's another good one let's
register every protocol handler that we
can in the browser so when you click on
these links it will try to redirect you
to this site this one has a permission
prompt so it's not that effective but
you can try to do it anyway while we're
at it let's try to get access to the
camera and the mic basically we're just
putting everything we can into this site
just all the API is let's just try to
just do everything we can
oh this is a good one did you know if
you call web window dot navigator dot
vibrate you can make Android phones
vibrate and there's no permission
required for that so let's just vibrate
the phone randomly why not let's
intercept every click and keypress let's
use a Safari picture-in-picture video
when you click on the page let's focus
it's open a bunch of pop-up windows and
bounce them around the screen let's
focus those windows every time you
interact with any of the windows let's
hide the mouse cursor with C it with a
CSS rule so you don't know where the
mouse is so it's hard to go and close
the windows let's trigger a file
download every time you click on
anything why not this is the code to
move the window around this is a code to
play videos inside the pop-up windows
how much time do I have
you've got a clock in front of you 1:45
ok ok I'm gonna see the last minute to
demo it ok every time you click we can
copy stuff to your clipboard so let's
copy a ASCII picture of a cat and that's
right here one of these cats copy it to
your clipboard along with the link handy
link to this website so when you paste
it in by accident to your friends you'll
get it will get spread further and what
else do I got to show there's a few more
things Oh show with some alerts let's
request full screen so on and so forth
anyway you get the idea let's see it in
action ok this is Safari we're gonna go
to the annoying site calm okay Oh some
files are being downloaded do I'm sure I
want to give camera access to the site
ok don't allow ok all right we're good
I'm gonna try to click on this cat oh no
oh no what's going on here
okay let me just leave the page
okay now I'm in full screen mode I don't
know what's going on let me close this
window
leave page I have some pop-ups flying
around let me try to close these if you
accidentally click on the window then it
alerts that a cat comes up and then it
also does a picture-in-picture full
screen video over here in the OS if you
try to close that then okay it goes back
if you try to get command W to close the
window it triggers a print dialog window
so actually it intercepts the command W
can't close the window the X button is
also removed here okay let's try again
command W oh no basically the moral this
story is the web platform is very
powerful and it lets you do very many
things and oh yeah this is a good one
this one does Bing searches for very
intimidating terms and it doesn't over
HTTP a gets its HTTP but it tries to do
it over HTTP so that it'll get added to
your oh yeah it also gets added to your
web history so you go history and all
those searches like why do I always have
diarrhea for example is added to your
web history anyway that's my top thanks