hi thank you for the intro as she said
my name is Antoine Butler and I'm a
front-end developer for an advertising
agency outside of DC called HD DG we
build you know websites and apps for
organizations like National Football
League Volkswagen and so on and I'm
really excited to be here because I'm on
a team of 14 developers who are
primarily full-stack they do really
crazy javascript stuff node and Python
development and I'm one of the few
dedicated front-end developers which
makes something like CSS comp really
awesome so I'd like to say thank you to
everyone for having me and not doing a B
track right now instead so thank you so
on to while I'm actually here my talk
embraced the vertical the future of hi
Pia queries when I went around to my
team I kind of asked them if you were
here what do you want to know about
vertical media queries and how to use my
things slipping here and pretty much the
consensus was what are vertical media
queries and I thought you know what
that's a really good question so maybe
I'll backtrack and make sure we're all
on the same page as far as what about
media query is so apologize if this is a
very entry-level introduction to the
subject matter so again what is a
vertical media query I'm going to
paraphrase the spec because it's
entirely too wordy which reads a media
query allows you to tailor your layout
based on any number of conditions
against a media type and those available
conditions are of course aspect ratio
orientation resolution color and size
and while I'm here is to talk to you
guys about size
because it's not just the whiff that
counts I had to that gift that gives me
a moment to breathe so a part of me if I
sound ridiculously nervous or if I don't
in the Amy because this is also my first
talk ever yeah and luckily I think we're
kind of running a little over so I might
be able to make this short you can get
everyone to lunch long time but I wanted
to quote Chris koya from a article I
think two years ago where he said
measuring width is a nice practical
example of media queries but it's not
the only thing available but despite
that if you go to any CSS gallery your
littered with websites that are
responsive based entirely on its width I
mean even media queries media query I es
peptides that are responsive almost
entirely based on their width so to kind
of reiterate what a media query is this
this is what we all typically do what we
see on the CSS galleries are we running
a media query and we're testing against
a width size the max with or men with a
vertical media query does the
perpendicular I'm just checking against
the hike hence the name and brace the
vertical so what why does it matter it's
that's a good question because I mean if
you look we what we all in this room
have done some amazing things using the
width as our primary condition but I
don't think that's good enough I think
there's opportunities for us do some
really cool things with our layout based
on height so one of the reasons that I
don't think the width is good enough and
while height is important is one because
content size is variable not intrinsic
and by content I mean words not images
because of course if we sell I image to
be one percent with and we make our with
more narrow the image gets smaller our
content our words
don't scale I we make our with scenario
and the content gets solar another
reason is that we increase the scrolling
which isn't a bad thing because the fold
doesn't exist but it is an opportunity
for us to improve upon the users
scrolling experience another reason is
device fragmentation and by device I
mean any electronic or mechanical device
that we use to consume web content so
not just handheld tablets but also the
laptops and eventual TVs that we will
peruse the internet with and a shameless
plug for my wife who is a rabid fan of
Wizard of Oz netbooks apples and
androids oh my these are the devices
that we're talking about not just the
handheld stuff that's in our pocket
right now also the laptops that or a
desk and yeah so question who here
remembers this I think it actually
originally was posted around 2010 but
they did a another article in 2013 to
discuss device fragmentation when this
came out I mean there was blog posts
left and right about how responsive web
design was destined to fail because it
was just too many variables if to me it
felt like responses fear-mongering it
wasn't like we could just go out and
settle the break the breakpoints so I
always hated that grab because it was it
was overwhelming you couldn't you
couldn't really grasp what needed to
happen what I like better was this
graphic from the same article which kind
of does a better job of explaining what
we do because it shows the list amount
of widths that we all have to deal with
doing responsive web your time but even
this only tells half the story which is
why this graphic is actually my favorite
because it shows that the height is just
as variable as the width I throw these
devices move from both directions and it
doesn't even account for the fact that
we can change the orientation of our
advices
which then makes art with our height and
our height width well my last reasons
why this is important is because squishy
is not good enough unless we're talking
dodgeball because I've watched my kids
play and doesn't matter how soft the
ball is so to quote myself and take a
drink of water delicious squishy is a
legacy solution but it is also the
foundation of responsive web design
basically show of hands who here has
ever done this not in an email so this
is old-school I mean I'm glad there was
a lot of hands because that means I'm
not the only old one here even though I
have less hair than most people this
this is what we all used to do to make
fluid websites this was what we did
before responsive web design was a thing
this is pre wide UK pre squishy this is
when tables were in and in this the same
premise of just filling your your your
browser's with is all that responsive
web design kind of relies on its core
tool and that's why we're here to this
side with a sky with his accordion which
is supposed to be a metaphor for how
websites like an accordion or squishy
horizontally even though you could hold
your accordion this way them still work
but anyway I wanted to keep in there
because he looks awesome and he's happy
anyway my point is that you can only be
squishy in one direction or reliably in
one direction and that's along the wit
so what do we do with that being our
limitation we actually can't be
responsive instead we have to adapt or
die trying I'm going to paraphrase
actually not perfect we want to
repurpose a quote from Karen McGrane for
a list of parts responsive web design I
won't fix your content problem where she
said smart organizations will see this
as a benefit not a drawback and we use
this
to make a better website not just a
squishy one she wasn't talking about
vertical media queries or going back to
adaptive design but the sentiment is
true here so again I want to go back and
then redefine get again what exactly a
vertical media query is a vertical media
query is not a responsive tool it is
actually an adaptive solution to our
content design and user experience
problems so now on to the meat and
potatoes of my talk why everyone is here
hopefully is to see some potentially
cool coat and this would be the fun part
this part I haven't practiced so much so
here we go so first up I wanted to kind
of investigate a an existing site an
existing opportunity for vertical media
queries and I wanted to make sure I
picked a website where the developers
who involved in it won't hate me so I
picked Wikipedia so the use cases
long-form reading the solutions that
Wikipedia actually do themselves can be
used on blogs articles research papers
it's not unique to Wikipedia anything
that has a lot of content this approach
that they do to their to the layouts we
all can adapt in some way for our own
purposes so I needed an article to use
as my example and since we have a party
tonight I figured I'm going to use my
drink of choice which was bourbon and
yeah finally tonight if I make it
through this talk so I search for
bourbon whiskey and the Wikipedia
article looks something like that when
you scroll it on your desktop yep yeah
ok now we're finished that was fast we
didn't read anything so imagine trying
to experience that on your mobile device
luckily we don't have to because
Wikipedia zone Mobile Pay
says users of supported mobile devices
automatically redirected to the official
mobile version of Wikipedia com which
looks like a much more pleasing and
consumable that when I when I inspected
the V iOS simulator I realized two
things one the markup was ridiculously
simple and simple enough that it could
actually serve desktop but instead they
give us two entirely different code
bases two entirely different URLs and
they redirect so I wanted to compare the
mobile versus desktop solution or UI and
essentially all they did was they
simplify the navigation they use an
accordion layout they Center their
images and they change the font to it
more readable serif all those things we
can do without our separate URL in a
separate code base so what I want to do
is build a prototype very bare-bones
kind of showcasing a use case for
vertical media queries but what I'm
going to do is not worry about the
simplified navigation because oh that's
just too much backward for day so here
we go so what we have here is very
dumbed down version of the Wikipedia
mobile HTML which is basically a div
with an ID content we've got an h1 for
our article title they've put all their
images inside of class thumb got an
introductory text and h2s Aria roles
that match the ID of the sibling div and
that's where their content is I don't
want to deal with that so I converted to
something a little more readable yay for
semantics and we with an article keeping
the h1 we're using figures instead of
divs we got the introductory text we
have an ID on our h2 and we're using
sessions for the content separation
instead of dips
and if anyone wants to actually follow
along from this point to see the more
fleshed out stylized prototype just bit
ly / wiki proto you all five seconds to
not do that and never going to just go
to some base CSS to kind of get us there
so first thing I did was again this is
kind of roughly based on the actual
existing Wikipedia com I just set a font
font weight font size line height
sans-serif font we're going to put a
border under our h2s and we're going to
flow to our figures to the right and
center of the text there's more in the
actual code example in that URL that you
can mess around with but basically what
we end up getting is a very Wikipedia
light layout this is essentially
Wikipedia I mean with links and more
images and really robust navigation so
this works now I'm going to go and throw
in some some media queries so the first
thing we do is I'm going to go with an
actual traditional with base media query
first that will essentially just tell
our figure to be full width and we
already have our content centered so if
you're on a device that's six hundred
fifty pixels small small or a browser
that is six hundred and fifty percent
power pixels wide it will Center your
figure elements and then we're going to
use a vertical media query and all we're
really doing is font family serif and
hiding all the sections and mind you
this display none is exactly what
Wikipedia is doing there's no animations
there's there's no nothing there just
toggling display non-display bak on
their div and it turns this into this
again if you check out the the URL
you'll see it's that I only do anything
else there's no redirect there's no
nothing so you throw in some some some
image loading love
slick nav and maybe actual images you
you would potentially render the mobile
version of Wikipedia calm unnecessary so
the benefits of an adaptive
wikipedia.com were adaptive anything
really comes down to you don't have to
worry about device detection which has
its own woes you work with a single code
base and since all of us in here write
code for us coach right the better right
and you get improved SEO and share
ability and it's great so Wikipedia calm
that's my first example my next example
is VW calm so much for picking sites
that people will be mad at me but this
is actually a internal project as well
so I think it warrants a little
backstory so VW con was recently
redesigned and this is their their nav
we did not design it we didn't build it
or anything like that and this this
fixed nav on the left they absolutely
love they met all the requirements of
the of the clients the UX everything
work you click more and you got the
navigation of slide out off the screen
this is not a mobile or tablet approach
this is just desktop and they liked it
so much that when they came to us for
the properties that we are responsible
for they wanted to reuse that exact same
nav except it had entirely different
requirements and those requirements just
don't work with what was designed and
approved so those new requirements were
primary navigation must support up to
six items and if we actually go back was
too fast ninja
there we go so this is actually full
screen on my 15-inch macbook pro I've
got enough room for two more items there
but if a mouth full screen don't have
room for two items and if I have my my
doc expose might have room for one more
item and if i'm on a 13-inch macbook pro
I don't have any more room for anything
so we're talking a desktop experience
that needs to be adaptive the second
requirement was that the secondary
navigation which is what you will see
when you click on more I needed to be
able to support an unlimited number of
items which means you can scroll within
it means the navigation can have 10
items and it can have 100 that's a whole
nother design problem but the third
reason and this is actually something
that i added to the requirements because
i used to do front-end development for a
government so i like to try to make sure
things are as accessible as possible I
wanted everything to be keyboard
accessible didn't want to have to rely
on JavaScript to to build out my UI or
to access content so this is what the
navigation on their current site looks
like when you when it's fully exposed
we've got the four primary navigation
which you'll see on the right and we've
got the list of secondary navigation
which is on the left and again if you
want to follow along from this point
with my own prototype please go to bit
ly / sticky nav I'm really surprised
that wasn't taken already people are
lazy so again bare-bones HTML this is
what I started off with nav element on
order list I chosen to keep my li for
the logo inside the the list instead of
using a separate header and then all the
additional navigation items are marked
up white so we're going to Li link an
image for the icon
and the link text within a span now we
can handle that image the whole tons of
different ways but from my prototype
that's the way I want with it that's the
way it is and like said there can be a
hundred of those if you want and now for
my disclaimer my following slides of
code are using less not sass because I
bet on the dark horse so anyone in here
with me oh and some of your lying you're
lying lying lying lying alright so first
thing I did was kind of easily themify
this created a theme variable just so i
can save colors and funny to meddle with
them later for hover states and things
like that the next thing i did was i set
a font size and you'll see that these
ian values go ridiculously long at a
point but i'm going to put the pixel
value affairs and comments you know
we're working with but essentially it
comes down to our nav based font sizes
11 pixels each individual nav item is 95
pixels by 95 that is a design
requirement which also makes the the
button potentially fragile if the the
text get gets too long and then the
exception to our primary nav size is
that the logo height has to have its own
so I put that in a variable I think we
set the drawer with which is the NAB
that sits outside of your view to 21
point 36 36 36 or 235 pixels and the two
magic numbers at the bottom which is
which are my favorite because this
actually allows this prototype to be
really flexible since this NAB has to
exist on multiple sites with multiple
requirements one site might say we only
want for nav items one site might say we
want to have ten so at any point you can
just change that that highlight number
or even the minimum number and enforce a
new set of rules on that nav so up next
we have the nav based styles this is why
I gave up writing notes on
gonna try to run through each a line of
CSS quickly but we're going to transform
the beam ave I'm going to move it to the
left so that the drawer nav the
secondary nav is out of view when a
position it fix to the top I'm going to
set the width and some typography
choices here so it kind of matched what
was on VW calm then saw the actual
individual navs the images in the spans
within them so I just go ahead and put
the padding's on there I've got some
text treatments another transition and
we're going to position our our imaging
spans to be in line so this is that
secondary nav with the the text is not a
perfect square it's actually kind of a
stack stack nav single line and the CSS
for the UL itself we set our width we
wanted to scroll that way it can grow
forever can just scroll within that side
pane and I chose to use CSS content to
actually style the separator between the
secondary nav in the primary and all
that pretty much just gives us this this
is our default navigation that appears
off-screen so that is our native state
with no other work done that is all we
end up well with and now for we're a
little adjustment to our variables for
minimum number and highlight number in
this incidence since I kept the logo in
the nav when we're counting how many nad
the limits we want to have have to add
one to account for the logo that's just
deeper into the CSS no one should be
meddling with that it's kind of like
part of the framework in a way so next
we had to create a outfits on that good
yeah I had to create a mixin that
basically was stylized this native nav
to look like a primary square and a
vital and I did so by using display
table which is our new old friend
we position it absolute and we're going
to position it off to the right notice
I'm not setting its top position because
we're going to automate that later and
then I tell the individual links to
display table cell vertical align them
in the middle and then just set the
padding and size on them and now I'm
telling my image to be displayed block
so everything looks like that when it
gets it's the highlight mixer and apply
to it so now we actually have to worry
about how to position everything since
we're taking a whole bunch of stack
navigation items on the left and
positioning absolute on the right and we
want to do that in a way that's not
fragile so I wrote a two mix-ins that
will basically do all work for me one is
called position nav yay for readability
that essentially just counts the number
of items that we want to be primary and
calculates how far from the top they
should be which is easy to do because we
already know how tall enough height is
the logo height is how tall each
individual nav item is so when we apply
that say position six items we get a top
position for all six they know exactly
where they need to be nice and the mix
in itself does all the work for us and
the less is a mixin to position the more
button because the more button now needs
to know where all the nav items above it
are and how many nav items are actually
visible so now this is just kind of like
a base well not really based this is
kind of a CSS to kind of kick start
everything so we're going to take our
first ally that we know is our logo
we're going to set the height on it
we're going to call the mixin highlight
so we're telling it to be 95 pixels wide
to go absolutes go to the right and our
exception here is that we're telling it
how tall it needs to be and then the
other exception is that the image
actually needs to fill the container
not be this tiny little icon and the
next line is based on our minimum offset
we need to make sure we stylized the
minimum amount of primary a map items
that we want in this case it's three
that's what gets passed to the mixin so
we tell the first three nav items after
the logo to be stylized and move to the
right and now we kick start the position
magic where we're saying all right as of
the second one start positioning all the
nav items and now for the fun part where
I had to pull back my little school math
and reverse engineer the a.m value for
for the body essentially I'm just trying
to get back to the root am I don't know
how I walk through this but it's in
there so I figured I should show it but
I'm essentially just figuring out the
first fraction for how much how tall the
nav is accounting for all the items that
you want to show and putting that
against the font size and then giving me
the e/m back to what our body is instead
of the actual nav the nav thinks
everything is based off of 11px but my
media query is going to be based off of
the body which is typically the browser
default of 16 pixels and then in that
same media query we are going to at this
point decide when there's no longer
enough room for the nav items to remove
them from the primary section and let
them go back into their the native
position off the screen and essentially
I'm just saying you know using an inch
child saying show the first four if
there's no space so the first five
there's enough space and in order to do
that I'm actually counting backwards in
my ad media query instead of a typically
adding one and another thing worth
noting is that I actually had to
position the more button based on a max
hi
and we're doing the opposite for the
individual primary items where we're
doing it on a minimum height so if
there's at least this one enough room
before show for if there's enough room
five show five and here is video that I
think will plays with showing then have
an action so yeah that's that's my best
use case actually for for for vertical
media whores right now and as you saw
it's not a responsive solution it's not
squishy we were originally going to go
with a squishy solution because it's the
easy solution in this instance we could
just make the more button fixed to the
bottom and then tell the client that no
it's really cool actually you can scroll
with in this 95 pixel wide container
which would have worked but the
experience wouldn't have been great so
now instead we have a perfectly flexible
component that can live on any VW
property based on a really simple set of
rules and it's my best use case right
there so what else can we do just some
ideas because really what I wanted to do
in this talk is kind of motivate other
people to start thinking about height
it's easy to overlook it let's stop so
other options are single page
navigations galleries you know you have
captions that sit on top of your image
based on your screen size you might not
have room for that text anymore what are
you going to do with it you just hide it
and say oh no you know mobile no one
wants to read the caption no we could
probably do some really interesting
things figure it out scrolling sites and
and takeovers those kind page
interstitial
or messages that are very subject to
limited height because typically we
design them to hold 100 words and the
client puts in a thousand so that's that
that's that's my argument for vertical
media queries and I don't know how long
that was hoping it was like 20 of 20
minutes so I thought and I said thank
you