good afternoon talking a little css grids for those who do not know
is a new layout is a new way to organize the page is something that
It is still quite green but you will see that it has a potential
huge and it's good I am fascinated by the truth it's very very good
start first ariel I'm an energy developer I'm
working almost five years ago
I went through quite a few companies before that
this go through many of the things that all of us went through at the time of
fight with the code this work with flash as many of you will have
also worked this pass through the tables as many others will also have
past and then good came the new way to build dips sites with
css this which makes things a little easier for us and now something better is coming the future
I hope this is the future because the truth is that it is very good that
are the villas
so as we make a grid let's think about it first we can say it is
a new way that allows us to define a structure where we have rows and
columns this item or we can choose what to put in each column in each row of
a very easy way now let's see
We have a normal grid, as many people will have experienced something as simple as that.
that we can hang this in many ways we can this
grab a match rubbing binds them left to right clicker
of the putter and well this is going to work like everywhere now you grid what
proposes is to think this differently we have several basic concepts that there are
to understand before starting to regret a little in the css
one of them is grit lines chris lines can or what we can see
exactly what are all the red lines marked
which are basically what makes up the grid are horizontal or vertical
on the other hand at we are seeing the numbered ones
there are six lines for the rows subject and four lines for the columns
on the other hand we have a grid track that would be the area between two
lines between two grid lines in this case there is this creature that contains the
content ya la side
grisel which is a unit the smallest unit that we can find within
the grids which is exactly all content that has that is between 4
games
and yell since it's basically the same thing as a network track only it can
contain several grip cels in this case we are talking about yelling and footer
now we will see later why
this this looks very closely related to a concept that we are going to see a
a little later
as we define a grid well following the example above in this
case we have 44 dips sandro a container
and we define for contaminating a new type of display that describes this what
going to do is all the direct children of that container will be
trying as a grid so far we have nothing we have the definition and the
elements are not yet positioned in that grid because we have to
say by css so here we have a couple of concepts
let's see if i can
in addition to display grid we have two properties
with template rose and template columns this is what we are going to say is the
definition of how many columns and how many rows will I have and what
size in this case what I'm defining for example is
the first road is going to be 200 pixels later it is going to have another 35 pixels another one of
420 another of 35 and finally one of 200 and for the columns there will be three
columns about 740 135 and another of 185 after there are basic properties
I'm basically centering the container at a width of 960 and
basic style properties for elements for the children of that
container something important we can use flex inside
of those containers this just using them to center
the elements on both the x-axis and the axis
we do see this we have the same values ​​that we define
in the css a column of 740 another of 35 that would be this space between the
content of the output and another of 800 185 the same for rows 235 420 35 and 200
we identify each grid with a number as we see here each greenline
why do we do this
that number will tell us where we want to position each element
we have these four properties that we will now see can be written
another way in principle we have scream to start grip volume scream rose start and
darling and basically robben what we're telling you
is i want you to start on the grid on line 1
as for the column and you end up at 4 I want it to start at row 1 and
i ended up in row 2 the same for the other elements in all defined
and if we see this example
huge
a company
very difficult
and complicated
I think I'm going to have to change the resolution
lets try
a moment things that happen
I don't know that he doesn't want to work
okay
to do something I'm going to do something very easy is
I have problems with the resolution
if you let me down
i'm going to change the resolution very easily that's the power
this time the display is perfect
is
and it's better
well I don't know if you see a lot but I hope much less you see
East
well we are
well after a little trying what good we have then
and as you can see the definitions and we have our
our perfectly armed shore
now
this same this same syntax we can write it also
we can say directly written alum and grid road where the first value is
the grid what would be the scream like and in the second value that would be the
I scream lumen and the same for each other
we separated them by a with a flash from Navarra
and it's a little bit easier way let's say we describe the same thing we can
do something else even a little bit more which for me is more complicated in
actually i would use this in general but hey you can directly define a
crit area where the syntax is grid rose start virtual long start grid
robben grip volume I really like more
this way because it seems a bit more understandable to me but hey this is another
way to define where our content goes
well so far what we saw is a grid in which we specify
Let's say the gap that would be the margin between each of the
elements and we had to specify it directly here in the grid row and the
cry of the 35 pixels refer to these 35 pixels and these 35 pixels thing
it's not that good because the truth could be better we could mean
Well, I have this gap and I just want to have the columns in this account
actual and actual rows without having to specify that margin good luckily
my life to the rescue but it's a Greek property in this
case this value is taking the 35 pixels for both the road and the
column but we could basically change it and
put a different gap for columns than for rows but this allows us
simplify this whole system a little bit and then now it's much more readable
we have three rows and two columns and we specify the gap with this
property
therefore our graph would be a little more simplified we would have to
basically tell that the second wickline would be this is
like the gap we are putting it directly the css
then we would have nothing more than 4 grit lines for those for the rows and 3 for
the columns
therefore our being is also changing a little bit but this basically
the same looks the same way
we may also like to use the word funk this will ring a bell if you ever
they will work with tables with span rose pan well this this syntax the levels
we are saying is I want you to start in column 1 and expand it over
the second is also the same as putting 1/3 is another way to describe it
in this case the future and the header as both are being exposed to more than
a column carry this key
I can also name each of those
and lines are set to 5 chetes it would be like
a parameter
this would be the name of the first of the first row has 200 pixels the name
of the second 420 the name the third and we give the final name to the row what
same for columns
then also in the css we can directly specify that name of
line instead of having to explain numerically
each of the rules and this added up is pretty good because it allows you
remember a little more you don't have to be fixing you what is the line that in
the one that I had to add well with these fairly descriptive names
we can specify in the same way and this code is going to
always be the same anyway you see this and it will continue to be exactly
same as it was before
missing the fruit that is a little wrong I think I missed
so have you put the align justify well
we can also do this specify the same name the same here for
columns and for the rows they all share the same let's say the
same
and what we specify directly is that name and the line number
then you can tell that ingrid row by
example I the only thing that is said specify is road because
if we go to the example again
in this case rose 1 start says that we are talking about the header is
saying I want it to start on the first line no I didn't have to specify
the second line because the algorithm understands that once you specify
the start is going to go yes or yes to the second line unless you
we specify that it goes further so in this case
we had to specify it but if not the soul understands in all cases with the
columns is just like it was going to take up to the up to the next line not what
we can specify nothing more with the first with the first call and nothing more
until now we have been seeing examples of an explicit grid in the
that we define in the css the size that the
columns and of the rows that happens if we add more elements have tips
extra added how are you going to see those tips good
let's see the example
I added 4 extra dips with more content
the grid algorithm what it does is it's going to try
apply the same the same definitions that we told ourselves in the
container to the other elements so how do you know they are two columns
I directly positioned them in the two columns and if I keep adding two I will
going to keep adding in the same way that's because the algorithm is
smart and knowing how to position the elements even when they are out of
explicit grid this would be just then we talk about and implicit which is
the grid outside the definition that we gave the css
now we have two more properties that we can
use that are grid auto rose and auto columns this property is what I
allow is to specify to the implicit grid what value I will have in
As for height, you have already used those new elements that are in the grid
implicit then in this case I'm telling you that all my rows that you create
that you think are outside that explicit grid have a value of 500
pixels and that all my columns have a value of 200 pixels
then it exists we see it is the same example
so our content has 500 pixels
and 200 pixels as we said here we can easily change this
and now our content has 100 because they are presented the same for
columns
We can also do something very interesting that esther bits are
which are grids inside the grid in this example that if you remove
inside maine which is our main content we have 3 sub contents
pretty simple
to those who in that same container I defined as a condition that will be
grid then all the elements are inside they will also be gray
ians in this case add a 10 pixel padding to separate it a little bit
of its container and a gray gap of 10 pixels for both columns and
rows and here we are introducing a new
concept that is this of fr that would be a fraction that is a fraction
I am saying that my columns are occupied
a fraction so there are two fractions of the fraction would be
the white space I have left in the container then I say I want you to
there are two blanks and this will calculate me
automatically if we see it
we have 3
let's see the properties so we understand how it is positioned by its
content 1 I said I want column 1 to go 3
that's why the funk is done until the end and in the others I put them both the
arrow 21 in the first or second column
the good thing about fraction is that it is an automatic calculation that is
pretty good pretty efficient and allows us to make laws the way
that we want this is very powerful so we will continue
another important concept which is I love the truth
are called yelling jazz is another way to define a grid we have this
grid template property arias that what we can do is define as a
sort of graphic representation we would have to do of how it is going to be
our grid so if you see it here we would have two columns the
first column has the header that is both in the first and the
second later in the left column we would have the content of the
across the side and the future also behaves like heather up to 100%
of the screen as we define then where each
good element we have this area grid property
basically I tell the header to put it in header
at least because they are not happy and the same for more
We see this and it will be exactly the same as the previous example, another way to
define a villa exactly the same
allows us to do things like it's not designed says the future in the end
we want it up and the axis of work lay down of the designers
well we do like this
we have football upstairs beautiful and the one I work and it's that easy to change
let's say this is so simple it allows us to do really cool things now
we will see another type of positioning
we can also define where the content goes according to its name now
we'll see
like we came here
we can use these kits that we define in complete ideas
when we select where we want our elements to go now we are going to
see
for example we have a law that we want to put on that grid that is on the outside
of anything else I say aside well I tell you know I want you to be in
the column where the content begins this is the quiz script start and script in
it would be to put me where is the content where do you think content and this
it is here that we define in grit temple tasks then I want this double and
this where content starts where the content ends and in the rows
I want it to be where heather starts and where he doesn't watch the content
if we see it
but it is a law that just begins in the header and ends in the
content against the rows and starts where the content begins in the
columns and ends the content that we define this we can
quietly change too
well i still want it to go into the future
and it goes to the future or anything we could well this
from the example of fasting
we can put what we want let's say answer with we have power to
whatever is possible and it's that easy we have to change the structure of the
free we are put it any anywhere total the css takes care
of all support
and we are this yesterday's description is complicated
there's a lot of red out there surprisingly internet explorer
supports it quite well which is a surprise for me for all the only thing
bad is that it has a slightly different syntax than what we are seeing now
in chrome and firefox this is actually red but good because it is supported
we have to enable it with a flyer to show how safari also
support well well we're still screwed this is a pretty aspect
fairly new that is still changing then well let's have
We have to adapt and wait a bit, but at some point we will be able to
use it as it is but as we inhabit it from firefox
well you don't see anything but we have to work in order and although I don't read anything
I think it is law to point c that is the gray point
and level and we have to do it between for chrome with flags
and we have to enable you to experiment it was captured by features because all
examples if they don't all look the same you don't see anything at all but well we can
and start using it to try things out if you want to do it
it's pretty good well this was all pretty examples
singles of what is gray gray with a fairly normal and expected law but what
happens with the real world well I found this site that I found
good enough to be able to enable it with grids because it has enough of the
things that we could recreate in this way if we see it
this is the stop site
simple
and if we see it on mobile
normal single column items to 100%
well I said well we could see how to recreate this in grids well
this is the sketch that tells me we can define on the one hand the grid lines
we have these three now I am going to tell you why in this example I don't use grid apps
and that is why we have a 28 pixel one above and another
18 pixels here this is something that is not contemplated in the green rose that
I proposed it in fact they did not give me a ball but to be able to specify different
grit rose grit rose gaps with a different gaps
pixel sizes in this case I had to do it because they were different
or put them both at 28 at 18 pixel speed the old way we saw
previously contained and the last green line
and at stop here we do have a gap of 50 pixels
they are oops the 50 pixels both for the columns compare the rose then
we can use grid up and we have the gdr the banner
content left and content right
let's see a little how is this
this is the hug the truth yes quite ugly because we are in this but let's say
that this is the last example I don't know if
let's look
well then there we define imagine this on mobile because this would be read
for mobile we define a container that is grid
we follow our rows and columns there is the auto value that explains to us that
it would be good to explain what it is basically we define a row in the
we don't know how much the content is going to be, so we say
auto that contained the height of the development height is going to be the height of your
content after we have 28 grid pixels that
up to this gap is another car that would be all of
the articles with the articles 18 gap pixels and another car to make
a short list of articles
I also tell you that the columns - 100% therefore takes me 100% of the
screen
and then basically what I did is position each element of the container
that would be this red they were going to the container both are in the one of chris
lowe one as we said this we can also ignore it
and it will look the same
and then we have the content that is on road 3 and ends on 4
and the content 2 that is in the network 5 and also 6 a little bit of an English father
that he had and nothing else we already have the half armed
for when we want to see the layout of this
if we see this example
we have the is quite similar to what the live site is
we are in mobile we go to the mean and stop
we define a max wheat and center it at 1,064 which gives the size that it was set
in the real site and we define on the one hand the rows that are going to be automatic in
both cases the two rows because because our content we do not know if it will
having more than one item can have one can have four by having twenty
so we want it to be automatic where we define a fixed height
and we can also define in this case how we saw the columns in
percentages we have 40 percent for the first column and 60% for the
second we position the elements
and we have something more interesting in the content
content 1 and content are néstor grids each of them
therefore all your children are going to be bought like grids
In the case of the content in stop, what we define is a gap of 10 pixels
that we love each other here
we took out the father in which we had a dance and we put the columns
they are we have them at 50% each one therefore this one looks like this we could
change it calmly we could put 30 and 70 so if
we make
and we would have a little bit different data if we wanted to do it
so well this is a real example of how we could implement it in the
moment there is support we are still
we are difficult in this matter but well I wanted to give you an explanation
pretty quick how it works it seems to me it's it's something that has a lot
potential and in a few years when it is really alive and can be used we will
solve life a little bit everyone you can download this talk by miguel
house also pdf and all the examples we saw are in me
I for unha if they also want to follow me on twitter sometimes I write things