good afternoon and welcome to making a
jack sexy if you get tired of listening
to me and just feel like being geeky you
can just go right to the source and just
skip ahead to the good parts adds up on
github if you'd like to read some
hastily scribe documentation you can
also check out my website sexy J s calm
but I have to warn you that it's it's
actually been deemed too risque for the
workplace by this guy who was very
direct in his opinion and it's
unfortunate because I think there's one
less user you know that I've reached but
if you think it's not safe for work but
you'd still like to try it I've created
another version for you I just passed
that along and you can have a netscape
navigator for experience but at least
it's compatible and compliant okay let
me just look through my notes here okay
yeah ah alright so some of you might
remember me from Jas humph oh wait this
is all I didn't realize I have to all
right well you can't see it but that's
my name down there um there you go i
wonder what else you've missed so far
yes i well yes that was me um so I had a
great time listening didn't speak
because I slept through it no I'm a UI
engineer for Major League Baseball a
long time JavaScript er long-form
improviser and all-around nice guy i'm
known as firth here and all around the
internets I've come to you today about
your data your never-ending lust your
insatiable taste for data and
asynchronous data and some sequential a
jack patterns that you can use for
loading and combining your data as well
as a little library rope called sexy
which makes it pretty
by a show of hands how many people here
have ever worked on an application that
uses Ajax and how many of you have built
a page that made more than one request
and how many of you have wanted the two
data data points to you know to you know
interact meaningfully okay anyone else
can leave this is about being able to
combine data from different points well
that's where the story starts and it
turns out that there's a little more to
sexy but we will wander down the garden
path in a moment you know so as we start
integrating more and more data sources
we want our code to you know be
maintainable logical for me I Major
League Baseball I just finished working
on the new scoreboard page which
requires about five different data loads
from different services so before
rendering every single thing I wanted to
unite the data beforehand but I didn't
want to wait you know for a chain series
of events I needed this to happen fast
and this is where the idea came from
sequential Ajax allows you to make
parallel requests and handle the
callbacks in sequence and sexy makes
sequential Ajax sexy so sequoias button
fell sequential Ajax just refers to any
Ajax pattern designed to handle multiple
requests while maintaining a proper
callback execution order the goals of
cilantro Ajax are basically to
facilitate the combination of
manipulation make it easy for you to put
these pieces a day together to find some
performance enhancement by using
parallel asynchronous requests to speed
the execution of the callbacks as data
comes back if all previous dependencies
are there go ahead and fire if they
haven't wait and when they get there
fire and I think it should be fun
because I think programming is a lot of
fun and I love JavaScript and I hate
when my code gets uncomfortable where I
feel like I'm really cool
doing something in so sexy has helped
helped make my job a lot easier and more
fun plus I get to respond to people on
Twitter as you saw before so it's
basically three types of sequential ajax
at least that I've you know discerned
there's cereal requests cereal response
which waits to send a request once it
receives the response from the previous
call there's parallel requests random
response where you send out the calls
all at the same time and then use some
sort of counter or other tracking
variables to determine when all your
date has arrived and then merge it in
some common call back and then parallel
requests your response which is what
sexy is which lets you fire everything
at once and then handle it in order no
matter what order they come back so in a
perfect world let's say we want to fire
off three requests the server goes out
does its thing those would be nice if
they spun to indicate movement but I
think you get the picture that this data
is going out and coming back it's really
nice when it comes back in order and it
can share data with itself but in a
world where time waits for no man or his
day job we fire at our three requests
again something happened at response a
it slowed down B gets there first well
those callbacks wait until they're
triggered by the event of the success of
a so let's look at some sequential ajax
anti-patterns maybe if you see something
familiar here you'll want to stick
around till the end here we are using
jquery if anyone's unfamiliar with
jquery i don't know look it up real
quick but yeah yeah actually yeah feel
free to just ask questions right now but
basically each one of these lines up
here is adjacent requests so you can see
in the top line we're requesting an
article in the second where requests in
the comments now this is sitting inside
of the callback so it has to wait for
the article to return before we can go
ahead and request the comments we then
bind the comments to the article and go
ahead and render it
the page the problem with this is while
it's relatively readable it's slower we
have to wait request response request
response and nested calls don't
necessarily scale at least not visually
I mean you end up with code that looks
like Charlie Brown on his back okay is
this exact so the second anti-pattern is
parallel request random response this
pattern is quicker these calls though
maybe not immediately obvious are
getting fired at the same time then
they're using a counter they're storing
their data when they return and using a
counter and when that counter I gets to
to it knows that it's finished with the
number of requests and it can handle its
send its command callback now a problem
with scaling this up is that you have
tix you know you have to keep storage
variables you have to keep you know any
time you had a call you gotta remember
go up change your variable and it just
sort of ends up being a little bit
crusty and long you know I like code
that's as small as possible does what i
want and is you know easy to update and
maintain so if either one of these
patterns look familiar meet sexy sexy is
a jaya well it started as a jquery
plugin it's a parallel request serial
response library so we're making the
request in parallel for speed and
wrapping and eventing your specified
callbacks so that we can put them back
in order and sexy ensures callbacks in
order every time well as of my version
my arbitrary version 0.0 point that
means zero point 8.0 sexies now stand
alone sort of thanks to open source and
John I've extracted the jquery ajax code
and put it in as an adapter so it's if
you look into the code you'll see that
it's in its own closure and it gets
passed in as a variable to sexies
closure as an adapter the point of doing
this was to make my own code easier to
maintain every
I'm there's a change to jQuery i can
update that any time I have a changed my
code I can update that and if anyone
wants to port this to another library
it's easy to write an adapter for it so
sexy is classy calling new sexy creates
a sexy instance to which you can go
ahead and start chaining your calls but
with a name like sexy which by the way
wasn't out of any sense of ego it
actually was it just another version of
short and sequential Ajax but after a
while I did think that this library had
to be sexy to keep up with its name so i
decided that new was old and that sexy
is the new sexy so sexy with currents
also creates its own instance you no
longer need the new call of the new
keyword to start your chain and this is
an instance this is an object here it's
not actually working off as some sexy
singleton and for anyone who wants under
the hood all we're doing inside of the
constructor we're checking when when the
function is called we're checking the
instance of this if this is sexy then it
was used with a new keyword if it wasn't
it was called without a new keyword we
just take the arguments and fight you
know we instantiate and just sort of
wrap it back around so the code will
stop here and then come back through
saving us a few characters and really it
was just for fun but I didn't think that
was sexy enough where am I going here Oh
up is the new down and down is in a well
there we go so this will also create a
sexy instance I decided that most of the
time I didn't need to put anything in
those parentheses so they just made my
code look big and so I decided to do
away with them this creates an instance
as well and we do this just by iterating
the prototypal methods and creating
static functions on the constructor
which will apply the desired prototype
method in the scope of a new instance
since it's a chainable api it's always
returning an instance so after you make
that first call what you have back is
your new object
alright so let's take a look at sexies
API sexy was designed to be expressive
and chainable so that the code looks
like what the code does there's a method
for each supported data type these types
reflect jQuery the jQuery roots with the
exception of the style method which I
added later for the sake of some sort of
completeness because I found that I was
using sexy to bootstrap apps by loading
in scripts and then data and i was using
text to load a templating engine or a
template that would get parsed by a
template engine i figured all right why
don't I just put my CSS in there it
takes two to three callbacks as you see
takes mean arguments there's a URL and a
call back with an optional defer in the
middle defer will force that call to
perform the way our first example did as
a serial request serial response this is
going to allow you to handle things like
server authentication if you need to set
a cookie before you start hitting an API
or if you need an API key or another
benefit if you want to change the
configuration of the next call if
there's something that's going to be
dependent on your previous call you call
you tell defer and then in the callback
I'll show you how we can manipulate that
next call it also takes a jquery
settings object because of the jquery
routes so you can refer to jake where's
documentation for that there's an
additional defer property so that you
can use the long form and still stop
your call the callbacks are just
slightly different from jQuery AJAX call
backs which return data and status
instead what we get our data which is
the response data of the current request
we get previous which is the return
value of the previous call back we get
next which is the Ajax settings of the
next request and then we get the status
which hopefully in your case is always
success so let's look at what a sexy
sequential Ajax pattern look
like here we can see that we're changing
to calls these calls like the like the
other example are being fired in
parallel right away and then the
callbacks are executed in the specified
order this example is using the verbose
syntax using full on configuration
objects these would be what you would
use if you want to post or if you need
to add errors or before send where we
add here oh this radio shows you how the
the value is being passed so when the
data comes back in the first one we have
the article we're just going to take
that data and we're going to return it
the wrapped callback knows that when it
fires this one to pass it in as a second
argument now we can just add comments to
the article and go ahead and render it
but big configuration objects aren't
sexy so we use the brief syntax you see
that we're still passing the article and
getting things done but if I'm willing
to get rid of two parentheses I think
I'm also willing to get rid of a
function that is probably going to be
used ninety percent of the time to pass
you know most of the time you're going
to use this it'll just be to marry two
things and so why not just throw in an
implicit call back so that the data just
appears we don't need to write out that
additional function there's another type
of implicit callback which is a pass
through call back so if you throw either
a jas or a CSS call in between odds are
we have no interest in manipulating
those data we're just going to put them
in the page and execute them so we pass
through whatever the last return value
was before it you could throw as many
Java scripts or style sheets right in
the middle there and that second
argument would still be article I don't
really recommend that because it's not
really readable I think it's better to
put your two things together but if you
had to it's available to you here's an
example using defer this this example
actually was inspired by something maroc
doing with hokey oh he's using sexy as a
test runner
so he wanted to be able to authenticate
request modify and post back so in the
first call we are authenticating you
could use this either with a cookie
based session or if you needed an API
key back because if you had an API key
you could just send that through into
previous and your next call would be
able to make an authenticated request
the second call you can see we deferred
we waited we called true we went we got
the article we modified the article and
then what we did by deferring the third
call which is going to post the article
back here in the second we can set the
article to the data of that call and now
this third call is now armed and
dangerous and ready to update your
article and for for sake of completion
we log out when we're done because of
the parallel loading sequential response
and the way that both jquery and sexy
use use text loading of scripts and then
Dom injection we're actually able to go
ahead and queue up script dependencies
so anything you see here will load after
the thing before it so jQuery UI doesn't
have to worry that jQuery won't be there
and the template doesn't have to worry
and as you can see all my pseudo MLB
libraries they'll load just fine as soon
as they're written so let's let's see
what a sexy makeover looks like we can
remember our original parallel response
parallel request random response that
now is reduced to this making the code
tidy and readable and I don't know sexy
I like it sexy also has a few additional
methods it has a setup method that
allows you to configure subsequent
request of a sexy instance this behaves
just like Ajax set up in jQuery only
when you do it it's not global it's only
two subsequent requests in your current
sexy chain at at any point you can go
ahead and
set them with an empty or faulty value
to set up something like this for our
article we may want to show a loading
indicator and then hide it when it's
complete but we may not care so much
when we display the comments so we can
just zero that out you can also pass
that right through to the constructor
because anywhere i can drop keystrokes i
do saving yourself some time sexy also
provides a sort of client-side
JavaScript packaging tool called sexy
bundle bundle makes multiple requests
and a single Dom insertion and then
executes an optional call back because
of the way sexy is designed the script
sequence and therefore your dependencies
are preserved so that long chain of
script loads can be reduced to this I
guess we didn't really save much but I
mean I'm nickel-and-diming over
parenthesis so I do what I can hear now
I'd like to introduce you to what has
become so far my kamasutra of sexy this
example just came up the other day at
Major League Baseball where we had to
implement in a hurry a new scoreboard
for minor leagues only the only problem
was that the data about the games that
were being played was stored in a
separate place from the data about the
games each game required a different
data file so came up with this idea and
here's an example of bootstrapping a nap
and then really playing with sexy so
this time what's different is up at the
top we are storing our sexy instance as
s which we'll come back later
foreshadowing we're going to load in
jQuery we load in a templating agent a
templating document will also load in a
style sheet and we will load in the
template now all right this is a basic
simple friends this isn't our scoreboard
because that had a little more code this
Jason that it would bring back is sort
of like a manifest it might bring back
an array of friends with just their
their user names and ID's so from there
we have to go and get the rest of the
information
so what we do is we iterate those
friends and for each friend we make a
request so what we're doing is we're
actually adding these new calls to that
original chain so these are all going to
fire as fast as this loop can iterate
all the requests go out when it comes
back we're going to push the incoming
friend onto a stack and then wait a
minute there's no stack well one of the
nice things was that we added this to
this chain so I did was create the stack
down here and we pass that empty array
up there so the first time it comes in
we have our array we push our friend we
loop through this while while we are
less than the final friend and every
time we augment that array and push it
back up onto the stack so our friends
array just grows as our responses come
back in and when we're done we shove it
into a template and put it on the page
so there are some known issues but
they're not come they're not unique to
sexy you know right now as far as I know
there's not too many or if any Kyle may
be able to correct me in some of these
with some of the stuff he's doing in lab
j yes detection of errors for remote
requests using JSONP script or style
which is loading a remote stylesheet
probably the more severe problem that
I've introduced is that loading a style
from a remote URL will fire the success
callback even if the request was an
error but the good news is most of the
time you don't need to do something
right after your stylesheet so just kind
of avoid that for now I prom you know
might say I should wait until the
library is complete but I say you know
if I put it out there and everyone can
see the bug maybe someone has the fix so
now we've just witnessed parallel
request serial response the pros it's
faster cleaner prettier I think it's
easier to maintain the API is chainable
and expressive you can look at the code
know what it's doing when it's doing it
and the only drawback is that depending
whether or not you're using it as a
plug-in or a standalone it's going to
add about
and a half or four and a half K of code
to your core library if you're using the
standalone odds are you're using it to
bootstrap so it could potentially be the
only script on your page when you load
all right if anyone has any questions
you have a question song do you have any
kind of a case like a request is taking
too long or something like that to do
something built into jQuery ok so it's
using hope for like JSON key which
doesn't have a timeout and whose fault
is that oh yeah i'm yeah i know i'm just
standing on the on the on the shoulders
of jquery yeah i haven't added any in
fact the most meaningful of code that
i've added probably if it needed to be
if i wanted to i could have just taken
out what i've done instead of having a
separate library and in like maybe six
to ten lines added it directly to Jake
worry there's really not much going on
i'm wrapping functions um you know
creating events but the sexy librarian
doesn't do much it just helps I do it
one follow-up question sure do you have
any shorthand or anything so if if a
particular request fails for some reason
to me do that request that exact same
requester do you have to actually in
your error call back like take dupe s
dot and add that one back onto it right
so this is still an earlier version so
my arbitrary 0.8 should probably do more
like 0.5 or four or three or two or one
I've done various things and pulled them
out and put them back and pulled them
out now that I do have a couple people
using it I probably have to be a little
more stable but yes there was at one
point cascading error handling that
would notify everything down the chain
there wasn't something that would
actually send backup to the same request
but in one incarnation I had the ability
to inject back into the chain so
essentially what we would need to do is
inject into the chain and then set the
pointer back
so I could add let's say another another
argument to the callback being this that
would give you access to everything in
the sexy chain and then add some
functions you know previous next to jump
around not currently there but if people
use this and like it I am more than
happy to add whatever people like Kyle
yes so give your list of a bunch of
scripts and obviously a bunch of those
with local scripts you're using XA
charged to lopat string mm-hmm you're
running all in parallel executables
really what if one of those in the
middle is a remote script okay so sexy
it has to you know in order to ensure
that everything else is there it has to
wait because in order to put a remote
script on I'm using just adding a script
node and giving it a source so it's
actually injecting right then and there
what sexy does is if there is a defer
anywhere in the chain but everything
else is free form you know like
everything else is ready to go parallel
the second that one that was deferred
comes back those will all immediately
fire again so as its as its iterating
through or as you're adding things to
the chain it will either if it's the
first thing immediately send otherwise
if there it has been something that's
deferred it will essentially subscribe
to the to the send of the last deferred
item so they'll bill all bill all fire
off in a hurry right after that remote
script loads so just by point of
comparison that's where livejasmin
kippur live Jace is still going to load
everything girl
but that's trade-offs that yours yeah
well I think there's definitely I mean
we've talked about this on and off over
the past year there's plenty I think
that I could you know leverage from
digging into your code and yeah so I
look forward to you know after this now
that the stress is done i can go relax
and i can actually pick your brain with
a clear conscience anyone else have any
questions all right well thank you very