hi everyone welcome to a je s convent
rack be I'm Kevin and today I'd like to
share with you my struggle with
something called impostor syndrome and
offer some hacks that you may be able to
use if you have the same struggle I am a
software developer and I work remote
from my home office for the company
called Koopa we're hiring JavaScript
developers of all levels find me if you
are interested in learning more so
working remotely I get to spend a lot of
time with my family and as you can see
I'm a dad I love being a dad there are a
lot of you know struggles I had at first
with being a dad gosh I've never been it
I've never you know dogs cats right but
another human am I going to be able to
do that take care of that like I said
this is Jackson um he's the one without
the beard and he loves Christmas and all
the decorations and you know as a dad I
want to want to do the right thing I
want to you know set him up for success
I wanted him to see me very successful
earlier this week my wife asked me to
set up some yard decorations for
Christmas they happen to be of the
inflatable kind and if you've ever
worked with those I have a lot of you
know tethers usually to keep the wind
from blowing them from side to side and
away and not only did she ask me to do
that she asked me to do it during lunch
and I normally have like stuff right I'm
it's like I really want to do what I
want to do and and she said well you
know he would really love it if you did
it before he came home from school like
he goes to a mother's day out and there
was like 45 minutes left and so I'm like
oh gosh ok so there's you know it's a
deadline
and it's it's pressure because there's
expectations and you know I'm like oh
gosh so okay so I get the box and unpack
it and you know the inflatable part it's
pretty much one piece there's this ball
of light tethers and it's a ball and it
looks so like just nestled together
right and it's like oh yeah okay I can
just gently pull that apart and then
I've got four tethers and I can go on
with my day this is 10 minutes into it I
had a lot of thoughts going through this
and I'm like gosh you know I've got
stuff to do I I can't what if this is
take takes hours like I'm not a not
expert I mean good grief and why do we
even have inflatables and who cares if
it gets blown away right I i was able to
that's a poor picture but I was able to
get all four of them out and and then I
got to this moment success right you
know what success when you have an
inflatable 6-foot dachshund Santa in
your front yard right and got me to
thinking you know that golly man that's
the struggle i have with software i love
when i get the dachshund in the yard
right like I'd love that and you know
that's why I got into softwares I get
that feedback and you know solve
whatever it is and you know it's real
success and you know even more important
are like you know the project managers
and the bosses and the customers that
love that success my customer loved this
success you know as a dad I was like
yeah God you know this is awesome but
the journey to that was not as as rosy
as it should have been you see I'm an
expert I will stand here and tell you
I'm 100-percent expert I'm an expert at
eating I'm an expert at talking with my
hands and I'm an expert at believing
that I can without a full understanding
of a problem or possible solutions I
will go through a thought process where
I talked myself out of whatever sick
Tess I could have what's crazy is that
some cases I've solved in a million
times in other forms but i'll still try
to convince myself that I can't do it
there's too many challenges so why even
begin right so really yeah this is this
is a real thing and it's called imposter
syndrome with impostor syndrome you can
just simply feel inadequate when in
actuality you're perfectly qualified for
the task at hand it'll make you think
you're unable to go a single step
further it's literally doubt that will
just manifest itself in a lot of
different situations like to talk about
a few of those that relate to our
industry so we are knowledge workers a
hundred years ago it wasn't knowledge
work it was you know assembly lines and
now everything has changed in our
industry with software the pace has
absolutely changed in some cases we're
not able to keep up with everything
that's coming out with frameworks with
databases with networks with protocols
and on top of that newcomers are
constantly in fear what they don't know
right and even how to learn what's next
like you know they're not even thinking
about the the task at hand it's what's
happening what am I going to miss or
what do I don't know about what does
someone you know think of me there's
often thoughts of you know what if they
find out I don't know how to fix this
I've had that a thousand times over my
career and what if I can't fix this Wow
does that mean I'll lose my job
software is made up of a lot of basic
things computing numbers formatting text
communicating over networks these days
it's really complex we have a formal
separation these days of front end
versus back end and what's interesting
is that if you ask a back-end developer
to help out with something on the front
end you often get a lot of reluctance to
say hey you know I at CSS I don't know
about that but the whole time this guy
is maintaining or you know this person
is maintaining a ton of protocols and
databases and etc right and on the flip
side the front-end developers you know
there's this huge fear that they'll take
the site down you know and you're just
like hey can you just write this
function we're sales people if you don't
know that we have to sell ourselves on a
technology right and then we end up
having to sell each other on why this is
the right way to do it management it's
hard right you have to have to figure
out what what's the way to sell it right
and then there are all these thoughts of
what if what if something I suggest
doesn't work right is it is it me will
they blame me like is there actual blame
if this doesn't go the way they said it
was again will I get fired right I've
spent a career building software for a
lot of companies and every now and then
I'll have an idea something for me that
solves my own problem and I'm absolutely
the worst at implementing those I when
we were we moved about six years ago and
we're looking for houses and I couldn't
find a tool that helped me keep up with
the houses we'd seen online the houses
we had visited and we either liked or
disliked and then of course we had
family that was
always asking what about where what have
you seen what do you know all these just
inputs that are coming right and it's
like I can't keep up with that so let me
build a tool and I built this real
hackish tool that did some web scraping
and you know pulled images from an MLS
database but it gave like one page for
everyone to like see and the feedback
from family was awesome and I started
sharing it with friends and they're like
oh man you should totally build that
it's awesome I need that i can use an
apartment hunting it's awesome yeah it's
awesome it's all my need you know I
talked myself out of ever building that
before I would say before I've written
the first line of code but i have
several versions of this one version in
Perl another version in JavaScript you
know I could see things like the
TechCrunch article that would do you
know like say why this failed right you
know because i didn't use this library
like that that was it that was the
reason and techCrunch's the authority
and they knew that and that's the reason
that you know i can see that so I just
shouldn't even do it done right so
that's the setup for impostor syndrome
there's all these thoughts and all these
different areas i picked a few of them
and you know i want to share like how
I've been able to hack this by no means
and expert it at this ideas I have to
present but because this this week an
imposter syndrome reared its head I'm
overly qualified for this talk and
preparing it I man I felt like an
imposter but overall it's about proving
to yourself what you already know being
confident not cocky about your abilities
is a hundred percent healthy it just
simply sets you up so that you know what
you bring to the table an impostor
syndrome you know we all know hacking
software and how to kind of go around
things with different protocols or
you route around a function or something
right so I try to recognize that
imposter syndrome is a lie I am lying to
myself and I tried to realize that I'm
in that thought process and where its
leading and then I stopped it's pretty
easy to train yourself to recognize
something I have a another thing that
happens to me periodically throughout a
year on a friday i'll be working on a
problem and i'm not able to i'm not able
to solve it but i don't want to put it
down that's the pattern and once I
started to realize it that I'm in that I
say you know what I need to put this
down because that's the solution it's
like I don't want to put this down and
so I have this battle and what's crazy
is every time I put that down I saw it
in like 30 minutes on Monday so awesome
but the whole time I'm telling myself
I'm not going to be able to solve it so
just simply recognize that you're in
this thought process of you know I can't
do this they're not going to believe it
no one's going to buy it and then start
to seek first to understand so I'm a
huge fan of a tool called ansible that's
in the DevOps community and it will
allow you to deploy servers and it does
it literally over an ssh connection one
of the opening screens has a little
message that spoke to me when i first
saw it it's just called gathering facts
so you point it at a linux box and it
starts gathering facts I thought man
that's awesome you know in these
situations where I'm feeling like an
imposter I just need to start gathering
facts right knowledge is power
it's totally okay to not know what
you're doing right ansible had no idea
what's on the other end of that so it
starts to to get input the system name
the time etc starts to take an inventory
of what you know it's okay you don't
like I say you don't have to be cocky
it's just confidence build up your
confidence in what you know I know how
to write with a pencil I know how to you
know put on my shoes proof right
functional programming is pretty awesome
if you've not played with or looked into
functional programming I encourage you
to do that not only for a way you can
kind of use that concept to hack
impostor syndrome but it's really
awesome with a function you receive
inputs so these in the impostor syndrome
world they can be facts or concepts and
then you can you transfer you make a
transformation and you you output
something that output should likely be
learning right something you've learned
it's just an idea to take something that
we know in our code world and bring it
into our thought process and
immutability is is another concept that
may help in this area it's helped me
earlier this year I started using
immutable Jas and I found a lot of
comfort in the fact that I could have a
mutation to an object or something and I
can compare it and it's all good right I
don't have to worry about that thing
anymore so you know in relation to you
too imposter syndrome I I carry along
like debugging sessions that take weeks
and days and hours and you know don't
carry that along just because this bug
two years ago took you days and weeks
you know to trace through a system it
doesn't mean that all and will take that
right just that is one thing it's
completely unrelated to what you're
doing right now
and I'm a huge fan I work on the front
end these days I'm a huge fan of Redux
and hot loader react hot load or time
travel that Dan abramov brought to Redux
from a language called Elm if you've not
seen that I encourage you to to find out
on youtube and look at the front end
debugging process but what's cool is if
you think about things in a mutable like
as a single state right you carry a
state along with these immutable objects
and you can replay history so if you
start batching things up and say you
know what yes two years ago this this
situation took us some lint you know
trace it through all the ops stuff and
it's okay right that was then we've got
a different stack now we have different
people I have learned a lot more since
then right just um just an encouragement
to kind of replay in history I have to
take this to heart like I constantly
will get my twitter feed and oh my gosh
they shipped one point oh that and I've
not shipped a single thing right they
got funding wow you know that's awesome
but the success of others is not a
failure of yours I mean wow that's like
it hit me one day that it's so it
doesn't mean I didn't do something right
one of the times i happened to be
holding my son and i was scrolling
through twitter right feeding him a
bottle and someone had shipped something
i had that feeling but guess what i'm
taking care of a human it's okay you
know i mean literally focus i lose sight
obviously when i'm in a thought process
of i'm an imposter and focus on the
value you bring to the situation right
that goes back to the inventory and just
build great software
if you're in a business it's okay to
know your market and the advantage that
your business has but just forget
everything else it's all noise I use
them as my editor and I'm proud to say
that I've used it for almost 15 years
there may be Emacs guys in the back
uh-uh but that's what I know I am able
to do everything with that editor I love
what all the editors that continue to
push the the web and space forward I
love what they bring and I love what I'm
able to bring back into my editor but
that solves my problem and I'm
completely confident in the head it's
okay and I really only switched to a new
language or a database or a protocol
when it makes absolute sense that the
course I'm going is is wrong I'd also
encourage if you're not using any sort
of testing tool to set something up it
doesn't matter what it is it'll just
simply give you a little bit of
confidence in a certain area that this
piece works it may be a function but
that's huge I think we lose focus about
scaling right gosh if we could just
scale to one before we're worrying about
a million it would change a lot of this
the way we develop things and also how
we beat ourselves up I think or at least
myself when you learn to program you
start with you know printing hello world
and you take that and you put it into a
file and it's procedural and you take
that and you break it up into functions
and you take that and you put it into
objects and then there's the war between
object oriented and functional
programming and yeah yeah but it's you
had to scale to one before you got to
something bigger and then as soon as
you're able to scale to one ship it one
line of code is enough to ship
and your customer that saw the
inflatable dachshund will do their their
jump in the air as soon as you ship get
feedback I took my advice yesterday as i
was putting this together impostor
syndrome was rearing its ugly head I
reached out to some friends that I
trusted and they they gave me a
extremely valuable feedback and how I
put this together and they offered
constructive criticism and feedback will
get get you out of your head that's
exactly where you need to be and it will
shift your perspective on the problem as
well as the solutions you have to talk
to people I heard a quote recently and
I'm I can't credit to someone but
software's about people I am an
introvert and I like to go and get with
my code and work on that problem and
come up for meetings when I have a
chance but there are other days that I
have to force myself into realizing hey
this this team dynamic and these people
are here to help me and reason about the
problem in the solutions just realize
that they have this from the same
struggle that you do with whatever it is
you're working on with code and how it's
deployed in the projects everything's
different but we all struggle with
different things make sure to ask how
they've navigated certain situations
that you might be facing right now or
you faced in the past it's always good
to get a different perspective on the on
the idea if you don't attend a local
user group do so because that can help
with these conversations and then
realize that you're not talking apples
to apples right what's a scaling issue
to you is not a scaling issue to them
and how this utility performs for them
isn't always how it's going to perform
for you this hit home for me with
testing and an episode of note up that
was I believe put out in the fall last
year and it was really eye opening
because I just had this perception that
everyone had testing right and it all
just worked for them and you know I'm
and because of this old busted stack I
can't I can't test or I'm never going to
be there our tests take hours to run but
if you talk to a lot of developers yeah
some you can even take days to run right
that we've got legacy systems and we're
bringing them along and what was
interesting about this episode is that
as I listened to it I realized that my
stack was integration you know the
people that were in that were on this
panel were all talking about unit tests
and it was apples to oranges and I was
like wow so we're not talking the same
thing right they can unit test I need to
integration test so that's it that's
that was it but up until then I felt
like an imposter about testing and my
test set up that I have carried along in
that particular project and as you're
talking so um share what you know it may
not be you may not think it's a ton but
to the other person it may be huge I
think pair programming is absolutely
amazing for this in the pairs that i
have been a part of I can't think of a
single time where we didn't come away
with something that the other person
learned and it i like to call it
shoulder surfing but i will pick up on
something that someone's doing and I'm
like how did you do that or what are you
using and it may be something completely
unrelated to what we're doing but if we
never had that that interaction I I
would have never said hey can you show
me how you toggle this key right
ironically it see it comes
two times when most of those are when I
pair with a friend of mine that uses
them and he will show me something and
it turns out what plug-in are you using
that's awesome when was it released and
its core to them and it has been since
like 1995 so that's fair but it sharing
what you know will build confidence in
your abilities and it will also help
someone so it's win-win make sure to get
comfortable saying this and then follow
it up with outout I'll find out just
approach each situation with something
you know and then something you'll learn
and you'll be okay there are known
unknowns and there are unknown unknowns
these can be extremely crippling it's
okay that you don't know everything
about the stack just know your piece and
trust others to know there's finally
just a note to be kind be kind to
yourself and be kind to others when
we're at a conference like this a lot of
people are learning and it's not okay to
not include them in a conversation
because they don't know as an impostor
I'll walk into a conversation and
they're talking about something that I
don't use so I'll instantly count myself
is not qualified to participate i
encourage you to bring people into the
fold if you see them not participating
and give them that comfort we have
complicated stacks and there's just a
lot of disruption going on with the
technologies and with how we're gluing
them together so just don't beat
yourself up so that's my story and and
the hacks feel free to find me this
weekend or reach out to me on twitter
keep the conversation going and let me
know if i can help you let me know what
works for you thank you