my name is Jennifer dewalt I am
from San Francisco and I taught myself
to code by making 180 websites at 180
days
hi my name is jay sean moments i'm from
brazil my talk with about year six you
can now have separated modules in
javascript and have arrow functions that
similar to lambda in another language
and fix a lot of issues that we already
have it bugs me
my name is special mark page I live in
San Francisco working for facebook so my
talk was about how we a job Polly fills
as a way to job in the language pictures
but for these standards even finalized
before it's implemented in browsers so
that we as a community can unify on a
single set of tools instead of diverging
libraries my talk was about parallax and
you strain in one design that means that
after user Scrolls we move as far up and
down the website and it gives the
sensation of perspective to the user
we're seeing that transcript is kind of
permeating everywhere from hardware to
robots to filter reality so I think the
web will keep being this thing that
connects us all and the core of it will
be the web platform things are we
working on today
you
for the last few months have been
working on virtual reality like Google
cardboard headsets and also like up
loose absolutely ethics I think I'm
making like trying to make like easy
interface for people to work on it and
also like a 3d audio like interfacing
with a Web Audio API and I had to make
it easier for people to like create all
those pretty walls and like to
experiment with it if you look at the
history of JavaScript over the last many
years it's still the case that
essentially with every year the new
tools and the new technology is
available in JavaScript and through
JavaScript are accelerating there's more
more things we can do with JavaScript
and we are also seeing a very healthy
addition of new language features
through sanitization and we are very
excited about that I talked here about
j2me jas which is a Java Virtual Machine
written in JavaScript we're using this
Java VM to run feature phone
applications on Firefox OS think there
are a few interesting trends in
technology over the past couple of years
and you're only going to see more of it
one is the entire software little Bluff
landscape getting more polyglot because
using more languages and more
technologies over time one interesting
thing I noticed in of 0 is how many
external systems you are using to
deliver our service it's about 50
external component
so software development going forward I
think will be mostly about putting
together existing building blocks and
gluing them together rather than huge
infrastructure investments
the future of javascript is it's still
being used more and more it's being
adopted by more programmers being used
in more programming domains it was
always in the browser because it got out
first when i was at Netscape before
Microsoft could make vbscript be the
single one and then it got into the
server side several times but the one
that really succeeded was node J s
nodejs is used all over now and
javascripts also been used in the
internet of things as well like the
tehsil system-on-a-chip engine of things