alright so yeah we're actually doing
that that's a real thing we're going to
do
it wasn't this part is yeah everyone
knows that this part is everybody
that real people
all right those my talk thanks it wasn't
actually my clock but I that's all I got
now so that was kind of I when I
proposed this talk i was like i'm going
to totally go into like the virtual
reality thing from jurassic park and i
was like kind of bullshitting but then i
had to make it real because i put it in
a github issue so I'm so we'll be
talking about this but just keep that in
the back of your mind okay and this was
another thing I was kind of joking about
what I'm going to make it real did you
hear when they were kind of doing the
jurassic park at the end theme at the
end there do you guys know the jurassic
park theme can we all hum it ready pavel
go tinted then that's good enough just
kidding just kidding keep going
throughout the entire presentation so my
talk is navigating virtual worlds in
cyberspace with virtual reality modeling
language right here vrml or verbal this
is a real vermel its berlin or the
virtual cyber pakka lips the death and
return of VR or how VR Mel was kind of
ridiculous but also totally right all
along i'm dan I couldn't think of a good
slide so here's my badge I'm d harden on
Twitter whatever feel free to follow me
or don't ok I work for the zappos com
like Pavel in the spirit of the HTML
comp here's a screen cup from the year
2000 of zappos com this is real I think
it was a SP classic or something I don't
know I didn't work there I take no
responsibility of anything on this image
so yeah also pushing Vegas JSP guys ever
in Vegas come to base jase or like hit
me or pothole or someone up on Twitter
and more like go nuts and not actually
gamble which is probably why you're in
vegas in the first place yeah so let's
take things back a little bit i know
that
is d HTML cough 2000 and all but we're
going to take it way back the gear is
1995 you guys knew that whatever it's a
guy guys according to the billboard
music charts at the end of the year
gangsta's paradise was the number one
song that's still in my car a virtual
reality was kind of everywhere there
were like 87 million movies that either
used or like alluded to or in some way
had something to do with virtual reality
you had like Lawnmower Man the net like
hackers I mean it was a crazy time
everybody was getting into the game
including various me then he would have
a virtual boy wow that's amazing it's
coming back at the end of this
presentation get here ready don't worry
about it the virtual reality it was kind
of this like huge clunky thing this is a
video I couldn't get to load right so I
turned it into like a 16 megabyte gif
gif not jiff so like there were news
reports and like I guess he's a reporter
and they're like strapping him into this
machine but like the game's kind of
looked like this this is dactyl
nightmare the decals going to come hold
on Oh
so that's a dactyl I guess the rest of
it's the nightmare but this is the kind
of thing like you would go to the mall
and pay like way too much money to strap
in and then you would never be able to
figure out how to do anything and then
the dactyl I don't know but this was
kind of a thing everybody really thought
that VR was going to take off so why
wouldn't you have some way to describe
it right so this virtual reality
modeling language initially known as
virtual reality markup language not at
all related to HTML but I think they
kind of wanted to cash in on that so if
virtual reality was going to be like the
big thing right like this this makes
perfect sense but you got to remember
like this was the Internet of 1995 like
this is a real thing so this this is an
actual quote I want everyone to kind of
take a look at this and we'll examine
some key points this is a quote from the
from the vrml spec version 1.0 see they
are rendered everyone say rendered
sensually if something is represented
sensually it is possible to make sense
of it vrml is an attempt how successful
only time and effort will tell to place
humans at the center of the internet so
that's all right um yeah that's what it
is right I think I know this sounds
ridiculous but I swear it kind of makes
sense because remember remember the
Internet of 1995 it doesn't make any
sense who used hot metal ever that's a
hell of a HTML editor like it was a
really terrible place and like let's go
back to pizza just take that end if if
you have never used the internet or if
it was like this crazy thing or you'd
like here the kids talking about surfing
like the websphere or whatever like you
didn't know how any of the shit worked
just a really basic thing like how do
you go to a website was a mystery when
there's all of this nonsense going on so
I think the rml was a good step in that
direction I promise so we're going to
come back to this because I said that I
would I think that this is really
along the same lines did you know that
this is a like a real program this is
the thing that there's there's an open
source version now you can like brew
install it and it's like depending on if
you're like have the right c compiler in
the right like phase of the moon or
whatever like you could run this shit
this is like browsing a file system and
I think it's a UNIX system I know this i
really think that there was a fear of
like taking these abstract concepts like
navigating a file system or going to a
website or buying something online or
ordering a pizza or whatever and you
really wanted to relate that to human
things like if you say like go to a
folder well by god you're going to a
folder you are flying to it and shining
a light on it and going to it so i think
vemos really kind of the same thing but
for the internet here is a real doe shit
via remote client it's awesome and i
love it blaxland right yeah okay so you
could actually move around in this world
and you could talk to people and you
could what are they talking about I
don't know whatever terrible stuff I
don't know this is a and I've kept this
iframe at 800 x 600 for like the real
experience but you could you could go to
these worlds and it wasn't just like
when you talk to chatting people online
like this is really your going to go
like to their like castle house and you
will chat with them and it's a real
you're there you are in two rooms or an
executive office or kessel haunted which
might be my favorite so there was a
variety of vrml browsers and like
looking there's a bunch here and these
websites are all still let these are
just iframes that I'm in bedding there's
like a bunch right keep in mind how many
there are here because this is another
thing that's going to come up later
there was kind of a lot of things that
people hadn't like they weren't taking
it for granted like does anyone even
ever say like my avatar maybe like if
you're customizing your character and
like World of Warcraft or so that maybe
it comes up but there are a lot of like
really deep very well thought out
spiritual things people
writing about avatars man like you'd go
on a journey and like you wouldn't have
to be like whatever you would choose
your avatar like if you wanted to be
like a fish or I think that's Crash
Bandicoot I don't know a bowling ball
like you could be whatever you wanted to
be in a way that's kind of beautiful in
a way it's also a little I don't know
it's something but I think a lot of
people this was very new to everyone the
idea that you could go and you could
talk to someone from whatever country
you don't know and they're from anywhere
they're not just your not constrained by
really anything except kind of your
terrible computer that probably could
not render this scene now we use viera
mel for everything right well ok we
don't so what would wrong like what what
killed vrml and i will also pause it to
you that is not dead i think i think
there's really a couple things number
one probably dial up when the last time
you heard heard this sweet jam yeah
that's beautiful um when you're going
through you're trying to render a 3d
world and like maybe if you've got like
that really good computer you've got 56k
like most people didn't and especially
when you're connecting to someone across
the world and the servers and who knows
and like you probably don't even hit
like you don't have a graphics card
that's not much of a thing maybe a
voodoo whatever but like this is a
problem right your computer your
connection like verb 3d is not a thing
that you can do like if you even today
like if you go on to some like the hot
new in the mo RPG or something it's
probably gonna lag like it's a thing I
think another problem with calm bubble
um remember when I said that there was
all like all these guys like a million
things they all bought each other so all
of these bought each other and bought
their developers and bought each other
out and then eventually computer
associates came in and bought the final
one and just said like I were done like
no more of your vrml so suddenly there
wasn't a market which is like really
you I mean there wasn't so it's okay but
i would say number 3 3d its kind of
that's a distracting gift at up 3d is
maybe not the most ideal way to do
things like I keep going back to this
idea of like you want to buy something
online you don't need to or like say you
want to go and you want to go to
Wikipedia you want to read about
platypuses or like this you're like a
tiger you want to read about tigers you
don't need to drive to the virtual
Wikipedia enter the library browse the
endless to like the matrix when like the
things come in like you don't that's
silly like you just type tiger and you
get it Tigers you don't have to do that
like you understand right so I don't
know but wait these were some of the
goals that they were talking about in
that ridiculous manifesto I mean spec
they want to perceptual eyes the
internet they want to kind of enable
people to get together and like of
course having cool VR experiences is
probably the main draw of here are all
right I kind of think we do all of these
things so maybe vrml was ahead of its
time select perceptual izing the
internet you're not so much if I was
like hey can you go to a website and
like click thing and whatever like
that's not that's not scary that's just
second nature to everybody right it
wasn't in 1995 it wasn't in 98 it wasn't
necessarily in two thousand or whatever
but like I feel like it's not so bad to
go to a website now just the idea of
going to a website isn't terrifying
that's the wrong order there's my cart
slide I was going to be like oh look
here's adding to a cart versus a real
cart but whatever let's talk about
enabling human connections and I
realized after this this isn't a human
i don't care i love this gift so like we
all know the Internet can be a terrible
place full of terrible people but like
who's made a friend on the internet like
an actual friend that you feel like you
know them who's made friends that are
better than like maybe some of your real
friends okay and i would i would even
pause it like I've known some of you
like through Twitter or through whatever
never met you until maybe like today
that's pretty powerful right and I
didn't need the lake I don't I don't
remember entering any of your vrml
Castle Haunted's or anything for us to
have a conversation although I wish we
had which and let me let me let me
digress for a second this wasn't part of
the talk but just wanted to say thanks
everybody for being really cool cuz like
I didn't really know anybody but like
everyone's been really inviting and I'm
was kind of terrified to do this whole
thing so thanks for being cool that's
that's me I'm the chicken right there so
anyway yeah that's scary i don't know
about all right yeah let's do it okay
cool huh so let's talk about cool of
your experiences um hey who knows about
the oculus rift like people are sinking
some serious money into that right and
it's like pretty cool how about did I
take out my google now I didn't it's
just impossible you can kind of read it
I didn't I shouldn't have made it the
same color is like cardboard google
cardboard is this thing where you can
basically cut out this kind of stencil
will make it out of cardboard or
whatever slap it over your phone and you
get a pretty good VR experience and
that's Google and that's like it's
really neat that's a thing we're doing
right now that's like brand new shit so
I think we're doing VR let's let's let's
go back to this
because this is really the crux of the
talk right here if the idea is that you
know you want to bring the internet and
make it something people can understand
and you want to bring multi participant
people in and I don't know about the
rendering essentially like I'm not we'll
leave that as an exercise to the viewer
I'm not going into that I think we're
kind of doing that like maybe vrml
wasn't the way to do that but
philosophically and this is a pretty
philosophical spec let's be honest I
really think they're on the right track
so let's hear it for vrml but wait
there's more you know how I said it
wasn't dead it's totally not dead
there's a few folks who were really like
and let's talk about the most unix thing
I've ever read in my life like that's a
stretch that's a stretch I don't know so
x3 dumb or X freedom as I will refer to
it is like this effort to get this stuff
into the browser so X 3d is kind of the
successor to vrml it's an xml-based
language and we all we all love XML
right this is kind of working in the
browser and like never mind that they've
shimmed it in with like opengl and like
canvas and like all this stuff they want
this to be a spec I don't know if that's
going to happen but like someone's
keeping up the fight and like their suit
like they have a fort be on github like
that's that means it's new and they're
really like Google cardboard and x3d and
vrml and freedom like this is a real
thing that people are working on right
now so never mind that this technology
is however old like it's a thing and I
think it's powerful because
so like we can inspect this and you can
see this amazing syntax describing cubes
and whatever but um yes good yeah i
don't know i know there's like eight
million ways we can do 3d in the browser
but this one has a spec that's pretty
good so I'm not saying maybe everyone go
out and do x3d but i will say that
pretty much every 3d modeling thing like
whether it be something fancy or like
Tinkercad or like whatever can probably
output X 3d or some of them can even
output vrml files directly so if nothing
else it lives on is an interchange
format I don't know that's something but
I guess I guess what I'm saying is I
know vrml sounds like I went into this
thinking vrml was kind of silly I came
out and this is someone who was really
thinking it was pretty cool back in the
day I think now it was ahead of its time
and maybe we're not using the VR part of
the vrml which is kind of well really
all of it but the philosophy kind of