hey everyone I'm judged man I'm gonna be
your host for today I'm just going to
give you a quick little intro and then
if I'm just could basically interest the
speakers that come out a few any
questions you can feel free to come up
to me or anyone else on the team so
judge Smits you're probably thinking
this guy has really excellent German but
no I'm actually I'm from New York I
don't actually speak German so I didn't
know what to do the intro and shy like
doing English but then that's kind of
douchey cuz like here's this American
come in and speaking English so I didn't
want to do it in English so here's I'm
going to try i'm going to try giving you
the intro to today's conference entirely
in CSS this is the challenge I'm a
little bit nervous about it I studied
all of the html5 element names I studied
all the css3 property names and so here
we go intro dot CSS or if you're German
intrusive set 396 anyway ok cool so
first of all hi um hi you all uh hi
everybody here is your intro I'm
basically just want to give you a
background about CSS com I'm sorry that
is that's not bad the numbers but then
the n.o and season let's see you soon
okay cool it's a nice orange uh so yeah
CSS come I think you'll love it it hurts
me too don't worry but before we start
just going to some filler content here
and you might find it a little bit
off-color you might find it the jokes
are somewhat opaque maybe some of the
jokes are a little bit of a stretch
speaking of the jokes I'm just going to
list them up you know stretch trying to
lighten the mood some of them might make
you a little bit embarrassed you know
make your face red or make you blush
better known as FFF Oh f5 but I am a
bottomless trove of bad CSS jokes so I
don't think of any trouble there they're
all funny but like
every tenth joke will float just right
and will be comic gold so just bear with
me if it seems slow gold also obviously
FF d700 so it's going to give you
background of the area here we are in
Berlin it's a conference about style in
a city that has style Berlin has so much
style if styles have style and that just
keeps repeating forever yeah it's like
just walking out on the street just
seeing people on the street a man it is
so stylish even here at berghain people
waiting in line have style you would say
they have inline style and because it's
Germany the line height is about to 2x
what it usually is where I'm where I'm
from but you don't want to use inline
styles is right that's bad you wanna use
his class and you know this is city
obviously a lot history it has a lot of
class I haven't seen this much class
it's almost too much class like villains
almost too classy I haven't seen this
much excessive class since I last used
modernizer about the area also we are
right next to the Berlin Wall if you
might know it's about two million pixels
to your left it is this solid border
that used to divide Germany until
nineteen eighty nine when it collapsed
so it's a it's actually kind of hard to
find you actually can't find the berlin
wall with CSS you're going to need to
use javascript using jquery i'm sure you
guys all know how to do this Jake where
you put in a selector so you just find
an area that has sold off and you can
find the Berlin Wall it's he's wearing a
jacket you'll see it shouldn't be hard
fun so about this address where we are
right now we are on in bleedin straße
and again I don't know german i'm pretty
sure that in bleedin straße in english
would just be a street address that is
disabled
it's my guess I was to breed I have and
about this particular section of this
area it's villas Beth it is a sim back
or another but the position of this
place it is right in the center of
Berlin you can see these beautiful white
walls the background here is white
better known as ffffff but it's actually
the building's little bit old so it's
faded a little bit is actually more like
a fa e bd7 better nose antique white
apparently fading is perfectly natural
this in a white space perfectly normal
if that happens I don't worry about it
this is actually like a parish you can't
really tell it's not on display but this
is actually you know a religious
institution so it's not on display but
if you were here like maybe 50 years ago
it would be more of a display none kind
of thing anyway so let's talk about this
conference it is an import from the
state's CSS com started we're gonna hear
more about that later from Nicole let's
talk about CSS cough actually hold I'm
gonna get a little bit more specific
let's talk about CSS comfy you it's the
first of its type its i think is far
neither the only of its type it is for
the organizers is their first conference
and i'm sure you know what that means it
is aunt child index one so of all the
children's like the index is one or as
some of you would say the index is one
so yeah sees economy you it's a it's not
for profit right so there's no margin
gonna make any margin on this hopefully
when they're done there will be nothing
left i assume what I hope is not the
case that they actually have extra money
and they just hide it so let's hope that
that is not happening let's talk about
the list of the speakers we have
excellent speakers there in the top 1%
of their field they are the backgrounds
are really really badass you would all
say absolutely badass so if during while
you're listening these speakers if you
are unable to focus next we have a
selection of delicious black coffee but
I've heard unfortunately we have is your
decaf which you know if you're not a
caffeine person is bad
add but let me give you some background
on that apparently the organizers asked
them to do decaf and all they said was a
999 999 and then just no decaf so I
realized that's a lot of background
jokes in a row so I'm just going to turn
off repeat on the background jokes sorry
about that its last one also mention the
toilet if you need directions ask me
later and once you so if you have to
drink less coffee gift p after you visit
the toilet and your empty if p
everything for your will be fixed
everything will be all right so
definitely give that a visit I want to
talk we have this policy they mentioned
it's the anti-drug policy so I just want
to give you in the in the context of CSS
what that entails so take this pretty
seriously don't disable user selection
on all elements that's kind of douchey
don't ever every seven images don't
rotate them 180 degrees like that's
pretty douchey don't fade all the
paragraphs 20 like I can't see them
after 500 seconds like don't do that
that that would be a jerky thing to do
and finally don't blink all of your H
ones all right so just doesn't God just
don't do that so that would be a
definitely fall under the jerk policy
one more point I want to make it's a I'm
sorry one point I guess it would be a
pretty important point I want to talk
about if you guys take photos or of
anything totally totally cool but would
love if you guys could share them you
can just you can display them online if
you want to or you could you know put
them around your block or both but it
would be a shame if after CSS conf we
were left with 0 pics so just make sure
you share them that's all I ask and
that's about it and so without further
ado I would like to bring up our first
keynote our keynote or four speaker uh
needs very little introduction so she
will get none lady and gentlemen
stubborn Ella Nicole Sullivan
you