thank you I jeds probably like my
favorite person in the whole world so
that was nice anyways this looks like it
works unicode poop there's a HTML entity
for that as well just good info to have
I think that's the last actual poop I
have in here so hopefully that helps
settle your stomach's a bit uh let's get
going if we can there we go so I had a
friends say this to me once I don't want
all those fancy features I just want a
program that eats ass and poop CSS and
that's really the thing that the pooping
is is about and I'm going to go ahead
and extend the metaphor for you into the
CSS preprocessor digestive tract and
hopefully that won't get too boring but
but i'll try to stick to mostly CSS so
we we often have information like this
this is a very small stylesheet we have
some variables some are pixels summer
colors and we mix them in and we've run
functions on them it's nice so so how do
we process that what happens whenever we
want CSS out the other end so how does
eating this makes a spoof this so
preprocessors as they relate to the
digestive system eating is probably
standard in I'd say chewing is most like
lexing I'll talk about what a lexer is
but I kind of breaks up the input into
more easily digestible pieces stomachs
are an important part of actual
digestion system so I couldn't really
leave them out but they don't actually
the metaphor is very broken so i just
added them in here as some sort of data
store that you're using because that's
really all it's doing maybe a additional
lexing so your small intestines are kind
of like the parser step so the parser
step is
uh taking out the pieces that you need
and putting them in the right places so
this would like be actually getting
nutrients and moving it to nice parts of
your body breaking things down would not
be part of that even though that's
something that the small intestines do
so just ignore that large intestines are
similar we'll call that the compiler it
really gets it ready for output that's
that's where our I I'm just gonna say
output but I think you know I and you
all know what standard out is and so
we're good there and I'm going to talk a
little bit about hacking this system and
so I just had to have the metaphor for
that so one way you could hack your
digestive tract is like lap band surgery
where they like make your stomach
smaller and then you have less memory
and so maybe your output is slower you
lose weight or one of the two so parsing
and compiling is really what I'd like to
talk to you about rather than the
digestive tract so parsing is is
actually pretty easy on a high level it
uses syntax rules of the language and it
figures out what every little part of a
string is and it breaks them down into
tokens so in this case you have the
dollar sign which in SAS means that it's
the start of a variable and then you
have the name of the variable which is
blue in this case you have the Equality
operator CSS uses the colon to mean
equals and so that's what SAS uses and
then you have the value it could be any
arbitrary string usually there are rules
about what can go there you can't have
unicode characters though it like if it
was in a URL or something it might work
probably just about anything there
except for a semicolon and then you have
a rule delimiter to say hey this is the
end of the rule and so that's pretty
easy you might be able to write a regex
to go through and and break apart those
things you're really looking for three
things in that case and filling in the
gaps you see the dollar sign is a
variable and then you fill in the gaps
until you get to a colon and you fill in
the gaps then you get
2 semicolon so that's really at the very
base of how you set a variable how a
computer breaks that stuff down more
specifically it goes through every
single character and it says is this
part of anything that I might know about
and it's a it has a few options and if
there's only one option then it says oh
this must be the dollar sign to mean a
variable but if two things could start
with a dollar sign it might look ahead
and do other things there's lots of ways
to write parsers that I don't even know
about here is my most simple example of
how you might write this parser in
JavaScript which SAS is not written in
the the most non congruent part of my
talk is that all of my examples is are
in SAS and all of my code is in
JavaScript so you'll just have to deal
with that mental trust point anyways we
essentially just looped through a string
we get a string in as CSS it's just text
it's a you have characters in there and
in this case we're just saying if we
loop through and the character is a
semicolon we know there's a semicolon so
we have a list of tokens and then we
push the semicolon token in this case
it's just the string semicolon which
probably might be okay for semicolon but
you'd probably need more info like the
variable is this type of variable all
kinds of stuff this is a very simplified
example so you want one of those things
where you're noticing a semicolon for
every possible thing in the language
unless it's dynamic and then you use
other techniques for those more
realistically you probably write a
parser generator some people might
disagree with me on this but but most of
the time when you need a quick parser
for something you can actually use
something like a peg that's a parser
expression grammar generator and you can
generate a parser based on expressions
and so you say that a class is actually
just a dot followed by an identifier and
then you kind of say like whenever I
build this up say an element is just an
identifier
or the the asterisk for everything and
identifier is can be anything with
dashes or numbers or characters and all
kinds of risks if you don't necessarily
understand the syntax or more or less
anything here other than that you can
kind of build up a language and then
someone will actually just generate a
very fast parser for you and you don't
have to worry about this type of stuff
unless you want to make it very very
fast in which case you do this by hand
and see which lips ass things like that
let's how those work so when you're done
you need to represent the code as data
it comes in as text it comes in as an
array of characters so this is text and
you eventually after lexing have this
you have the variable starting of the
string you know the value of the string
you know that the next thing is equals
and that the value of the everything so
you have that and you want to actually
add structure so you take the variable
set you know that this needs to end with
the semicolon you say actually the way
setting variables works is it has two
sides and so you're going to build an
arbitrary object that says the left side
is the variable name and it's blue and
the right side is the value and it's
three BBFC I don't know where that value
Jed had all the switching names this
morning pro tip that was a good move
stylist have structure so even further
you might have the stylesheet object
that wraps that whole thing so if your
your whole style sheet was just one
variable declaration it might look kind
of like this you'd have you'd have an
object that said my type is a style
sheet and in it it has declarations and
the first one is a variable that's set
in a certain way the second one is a
declaration the selector is the stuff
class inside P tags and the rules are
left color value the color of FFF so
we're just saying stuff p stuff has the
color of white and that actually might
look more like this in SAS so you have
bodies then you have a tags and they're
nested inside
the hover states are nested inside so
you actually have what what ends up
looking like this whenever you actually
break it down I can make this smaller
for you maybe I can't there we go closer
so we end up with a hierarchy we have a
style sheet and we know that we have a
body rule and we have an a rule and
inside of those we have rules and inside
of those we have rules and with with
sass you can nest infinitely I think
Nicole once said that you should follow
the inception rule and never go more
than four levels deep which I like that
is that is good but technically you have
the ability to go as deep as you'd like
in normal CSS you can only have one
level but it's still a tree it's just
not that tall of one anyways this is an
abstract syntax tree that's what I've
been describing it's confusing because
there are almost no rules if anyone asks
a knapsack an abstract syntax tree is
just a list of things that contain one
thing or other lists of things i like to
call them arbitrary syntax trees they
almost don't mean anything they're
they're actually they've got such a cool
name that you want to drive more value
out of that name but really all it is is
a representation of the meaning of your
syntax in a structure so in the case of
CSS we don't want just there was a
variable than this and then a semicolon
and then this like there's no actual
structure that means anything we want to
be able to say that this is a group that
contains rules that contain groups that
contain rules and we know that the
things inside of a group apply to only
its outer selectors so what can we do
with it lots of stuff and that's why
it's fun so i'll go into what we can do
with it and in a second but the
compilation step is the first thing you
would normally do with it compile it to
CSS so reduction is the first step
whenever you're dealing with something
like compiling sass into CSS you have s
CSS which we've been using here and it's
kind of like a superset of CSS most of
the things are very similar and so we
want to take the data from the SCSS that
looks kind of like this we have a
variable that we're setting to blue so
we're saying blue is that 3 b.b number
and then we have a rule that uses the
variable and that's not valid CSS at
least until CSS level for Nazi SS for
CSS unburdened level for totally
different guys come on the yeah so this
is not valid CSS we couldn't compile
this we couldn't turn this back into a
string and have this actually work in
any browser what we want to do is reduce
the variables away so in this case we'd
say find any place that has the value
where the type is a variable and the
name is blue and that'd be pretty easy
and then just replace it with the value
of the blue variable and you might be
able to do that in your head very easily
it's somewhat complicated in code we
won't actually have to do that and so
you end up with this and this ends up
being actually a completely valid CSS
syntax tree we just have a rule and the
name is the color and the value is a
legit color and we can just compile that
single rule into CSS and there's no
problem and that's valid one hundred
percent valid CSS you could even use the
SAS lexer backwards not that lectures
work that way but because SCSS works
that way you could turn it back into
what the SAS the SCSS representation of
this would be and would be completely
valid CSS in this case and what you
would do is just do that on the most
specific node and then you'd go up and
you do that on those nodes and then you
go up and you go up and you compile so I
lost too much recursion everybody's Fred
so you're
shin comes from this and you're able to
output this and you do that recursively
leaves the trunk and I say leaves your
trunk because they're like there's a
split somewhere in the middle of the
room of people who say that that's up
the tree and there are people would say
that that's down the tree and I think
it's probably down the tree but because
you're going leaves the trunk but
whenever you represent a sin texture you
actually draw it upside down and so it's
actually more like stalactites or
something and we should just change
abstract syntax stalactites from now on
if you would or arbitrary syntax
stalactites would work for me anyways so
we take something that looks like this
we put it into the structured data you
don't actually have to read that but
this is you know some arbitrary way of
saying there are declarations with rules
inside of them and we know what they all
mean and it's just big and ugly and we
reduce that to something that is valid
for CSS and you want to know what's
going on here but we no longer have
variables in there we no longer have
nested structures it's all a valid tree
and then we're able to just turn that
back into text again so it takes one
type of text converts it into a known
but arbitrary data format and then it
converts that data into a different but
arbitrary and known data format and it
converts that back to text so that was
like a very long drawn-out way of saying
that it takes text turns it into data
fiddles with it and then turns it back
into text so there's a very
sophisticated graph on seeing that more
apropos to the title we have our
digestion system I threw in some some
buzz words streams I don't know what
that that would be I guess you pipe
saliva into standard in anyways uh this
is this is really just a silly metaphor
the only hard part is actually there in
the middle we're pretty good at parsing
you can use parts of expression
generators were pretty good at even
knowing how to define languages as
context-free grammars or regular
languages there's this whole automata
theory on all that stuff so we're pretty
good at taking text and turning into
data very pretty good at turning data
and putting it to text is just the
reverse so the the magic of SAS actually
you know other than some speed things
lives in in the data one today to do
data to conversion and it's it's
interesting how they do some of that
stuff that's not really the point so I
want to teach you what you can do with
it data one can be interesting just
reading the data can be pretty
eye-opening so data one would be that
data that once we turned it into a
structure that represented our SAS what
could we what information could we get
from it we could count how often we use
variables or we could change them before
they ever get used we could move rules
around we could reduce things we could
lint we could change the output formats
we could output to multiple formats
there's a lot of work you can do by
having your styles as data and it's
super cool to me so as long as your data
is valid at all points it doesn't matter
you can send it back in so you could
take in text turn into data throw that
data away create your own whole new data
and then compile that to CSS and that's
fine just wouldn't have any bearing on
what you put in and that's that's a-ok
thing I guess sometimes so I wrote this
a very important modifier of rules and
so you would pass this in as a filter to
your ast so your data comes in and what
it does is says find me all the rules so
you don't want to find the selectors you
don't want to find variable names all
you want to say is anywhere where
there's a rule that has a value let's
check that out so we'll say if it has a
value say the value plus important so we
save every value as important and then
write it back to the tree I
then recursively do that so we call
ourselves over and over so we go all the
way down and hit every single rule in
our entire CSS file and then just return
all that and then we compile that and
now every single one of our rules is
important in the output and you didn't
have to write those by hand so this will
save you a lot of time doing what your
are going to do anyways which was
probably just add important to
everything luckily we can do the reverse
the undo intern work AST modification
tool so we go through every single node
we find if it's a rule we say if it
matches important return null so delete
the rule entirely don't turn it
unimportant just say if this is
important then it should die forever
which is another valid opinion to have
outputs may vary and that that type of
logic works in every preprocessor
obviously that code will not work in
every preprocessor everyone has
different ways of storing nodes and
values and things like that rework is
one by TJ vision media who has five or
six hundred modules on github but it is
made specifically for AST hacking he
actually ships it with no features it
literally just takes stuff in turns it
to data and then turns that data back
into CSS and then it's up to you to
stick stuff in the middle so you might
be familiar with the term middleware so
you write a bunch of little middleware
pieces that change nodes around and you
say if I want to add variables I just
add one little piece this is variables
and that's the only thing I want to use
in my preprocessor so I'm not going to
add it nesting and I'm not going to add
in gradients or a variable one of the
pre vendor prefixes all that kind of
stuff you don't need them so don't add
them in or you could do totally custom
stuff so a little more real world a
problem that I actually ran into in my
day to day work is that compilation of
styles is fast you can take a SAS style
eat or stylus in the case that I that I
originally had and you can compile
Styles pretty quickly so it's rarely the
bottleneck in anyone's build step if
they can get slow some people will move
to lib sass for that kind of thing the
asterisk there is until you want to hook
it up to a change event so if you hooked
up the color picker to a change event
and said on change you know 60 times a
second or whatever that that can do go
back to the server recompile all my
Styles with the new value and set this
variable just to this this new value
that I have on the change thing and then
send all that back up delete all the
styles and put all the new ones in that
would never work and luckily now that
you know about a STS you could fix that
problem so in something like a theme
builder you would want a size slider or
color picker to do all this stuff in
real time so the only way we can avoid
the time it takes to recompile is to not
recompile and luckily we can capture
that data at the data level and use that
to our advantage and still only ever
write the SAS or the stylus of the this
the rework that we want to write so I
will open up a demo for you this is a
fun little page it's got a pun for for
Jed leaf and tree just to point that out
for everyone thank you so what we have
here is a pretty simple page I put it
together it's an express app it's if you
saw the first slide I had a link to it
but you can get it will be on the left
side too and you can run it from from
github so what we have first is I'll
pull up a my CSS my CSS is my personal
compiler for for CSS all I did was add
variables i use rework to do this and so
i add this one little guy here that says
VAR and then I pass it a variable name
and then in in the compilation step it
adds in my actual variables which
I put in in my server I don't know why I
did that but that's where it is so I
take these and I essentially replace
those so I wrote a a a middleware
component to rework that just goes in
and replaces those variables with the
actual values and that's pretty simple
and so if you come here I can show you
the output and you'll see that there are
actual background colors and there are
actual widths and and all this kind of
stuff so it's real it happens it's fun
and it works and yeah so some things
that dev tools is really good at is
saying hey I know where this rule is
working on my page I can go and say I
can right click on something and say
what styles apply to this element but
you don't actually have a lot of insight
into how your sass variables map up two
things on pages you don't have that it's
compiled to CSS before it ever gets to
the browser so we have that information
that's what I also did was I grabbed the
AST stage and I flipped the AST on its
head so you can take your variables and
you can say which selectors do they
apply to and which rules work on those
selectors based on that variable so you
might say if bgcolor ends up being black
then you would say it would output in
the end output that the body HTML
bracket background color colon black
close bracket right and that would be
the rule that's generated from a black
BG color and we have this data available
to us as JSON and if I change anything
in our CSS file this automatically just
gets changed it's not something I have
to maintain separately it's just
completely generated from the ast of our
stuff and so I have a few things here it
says to next to BG color and I can hover
over it and says the BG color of the
HTML element which is the total wrapping
element the body which has a margin on
it comes down to to where the the margin
is and then the font color of leaf them
alone is the same as the background
color and so we see
that we actually have two rules where
it's used it shows up three times on the
page and we can actually position
something over every time we see this
variable we can also come in here grab a
pick color picker and change these in
real time so we can have you know 60
frame per second recompilation of styles
because we know exactly which elements
are affected by this we don't have to go
back to the server recompile you'll
notice the the text is changing at the
same time as as the background there we
can actually just pop into here and
check I just inject a style element with
just that rule in it and that rule says
the body and the container sub-header
now have this new color and it just
overrides our current styles so that's
pretty nifty and that's information you
could never get from devtools until they
have deeper integrations with this stuff
you can also do fun stuff of border
radius I like this is is this trippy it
right here ready for this oh there's CSS
for you this is my favorite one just
that's going to translate well in a
slide deck anyways that's actually just
about all I have does anyone have
questions