[Music]
[Applause]
thank you very much
trigger warning the next talk includes
mentions and pictures of diseases micro
massive devices and unapproved medical
treatments my talk is called how
community made me a t1d cyborg diabetes
is a condition condition for
approximately 420 million people
worldwide roughly 10% of them like 40
million are type 1 diabetes type 1
diabetes often and ridiculously refer to
as the bap type of diabetes is
irreversible it involves multiple daily
injections and finger pricks and gives
you rollercoasters in matters of blood
glucose resulting in unstable physical
condition this talk is a short shout-out
to the community that calls itself we
are not waiting because we are not
waiting for an adequate medical
treatment of type 1 diabetes which is
possible but not approved I was
diagnosed with type 1 diabetes in 2005
so was my daughter in 2016 there as of
current best approved therapy include
wearing an insulin pump connected to
your body and a continuous glucose meter
a CGM measuring the glucose level every
5 minutes
many more people with type 1 diabetes
like 97.5% are still on a injection pen
and fingerpick therapy therapy also
includes recalculating your required
insulin dosage on a daily level counting
carbohydrates in everything you eat and
convert that into the insulin units it
took me 13 years a child and a community
to learn how to best treat that beast
during these 13 years I mostly ignored
it
I felt unequal I had doubts I was
mismanaged as well as I mismanaged
myself and in fact I was lucky to still
be alive
and then in November 2018 I became a t1d
cyborg and my daughter becomes a t1d
cyborg at night so today I wear an old
insulin pump with a cannula going into
my upper leg or my tummy I wear a CGM
that continuous glucose meter on my
tummy or my upper arm I constantly carry
with me Micro PC in my pocket as well as
my smartphone
so let's attach to all that and I
basically depend on internet and rock
tape a cyborg MacGyver and the
Neuromancer all are ones
so color let's come to that Micro PC the
community is actively developing the
software that runs on that little PC
device it's written in JavaScript go
Python bash script and other languages
you have to build that device yourself
it's do-it-yourself and still or because
of that it's more advanced than any
other commercially available insulin
delivery system in fact there is no
commercial system that administers
insulin on prediction my gratitude goes
to this community
it was 2014 that four people closed that
loop of insulin delivery and started a
movement and a community this community
it has now more than 500 contributors on
github it has a thousand members on on
the discussion channel on your own
guitar many more on that database CGM in
the cloud and even more in
Facebook group and the regional Facebook
groups or other groups or meetups so it
will maybe that I owe my life to this
community in the last six months since I
started looping I learned more about
type 1 diabetes they learned in that 13
years before much more and I'm still
alive
thanks to all the people in the we're
not waiting community so please think
about contributing to a community
yourself it saves lives
if you don't feel self-confident enough
to contributing code contribute in
documentation participate in a meet-up
or star 1 discuss with people and share
your knowledge spread your developer
love plays thank you
[Applause]