I'm here chick chick chick chick chick
one to JavaScript brothers and sisters
can you hear me out there I gotta
introduce me alright cool so this guy
says that apparently you could do no GS
server-side scripting in Photoshop yeah
my name is andy hall i came from adobe
japan the file now has a new menu option
called awesome mode because it's awesome
that's why it's called awesome mode so
this without further ado is Alec
smacking my cat ow
I'm Alex macaw and actually we're
already off to a good start because in
my last presentation that Jays Kumpf I
actually spelled my name wrong now pay
attention because this is what we're
about to see is I think basically the
future Photoshop right ok Photoshop new
layer see you do a demo and it doesn't
work what happens all right I'm pleased
to see that as soon as anyone puts up a
chat at a conference people try and hack
it with cross-site scripting so goods
good sign for a tech conference oh it's
going nuts ok Photoshop ok photoshopped
what is the difference I would just like
to introduce you our next speaker
Michelle budzinski and I work also on
this project called Antarctic Jas and
it's maybe it's hard to like uh get this
from the name but that's the JavaScript
conference and Antarctica what is it
then ok Photoshop this is crazy hold on
ok Photoshop I've never had it not work
this well one ok I didn't prepare the
presentation actually I made a game
because it's more fun to talk about
games while you play game right and now
he's gonna be talking about testing CSS
you guys have any problems without it so
oh one more thing even if I'm a game
developer I'm not really good player so
I second gaming and like playing and
talking in the same time it's impossible
for me so i will probably
yeah I improved this but I improved the
wrists bound algorithm recently so it
should work better it's a pretty strange
world and I don't think there's lots of
solutions out there for that yes as you
said it's a strange world and I'm a
strange guy so okay Photoshop why does
not work ok Photoshop this is really
strange
yeah oh wait okay okay photoshop i do
not know why this would happen one
moment okay photoshop okay photoshop
this is a nightmare I guess you're all
wondering why is he wearing a bow tie
and I heard it's actually thanksgiving
today so maybe that's the reason or
maybe I'm just very happy to be here or
well I'm simply a strange guy so maybe
that's it okay photoshop okay photoshop
thank new layer ah what is it doing yay
okay sorry because i have no idea where
my next slide is okay upper platform and
I'm from I'm from Sweden so I I guess
all of you kind of have an idea of
Sweden and I bet it's a lot like this
okay Photoshop why would that not work
ah this is really crazy alright so let's
pretend that demo worked because it's
clearly doing something here but it's
it's not like that it's worse it's more
like this oh no no we started doing
quite a lot of our sensibility stuff in
html5 and for example like I'm in
Photoshop you have yes enhancing
enhancing enhancing we actually
pioneered a specific genre of music
called melodic death metal enhancing and
handsome and handsome should I turn this
off enhancing and okay
so which one is the next Oh date
all right ok so what exactly like okay
give me a second if I want to create a
game for the conference next time please
punch me in the face
right now you run your cameras right in
Hollywood and the enhanced feature is
just hooked into the undo function and
earlier i blurted three times so I say
okay Photoshop come on okay Photoshop ah
died Photoshop oh we have Brian chills
that's great to be here thank you for
having me in Manila thanks Thomas and
Rico for organizing this my name is
Brian if anyone actually knew what song
that was or what band please tweet it to
me and I would be very warm and fuzzy
inside this is one of my favorites we do
a little channel change hang on there
you go so hop the TV glitch effect this
one this is my favorite TV glitch i
think is going to be the page curl of
the 21st century right so I guys I want
you all to go out there and throw TV
glitch affected everything and it's
great because we don't really have TVs
like this anymore and i love how in
movies they always have analog you know
TV glitch on digital signals so go do
lots of that that's good explore it play
with it okay Photoshop way come on one
last time work Oh Photoshop
okay Photoshop okay photos up okay
photos up we're really honored to have
him here ladies and gentlemen Charlie
crane hey okay thank you uh okay photos
up ok photos up oh god I come from hum
toh toh oh never heard of it he have
statistics about citrus for NPM
modules and then which is number six
hangzhou china okay okay so I built this
little demo aware you have to keep
moving the mouse and the more you move
the mouse the more changes the color but
if you stop moving the mouse you don't
touch it it kind of fades out to grey I
stole one of the open source games a
example of the impact jes engine this
actually has never failed in the office
it must be the I don't know max anyway
you say okay Photoshop things they
enhance enhance enhance enhance enhance
okay that is the applause of pity but I
will take it I only need a tow for a
message to me are no message at ha so
one messaging one message out if there
are two players in the area how many
message are needed to notify myself and
a notify to another player so to
messaging for message up that feel okay
and the character is always running and
it jumps when you scream so let's try oh
yeah alright so this is I'm showing off
the blur um this is something I'm gonna
try this is not going to work so I have
a blur plug-in which I just got working
there about Donna playoffs in one area
how many messages Amelia holy no
protest can hold this online udaas try
this this is not gonna work hang on but
let's see let's see enhance
enhance enhance enhance okay um so so
this is it see you notice the blur
Hannah Nate's which is really cool we
use the scaling of transform node I
won't apologize to Andy so Andy you guys
are all here but for the video I
couldn't get this to work yesterday the
trick Andy is to get it to respond to
any words you say so try that next time
okay enough you get the idea it's creepy
it's haunted right so if you smack it
like like an old TV he respond i will
just want to reflect a little bit this
was like the first Josh conf in Asia and
the second Jays conference after Jess
camp last year yeah so get like a little
subtle head movement from Emma there um
how creepy is that you look this up
actually i pre-ordered 450 + what he is
saying + 280 more that's a lot of coffee
i actually i was i was thinking that if
I I didn't have time but I wanted to
wire this up to the Web Audio API with a
beat detector and have her doing like
you know
so next year next year and my head
that's almost 650 530 yeah not on stage
is pretty hard 530 coffees that went
through that's it