hi thanks for coming I'm Rebecca Murphy
I am a JavaScript developer based out of
Durham North Carolina working as an
independent consultant buderim whoo
North Carolina not jet lagged anymore
thank God without a couple days and a
lot of drinking so yeah I want to talk
about modern JavaScript today and you
might have seen a blog post that I wrote
a couple weeks ago about this which is
kind of in reaction to someone who wrote
the blog about whether JavaScript was
kind of about to follow in the footsteps
of pearl and its its sordid history and
terrible misuse back in the day and and
in the slides in the blog post the
author whose name I'm conveniently
forgetting right now links to a slide
deck about modern pearl and this effort
in the pearl community to kind of try to
rehabilitate pearls image after terrible
terrible things were done with it in the
1990s and early 2000s and it kind of
resonated with me reading through it and
reading through the evolution of pearl
and how that community is trying to make
up for past mistakes and so I wrote a
blog post and wanted to talk about it a
little bit today at jas comp but first I
kind of want to take us back to 1900 ish
and talk about another community 110
years ago or so that decided to take
charge of his destiny because the powers
that be weren't making things happen
fast enough for them and they were they
were people who they were kind of the
hackers of the day they were the
developers of the day they this was
Brendan Eich and Douglas Crockford and
Alex Russell and some guy who's really
really tan
as these days were the hackers of the
day and they were automobile enthusiasts
these these new horseless carriages were
on the scene and they saw tremendous
potential in them both as a as a means
of entertainment and leisure and
adventure and also as a means of making
money these guys were working on some
really hard problems at the time they
were working on problems like how do we
get a light to shine off the front of a
car and they were working on problems
like actually how do we build electric
cars any day now those batteries will be
small enough that we can make them fit
and and so they were these were the
important problems of the day and they
were working really hard to solve them
in 1903 this guy named Horatio Nelson
Jackson was the first person to drive a
car across the country um this is about
what it looked like and it took him 63
days to get from probably New York to
San Francisco or there abouts this is a
big deal this was a thing like there
were guide books about how to do this
like this was a this is an adventure
this was and you had to be really rich I
don't know if you saw on that first
slide that one of these cars cost about
three thousand dollars which in today's
dollars about seventy two thousand
dollars so you had to be rich and you
had to be adventurous and you had to be
kind of prepared for everything in 1919
about 16 years later the US military
fresh off winning World War one helping
win world war one decided they were
going to try the same thing and this is
about how it went and not so well and it
took them they cut down the time to 61
days to get across the country and
terrible terrible things happen on this
part of the reason was they were using
fancy technology like solid wheels to
try to get there so in in a guidebook
from the time the the author said you
started out pretty much by the compass
finding or endeavoring to find the best
road if roads existed you could not tell
beforehand how long your trip would take
or whether in reality you would ever
reach your destination and when I
this I said hmm sounds a lot like our
lives right now in some ways we are
embarking on making JavaScript better
embarking on this adventure but when we
start out with a project we don't know
how long it's going to take to get where
we need to go we don't know whether
we're ever going to get there at all
necessarily and this is especially true
I think for you know we we are this is
rare air that we are breathing in here
we are the best and brightest who drove
you know flew our asses to Portland to
come be here for two days and and learn
what we can but I think this is
especially a problem for the everyday
users of the language that we're here to
celebrate and learn about so the bottom
line is that getting anywhere in the
early 1900's was completely a
do-it-yourself affair you really had to
be up for adventure there was very
little help from the powers that be
federal government the federal
government was didn't really buy into
this whole roads thing quite yet there
were a lot of people who were lobbying
for it but time after time you know
people would try to get the federal
government to pay for roads and to take
this seriously and they just weren't
interested individuals its individual
towns and counties and even states their
interest in solving these problems of
infrastructure was all over the map so
you had states like Pennsylvania that
we're doing a really good job of
embracing roads and paving them and that
this was important and you had states
like New Mexico where that convoy got
trapped in quicksand and almost didn't
make it so there were just huge
uncertainties when you embarked on
anything like this the guidebooks
offered advice about how to do it but
experience was really the only way that
you could hope to make it across the
country if you wanted to and even the US
military convoy in 1919 had to take a
civilian pilot with them who had driven
this road before because they didn't
trust that they could figure out how to
do it themselves so the problem the
bottom line problem was that people were
trying to do things with these new
it's called automobiles in the
infrastructure simply didn't exist to
actually pull it off and so in 1912 this
guy named Carl Fisher was out looking
for some cider probably got drunk
driving home in the dark in the rain he
gets lost and he climbs that he's he's
an enterprising new hacker and so he
climbs to the top of a pole lights match
hoping he's going to see a sign in the
dark to tell him which way it is back to
town instead he sees an ad for chewing
tobacco and he's really frustrated this
guy actually helped start the
Indianapolis Motor Speedway like he was
a big mover and shaker in the in the
automobile world of the early 1900s and
he saw that this lack of infrastructure
this lack of a system was limiting the
ability for automobiles to become the
thing that he want to see them become
and so from this moment his life's work
was born he decided that he was going to
build a highway across the country and
he said let's build it before we're too
old to enjoy it and to be clear when he
was talking about building a highway he
was talking about building something
that looked not unlike this we're not
talking like four-lane interstates or
eight Lane interstates with pavement all
that he just wanted a clear way to get
from one place to the other and this was
considered a fairly good road this is
actually a piece of the highway that was
eventually built I think this is in
ionno Nebraska or something like that
looks like Nebraska right so this was
considered a fairly good road and this
this was all that he was aiming to do
maybe pave some parts of it but like
just having a road exists and like I
said the people in in rural America
weren't really interested in putting
forth the effort to make this happen
they saw these 72,000 dollar
contraptions driving down there roads
scaring their horses and they didn't
understand why they should pay money to
try to improve the situation and so you
had these these enthusiasts these
evangelists and they were having a
really hard time connecting
with the people that they needed to
connect with in order to actually make
this happen so this is what they were
after this is about what they were
working with at the time and this was
you know this was a road nominally
speaking some places it was even worse
than this some places mountain passes
were not even wide enough for these
military trucks go down so this is what
they were working with and so Carl
Fisher got in touch with the people of
Goodyear and the people of packard in
the concrete companies and said let's
raise some money the federal
government's not going to do this for us
let's raise some money I think it'll
take 10 million dollars to build a road
across the country he's wrong cost a lot
more than that to build 3,300 miles road
even in 1912 1913 but he organized the
Lincoln Highway Association and so then
know that L was not for loozer that L
was the Lincoln Highway he organized the
Lincoln Highway Association and like I
said the ten-million-dollar goal that
they had was not it wasn't realistic and
they had a hard time raising it anyway
and so they decided that they were going
to kind of scale back their goals and
make their goals things that they could
achieve make their goals things that
were attainable and that would help them
move toward this reality of
infrastructure that they want to see
they decided they would choose a path
they would put up signs and they would
plant seedling miles out in the country
and the sea-thing miles are interesting
because what they did is so I told you
they had the concrete companies that
they had partnered up with the concrete
companies knowing that they would make a
whole lot of money as soon as people
started building roads the conquering
companies agreed to donate a mile of
concrete and in exchange towns that
accepted that mile of concrete would
donate the labor or raise money for the
labor to build one mile of road they
would build this one mile of road out in
the middle of nowhere and people would
drive over those terrible rutted roads
to come to this one mile of pristine
highway in the middle of nowhere and
suddenly all the townspeople who did
want their horses frightened started to
realize this might not be such a bad
idea after all this whole highway thing
this is where we come back to modern
JavaScript and what I want to talk about
today we need to choose path we need to
put up signs and we need to plant these
seedlings miles and this is I'm going to
talk a little bit about what I think
that means to JavaScript but yeah there
we go so the path was very was a key
part of this they what was going on is
you had all of these dis transistors
with no central authority trying to you
just doing things in isolation roads
went from one town to another one County
to another rose didn't go across states
and roads certainly didn't connect one
state to another and so this was part of
the vision that these guys had was that
if we can say this is how you get from
New York to San Francisco then all of
the services that need to emerge all of
the infrastructure that needs to emerge
around this path will happen if we can
just say this is the path so without
that path it was only by investing
tremendous effort that people could get
from one place to another and without
this path without knowing how you get
from New York to San Francisco without
knowing how you structure a JavaScript
application without knowing how you do
more than manipulate the Dom people
don't know what the heck to do so a few
things that I think that we need to do
as a community to say this is the path
number one the core that all the
libraries provide Dom manipulation Ajax
event event binding array utilities
those sorts of things that needs to
become a commodity that process I think
is going to be extremely painful alex
russell who may or may not be in here
will tell me that it can't be done he
might be right but i think that the core
needs to become a commodity we need to
agree that you know years later we have
figured out how we select Dom elements
we have figured out how
we iterate over arrays now of course
like the j s next has figured these
things out but the fact is normal people
are still developing with the old eyes
and they will be for a long time as a
community we can't I think that if we
wait for the browsers to give us the
tools that we need we are just going to
be in on hold until sometime a year two
years three years from now I don't know
where as as a community and especially
as the larger community of everyday
users we are going to be on hold so
number one the core needs to become a
commodity that means that we need to
figure out what are the api's for doing
these simple things that we always need
to do and there can be different
implementations of those api's and
that's fine but we need to agree this
these are the api's and you can pick and
choose you can get your Dom stuff from
jQuery you can get your ex HR from dojo
and you can get your rate manipulation
from Yui if you want to and andrew de
pont did a great job I hate told me not
to say any more nice things about him
but I'm still going to do it it's give
me a dirty look energy Pont did a great
job talking about a specific example of
this in function prototype bind we know
that that is going to be how it is and
it's time for for libraries to think
about adopting that even if it means
breaking backwards compatibility because
that is where we are headed and that
that sort of functionality needs to
become a commodity not a branded feature
number two we need a standardized module
system so that when one person provide
one library provides a Dom utility in
one library provides an xhr utility in
one library provides event utility we
can cherry-pick the pieces that we want
we can start to build Best of Breed
solutions instead of being locked into a
single vendor for our entire JavaScript
application and again we can't wait for
browsers to do this for us i'm really
excited about what Mozilla was talking
at the Mozilla dan dan Herman Dave
Herman when
I'm excited about what he was talking
about today that is not going to happen
soon enough we need to start demanding
this now and we need to start figuring
this out now until this exists we are
going to be locked into these silos of
libraries these silos of tools or we're
going to be stuck figuring it out figure
it out ourselves if we build roller own
solutions I'm really excited about AMD
I'm really excited that dojo has
embraced AMD I hope other libraries are
going to start to do the same I had a
great talk with Luke Smith yesterday
about why you eyes module system and how
there may be a path for them to also
embrace AMD I want to see everybody just
say this is how we're going to do it is
it perfect I don't know but until we
figure this out we are stuck in these
silos or we are stuck in these rural
your own situations number three and
kind of a part of the module problem is
library agnostic dependency management
this needs to be a huge priority for us
so that we can start mixing and matching
we again need to agree this is how we
will start requiring things and it's
kind of an embarrassment to the language
no offense to Brendan that 15 years
later we are still many people are still
managing their JavaScript dependencies
through script tags that that is not a
that is not a 15 year old answer to the
dependency management problem and yet it
is in many ways the best answer that a
lot of people have come up with so we
need to start saying stuff like this
right now if you use underscore and you
use jQuery then you have huge
duplication as far as there are rare
utilities in them and that's that sort
of problem happens with lots of
combinations where these micro libraries
are great but if there's duplication of
core functionality and then those are
bytes that were sending over the wire
that we don't need to send so we need to
start prioritizing breaking things into
the smallest rational piece the sign for
this part is pretty easy I think the
signposts they took the guesswork out of
navigating across the country they made
it so that you knew where to go you knew
which way to turn
uh when you got to an intersection you
knew were where you were going which was
not a thing that you knew before the
Lincoln Highway came along it was kind
of you asked the farmer maybe he tore
down the farmers fence to get across his
land I said this in my modern JavaScript
post I just want to say it again that
you know god bless everyone he's working
on making the next script loader because
we don't have enough in the next
templating engine because we don't have
enough and the next array utilities to
look so you don't have enough but all
these things in the world like I'm so
glad I'm not really glad that you're
writing them I'll be honest um I want to
see people smart people the people who
are smart enough to write these tools
explaining to other people how and why
to use these tools and working to
improve the existing tools I think that
it is a position of hutzpah how do I say
that he say it at him Oh hutzpah to say
that I can do this better than than
someone else who has done it before and
who is thought about before and who has
closed 50 bugs on their own project
about this thing that you're just
sorting to think about I want to see
more education education is that is the
signposts of our of this problem is
letting people who don't get to come to
these conferences understand why these
things are important and how to use them
I think it's something that we're
struggling with it's hard to create
sufficiently complex examples that are
sufficiently simple to understand I
think as a community we need to work on
that and start putting up these signpost
so that people can can know which way to
turn seething miles so we talked about
what what those were as far as the
Lincoln Highway again I think that it's
education in demos I also think its
users asking demanding from libraries
this intentional operability this
intentional interoperability that looks
so good on screen it's really hard to
say pressuring libraries to the
libraries are the people who say that
you know those fancy cars are going to
scare the horses
we need to be as a community saying I
demand this indent this interoperability
we've seen some good examples of it
already I think that libraries are
naturally hesitant about this because
there will be winners and losers some
person some libraries the DA
manipulation tools may win in some
libraries event system a win it may it
is going to lead to fragmentation but
it's also going to lead to us coalescing
around a best-of-breed solution right
now there are a lot of social rewards
for releasing new things there you know
you release a new script loader you're
on Hacker News you release new
templating engine you're on hacker news
there's a lot of rewards right now and I
think the rewards are a little bit
misaligned we need to somehow I don't
know how we need to find ways to reward
the people who are doing the grunt work
of closing the tickets and fixing the
bugs and improving existing solutions
and I do think that a lot of this is
going to be up to users to not flock to
the shiny new thing but to to respect
the work that has been done and I'm not
saying there's not a need for new
solutions there's not a need for new
tools there's always that god bless the
people who are doing if we were doing
good thinking in those areas but I think
that we've shifted Verret we're very
much on that side of the pendulum swing
and it's important that we come back a
little bit and start educating people
how to use these tools and improving the
existing tools we have seen some good
examples of this promises landing and
jQuery was pretty exciting for me
because in theory like it was sort of
the first demonstration of the theory
that you could make an xhr request with
jquery and hand it off to something that
understands the promises a b.j I don't
remember it handed off to something that
understands the the promises API that
doesn't have to be jquery that was a
huge and exciting thing I want to see
more of that I dojo just spent a huge
portion of their 1.6 release changing
their digit and dojo modules over to AMD
modules from their own custom a
dependency management system that's also
really exciting uber j/s is another
project that is kind of working on
coming up with a common solutions you
know canonic
solutions to these problems that they're
solved their solved problems we don't
need to solve them over and over again
um I already kind of touched on this
don't be Denver um and I think that we
need to it needs to be okay for people
to say don't be done versa Denver and
towns all across the country when this
when they were planning the route for
this highway across the country they
wanted to be on it you know now you get
pissed when I highway comes through your
town but in the back then that was the
most exciting thing that was happening
once people kind of got on board with it
was was they wanted to be on this
highway because it was especially in the
rural West this was going to be there
their salvation to be on this Highway
turns out all they have is like a bunch
of mcdonalds now but so Denver um once
this route was announced Denver said
officially we're not on the route but
we're going to put up signs saying that
we are and the Lincoln Highway
Association had to have a special line
than their guidebook that said when you
get to Denver or when you get in your
denver keep going straight they're lying
and again this is a tough thing i don't
want to say all fragmentation is
terrible but i do think that as a
community we need to we need to think
about how do we get on how do we get on
a common path what is that is there some
common path that we can arrive at and i
think it needs to be okay when skeptics
say you this is not helping us move
forward this is diverting us from the
true task here I think that as a
community there can be a lot of heated
discussions when skeptics say I'm not so
sure this is the hot new thing I think
we need to embrace those skeptics a
little bit more and welcome those
conversations the skeptics may be wrong
the skeptics may be right but we need to
welcome those conversations and
appreciate them as part of the larger
conversation where you're having about
how to get where we're trying to go so
it's up to users to ask is it designed
well to play with others what does this
solve it that hasn't already been solved
why is it better to use this than for to
work with something that already exists
and it has a legacy of community and
bugs and all that and does the author
know what they don't know you know just
the author even
lies what problems they haven't even
thought of because they just released
this last week versus the lifetime a
tool that has been around for years and
years so modern JavaScript we need to
figure out the path is we need to put up
signposts need to plant these seedlings
miles and let's build it the forward