usually when you're programming Arduino
you use things like C and C++ which is
what I use all the time now but as an
introductory thing when you're used to
using javascript going over to see is
kind of annoying they also have
libraries for Ruby and Python or if
those are languages that you're more
comfortable in as well the first thing I
did was make something light up which is
the hello world of hardware you make
something light up so I over a weekend
hack pack weekend I made some lights
happen with JavaScript and it felt super
powerful I was like this is so neat I
have made this happen and then the
second thing that we did is make this
sweet Christmas sweater do you guys have
the node knockout so every year does
anyone participated in the node knockout
I see a hand to applicants ok so the no
doc out is a worldwide competition that
happens once a year the year that we did
it was had 700 teams around the world
you get a team of four people and you
build a product together in a weekend
and at the end of the weekend you submit
your project and it gets judged by a
panel of judges so we built this
Christmas sweater where you go online
and you type in something and it shows
up on the sweater the most useless thing
ever but we won the Innovation Award
which is really awesome we have these
great boxing shorts that they sent us so
that was super fun and it was it was a
great weekend and I learned all types of
things like so those that thing is
called an LOL shield which stands for
lots of leds and in order for have words
go across it you have to control each
individual LED and pass on a library
that has fonts so that you can spell
words I just always assume that ok you
just type the words and then they show
up but it was interesting and need to
control each LED and figure out this is
how we're going to make the word go
across the screen so there's a lot of
stuff in the node wats community which
is really neat there is no bots day this
is some this is these are
begins that happen usually in July where
people from around the world just make
really new cool stuff with node BOTS and
share it's not a competition or a
hackathon people just make cool stuff
I've seen one really neat thing about
node wats day is that people of all ages
participate I see families I see like
dads and moms go with their kids and
build neat robots over a weekend and
demo it it's a really neat experience
for everyone I had great experience at
jas calm and robots calm the
original-jay has comp in Florida that
inspired all these amazing j/s comps
around the world and robots calm which
is a relatively new conference which
just focuses on node baths and chris
williams who runs Jay esscom built node
serial port which is the way that our do
we know talks to your laptop and so he's
really passionate about node bots so he
put together these sweet activities at
JS com node copter which I think you're
seeing a demo of later is a way to
control the AR drones from JavaScript
the AR drones work like a web server
where you can just send it commands from
your laptop the coolest thing I've seen
so far is there's a video online I'm
going to reference a couple things
there's videos on my blog I'll share a
link later but the coolest thing I've
seen is a gentleman you know Dance Dance
Revolution ddr the game where you dance
so you hooked a bit ddr pad to an AR
drone and did Gangnam style as part of a
hackathon competition which was really
neat so there's lots of cool stuff you
can do node rockets is also really
interesting they are rockets controlled
by javascript which is it seems like a
terrible idea but no one has been her
yet I don't think and node boats are
literally boats that race in a swimming
pool that you build over a weekend so
like
said you get the parody ar.drone I
haven't seen a work with other drones on
their open source and they're really
awesome you can also make your own
though I've seen some people make their
own drones that you're neat the parrot
AR drones aren't cheap so usually I ask
someone that works at a company that
owns them if we can borrow them you can
treat your laptop as a server and make
them fly the node boats on these are
made out of soda bottles and you can get
a servo and an Arduino make sure to keep
everything dry inside on and you can do
really neat races around the pool you
can find all this stuff online there's
videos on node wats calm the node
rockets is what's really interesting
they use PVC piping as a base and a hose
and soda bottles and they got some
serious height I saw them going at least
four stories high it was pretty cool and
so there's a whole world that I've
discovered is part of jas coffin robots
conf is also introduced they gave away
spark spark cores which are tiny Arduino
'he's that have Wi-Fi enabled so as you
can see compared to the hand it's really
small and you can use it to talk to all
kinds of things they're designing it to
use at home they just released one
that's actually nineteen dollars which
is awesome and you can use it to talk
two things around your home especially
things that have existing Wi-Fi their
concept is to make the smart home and if
you look at their repository for the
spark or it's really neat because it's
completely open source hardware it's
actually the best open source hardware
repository I've ever seen because you
can get everything from the Eagle files
to make your own spark or if you have
the means to produce one of your own
they're like just make one of your own
you know you don't have to buy it from
us so the schematics everything is
included in their repository which is
pretty awesome so these are some
projects that people have made this is a
doorbell
um that works outside and it sent you an
email when someone's out your door which
is pretty cool this is a word clock
which is a really cool looking clock
another thing that I discovered a jay is
comp is super awesome Sylvia she is
great if you have not looked her up
please do if you've not seen any of our
video she was the keynote last year at
robots comp her and her dad built some
really neat things and one thing that
she built is a watercolor so it's a
watercolor machine where you upload an
SVG to the machine and it paints it just
in watercolor so you can just put an
image and it'll watercolor it matches
the tone of the image exactly as well
it's really neat so she was she's super
and smiling because also she's 13 and
she's done all the stuff online so I got
to meet her find out what she was
interested in and that was a really cool
experience so then after that there's
also this show have you seen the show
it's called control-alt-delete you
should look it up I don't know if you
guys can get it here but if you pirate
things it's a really cool show um not
that I endorse it so some things past
yes constable Z's are instructables and
as you can see these things are becoming
pretty mainstream they partnered with
home depot and radio shack and other
really big online institutions to do
do-it-yourself stuff at home which is
pretty neat I think it's especially neat
because it shows how much mainstream
this stuff is becoming and how
accessible they're trying to make it for
everyone you can go on instructables and
find how to make food or how to make
some really neat stuff and this these
are all light up clothes and different
things like that the suit in the middle
is a Tron suit that I tried to make it
did not work out that great but it looks
awesome in the picture but but yeah
instructables has all kinds of things
and there everything is step-by-step so
if you want to build something in
hardware it's really detailed there's a
support forum if you
have trouble and hopefully we won't end
up like me and you can make something a
little bit better than that I also
discovered as part of that research
Becky stern she works for Adafruit and
Adafruit is a company that does open
source wearables and they also sell
parts like Arduino they do the there are
doing is that you can sew into clothes I
think it's the Adafruit flora they do
now you can also do a conduct conductive
thread so you can take an Arduino so it
into your clothes take conductive thread
and sew in LEDs and different things
like that it's really neat and they have
instructions all over online I worked
with a 13 year old girl who made a
sweatshirt that has directionals on her
back so that when she rides her bike she
can just hit a button in her sleeve and
she has an arrow on the back of her
sweatshirt which is pretty cool and they
have all the instructions for things
like that on Adafruit they make this
really neat stuff that on the top left
is makeup that's conductive makeup so
these girls put on conductive material
into makeup put these LEDs on their
foreheads and it looks awesome I mean if
you were walking down the street it
would be really startling but it looks
really neat i think that tie changes
color with music a lot of this stuff you
maybe couldn't wear to work every day
but it's really neat those videos online
and like I said they're on my blog as
well this is a microphone holder that
changes color and that's a sweet bike
helmet and no one can miss you if you're
wearing that bike helmet so these are
all the things that I've been learning
about in the past couple years the world
is the world of open source wearables
and open source things have been really
accessible people are also super nice
the first couple hackathons I went to I
was just like I don't know what I'm
doing someone next to me was super
helpful and now when I'm in a hackathon
someone's like I don't know what I'm
doing I'm like oh let me show you it's
pretty it's an awesome world I'm sure
you've had the same experience though I
had the same experience in the
JavaScript world it translates really
well to node by
it's the same attitude of let's all
learn together so this is the first
thing I mean it's really ugly it's a
Christmas ornament with a light in it I
even tried to like put other stuff with
it to make it look a little bit better
but I just figured hey I want to make
something that looks nice and is a
wearable and I want to make it of my own
so I did that and that's going to be a
while actually took me a while and this
changed color based on your twitter
status so if your twitter status and
that's on my github if your twitter
status is sad it changes to blue and
things like that and so this is the
first design of it and this is the
second design of it now it looks little
better and these cat these cad files are
online as well if you want a laser cut
flower or on or the I guess the body and
the necklace you can do that but it
changes color based on your Twitter feed
so in order to go from really ugly
jewelry to this I found some people on
etsy and I was like I need to design
something can you help me they're like
okay and I got designs from them and I
worked with them to collaborate on
something like this and now we're here
and this inside a Julie bot lives a web
server that is four millimeters by four
millimeters which is crazy so small um
and all the things that I learned from
nodebots translates here all the
bluetooth module zywert in a node bas
translates to this tiny bluetooth module
that we're working with now and some of
them some of the components i'm using
are the same like the same motor that
you use and you get from Adafruit is
what we're using and the same type of
lipo batteries is what we're using so
all of this stuff has translated really
well to doing this full time now and
we're part of a highway 1 accelerator in
San Francisco and they've been really
helpful but I wouldn't be able to do it
at all if it weren't for no advice in
general so if you want to get started
with this I want to say it's easy right
that sounds like it might not be easy
but it is
um feel free to reach out on my blog or
Twitter or anything this is what you
need you need an arduino uno and you
need an LED and if you go to the Johnny
Five repository and just look in the LED
library it's really you can just copy
and paste some code to get it working
for the first time and once you get that
working for the first time you have that
blinking light in front of you with such
an empowering experience you feel like a
god you're like I have made this happen
so I highly recommend and I hope that
some of the stuff you see today inspires
you to get started and feel free to