oh my name is Franco I'm from England
and I'm a junior JavaScript developer so
I'm kind of new to this well to trying
to prove myself in this world with all
you pros out there yeah so remember that
junior bit because in my story which I'm
going to tell you that's important yeah
so recently I made a web based like app
for the company I work for and it's
basically like very simple actually but
it looks quite simple it's basically a
quiz and the customer people just use
like they go and they use the quiz
answer the questions and depending on on
their preferences in the in the quiz we
give them like a tailored Pinterest
board for them to upload to their
Pinterest account so yeah that's kind of
cool and I'd you know I tested
everything and made sure it worked
you know I tested it again made sure it
worked so yeah drop all done right then
they put it live and they started
promoting it and I started promoting at
Facebook and it stopped working
and obviously I'm like wow I really
thought I checked everything I really
thought was working and suddenly
everyone's time you know we're losing
money you're costing us money so I have
to find out why it turns out so they
were promoting on Facebook and what was
happening was the customers were users
would find find this promotion on
Facebook but that'd be using their
phones that be using it inside the
Facebook app so be clicking on this link
which would open up inside of the
Facebook app so how many of you just out
of interest know who heard of in app
browsers all of you okay how many of you
had problems working with them okay so
so maybe it's fairly common then yeah so
it wasn't working on basically what was
happening I looked into it
the user the customer of user know what
the correct term is would use the quiz
and then it would get to the end of the
quiz and then we just reset it would go
to the start it like like the pager to
refresh and obviously I have to try and
debug this but how am I going to bug
this in you know browser you know
there's no console.log there's no like
tools and stuff that you can just pop
open like with Chrome or Firefox
probably running out of time there but
yeah so basically I had to do some kind
of like reverse engineering I had to
actually test everything inside Facebook
and I couldn't use console.log so I was
try this website on the Internet which
kind of gives you a console so I was
able to use that to test I found out
that basically this in-app browser
wasn't storing cookies so Pinterest was
sending back this a war key through a
cookie and obviously that wasn't working
because it wasn't wasn't saving anyway
but what it was doing was it was sending
a new URL to the user with the OAuth ID
in the URL so hence the page refresh so
obviously I had to like figure out state
obviously I'd need to save state now
something I didn't have to think about
before so I had to start checking can I
use local storage yes luckily I was able
to use local storage so save the data in
local storage it was bit kind of hacky
basically when the user goes to the site
I have to check if they've been there
before and if there's any data in local
storage and then reload the quiz with
you know the answers are already
prefilled so that was working got it
yeah but real pain in the ass because
every time I was testing something I had
to clear the cache inside Facebook in
that browser but you can't just very
easily clear the cache there is actually
if you go to the settings there is a
button like delete all data but it
doesn't delete all data because it was
still showing me information which you
know old information so every time I
wanted to test something I had to delete
the app and reinstall it so and out took
bloody ages as well it's like and every
time I did that
I kept getting reminded how like
Facebook app has like three out of five
styles or something or two and a half
stars out of five on it on the App Store
so probably good reason to that yeah so
what did I learn I learned that
communication so if if I had
communicated with the marketing team
I would have known that the problems
would have all the testing that we
should have been doing would have been
focused more inside Facebook app and not
outside and web-based stuff where I
could test freely in Chrome and Firefox
with all the tools dev tools available
to me yeah just in time
[Applause]