Hi, everybody. I am Ashe, I will be your guide today to describe our exploration
Learning and JavaScript World. Sorry i'm not a machine learning expert
That, but my mom is. She is an audiologist by training and she does work in digital filters
Acoustic models for hearing aids and then continue to work as speech recognizers.
I remember working in her lab one summer and people said these weird and intimidating
Then, and all these strange things on the wall, I'm overwhelmed. in
I basically didn't understand the time for it. So the process is also impressive
-A process of approaching her I can go to her and say, "I know what a cross is
Entropy is, "She's like," That's fine. Can you explain? !! "I think I can,
Explain to you and be fully prepared to use it. I have been learning deep learning
Out of curiosity, a little excited about the future, and also a sense of presence
The coming horrors of robots, they are going to consume all our work, and maybe
Our society may be ourselves. There might be the case for this matrix pod
Will happen. I have some exciting news. This is very, very impressive.
And they are a bit stupid. Like a fool in a very basic way. They are like this
May not accept your job-at least not in the next year or two-but they are
Change it, and change it very significantly. Now this is a very exciting moment
Enter this field. There is a huge amount of research and many new tools
We can use. Let's dive in. Before we dive in, I want to give a single definition.
I made this speech and a student was like, "So you say tension is like 100 times, that's
A terrible word. I feel nervous now. "Tension, if you look it up on Wikipedia, it's a number
Fields closed by some free operation. I would say that a tensor is a block of numbers.
We can have an actual block of numbers just a number, i.e. rank zero
Tensor or scaler. We can have a number, a line of numbers, a vector, an ice rink
1 tensor, matrix, square or square newspaper rectangle arranged by tensor, we can
Prisms are arranged in tensors, and they are constantly changing to become more and more difficult to draw.
So I don't plan to paint them. I just defined your tensor because I'm about to talk
About Tensor Flow, it is a state art machine learning framework. Available now
In JavaScript. So, let's break down the available, so in use
C ++ API, I am using the Pipeline API, I have a good grasp of mathematical operations on the CPU
GPU, capable of doing more operations in a, the parallel precision is slightly lower, and,
Then on the TPU, it's like a GPU, but there are even more, even crazy, computing units. it
Is Google's dedicated hardware, which is optimized for machine learning
especially. It turns out that machine learning is a whole bunch of very simple operations,
It is therefore desirable to be able to simply parallelize operations. JavaScript binding
Currently giving us CPU calculations under Node, and then Web binding is executed using WebGL
mathematics. Soon, node binding and the Tensorflow team promised to use a C ++ backend
Means that we should have performance equal Python libraries. Web binding
Performance using GPU is only half unfortunately C ++ libraries, but
You can do this in your browser, which is pretty cool. Another important part about doing
Machine learning research and development of these models is an ecosystem around core processing
The library and ecosystem we are using is huge in Python, and in the ecosystem
JavaScript is sad. And, it doesn't matter. If any Propel people or anyone doing science
Computing in JavaScript is here, I want to say your job is great, I really
Expect it, and its size community is currently small, but if
The history of the JavaScript framework is any indication that we will soon build a big and interesting one,
And a strong software ecosystem. Just the current situation is if you want to build
Your own great deep learning models and training their datasets
You might need to train on multiple computers in order to access, then you might go
Do this with Python in the cloud, but you can take these models and this is
Exciting things about tensorflow.js-you can take them and run them in the browser. it
Means you can use the power of machine learning to not send all of you in the browser
User data is sent to a provider in the sky, and you can continue to train those models
local. We can do something called "transfer learning" where we cut off the last point
Model, we adapt it without retraining all models deep
To give users machine learning, there are no advantages of machine learning
Privacy impact or entanglement surveillance. I just say "model", for example, 500
Times. What is a model? Let's say we have already happened
The world, this is a snake or it is a picture of a snake we want to model. we think
Understand it somehow. We want to simplify its version. This is the model: it
Is a simplified version of the world transformation into mathematics. So, in this case, we are leaving
Turn our snake into a wave shape. Through machine learning, we go through the training process there
We want to find a set of model parameters that allow us to adapt to the world as much as possible.
We can imagine trying different parameter sets, like different waves, random
Until we find something suitable for this snake. This is not ideal. We can sit here all day.
We do n’t have good metrics we are doing and we do n’t have that feeling
We are making progress. So we really want to find a way to pick
Some parameters, waveforms and its set iteratively improve it and do what he wants
We naturally improve ourselves and understand the situation before we find it
It fits well. We can implement a process called stochastic gradient descent. What if you are
Machine learning experts in the audience have various gradient descent techniques.
We now look at the simplest. Let's talk about a paint splash and i have no model
it. If I wanted to simulate the splash of paint, I would almost certainly not do it,
But I will treat it as a line because there are two parameters to make it easy to visualize
We need to visualize all kinds of things for them so i want to imitate splash
Paint as a line and we will become happy about it. First, I ’m going to throw
A coordination system under it, I turned around and divided these into X and Y points. I want to go back
Entering my depressed high school recall algebra to remember the equation
One line is Y = MXB. I have Y, line, B is line interception. If I choose random values
For these two parameters, I will get a line. I need-any two random values
Give me a line. This line is not very good. So, at this point, it is obsolete
These two points are good, if we go through and find that deviation
The whole set of examples, then what are we looking at a quantity called "loss". Lose,
How bad a long-term relationship is, just like the feeling you end up feeling
We did, and our model fits the data very well. This is a self-whipping machine learning ...
A common loss we use, especially for regression, and this is what we are doing
Now called mean square error, meaning we take the difference between the averages
Model and ground true squared. If we write it in JavaScript, it will
It looks like this. We can reduce the data and find the differences between the data
Our model predicts the value of this data point and the actual point, squared, divided
It presses the length and then gives us this function we can pass in-we have
Line function. We can pass model parameters here. Any two model parameters are in progress
This data generates specific losses. This means because we have two
Them, I can imagine it on a plane and say that this will be the slope of our line
-邋--and the height of the X axis it is, and, for some given model parameter set,
In fact, for each set of model parameters, there will be some losses. So what can we do
Now figure out what was the loss and poke around that if my line
Comparison ? What if it's not so fuzzy? What about higher or lower? one of
Direction, we will reduce losses, and so we have to take a step in that direction
Along two axes. We will do it again. More slopy, less slopy, higher or lower. once again
Then again. At each step, we are using losses to indicate our direction of movement. Lose
Tell us where to go. It reveals that it is a lost landscape for us. what
What we are doing is we are working on the slope of this landscape at every point,
The general mapping of the slope of the landscape is its gradient, so this process
What we are doing is gradient descent. We roll down this landscape like rain
Fall into the closest valley truth. So there are many ways
We may adjust this process. One is to notice that if we calculate the loss for everyone
In the example, all the paint, that takes a while. Is not
It will take a long time to find a line and X, Y points, but if we have a larger model,
Then calculating the loss can be quite expensive, so we might catch some examples,
random. Randomly, you might say, if you want to say casually rather than randomly,
So this gives us a random descent gradient. We may choose other parameters
The size of the steps we took. This is called the learning rate. These quantities, sizes
The number of batches, such as the number we see, or the learning rate, they are
Did n’t learn, we do n’t train them, so they are not called model parameters, but super
Parameters are a very exciting word, and I don't think the model learns them
During training, we set it manually. We train the model, which usually runs hundreds of
Experiment and stare at the chart until our eyes bleed. Ok. This is a line.
It's like a very simple, very simple feature, and maybe not very useful, right? Have
We may use it for further functional learning. For example, we might use one of these
A set of sigmoid functions. These mimic neurons. Here, neurons are firing,
This is not the case here. They go well because they-because of this they are different
Essential .. [Sound Distortion]. This is a difficult feature
A complicated function. That's it
X's math and zero. That's it. That function is easy to think of. We can imagine
Right, and-can't write a JavaScript series. The original one
Simple and easy to calculate is great for deep learning, where,
Once again, we did not do very interesting or complicated operations, we are definitely doing
A lot of people. We can imagine stacking up these rectifiers and we will be here
There are four layers, and four neurons are densely interconnected into two layers. Because they are densely interconnected,
We want to say that each neuron is fed by everyone on the second layer
Neurons in the first layer. So this one, for example, its input will be weighted
Sum inputs from all neurons to the previous layer, if you want
It, because of the shape of this function, what we are really doing is nesting if statements.
We nest if statements in if statements whose value depends on the previous output
If statements, their thresholds are basically completely hard-coded. Next time you see the protector
Created a deep neural network at google just think about it, this will do something impressive
Google researchers have figured out 50 million random values ​​hard-coded in order
Do something impressive, which is basically what's going on. The impressive part is obviously
The training process found out our own hard-coded values, however, in
In the end, what the model is doing is basically lucky with a bunch of spaghetti codes
Simulating our brains is good. Even a model like this, the relatively small one, if
We consider the number of interconnections we see that between these two layers of neurons
We have 16. For a line we have two parameters and we are able to think
About its losses. This model has 16 parameters, I do n’t know about you, but
I can hardly imagine a 17-dimensional surface. It gets worse. What we see
Disclosed here is the visualisation of Loss Resnet's landscape, which is an image classifier.
Resnet has about 60 million parameters. It means that this is a heavy approximation. These ones
People made some interesting projections in order to make it even like something
Three-dimensional. Someone said the terrible thing of living in the base
The sea will wake up one day and consume the world. They have length, width, depth,
There are several other things, and maybe what this Lovecraft is talking about. Ok
News is that you don't have to train those role models. You don't even have to think about
They or keep their loss landscape heads in your loss because you can install them with MPM! with
It looks like-of course, if you want to train those models, I highly encourage it.
We will look at a transfer example to learn where we take a pre-trained model
Then train it to do something else. It lets us make the most of all our training time
In the bigger case, in this case, image recognition model and then use it to solve another problem
space. So we are going to transfer learning, what are we going to do, this is an example,
You can mention it on GitHub. I'm going to play Pac-Man with my elephant friend Tallula.
The way this works is I choose a bunch of examples using a webcam that represents an image
up down left right. I'm turning to the left. I'm trying to get into the framework,
Try not to find a representative in the framework, or give the network a representative
Where I'm going and how to hold her feel, you can see that I don't. we
Go train it. It's low. Then, when I play, the network will be highlighted
In the yellow direction it thinks I'm moving in, we can see that it works well,
At least Pac-Man didn't hold Tallula as well until I started getting stressed
My way during training. If you want to destroy friendship, use your friends as
Controllers are a great way! Now I am eaten. I was eaten. And i am happy
The report says that we are still friends! Thing we do is what we do is MPM installation
Everything including Tensorflow. One thing we did was install Tensorflow. then we
The model is loaded. Our model you can also install MPM, this special
The model is provided somewhere. And because we are transferring, we are
Going to make a little surgical model, so we're going to pull out this layer
conPW13relu, whatever that means, then we will build a new model
Use the main input as the mobile network output that is low but not the last layer. Actual final
The mobile network layer will be, like, 200 probabilities, or probabilities
There is a cat in this photo. Probability this photo contains a cow. Probability
This photo contains a laptop and then turns on an image of whatever category
The mobile web has been trained for recognition. What we wanted before, what was in it
This image has been reshaped into some arbitrary chunks of interesting data, but there are
It hasn't been eliminated to what it contains. We will see more in a second. When
I am adding examples and this is what is happening, it is controlling the dataset being built
A set of sample data. Then we build our model. Our model will take
The output of this Tensorflow layer, it is squashing it, it will finish it
A configurable number-let's call it 100-densely interconnected relu neurons, and,
So, in the end, we will have a soft Max layer. It is a different activation function
This is useful if you want a probability distribution, so, in this case, what we want
Probability distributions. The Num course is under four years old because we have up, down, left,
And that's between all the decisions we have to make. Output of our network
Will become relative probability I hold her, left, right, or
and many more. Then we configure an optimizer. We did not use stochastic gradient descent,
We are using the Adam technique of random gradient which is better. This is a little
A little smarter about how it decides the steps it needs. We want to compile this model
Has a loss function, and the loss function is "cross-functional entropy. The reason
If we have this example, that's an example I hold Tallula upside down and say
Down, the network predicts this-which is technically predicting what I am holding
Her right-how bad is this, really? Because, like, it ’s very close-predict
Is wrong. If these are flipped, it will think it is still a bit wrong
I have a 10% chance of holding her correctly, you know what? Reply
That question is what classification cross entropy does. How much is confused by this model
Different probability classes? Now you know. Finally, we call it suitable for this
Is actually starting to dispatch things on the GPU and we get these callbacks every time
When the batch completed. So every time we have calculated our loss
If we have updated the weights, then we have taken a step. Row. To play games,
We ask the mobile web to make predictions and we run our model to give us one of four probabilities
Course, then we find out which one is most likely, we do it. That is
Parkman. That is the tense of transfer learning or flow.js. I hope we go back
Understand what mobile web we are getting rid of, and, to do, I want to load
Mobile web, load the JSON file we loaded back in the browser. Here we will see
This is a deep learning system that lets us describe the Caris model as a bunch of layers,
Here it is the layer. come on. Click. So a deep learning network that recognizes images
It usually looks like this. We have got convolutional layers and normalization
Layers and activation layers. Activation layer we know what they look like-those
This is the relu layer we saw before. Normalization ensures that our values ​​are between 0 and 0
One person, they span a single batch, which is why they call it the batch layer. convolution
Layers have configuration parameters, like many things in machine learning,
They sound difficult, but they are not difficult. Convolutions are basically Photoshop filters.
If we have a bunch of input pixels, the convolutional layer will grab some blocks
Those pixels pass the filter and output it. It will filter the filter
The entire image produces an output image. If we do not allow this, you will notice
The filter slides down the edges and then we get something slightly smaller. We can
Decide what we want. This is one of many tunable parameters. Here comes the convolution
Various shapes and sizes. This is three times three. The key here is this
The filter is the same image throughout the process and it is trainable, which means
Actually, let's see what it means. So I left and went to the mobile network. place it here.
This is what happens in each one we see many, many convolutional layers
prior to. Yes it looks like a bunch of crappy Photoshop filters because it's a bunch
Terrible Photoshop filter. The interesting thing here is that it has started edge detection
And other distractions in our vision that mimic visual processes
Core twelve. This happens naturally when you train a system that can create these
Isolated image classification filter mimics image class tasks
We ourselves realized that it started to do the same thing as we did
Do, this is an interesting validation I think of this model. So I hope this will be popular
Learning is a bit less scary, implementing it is just a whole bunch of operations,
A bunch of adjusted spaghetti codes go through a very simple but big process. our world
Full of information and our interaction comes with it
Machine learning system. The system is not perfect. They have no training
We give them the data, and like them, they internalize the data's biases, and,
Just like us, they can be pushed into the services of anyone who wants to use them. There
This proves that the neural network is a universal approximation, which means that any function you have
Give them they can approach some level of precision if you believe in our own perception
Is a computable function and then we are moving into the basic task of the world
Cognition is now a machine where we can train things. So these are not real.
These are conceived by deep learning networks whose loss function is another network. The
The two networks improve each other and learn what dreams look like.
This is not Barack Obama. This is an actual recording of machine learning Obama synced to
Obama speaks. Existing systems can produce speech that sounds like anyone
it is good. So how do we respond? With the world we cannot believe in our eyes and the world
ear? One way is to ignore it and say that these techniques are not so good
-But. But if cognition is a computable function, then our society and ourselves are games,
It turns into a robot and is very good at playing games. In the history of computing,
We see these trends. So, first of all, very important work is done on a large main frame. then
The processor was improved and work turned to personal computers. Then the network improved and we
Put everything in the cloud. Now we are seeing the tide disappear when we start
Realizing how much power we have given up to know everything about everyone,
How much danger we rely on to feed on picking boxes outside our control
We have knowledge. So the information I give you is that these technologies are not necessarily opaque,
And they do n’t have to concentrate, and we can master the power of robotic thinking
pocket. We can use them to create, not just create forgeries, but previously discern the truth
So this is just the beginning. Everything we see here today, I think it's quite
Impressive, I think it will look downright awkward in a few years
You can talk to euro bot-your robot assistant, your voice mode will never leave
Your wrist. Thank you. [Cheers and applause]. If you are interested, you can find some people here