so I'm here to talk to you about
creating custom modules using Yui on how
to once we have it how to submit it to
the Yui gallery so yui so this is a Yui
3 this is the our new Yui instance and
it's pretty much everything that we need
in order to get going with Yui 3 it's a
self-contained function that it will
return soon instance of the why up dude
and it will provide like ass unboxing
for us to where we can start building
our modules it's a sign this way so you
can have multiple why you are instances
in the same page and your guarantee that
they won't be colliding with each other
so that way you can put as many things
you want without ever having to worried
that things might break up all you need
is to include the script on your page
and you're good to go so with that we'll
talk about why you I add so why do I
that ad then you can include your the
name of the model you're going to be
writing full and then like I say you're
you get a call one for a callback
function with the why instance and then
you can start typing or everything you
need all your properties you just attach
to the wine instance your new module and
boom you're done so this is really all
it takes to create a Wi-Fi module you
can also name is place your module if
you need to by using the keyboard
namespace this case which is you know
creating space full bar and then we just
touch that to the Y instance we start
running all our code inside that
you could also do versioning so in this
case once we're done declaring
everything that we need to for our
module at the bow at the very bottom we
can pass an argument which is a
configuration I mean version this
version this number can be anything you
want has nothing to do the version of
the why object this is related to your
module and you can also specify
requirements that you module my needs so
you know in this case i'm specifying
that full it's gonna need the node
module and this was what's going to do
is once once we include foo in the page
it's going to also include note for us
automatically behind the scenes three
powerful stuff but also we can we can
make our model a little bit more
interesting by augmenting yui base so
why do I base provides a standard
template for us to create a set of
modules that are gramma consistence are
along the way but it's going to do that
by giving us like a name property it's
also going to provide us an attribute
properly it's going to extend event so
we're going to have all the goodies of
hobby custom event on our module it's
going to provide unique methods on the
stray methods are so that are very
important stuff if we want to make our
application to be a little more
sophisticated and also easy to easier to
scale so attributes are like I say it's
just going to give us a consistent API
and on the communications and sort of
like a blueprints of how your arteries
are going to be hey Ilan along the way
through your or your application it's
going to have built-in setters and
getters for us so that way and we can
modify them as we need them to do
whatever we need them to do it's going
to provide a name spacing and I'll see
ya so everything going to be talking
about you can also refer to the
documentation developer de yahoo that
comment / Yui but let me show you an
example
um so going back to our full a module
here we're going to create our class
right now we're our base class object
and then we're going to augment it with
the name propria and now my class is
going to have my name right whatever you
want it to be we can also like I say use
the attributes propri to declare all the
attributes our class is going to have by
default and then once once we're done
then all we need to do is just we're
going to extend our class with why that
base and then automatically as we do
that everything is going to be all the
preparation of bays are going to be put
into my class attributes event I'm so
that way we really have a module with a
feeling lines of code a model is ready
to go that can do all these cool things
like events right so by doing that we
get for free custom events we get bubble
event even I then broadcast them so in
this case right if we were to create a
cloud we had a class called goonie and
then we are going to associate a method
that says never say that okay and then
what we want to do is I want this event
never see that happens we're going to
fight when I broadcast say hey you know
I've been called let everyone everyone
that's subscribing to me listen you know
so here when we get our object my goonie
we can subscribe to to the event never
say die and once this guy's fire we're
going to be alert and hey you guys so
cool thing or one thing you you you want
to notice is that we actually isn't
listening for goonie column never say
die because why you are based give you
the name is spacing that we talked about
with the name attribute so this way it's
easy to have multiple broadcasting
events on the same on the page on your
module
by just declaring the name attribute
trickles out yeah you can you can
probably learn more about events and Yui
based on the documentation just want to
go over through the main stuff but I
don't want to extend tonight so once
we're done with our modules right what
do how do we include them in the page
right we you know we really worked on it
and it's ready to go how do we load it
well this is several ways you can load
our modern Yui 3 first one is by
inclusion so let's say we have the
simple really simple module today right
that all it does it just told us what
days today so if we were to use that
module then we're going to be using the
keyword use we're going to include our
two-day module and then what's going to
happen is why instance is going to have
all of this ready for us to you so in
this case I'm also requiring note so at
this point today I know our being
loading the page so i can use all the
notes all the cool knows stuff so why
don't one when it's going to get a
reference to an element with the ID one
and then we're going to set the content
to today's date really simple way to use
to load your models on the page if you
have you can compare concatenated
everything together or or you can put in
the script tag on top wherever you want
you could also pass a configuration
object when you're loading your modules
are so to the Yui function you can you
can pass a module configuration object
with the name of your module the path to
where the new model is hosted and all
and all the requirements are so this is
this Way's all of a more advanced but if
you need to you can you can use it they
prefer way it just is why do I use it
just takes care of everything for you
but then again at this point y will be
ready with everything you specify here
pretty simple gets you up up and running
through it pretty fast this day said
there's a third way to load modules you
know in your page and that is using the
Yui gallery so I'm going to talk to you
guys about the Yui gallery no not
because it's something something really
cool that I love and I'm basically just
going to show you how to be lazy we
writing your code and just use Yui
galleries to do your work for you pretty
much so why do I color you get instant
access to first class citizen modules on
modules have been written by developers
to developers are you Adam simply by you
on your way initiating them on your Yui
use statement you do why do I use and
then you pass in the name of your module
done some of the modules examples that
we have right now so we have a walk you
module we have an accordion weekly we
have a Twitter module so they say
hundreds and I think it's like 90 right
now across 100 so and it's growing
growing sofa so really powerful stuff
pretty cool it will let you load any
module that do all this cool thing but
just using Yui that use so this is
really cool this is I love it so let me
just give you a quick demo that i put
together with a few lines of code what
I've done here I have a set of tags
right here well things that I want to
look for okay and then I have a tag
cloud so i'm using this case the
drag-and-drop module which is going to
allow me to drag these elements around
the page and drop them into another
object i'm using the YQL module which is
going to allow me to do queries to
flickr all client side and it's going to
determine all the pictures that match
this talks
and then of course i'm using all the
known and an Athenia that's that's about
it so with three modules I'm able to
simply create this with a few lines of
code in five minutes so if i were to
drag iphone here no uh yeah it's just a
little slow but just the Wi-Fi it's all
of it and now is getting all the
pictures for us but yeah so basically i
also drop the tags into I mean to talk
into the cloud with the white qmo do i'm
able to query flickr and get all these
pictures that much iphone and then
presented naming the page with using the
node and the animation module so if i
were to you know i can i can drag on I'm
gonna do it because it's very slow but I
can drag as many taxes in one here and
then it's gonna do the same thing nice
looking for iphone a bluebottle so yeah
I guess people who were blue bottle
coffee with his iphone ticket I don't
know anyways but yeah let me show you
one of the most important pieces of the
code so why you I when I gonna wanna
accentuate my mom my Yui function I can
I can pass this this this is optional if
you know that you want to be using a
specific version of a module you can
specify by ah according the the date
where the module on the first diversion
of the model you're looking for but if
you don't that's that's totally fine and
then right you know right after only on
our entertainment we start putting all
everything that we need um so gallery
YQL it's going to pull in the gallery
walk your model for us and we don't need
to worry about what it is or the path or
and we just know it's gonna be it's
going to be available to us it's going
to
for us to use and then once we get that
we're easily just able to query flickr
with the talks and then once we want one
we get the query back then do something
so few line of code boom I'll you know
three powerful applications I love this
so the cool thing about this is that you
can actually contribute to the wire why
do I gallery because he's open to
everyone it's open for everyone all of
you can be running models right now and
now you can submit it to the to the
gallery so benefit your code will be in
yahoo CDN so what this means is that you
once you submit your your module anyone
can use it by just on the on the on the
on the youth statement huh this gives
you also yeah so your module more or
less the process it takes like one week
and your mother will be up and ready to
use that this will be a lot of obviously
disability and I like I mentioned before
is it accessible within your Yui that
you stay men and also you'll be
contributing I mean part of the JS
community so pretty cool so how do you
do this it's real easy just follow these
five steps you create your module just
like I show you today on you create a
white-white library account you fork Yui
3 and github we open source go get the
code mess with it use some in your
module to us then we are proven and then
we return on yahoo servers pretty cool
if you ask me so um you wanna start
going well I your love recom / gallery
and yeah that's what I really for for
you guys for today