okay hi good working Mike yes cool okay
so hi my name is Dan I'm gonna talk
about javascript in space well I got all
right so uh yeah twitter handles d
harden if you want to follow me for bad
tweets I got him so space like I really
like space I get really geeked out about
it so if I get all like giggly during
this talk it's because I think space is
so cool but I'm not really smart enough
to be like a rocket scientist or like an
astronaut or something so like if you're
interested in space and you want to like
learn about like what can you do like
what can just like whoever do so one day
at work we were having a hackathon who's
ever done a hackathon yeah lots of
people holy crap ok so there's usually
like a theme like oh we're gonna like
work on you know something with like AWS
so we're gonna like solve this problem
they didn't set a theme to this one so
we were like alright man we're gonna
like do a weather balloon and we're
going to take this weather balloon and
we're going to get it like super high in
the air as high as we can get and we're
going to take a picture the earth and
it's going to be awesome spoilers it
didn't quite go that way but it was
still pretty good so the deal is you
could just get a weather balloon and
they can go up to like a hundred
thousand feet easy which isn't
technically space but for the purposes
of this talk it's space okay alright
cool so we just needed to get this thing
up there but more importantly we need to
get it back so there's a variety of
problems with that like number one okay
we can strap it to the balloon that's
that's probably fine but like can you
drop a GoPro from like a hundred
thousand feet and it's okay maybe I
don't know and then once you've done
that like how do you figure out where
the hell the thing went you can't really
see a balloon that's a hundred thousand
feet in the air we tried so here was a
kind of a step-by-step process of what
we were working on we found a box and we
hole in it and shut up we just like okay
so we've got a box we got a GoPro we
have a scale let's just try and figure
this thing out so we kind of went on
amazon prime i was a three-day hackathon
so we kind of had like a day for the
idea a day to like order the things and
then like a day to actually do the thing
so we were we were super super pressed
for time so someone kindly donated a
GoPro that was like almost certain to be
destroyed so good for them we bought a
parachute we bought a weather balloon
they're like twenty bucks it's kind of
surprising how cheap they are we bought
some like paracord and then we're like
okay well just lap all these things
together and it'll totally work we had
to do like math which I'm not very good
at but with you know whatever turns out
the really tricky part with making a
balloon is like there's websites like
hab hub is a really good website you can
figure out like here's my payload and
then like if I put this much helium in
the balloon it's going to go up this
fast and then like the prevailing wind
conditions and blah blah below my god
you just want to figure out where the
balloons going to go and they go for a
really really long time so we kind of
did our best to figure it out so we live
in Las Vegas which is in the middle of
the Mojave Desert so there's a lot of
nothing which is good if you want to
like launch a balloon and not land it in
like somebody's yard which was kind of
what we're trying to avoid so we kind of
got everything together we did a little
research on how we were going to track
it and we came up with kind of a kind of
sort of compromise solution so like I
said we only had a couple days to do
this in four teams that do this
regularly or professionally they use a
standard called a PRS spoilers this is
going to come up later it's a actually
an amateur radio thing that you can use
to track the balloon it sends out
packets that say hey I'm here I'm here
I'm here we didn't have time to do that
because you need to actually have a ham
radio license they even use it so what
we did was we bought something called a
spot GPS it's used for like climbers if
they're you know lost on a mountain
somewhere they can push the button it'll
tell you where you are the spot GPS was
like two hundred dollars
something and we figured like we could
probably return it as long as it didn't
like plummet to the ground and explode
so we're making a lot of assumptions
here about like will the parachute work
so here's our completed spacecraft
spacecraft because it's going to space
we painted it pink so it would be really
easy to see we put a nice note on it
that said hey this isn't a bomb it's
like a science experiment we just wanted
it to be really friendly looking because
if it did land in someone's yard we
didn't want like the cops get called
here's a very scientific diagram of how
it works the gist of it is it's
incredibly not complex we have a box
with some stuff in it like a GoPro we've
got a line going up to a parachute and
that gets attached to the balloon so as
the balloon Rises in the air the air
pressure drops the balloon gets bigger
and bigger and bigger at some point the
balloon pops that's kind of your really
limiting factor as the balloon gets too
big and pops so the idea was this
balloon would go up it would pop it
would fall and then the parachute would
just happily open up and then everything
would be perfect for ever and it was our
initial process just like impossible to
just all right to the ground it didn't
work at all we tried like maybe maybe
for like a second it was nighttime you
know we did her best so it wasn't like
incredibly encouraging but the parachute
did open up a little bit so that's
enough right besides wouldn't leave
three days so we're going for it so none
of us had a truck so we rented a truck
we rented a tank of helium we were going
to start with hydrogen so there's like a
helium shortage right and we felt like
oh we don't to contribute to the helium
shortage and it's probably expensive so
like hydrogen all works super well so it
will like hydrogen will absolutely lift
your balloon really well but like it
also did that for like the Hindenburg
but you know so we went to the place
where they sell compress air and we said
oh we'd like to get some hydrogen
they're like yeah totally great whatever
and he's like did you know that when you
open the tank of hydrogen it immediately
combust and it's so hot that you can't
see it but if you run your hand through
it it burns all your skin off and
there's just like a guy sitting behind
the counter he's like but we like to go
to the desert and fill balloons and
shoot them and they explode really good
and we kind of said well we're really
trying to not explode like ideally we
don't want it to explode so turns out we
could get some helium which was really
good so we threw this sucker into the
tank of our truck and took off to the
desert on the way we were attacked by
dust devils because the desert is
terrifying we also went to a really
weird McDonald's with this amazing wall
art it's got nothing to do with this but
take take it in for a second so this is
a picture of kind of where we were it
this is just an untouched picture it
just looks like that absolutely gorgeous
Joshua trees whatever so we get out
there right and ideally you would have
some type of regulator that would tell
you like here's how fast the helium's
going and like then you can figure out
like how much is in the balloon like
maybe have a little scale to measure the
lift we didn't have any of that but we
did figure that one of the people on our
team julian he could kind of hug about
this big and that's probably about how
big it needed to be so we just filled
the balloon up until Julian could hug it
we met we measured in Julian hugs so we
kind of did the problem was it was
absurdly windy just ridiculously windy
so this balloon is going crazy and they
are ridiculously thin we wouldn't have
lunch if we had any time to actually
think about this but we kind of had to
so here's our intrepid team its helium
don't worry it's okay he didn't actually
breathe a knee in he mighta breathe a
little in don't worry about it so we're
filling this balloon we're like super
excited we drove out for about an hour
and a half we'd had at this point almost
three days of solid work we've invested
our own money we got this stupid helium
tank we didn't die to the hydrogen and
this is basically what happened so it
exploded on the ground like right here
so we got the balloon filled up all the
way that it needed to be the only thing
we had to do was let go the wind blew it
onto my face and then my sunglasses
caused it to explode so it was like over
in an instant like bang balloons popped
and we're just kind of standing there
like did this really happen you know how
like rubber gloves they're covered in
like powder the powder was like shoot
like honor it looked like a cartoon like
just powder shoots in our eyes and we're
just like okay well did we get a backhoe
we didn't get a backup balloon of course
we didn't that's crazy talk and so that
was like really sad so you know come
monday we're doing like a demo of our
like awesome hackathon we're like yeah
we we got this balloon and we were going
to send it up there we were going to
take pictures you'd be able to see like
the curve of the earth and like that's
amazing where are the pictures and we
said we got some cool pictures of the
ground so we didn't really want to give
up right because we got we got so close
but outside of the bounds of the hack of
time that the hackathon hack of time we
we actually had time to kind of get our
together so we all got a ham radio
licenses hey I didn't expect that to
happen I didn't think that would be part
of like launching a weather balloon but
you know you kind of get into it so the
four of us like learned every bike what
we needed to know about amateur radio
and like did a lot of studying and took
a test and so now we've all got call
signs and like amateur radios and we
were playing around with ham radios and
this thing just completely spiraled out
of control we forgot to bring to helium
that tank back so we lost our deposit
and basically we were in this thing at
this point like okay we've got to do
something so we figured out like hey
okay we've got our ham radio licenses so
we can actually use
aprs to track this balloon so how are we
going to do that enter project con pollo
that's a very technical name a friend
Pavel who is also part of the team
created this it's out there on github
it's just mock and I his username / gian
paolo what this guy is is a little
library that runs on a Raspberry Pi and
gathers data and handles sending the
aprs signal and all that good stuff
totally custom totally awesome so it
took us forever to like actually get all
of this together but at this point we're
feeling kind of good like hey we're
actually going to do this the right way
as opposed to just kind of throwing
stuff together for a hackathon here's a
picture of the payload kg 70 x is
popples call sign I'm kg 70 YF now
dashana there also has one like I said
we didn't expect it in this project with
ham radio licenses but you know whatever
you can see the Raspberry Pi there as
well as an array of sensors we took like
temperature data humidity that kind of
thing so we you know after quite a lot
of false starts it took like a year for
us to actually get everybody on the same
page but one day we decided like let's
just do it so all of us got together we
met up and we just kind of hacked and
put it together and we said okay let's
let's launch this thing here's a picture
of the the new and improved spacecraft
we made it really shiny which is not
only cool because it's shiny it's really
good because airplanes radars can see
that better we didn't think about that
before so it may be a good thing that we
didn't like launch in the air if you're
curious if your payloads under like four
pounds you don't have to tell the FAA
which is cool because I don't know if
they would have loved this or not but uh
so we've got our cool spacecraft we've
got our hardware it's running JavaScript
awesome so we head out to the desert
we've actually got pictures this time we
drove out to approximately the middle of
nowhere and we got our helium tank that
we now own whatever
we got a wii another thing we figured
was that if we had like a sheet maybe we
could hold the balloon down it wouldn't
go so crazy so we just kind of got all
of us together and started inflating
this thing and we still didn't really
have a means of measuring how big it
needed to be so we just tried to
remember how big Julian can hug and just
sort of went with that ended
you can see tie you down here laying
under the balloon trying to tie the
thing together you can see our parachute
just kind of hang in there despite our
best efforts and how professional we
were feeling we were totally still
hacking this ham radio licenses or not
so we inflated to where we thought it
needed to be we tied it down and we just
let it go and it actually took off and
didn't explode in our faces this time
here it is in flight and it actually
took off so we were kind of just stunned
you can look at this stupid expression
on my face like that's the look that's
the look of a man who had had a balloon
explode in his face before and can't
believe that it's off the ground have
you had also been there for the original
and was equally stunned ty had not and
he just looks like he's walking away
like from an explosion like he's like
the coolest guy ever in this picture and
we're just like ghoul what so anyway we
calculated that I'll leave that up for a
minute we calculated that this balloon
was going to take like I forget like an
hour to to actually go up and land and
so we just kind of had to kill time so
you know I let me tell you about this so
there's a website called a PR SFI if you
are transmitting a PRS signals using
amateur radio you can just type in your
call sign and you can see where the
thing is that was the other amazing
thing is that that actually worked so we
could see this balloon overlaid on
google maps we accidentally entered the
wrong character code and it's labeled as
a house instead of a balloon so on the
map there was this house just kind of
like floating through the air like up so
we're just kind of watching this thing
for an hour whatever so like we took off
the in and out because I don't know what
else you going to do like once we let go
there was literally nothing we could do
it was just kind of out there what was
cool was a couple of us had tweeted out
the link to follow the thing with the
radio tracker and we had a few
people who had seen that on Twitter on
Facebook and whatever we're keeping way
better tabs than we were so we're just
sitting there like eating burgers just
kind of whatever and they're like hey I
think it's falling and sure enough you
look at the altitude and the number had
stopped getting bigger and it started
getting a lot smaller faster so we
hopped back in the in the truck and took
off after it so what ended up happening
was this thing flew for miles and miles
and miles i'll show you a map in a
little bit and it landed like way out in
the middle of nowhere by a dry lake bed
if you noticed you probably i don't know
if you can see them on the projector
there's a lot of power lines and like a
balloon with lots of cables and power
lines or like a super bad combination so
we were kind of terrified that this
thing was like out there burst into
flames because the thing is we lost a
connection to it so this thing's flying
in the air and it's sending out radio
waves right but once it gets down to
kind of a certain altitude it can't see
any more radio towers so we could only
track it to about 4,000 feet and then
it's just kind of where did it go so we
just drove around the desert to where we
kind of thought it was we found all
sorts of cool things out there like some
weird trash and like a cool cactus and
some tarantulas but we didn't find the
balloon um so we walked around until the
Sun went down we were out there for
probably two or three hours just
wandering around the desert looking for
the stupid balloon and we couldn't find
it so I'm having flashbacks about like
the last balloon that ended super well
I'm like no we got so close like we
actually sent this thing up and now it's
just out there somewhere so we went back
back home next day and kind of did a
little math and you know we could
actually analyze the data and we kind of
figured out like well maybe you know
looking at this map it maybe landed over
here ish kinda so the next day Pavel
went out and just sort of wandered
around the desert you can see his tracks
here you're just kind of doing this
random walk and we found the balloon
we've actually friggin found it I like
look how happy he is we've lost it I
mean but then the thing is okay did it
actually like work like software-wise
did we actually like take that cool
picture of the earth we totally took a
cool picture of the earth like that's
the friggin earth so I know it's like a
grainy like 640 by 480 picture but like
epid but it's like a real thing that's
the radio antenna hanging down we didn't
position it in a very smart place
compared to where the camera was so that
was really cool like that was enough for
me but Pavel kind of helped take it to
the next level so we actually had a
video and because we had this video we
also had the aprs data and we also had
the data that was gathered by the
onboard software so using that we were
able to overlay the video with where it
was on google maps so this is available
i'll send out the link and if you get
motion sick maybe don't watch right now
so this is the balloon taking off it
took off really fast like really really
hair like horrifyingly fast i'll kind of
skip forward to some interesting parts
but the cool thing is you can kind of
see like how long it's been the
temperature we were getting what the
altitude is which way we're facing so
you can see here we're at about 7,000
feet things are already kind of tiny
fast forward a little bit more 12
minutes and it's starting to look a lot
like the google map we're approaching
25,000 feet the temperatures 31 degrees
fahrenheit we can go even further we're
around 60,000 feet and you can see on
the on the map kind of where this thing
is going and it's just really cool to
actually be able to at least I think
it's cool to see the the video that this
thing took so it got to here's 80,000
feet which is ridiculously high let's
drop to negative 27 degrees Fahrenheit
that's Las Vegas right there that
kind of area right here it doesn't look
very cool from this high up but this is
actually Las Vegas and we can take the
google map here and kind of scroll over
and you can kind of match up what this
is next to what the google map is seeing
so we got 280 1000 feet we got we ended
up past 90,000 we got to almost exactly
a hundred thousand feet which we were
trying for like 90 or 95 and we managed
completely luck out that's a really good
view of Las Vegas if you can see that
long that kind of long road in the
middle is the strip yeah kind of neat uh
we face the camera facing down it would
have been cooler if we'd had it like at
an angle but again we're you know not
perfect at this so once we get to write
about a hundred thousand feet the
balloon pops and it starts just freaking
out we had absolutely no stabilization
or any thought into that and so this
thing is just kind of like flopping
around like this and trying to take
video this is kind of where I thought
that like a lion would break and the
thing we just plummet to the earth but
it held on so you can see that it
actually fell at not terminal velocity
which means the parachute popped that
was kind of the other really exciting
part is that it wasn't just plummeting
to the earth it was plummeting in a nice
controlled manner oh that's cool that's
a giant solar array out in the middle of
the desert I had no idea that was there
it's like a mile or two miles long crazy
I was kind of wondering if we were going
to like fly over area 51 or something
and like get in trouble but you know it
appears to be okay so this thing you can
see it falling I'm just going to step
through this a little bit it's actually
kind of cool to watch it here's a really
neat and terrifying part so let me
scroll back just a teeny bit so you can
see yon cat right here let me go to the
map view because it's a little more
obvious so you see this right here those
are mountains and you see this right
here that's the colorado river when we
saw that the balloon was heading into
the mountains and then
it got past the mountains into the
freaking River that's like the worst
case scenario because everything before
that is a nice flat area we didn't want
to have to hike too much and then just
by pure freaking look it caught a gust
of wind and turned the opposite
direction if that hadn't happened we
were so screwed so the camera cut off
right before it hit the ground but it uh
it just kind of ended up there in the
desert so you can see it's kind of final
resting place right here and I'll zoom
out a little so you can see kind of how
far it went so the scale here is well I
don't see a scale but it went a long way
like way longer than we kind of thought
it would but um this is out there at
Mach and I doesn't net / neon pollo
player like I said I'll tweet it out or
something but uh if you want to play
around with it we've also opened up a
repo with kind of issues and the data
that we got from this thing so we're
just kind of playing around with it and
seeing what we could do better next time
because now that we've actually
succeeded at it we want to do it even
better so besides all like the technical
part and kind of like how cool it felt
the best part of this was just like
hopping in the truck and driving out to
the desert and like having a good time
if this had just been like we're working
on a project and yes we did the project
and whatever it would have been cool but
it was it was genuinely genuinely felt
like an adventure there's something
about like writing your code and working
on your thing and then going out there
and like making terrible mistakes and
like having stuff explode in your face
that's like super exciting I work in
e-commerce so that doesn't usually
happen it's only like metaphorical
things that explode in my face so this
was really fun I guess if there's one
thing that I would make kind of the
summary of this talk is to like get out
there and have an adventure and try to
launch a thing into space even though
you're absolutely not qualified to do
that but that's about it I can't see the
clock but that's a that's the gist of it