hello my name is sarah i'm from new york
city I'm a JavaScript developer
i'm the CEO of Julie back I'm from New
York City right now I live in San
Francisco them I studied computer
science and at Penn State University and
I've been building software for 13 years
so my talk was about going from working
with javascript in in hardware learning
more about hardware through JavaScript
and then taking that and doing working
on hard work full time and building a
hardware startup yeah so I've been a
huge JavaScript man for a long time I
started working in JavaScript about the
same time I started working in startups
I really like JavaScript for many
different reasons but because it's both
a server-side and client-side language
that's really neat I really
enjoy making the web faster and
JavaScript has a lot to do with that I
enjoy working on large scale projects
and one thing you really appreciate
about javascript is that if you work in
the web no matter what back in language
you're you're using you need to have
JavaScript on your website you can't
really get away with it without having
it so I think that really makes it
something super important to the
Internet in general oh I think that it's
been really exciting to see JavaScript
and hardware take off after the last
couple years I think we're seeing a real
revolution in hardware I think that
things like Arduino and 3d printing
makes it really accessible to build your
own products at home I think that we'll
see in the next couple years we'll see a
lot more people turning to hardware and
I think that javascript is a great way
to get started into it and my hopes are
that JavaScript and node box and
JavaScript enabled hardware will birth a
lot more hardware company
so this is a gorgeous City it's winter
in New York right now so it makes it
that much more beautiful here the
weather and the people are so nice and
the conference in general jayus comp in
general are super famous for being just
wonderful accessible places but here
it's hosted in a beautiful place to
teach the speakers are super
knowledgeable and we're learning about
lots of cool stuff they've made sure to
have a spectrum of talks everywhere from
hardware to es6 to CSS and everything in