Advancing Focus
- Glen Goodwin
folk
>> Hey, everyone, we're starting back up again.
So our next speaker, he's an ultimate frisbee
fan, he plays three to four times a week,
which is insane.
I don't know what that looks like, and he's
also a craft beer fan, who likes craft beer
here?
Cool, all right.
OK.
So advancing focus with, please him a round
of applause, Glen Goodwin!
[applause]
So thank you, Paris, for the introduction.
Greetings, everyone.
Before I start, I just want to say as I look
out into these blinding lights, look out at
everyone, that I, like all speakers who get
up on the stage, am nervous as hell, so thank
you all in advance for bearing with me, for
laughing at my really lame jokes, and for
joining me on this ride.
So --
[applause]
So let's get this ball going.
Ball rolling.
My name is Glen and I am here today to talk
to you about the most exciting part of working
with browsers, a topic that will literally
make you shout with joy and I can tell that
you are all super-eager to hear about the
stupendous, amazing, and totally riveting,
focus subsystem.
Yeah?
[cheers and applause]
Wow, that was pretty good.
I had a whole section, everybody cheer again.
But you do pretty good.
There so I know this isn't the most glamorous
thing we could be discussing today but sometimes
we have to go down into the weeds, we have
to take a long hard look at the tools that
we are given as web developers and we need
to ask, could it be better and that's what
I want to do today, with the Focus subsystem
and specifically how we interact with the
Focus subsystem programmatically within JavaScript,
so we're going to dive deep, and we're going
to ask, does it work well, does it meet the
needs of the developers?
Could it do more to be better?
So in order to answer these questions, we
need to know exactly what we're talking about.
So I want to be very clear on this point.
When I speak about Focus, I am not talking
about this.
As cute as this little guy is, we're not here
to talk about focus in terms of attention.
We're not talking about, you know, blink and
MarqUee elements.
So fields and elements is what we're talking
about, where input is directed.
When we press a key on our keyboard, focus
is the system that directs that our form and
specifically to the field, so when I press
a G here, the focus system ensures that the
G appears in the correct place.
Specifically, Focus as it relates to user
interfaces is the process by which with the
computer decides what part of the user interface
receives any human interaction.
Be it a mouse click, a keystroke or any other
type of user input, including accessibility
devices.
For any given input the computer must decide
where in all of its interfaces that input
is being directed to and once it determines
where the input is being targeted at, it needs
to send it there.
I call this the focus flow and I press a key,
it reports an operating system that a keystroke
occurred.
The operating system determines what key was
pressed.
Next, the operating system then determines
where the user is currently targeting their
input A
More precisely which window is the focus?
If the browser is the current window focus,
it tells the browser about the keyboard press,
browser then does exactly what the operating
system just did, but it does it within itself,
right?
So it determines which window or tab within
the browser is targeted to receive the input.
Once the browser has determined which window
or tab has the focus, it finds the associated
top-level DOM element for that window or tab.
The DOM document tracks which specific element
of the DOM is currently targeted to receive
input.
It does this in a property called activeElement.
Whenever focus is changed in a document, this
is the series of focus decisions at every
level.
The
active element, along with the focus and blur
methods, and the four events, focus, blur,
focusin and focusout.
These make up the focus systems that we know
and I don't want to say love, but use every
day.
That's what we're going to talk about today
with the focus subsystem.
So I'm going to take a long draw of water.
Bear with me.
So the focus subsis is tem was introduced
in January of 1998, with a few tweaks a few
years later.
And unsurprisingly, the focus subsystem hasn't
changed significantly since then and that's
fine, it's a 20-year-old API, and it does
its job.
Or does it?
So say that you are an incredibly dashing
web developer named Glen, and you need to
write a web component that wraps a single
field for entering a user name, something
like this, right?
And your customer comes to you and say they
want the "Enter" key to advance the focus
to the next field.
So our code might look like this.
And a note here: I am using a library called
ZephJS to define the web component.
It's a tiny and powerful way to write web
components super easily, you can check it
out at ZephJS.com.
So we have a customer that wants a web component
for entering a user name and that they could
reuse and it must advance the focus when"
Enter "Is pressed.
So here's our code again.
I'm going to go through this pretty quick,
so bear with me.
So we define our my user field component.
So with ZephJS you provide the name of the
component you are defining and a function
that describes the detail of the new component.
Within this definition function we define
our HTML content for our component and we
need to tell our component how we want to
handle the key-up event in the interval element.
The keyup event is what we are watching when
enter is pressed, right?
So that's our code.
That's our admittedly simple component division
for our user field.
Once defined this code is going to be used.
So by now, most of you have noticed this line
right here.
This is where we want to put the code that
will change focus when the enter key is pressed.
But there is a big problem here.
With our current focus subsystem, in order
to advance the focus from one element to the
next, we use the element focus method.
Element focus is executed on the element we
want to give the focus to, but then how does
our web component know what element it wants
to advance the focus to?
A web component is built to actively not know
what exists outside of it.
So using the current focus subsystem, we actually
have no easy way to just tell the focus to
advance to the next place.
This is the first problem I want to call your
attention to with the current focus subsystem.
There exists no programmatic way to advance
focus.
Now, some of you are thinking that Glen, you
should probably just walk the tree and you
can start at the current element and locate
the next element which can receive focus and
you can advance to that that's super-easy.
Well, this brings up the second problem with
our current focus system.
What makes an element able to receive focus?
What indicates something isfocusable?
And there are some easy elements here.
If an element is an input tag or a select
tag or a button tag or or the this was a new
one to me the first summary element of a child
element or it's content editable, except if
it's disabled or the tabindex is equal to
-1 or it's hidden or it's within a disabled
forum or it's otherwise not visible, or, or,
or, I mean there's so much I could keep going
on.
See, determining what is focusable is really
hard and even more problematic is that it's
incredibly inconsistent across different browsers,
Chrome may handle a select element different
than Firefox does, and that doesn't even begin
to take account in the are react.
They didn't account for them at all 20 years
ago.
Aria a has huge implications on focus.
It's a big part of this question understanding
it is very tricky and it's full of edge cases.
Someone made this lovely chart.
This compares all the an element could be
focusable.
I tried to shrink this down but it would be
16 stories high on the monitors if I did it.
It's just crazy long.
Of course, we can all go to the specification
and that should be super-easy to understand,
right?
Yeah?
So Section 6.4 of the HTML specification details
the focus subsystem, and here's what it says
about how to determine if an element is folk
focusable.
So I was going to read this aloud verbatim.
I suspect half of you would have left immediately,
but honestly if you just look at it, it's
complicated and it's confusing and even if
you read the whole thing and you get down
to this last line right here, this basically
says that browsers can make anything they
want be focusable or not at any time.
So trying to determine what is focusable is
not something we really should be in the business
of doing as developers.
Smarter people have tried to do this and every
single time they try to do this, they get
it wrong.
So essentially we have two problems that I
mentioned, right?
We have no easy way to programmatically advance
the focus or programmatically move the focus
backwards.
We also have no easy way determine what can
receive the focus, what isfocusable if we
wanted to read the tree.
And internally in the browser, both of these
problems are already solved.
This is just not exposed.
The focus subsystem today is mostly a passive
thing.
We can read it, we can tell where the focus
is and what it changes and we can direct it
if we know exactly where to direct T and this
is OK, but it's not enough.
It's not enough for modern web development.
This is a 20-year-old API and it's really
starting to show its age.
My web component example there, it's only
one small slice, one small example of the
problems we are facing with focus.
20 years ago, we hadn't even begun to envision
all the things we would want or need to do
with the web.
And as we continue to move the needle of what
can be done in a browser, focus will continue
to become more and more of a pain point for
developers, but I think that we can solve
these problems.
I believe we can make focus better.
We can make it more powerful and easier to
work with, and we can make focus help us do
what we need to do.
And all of that begins by exposing three simple
functions.
First, we need to expose that method that
determines if something can receive the focus.
Second and third, we need to expose the methods
to move the focus forward or backwards, regardless
of where the focus currently is.
And consider what other focussings we could
expose or add to make focus better.
What about a function to trap or limit focus
to a particular container, meaning that focus
would cycle through the focusable elements
in that container, but never out of it until
told otherwise.
Especially useful in dialogue boxes.
wouldn't a function that takes an array of
elements and does the ordering for us programmatically
be really helpful?
And there are other things we could be doing
to make focus more understandable.
Lots more.
What if we had a previous active property
or a history array to track what was previously
focused.
That could be useful.
Or a programmatic way to set an element once
the page was loaded.
That might be nice and there are probably
other things I haven't considered.
All of these functions and properties, they
can make focus so much more useful, so much
more better, we just need the courage to make
the changes.
So let's get some more water.
So like any good developer with a new idea,
I set out to address the shortcomings of focus
by writing a new library.
Obviously I didn't want to try and write my
own isfocusable method, so naturally I did
what we all do on the internet: I stole one.
The tabbable library is written by David Clark
and it has a passable isfocusable method.
But
it's passable for what I needed to do, so
I used that to get started.
And from there I added a global object called
focusManager.
And I had to ask the question, why isn't this
something browsers natively have?
Isn't this something everyone would want?
Isn't a better focus-system something everyone
deserves?
Surely there must be a way to help everyone.
So let me tell you about how I tried to change
the HTML specification.
First, as most of you may be aware, there
are actually two separate governing bodies
maintaining the HTML standard at the same
time.
We have the W3C and we have the whatwg and
each much them work on the specification at
the same time, independent of each other.
One might think that isn't a good idea and
it really wasn't.
So they signed an agreement to work together,
and they decide that the HTML specification
work is going to be done entirely in the whatwg
and we finally have a single body overseeing
the standard and everyone is super happy,
hurray, cheers, right?
Yeah!
Now, let us say that you can an incredibly
dashing but not super well known or popular
web developer and you want to propose changes
to the HTML standard and you might Google
and surprisingly enough, you might get the
WC3 process document as the first hit.
Yay, that sounds like great fun, right?
It was not.
Seriously it is an awful thing to have to
read.
Never, ever read that document.
But if you were persistent, you might eventually
find something called the web platform incubator
community group or the WICG.
It allows people like you and I to make proposals
so this sounds exactly what you were looking
for, right?
So you write up your idea and you submit it
to the WICG discourse group for discussion.
But things go really slowly.
A few people read it but none of them seem
to care and right about that time
you realize that you need to get your proposal
in front of the whatwg eyeballs.
What you don't realize is both of these processes
have the same fundamental flaw.
The process for submitting the proposal is
pretty easy, but the process for getting anyone
to look at it or consider it for that matter
is incredibly hard.
In order for your proposal to get any kind
of response, you are first required to sell
it.
And not everybody is good at selling.
I am not good at selling.
The whatwg process requires you to find, you
have to convince buyers that your idea is
worthy and that's really hard, especially
if you're an incredibly dashing but not very
popular or well known web developer named
Glen.
So you do what you think is the right thing.
You do what you think is best, and you make
a tweet and you write a few articles and you
post to Reddit and Hacker News, and you promote,
promote, promote, you do literally everything
you can think of.
But still, eyeballs are hard to find.
So you decide to take your idea on the road
and you tell the best developers in the world
about your idea.
Hi, everybody!
I have an idea!
[applause]
And that's called pandering, just in case
anyone is keeping track.
You take a roomful of great minds and you
tell them about the focus traversal API proposal.
This is my proposal to make focus better.
A formal proposal to the HTML specification.
This proposal formally introduces the concepts
of focus traversal.
In the proposal I suggest a set of additions
to move focus forward.
This includes creating the top-level window
property called focus manager and to using
that, to expose a series of properties and
methods for working with focus traversal.
It contains as previously described functions
for determining what is focusable.
Functions for incrementing and decrementing
focus.
This is the proposal that I have submitted
to the WICG and the whatwg and now I'm telling
all of you fine folks about it.
I have even fleshed out my original library
and I've made a working polyfill for the proposal
that you can use today to shim all of these
cool functions into your applications until
we can get an actual implementation in the
browsers.
Unfortunately, though, actual implementation
is a long, long way away.
As I've said, the whatwg process for enacting
change requires you to convince browser manufacturers
on your own that your idea is worthy of your
time and I can count on zero hands the number
of browser manufacturers I know how to talk
to.
But there is hope.
You.
You can help me.
I need people to comment on the proposal,
on the WICG or the whatwg and get involved
in this process.
I need people to download the polyfill and
try it out and find the bugs and help me grow
the code.
I need people to come up with new ideas for
new focus functionality.
I need people to write tests, I need people
to be involved, and I especially need people
to help spread the word.
So to that end, I am going to live tweet from
this talk right now while we stand here, it's
very exciting watching me use my phone in
public.
So I'm going to send this tweet here.
All right.
All right, so that's posted to this address,
and with this text.
And I need all of you to go retweet it and
help spread the word with me.
So it's posted now.
Please do go retweet it.
Spread the word.
Together, and only together, we can make focus
better.
We can make it more powerful, and we can make
it easier for everyone.
And finally, if you are a browser manufacturer,
and this is the best graphic I could come
up with for browser manufacturer, apparently,
if you're a browser manufacturer, or you have
any sway with them, or you know one or you
know how to get in touch with one, come talk
to me.
Let's figure out together how we can all advance
the focus.
That's it.
That's all I had to say on the subject.
Thank you very much for listening, and for
retweeting.
Please go retweet, and I hope to talk to you
all in the coming days about focus or life
or maybe just about really good beer.
So thank you for your focus.