my name is Aaron queen I created this
thing called Sami Jas which Chris
probably mentioned but it's a little
framework based on top of jQuery you can
go check it out it's pretty awesome but
not that awesome and that's why Chris
wouldn't let me talk about it here but
instead what I'm going to talk about
today
something is you're in my heart and I
think everyone here has extra extra
JavaScript passions things that outside
of JavaScript that they're passionate
about an extra code passion so one of my
passions kind of nodes really well with
the Jay s complement ality and that
passion is bacon so not just bacon in
the sense of oh man I love eating bacon
it's awesome no bacon in the sense that
I make my own bacon so okay I already
went over this I also want to mention
the on github boom quirky so if you
actually want to see code I've written
these we're not going to talk that much
about code today go to github slash
quirky I'm also the founder of this
little thing I started in New York
called code food bar and the idea behind
code food bar was that in New York at
least we have a lot of meetups and our
meetups are centered around hey
everybody let's have a presentation and
hey then let's go to the bar that's
really noisy and fills with other people
who aren't developers and we can't
actually talk but well like drink and be
like oh yeah yeah yeah but what I wanted
was to find a way that developers can
sit down in an intimate setting over
good food and have actual discussion so
I started this thing a couple months ago
in New York and we hadn't in Edinburgh
when I was there and I kind of want
other people in other cities to start
them too and then I want to travel to
those other cities and have good food so
please if you're interested in talk to
me later so quick little prologue I
don't know
I'm gonna run out of time now but I'm
gonna go quick so prologue my brother is
a day trader and he's not really
developer and we have disagreements
about certain things we're very
different was he like
you know likes money
I do like money but that's not my main
thing and we're feel like Manhattan I'm
still a Brooklynite at heart so keep
having this intense argument basically
like every time we're at my parents
house together my parents are not
exactly great cooks what happens is we
start talking about Tomatoes he is
especially in the summertime you'll get
these really amazing amazing fresh
heirloom tomatoes and I think that those
are the epitome of tomato that is what
tomato is and I tell them that I'm like
in the winter I'm not gonna eat a tomato
I'm not gonna eat this crappy mealy ass
plum tomato that my parents have at
their house and he starts screaming at
me he's like what do you mean you're not
gonna eat a tomato it's just a tomato so
the title of this talk is making bacon
making code so we're gonna start start
off from the beginning a brief history
of bacon up until the 19th century or
the 20th century so bacon began as a
necessity like truly a necessity
basically if you didn't have a way to
preserve meat through the winter you
would die so people figured out that hey
if we salt stuff and smoke stuff this
meat that basically pigs will only
produce certain times a year or other
animals - hey we can cure this meat and
fix it so then we can use it all year
round so here's some awesome historical
photos here's a guy very unsuspecting
pig waiting there and there's winter
medieval winter which I would not have
wanted to been alive during and bacon
started earlier in like other cultures
but we're talking about bacon here not
just cured products but people were in
the north of Europe basically when salt
came around they figured oh hey we can
take this thing called salt and we can
mine it and then we can use that salt to
make products that we have and produce
that we do and create during the summer
months in the spring and use it
year-round or use it for many more
months
- like I said true me means that Johnny
doesn't have to die basically they were
like oh hey Johnny you're not going to
survive the winter because we ate our
Pig and sorry okay you live to 28 years
old you're not really looking you know
it's like this guy he's like 32 it's
like oh man that guy is old but
specifically I mean we talked about
curing lots of stuff we cure produce
like pickles we cure things vegetables
I'm sure everyone here might be fans of
pickles I love pickles personally but
there's some kind of pinnacle of curing
and that pinnacle has to do with the pig
itself basically the pig is a Noble
Beast it's not a predator it basically
for it it's basically a forager in the
wild and in the inn when you raise pigs
basically you can feed them very cheap
things and very easy things and they'll
they'll keep surviving and actually a
lot of people recently have started
taking pigs as pets I don't know if
you've noticed this but they're they're
quiet soft lovable animals but yeah
that's a beautiful pig so this is a red
swaddle which is an heirloom Pig and
they're soon they're they're slowly
bringing these back and we'll get back
into that later but can anyone tell me
where bacon comes from on this pig
anyone that like someone said belly so
yeah belly belly is the right answer
that's bacon right there and bacon is a
very specific thing when we talk about
like prosciutto or things like that
those aren't bacon those are other cured
pork products prosciutto actually this
is prosciutto right here this is what a
lien guanciale the other Italian cure
meat pancetta also comes from the same
thing as bacon but instead of smoked
curing it or salt curing it they roll it
up put in a none tight package and hang
it for a month I've made that before too
it's quite delicious
but why bacon you know we have all these
other pork products so we figured out
the pig is the ideal animal because
awesome why bacon why do we why why is
bacon so important so we think about
ultimate combinations and you know
everyone's like okay peanut butter and
jelly peanut butter and jelly is the
ultimate combo sorry sorry peanut butter
and jelly is not the ultimate combo
flavorful meat and plentiful fat is the
ultimate combination and we find this
all over and not just in bacon but
obviously in in beef too if you've ever
had beef short rib slow-cooked beef
short ribs that's also a flavorful meat
plentiful fat but bacon is the ultimate
combination of the ultimate combination
it's the ultimate ultimate and what I
mean by that is not only is it not only
is it flavorful fat and plentiful
plentiful fat and flavorful meat but
it's also salt which is anything
combined with salt is an ultimate
combination and also smoke which is like
squared so chapter 2 making bacon so now
here we get into the nitty gritty if any
or if any of you are vegans in the
audience all right I'm sorry you saw you
saw the bacon this morning you you've
been around bacon enough to know that
that it's going to be there you can't
really avoid it I'm down I'm down with
the vegan cause I just like me
so basically the bacon this is a just a
fact I'm not even gonna you can't
question this the best bacon you've ever
had is the bacon that you've made
yourself Bar None I'm sorry you're not
even if it's even if it's not as good as
someone else's bacon like when you've
had in something they mean it trust me
it's the best bacon you've ever had so
right now I'm going to try to see if I
can navigate here and show you guys a
little video I don't know if the sounds
working
welcome to making bacon is there and
quit so we'll go into more detail after
this it's kind of like the video when
you're in Disneyland or something they
show you the initial video then you go
on the ride
a very chubby hand
mmm that's the taste of victory my
friends you guys are all hung Jesus
Christ torture
all right so really quickly we're gonna
go through kind of what you just saw in
the video basic step step one procure
ingredients so the only ingredients
really need are what's listed there and
it's really simple way simpler than you
could possibly imagine
you get a pork belly hopefully you have
a local butcher that can supply this to
you I have my butcher Louis Paesanos
also known as the friend and they are my
friends and they supply me with
excellent pork belly next thing you need
kosher salt which is not the salt that
you get in a little Morton's thing it's
like a big thing of kosher salt but it's
a they sell out the grocery store a
bunch of spices and pink salt which is
the only ingredient that you won't be
able to find in a regular grocery store
but you can get it mail-order and it's
like for a bag like this big like $3
seriously and you need a tablespoon per
entire five pounds of bacon and then you
did a big big asset block bag like two
gallons so step two curing so just to
tell you a little more details about
what curing is so you guys can leave
here knowing really what bacon is all
about curing and smoking are really
doing the same thing what they're doing
and I'll try to explain this in ways
that you can understand so when you cure
bacon all it's doing is over time and
over the course of a week here as you
can see is or that's by day daily daily
it's the moisture is going down so what
salt does this miracle thing is it takes
moisture out of whatever you put it on
basically you know when you like salt
tomatoes when you're making a salsa and
then ten minutes later you come back and
there's like a pile of tomato juice and
these like really mealy little tomato
bits that's salt that's salt at work all
it's doing is drawing moisture out so
why that works for curing is because
certain bacteria just or most bacteria
can't live without moisture they feed
off of it that's how they survive so
when you take the moisture away you kill
the bacteria or kill the potential
bacteria and then what pink salt does is
it doesn't even better plus it adds this
extra flavor plus
the chemical is in sodium nitrate which
are pink salt also promote the specific
bacteria that's good and prevents bad
bacteria so step three and this is the
hardest part
you wait for a week right and that's a
really really hard because you
see it in the fridge and you keep
turning it over and they're like oh my
god this is gonna be so good but you
can't touch it obviously it's raw you're
not gonna eat it raw and the step four
is smoking or baking so if you want to
smoke at home you don't need a smoker if
you have a kettle grill you take a
kettle grill you put some charcoal on
one side put a drip pan underneath it
put it down let it get to medium heat
put the cover on an hour and a half
later you check it check the temperature
when it gets up to 150 perfect you take
it off and it absorbed all that amazing
smoke from the charcoal grill but what I
do at home too and I don't have a
charcoal grill handy is you just put in
an oven at the lowest temperature
basically you're bringing it up to
temperature that's all you're doing and
then Step five isn't you enjoy the
out of your hard work so the things you
can do with your bacon you you can
imagine come on like what do you do with
bacon you make BLTs you Clarence without
here's one that I get from my own life
and I suggest you do yourself if you
have bacon you're like hey buddy I know
you have all those home brews that
you're making because I know a lot of
people do home brewing it's like here I
will trade you this chunk of bacon for a
six-pack of your homebrew another guy's
like oh dude it's like old school
bartering it's pretty cool and basically
you add it to anything and it's awesome
eat it love it so alright we're gonna
step back a brief history of bacon part
two so this is where we get into
something that's very true to my heart
and probably true to probably true to
every vegans heart too but basically
winter ain't gonna kill Johnny anymore
we're in the modern times we have
refrigeration you know we don't really
need to cure anything so curing things
becomes a way to add flavor and imbue
something that we think will make our
food better it has nothing to do with
actual survival so when you get from
making bacon as a way of surviving - oh
it's just gonna add flavor hey let's see
if we can shortcut that entire system so
how do you systematically make big in
production cheaper it's really easy
actually
first you feed the pig surplus corn in
America okay we have this ton of corn
pigs don't normally eat corn but it
let's feed it to them and everybody's
like oh this is awesome we have all this
extra corn and we don't know what to do
with it it's not human grade humans
can't eat it let's just feed it to our
animals and holy crap they're getting so
fat this rules
and we'll see why that's not the case in
a second but anyway then you also breed
the pigs for size and production so they
also realized oh hey we can crossbreed
get rid of these heirloom breeds that
sometimes produce like really a lot of
fat and sometimes are really a lot of
food and sometimes they don't let's just
breed this perfect pig that will produce
the perfect amount of fat and the
perfect amount of meat and we'll just
it'll be really cheap for us to produce
third yeah mass-produce the flesh and
the fat and okay so this is the part
that's gonna freak the out of you
guys I didn't know this until like three
weeks ago or a couple months ago
basically the bacon that you eat that
the Hillshire farms bacon that you get
at the grocery store
it hasn't been cured it's been cured for
maybe 40 minutes an hour two hours what
they do is they take the pork belly
which come off this factory line you
know don't even imagine the kill floor
it's not even it's not good right now
but you get you get the bacon you get
the pork bellies cut them into perfect
squares right with a machine that's just
like a cookie cutter and then you take
this giant imagine this giant hypodermic
needle filled with salt and water and
other spices and let's just inject that
into the pork belly and all it does is
it it's like oh here we had this thin
pork belly because we had this pig that
we were feeding on corn so it's not
producing that much unnecessarily a good
amount of meat hey if we inject water
into it oh look it's like that big it's
awesome and we don't really need to cure
it for you know for next Adam necessity
so we're just injecting salt water into
it brine and preservatives to make it
last longer so that's where it comes
down to this cook bacon should not look
like that that's the bacon that everyone
here is probably familiar with today's
bacon was actually really good I was
really impressed
but cooked bacon right you put it in the
pan or the ho sheriff arm is baking you
put in the pan ten minutes later it's
like this thin and really crispy that's
all that water
they inject it into it just seeping out
when you get a real pork belly and you
chop it yourself and you everything
yourself
it's a thick beautiful slice and you
bite into it it's like a piece of meat
it's like a deli slice not this watery
ass right it should look like that
that's the bacon that I made that day
Brian Mitchell who's taking pictures had
a bite of this you can go to him later
and be like was that bacon good all
right so where do we go from there where
do we go from this point where were mass
producing bacon so at some point someone
realized that the mass-produced crap
doesn't taste good and what they did was
they kind of started this movement this
underground movement to to really get
bacon to back where it should be and not
just bacon but all food there's another
slide just so you guys I'm just keeping
you on track so names you should know in
the slow food movement I don't know some
of you might know they some of you might
not but write them down or check out
slides out later and do some look them
up on Wikipedia it'll be good Alice
Waters creator of the Chez Panisse in
San Francisco she also wrote a bunch of
cookbooks and she was kind of this San
Francisco founder of like hey we're just
gonna grow our own food and use it in
our restaurant Michael Pollan I don't
know if you've ever read The Omnivore's
Dilemma
but a lot of what I am talking about
here today I learned from that book and
a couple other books Carlo Petrini
he is actually the Italian founder of
the slow food movement which is an
actual thing an actual organization but
now has worldwide locations dan barber
okay you go home today you're gonna go
home everyone watches TED Talks right or
most of you guys come on we're all smart
people we like watching them on the
train whatever
Dan barber did to TED talks I just
wanted some food conference that they
have on Ted calm and then he did one
this past year and it's amazing if you
if you're interested in food at all go
talk to him
Michael Ruhlman okay Michael Ruhlman
Douglas Crockford Michael Ruhlman
Douglas Crockford is to JavaScript as
Michael Ruhlman is to charcuterie
you know JavaScript and good parts
Michael Ruhlman book wrote this book
called charcuterie which is like the
manual he did all this research and met
all these guys and all this research to
find what how do you
these old-school meats and how do you
cure these old-school meats so those are
two guys they're like brothers once ones
got kind of like a Dan Brown thing going
on and you know good ol crock-pot anyway
so we're going to take it back a little
bit and get something maybe you guys are
actually interested in because I've been
boring you about bacon for a while but
the Heritage and slow food movements
have kind of a lot of tenants and things
that they kind of talk about all the
time and three of those that I bring to
I bring to heart our sustainability
respect and knowledge so we're gonna
talk about those in terms of code and in
terms of also in terms of food but I
think we'll go back to what those
actually mean but just think about those
for a sec so but what I wanted what I
really wanted to come here and talk
about when he asked me to do bacon talk
it's like I gotta put some kind of
message in there I got to leave you guys
day one with some kind of message that's
not just specifically bacon related so
the message I want to leave with you
guys with is about how can we use these
things that are principles that have
made the slow food movement and the
heritage food movements so powerful in
this day and age and bring them to our
own lives in our own work because we're
not all shark routiers
so we can't always use them day to day
but how can we use them in the code
world so what I want to tell you is that
JavaScript is the pig of programming
languages they're like what does that
even mean
javascript is the pig because of these
three things which are all really the
same thing if you read them really
carefully but basically javascript is
it's versatile meaning like you can it
has so many uses and it's also I mean I
think JavaScript is a noble beasts in
some ways it it won't hurt you
necessarily it's only its cage it's it's
it's maybe its producers like our
friends at MSFT who will who will you
know make it not so good and make it
hurt us but or give us the will give us
some kind of disease anyway so anyway
it's it's got many many uses now we know
it can be used on this
xiety can be used on the client-side it
can be used basically anywhere bacon
lardons as I said trade for beer
whatever so more more JavaScript here so
what I was saying I want to copy kind of
the core beliefs of slow food and bring
them into JavaScript so what's what does
that mean sustainability so
sustainability in in slow food terms
means means like how do we how do we
treat the animals and how do we treat
the production of the food in a way
that's not gonna kill us or not gonna
hurt us 30 years down the line in terms
of like bacon it's as we're talking
about it's you know injecting pork belly
with brine isn't gonna do us very good
thirty years from now in America being
the most obese nation in the world right
it's not doing us very good and how do
we and also you know feeding them corn
that's not sustainable corn is only
cheap because of this crazy surplus what
we have how do we make something
sustainable so in terms of code in terms
of JavaScript sustainability is not
equal to unit testing in the Ruby
community there's this really weird
thing I'm a Rubeus by day two for the
most part I do a lot of JavaScript but I
got into JavaScript primarily through
Ruby in the Ruby world there's this
weird thing where everybody it's like
this big circle jerk of unit testing
where everyone is constantly saying and
I'm gonna get some chalk and for
that but but but that's cool you guys
are my bros right basically everyone's
like the only way that we can make code
that last ten years from now is if we
you know write user stories and test it
and have this automated test suite then
we know that you know ten years from now
or five years from now when our app is
still running because it's gonna be
running in ten years here right we have
our unit test and we can prove that it's
working and that's not sustainability
sustainability is about same code and
same developers and that means writing
code that's readable writing code that
people actually like working with it
means treating developers like you would
treat that heirloom pig or that Wagyu
beef cow and you feed them
and you feed them a lot of delicious
grains and you treat them really well so
that in the end they will produce some
really awesome code for you
it also means coding for fun and coding
for the sake of code and not just coding
for the sake of you know these five
lines in this JavaScript function are
gonna make me a million dollars or
Twitter's gonna make me other dollars
it's not sure that's gonna put the bacon
on your table but it's not gonna make
you feel good at the end of the day and
to be sis to have a sustainable
environment where we're constantly
working on JavaScript and constantly
looking at code that code has to be fun
there has to be something that we find
in it that's actually fun and that's one
of the reasons I love this conference
because everyone has such a good time
and not because not because it's well
factored or saves time we're not just
talking about like writing code
generators or doing something like that
we're talking about really thinking
about what this code means for us down
the line coding for glory
you know we're coding because if you
code enough and then also have an
obsession with cured foods you might get
to speak at Jay s comp right so there's
some kind of glory in that - respect -
and so in terms of this slow food
movement respect you'll hear if you
watch a lot of Food Network these days
or read Gourmet magazine rest in peace
or read Cook's Illustrated you'll you'll
hear a lot of this thing where they keep
saying respect for ingredients or we
have respect for ingredients respect for
the local ingredients and our respect
for our food and we respect the
traditions it's constantly the word
respect is thrown around a lot and what
that really means is I'm gonna take this
beautiful piece of bacon and I'm not
going to cover it in general Chow sauce
that's what it means really it means
here is this beautiful thing that I've
worked really hard on and I'm gonna put
it out there and I'm gonna respect it in
a way and treat it in a way that that it
deserves
basically so for a code that means code
is a craft so if I'm talking about being
an amateur shark Kuti a
in my code life it means and wait all
right rewind when you go on my github
page and you start looking at all the
crappy Ruby code I've written and you're
gonna be like not every piece of code
you're gonna put out there is going to
be this most beautiful thing that's not
the point the point is is if you treat
the code that you're writing as this
operation as this process of making
something that will last and making
something that you're proud of in the
end of the day as like a craftsman then
then that that's what we need because
otherwise we're all going to burn out or
we're gonna keep putting crappy code out
there so treat your projects like you're
occurring bacon you have to do it think
about it put the effort into it marinate
it cure it wait a little bit come back
cook it up it's going to be good which
means you know not and that means not
only like I said respecting the code
itself and respecting the code as a
craft but also respecting the pace of
you're writing a code don't just throw
some crap out there because you need to
have this latest open source thing in
out there it's cool if you want to write
a router for node or a framework for
node and put it out there that's awesome
I think we should all write node routers
but in the end of the day if you're not
if you don't have respect for the code
itself and you're not going and you're
not treating the project that you've
created with respect no one's gonna
respect your code either and the way the
open-source success and an open-source
to have a community to build a community
about around your project is being a
code craftsman it really makes a
difference and I think Ryan of node is
like the epitome of code craftsman where
he spent so much time thinking about
every single detail of the project and
rewriting it and rethinking it and
turning it and making it awesome and
when it comes out it's going to be the
most awesome bacon you've ever had but
as spider-man said or spider-man's Uncle
Ben Uncle Ben said with great power
comes great responsibility so if you're
treating your code as a craft and you're
putting all this stuff out there just
like in the
world if you don't respect the code and
you put a lot of code out there that
doesn't really mean something at some
point someone's actually going to use it
and then you're gonna have to support it
that's how it is starting on the day of
github when you put everything out there
someone's going to use it and file an
issue on your project this was just a
joke
and that's that's your problem you have
to be responsible
so probably the key point that I wanted
to you guys take away from this is the
idea of knowledge and knowledge of food
so I just waxed on for about 40 minutes
about bacon and what the hell is up with
that
I gained that knowledge because I cared
about it and when I looked at the when I
looked at the bacon and I was eating
this food I was like what makes this
good and what makes this what it is in
the food world this is knowledge of not
only the food and the process itself but
knowledge of the past and knowledge of
what's come before you because there's
this guy in New Jersey right
hypothetical situation comes back one
day at his house you know he was raising
some pigs in his backyard
one day he kills the pig and forgets
that he killed it and just leaves in his
backyard and he also happens to live
near a salt mine this is actually the
story of how bacon was supposedly
created in France by the way and he he
just leaves it there and it falls into
the like rolls into the salt line and
then ten ten years later are not tending
to ten ten weeks later he comes back and
it's like wow huh
this pig doesn't have maggots on it
maybe I'll eat it any good that's that's
the that's the story of bacon ten weeks
later so and so anyway the point is is
that if a guy in New Jersey did that
yesterday or you know he he did it
because he had no idea what he was doing
not because it was an accident so when
you discover when I discovered oh wow we
can route on the hashtag and make single
page applications I was a idiot
because people had done this for so long
already and I was just like a noob who
figured this out and then found a good
way to to wrap it up in a project but
the point is is if you really want to be
a talented open source developer and a
time to develop
in general you have to have knowledge of
the past so and this also means never
code something without learning
something from it so if you're gonna
write that node router and you're just
basically copying and pasting code but
then changing a couple lines because you
think it's better and you don't learn
anything from it then there was no point
of doing it originally this needs
sharpen your butchers and I sharpen your
mind is your butcher butcher's knife
knowledge is the tool not a tool the
tool that will get you a the job that
you want which will make the projects
that you want to do and more
specifically know what you're doing in
the code world know what you're doing
when you're using other people's tool
tools so if you're using node look at
the source code read it if you're using
Sam you look at the source code just our
jQuery especially jQuery source code is
pretty readable read it think about it
know what's going on in there because
that'll only make you better for it so
here's here's the here's the final
thought I want to leave you it so if we
say that the pig our JavaScript is the
pig of the language world what is the
bacon of the JavaScript world and I
think hopefully we'll figure that out
this weekend it's not a one-time thing
it's not like bacon done JavaScript's
over it's more about constantly striving
to make a project and make code that you
feel is worthy of this of this
description so that's it thanks you guys
for listening I hope you had a good time