okay so guys I'm here to do a lot of
different things and to talk about stuff
that's kind of comfortable so you're
going to bear with me but I'm going to
do my best we lie on iso 10x programmer
we don't usually think about this
concept what it actually means it's a
hero myth it's a way of whining to be
it's aspirational it's the thing we all
want people to see us as the person who
for width for who which if we weren't
there everything would fall apart but
there's a downside to that even subsec
as amazing he is as many modules is made
means very little without the rest of us
to use them we forget about that we feel
bad when we don't measure up we feel bad
when we aren't the person we want to be
we let that be used as chacos or
something to make us feel like we or
lesser because of it I see a time and
time again especially with people who
aren't as old as we are as people who
are in their 20s or 18s people like my
friend who's an iOS developer working
12-hour days for an internal deadline
for two weeks straight I'm going to tell
you what I told him your pleasure
treating you like you need to quit
either by malice or just a mission they
are letting you burn yourself out it's
not healthy there's no reason for it but
we let it happen time and time again
because we can just forget about what's
actually important
programming is neither a race nor
marathon is about being first it's not
about being the fastest about getting it
done that day it's about a lifetime of
training it's about meditation on it's
about thinking about how to get better
over time over the long run because
we're in this till we basically can no
longer do it one way or another and
programming is not just something you do
with your mind we forget but it is body
it is something that we do with our
hands it takes effort it takes work we
don't want to always think about we
don't want to realize that it's not just
some something that comes from here it
comes from everything and it's hard on
the body it's hard on the eyes it's hard
on the mind in ways we don't always want
to admit the fact that we tie ourselves
up so much that we can't do other stuff
that we enjoy of course we're cheers
come we know all this we're better than
that Matthew we have learned these
lessons Chris Williams one
of the best brightest people i know does
more than i can fathom at times but the
same point guys he's constantly stressed
out he's constantly overworked he has
back issues he complains to me about
being paying having time to do exercise
no matter how awesome you are you can
become very myopic about what's
important to you to the point where your
health can deteriorate we think a life
at home and work we bring work with us
we use the computer for fun instead of
actually doing something else so that we
never actually get another mind frame
and we're very good at deceiving
ourselves that this is not actually
happening and we hate admitting it we
hate vulnerability to the point where we
would rather just not omit exist at all
we say to people fake it till you make
it take on projects that you are not
comfortable with but never admit to that
never ask for help well that's it goes
alone stack overflow and it's anonymous
so I am breaking a lot of rules right
now people I might be a bit crazy about
ask you right now to let me be very very
vulnerable for you for the few people
who do not know me my name is Matthew
Bergman I am a rubios masquerading as a
node.js person but I work in a small
console's II called Nova fabrica it's a
ruby shop and some of you might know me
from Cascadia jas where I gave a talk on
cryptography the awesome hat guy and I
have ours you might want to get up you
might want to come closer guys I'm sorry
there should be a stage but there isn't
so we're going to work with what we have
but this is my talk ours i stands for
repetitive stress injury this injury
that happens over a long time from
repetitive from the repetitive from rip
evan movement or position and we're
talking years many years ours is not
something that just happens because you
were typing weirdly for a few days it
comes from a lifetime of choices and it
doesn't happen just from work your body
doesn't suddenly change because you're
no longer at work occupational hazards
are just hazards that happen occupations
I don't overwork people I work 20 to 30
hours a week you can look at my invoices
you can ask my boss but this still
happened to me because life builds up
how we relax with our TV or video games
I probably played 12 hour days straight
with persona 4 I probably done more
damage just from how I relax and from
actually working on code or drinking at
bars not really looking how I sit down
or just life a friend of mine asked me
of working in bed it's bad it is sadly
it's very bad but those choices we make
and those choices happen whether we
realize it or not you cannot look at a
person and know that they're healthy
move you can't will get yourself and
know that you're Oh see this happens
we're doing a live folks you mess up I
thought I took care of myself I did
because I worked out I exercised I
quantified it but as I said before we're
very good as sieving ourselves very good
because I thought it was half it's not
you can't look at a person know that
they're healthy you can't look at
somebody and you can't look at yourself
and know that it comes from taking
meticulous notes because just because
you feel good today doesn't mean that
tomorrow you're going to feel good in
2013 my hands began to feel different it
began as a small ache for my elbows to
my pinky and ring fingers
the third but it didn't go away I
started to stress out about it and when
you stress out you start researching and
that only leads to one thing on the
internet cancer or in my case diabetic
neuropathy because my grandfather's are
diabetic as ones my biggest fears I'm
terrified of getting it one day it was
our cubital tunnel so I went with the
worst option because that's what you do
I stress myself so badly that I start
having other physical symptoms good
stress can do that I got pain in my legs
my mouth felt fuzzy I thought be able to
sleep I was breathing heavily all the
time while I went to my general
practitioner I was in so much pain I
couldn't walk and that was
stress-related but he thought it was all
stress so he told me to relax it gave me
an ties I hills and sent me on my way I
did feel better not perfect but I wanted
to believe so I let things rest and I
had a trip to go on I was going to know
copy you she has copy you I was going to
have so much fun Oh God but Don I got
off the plane my arms were numb and
burning there was a few days before the
conference so I do what is probably the
stupidest thing to do in that I continue
to type I continue to work working
through pain is stupid it's always
stupid but you don't want to believe
it's going to get worse so you continue
and the ping does get worse I start
leaving events early and people who know
me know me I party late I was out to 4am
last night I'm so here doing this and I
will be out tonight again at 24 am
at no time for you I was leaving at
eleven running bass trying to not die
from the pain and pain is really
draining it makes you very aware of the
small choices you have to make
throughout the day like budding shirt or
just opening up doors because it's
mentally taxing you only have so much
any energy throughout the day and you
use it up I'm gonna have to continue if
I forgot and it's depressing dude you're
good please continue with the slides you
didn't you when I got to jjs console try
to control myself with it being
something simple like golfers elbow or
ten nights because they'll sound simple
and can be remedied in six weeks but
there still are sigh they're still
problematic they're still hard on the
body of course I keep using this term
without really telling you what it means
bars sorry RSI is an umbrella term
includes a lot of different syndromes
like runner's knee Qbert ah no focal
dystonia and of course carpal tunnel but
carpal tunnels just one when we focus on
just that one syndrome people can forget
about the other ones and ignore the pain
that might be having other parts of
their body hearth I is just it's micro
traumas to the ligament and muscles it's
information of the nerves and the
tendons it's scar tissue building up its
impingement is entrapment it's your body
not working correctly
parts are overworked parts and
underworked the pain moves I used to
wake up in the middle of night fearful
that my shoulders would not be good the
next day instead of my arms because it
would change I wouldn't know how to deal
with it moved sometimes because it'd be
different it wouldn't be what I wanted
because the pain is just a symptom and
your body is wrong and you know it's
wrong because it doesn't move the same
way as you know it's not just the pain
just making it you're truly scared by
the time I got back from jazz calm I was
in so much pain I couldn't look at a
computer correctly but because i was
still in denial i'm a moron so I
continued to type if you don't take
anything else from this talk take this
working through pain is always stupid
don't do that it took me an extra two
weeks to take off time and by that point
I couldn't sleep at night because I had
so much pain in my neck I didn't know
what to do I remember just actually
canceling on friends app to try to get
to the subway being so much paying for
my fingers I couldn't walk correctly and
it's running a shower at night and
sitting down and not knowing how we go
on for another minute let alone another
hour a day a month a year this I'm
suicidal I don't know what I'm going to
do I started thinking about getting my
grandpa's instantly medicine to stop my
heart cut my throat with a knife jump
off a bridge
it's so easy to get their people much
easier than you think when you're really
pushed and you don't know what you're
going to do I tell no one I tell no one
because I rationalized seeing that
psychologists won't help because the
pain is what's causing my depression and
the pain is real is not an emotional
problem that can take another tack to
it's not going to go away I don't tell
my friends I don't tell my boss I just
try to deal and go see doctors and that
was a mistake I sort of talked to
somebody but I didn't because we're
afraid of vulnerability were afraid of
meaning they were not good enough and
the bathrooms don't really help because
you're just a bunch of ailing tap tests
you're not something they easily
understand because they're just human
there there fallible they're just like
us when we're trying to bulk something
it's not simple it's not easy but we get
so frustrated when they don't know
eventually I have two MRIs dimensions
the three months into the process three
months I still kind of grimace when I
think about how long I was in pain the
second one tells me that I do have a
thickening the omen earth which is
cubital tunnel so my original diagnosis
so many months ago was right I saw a
physical therapy it helps a bit but only
a bit because it's only six weeks long
six weeks is not enough to recover from
all the damage at the end of it I'm
still in a lot of pain and i'm still
depressed and life goes on while you're
dealing with all this and november i was
giving a talk at cascade areas
some of you might have saw I did a
really good job I was dying through that
talk people I nearly quit three to four
times i called up saying i can't even do
the slides i was in so much pain from
trying to just type it out I'm happy I
did it but I'm not going to tell you
what's easy because it wasn't I
literally did not know how I was getting
through it at the end of the talk I took
two percocets basically just sat down on
the floor because I nearly was spent
that day so I decided I needed to be
more active and how I was dealing with
this because I kept waiting for other
people to tell me how I needed a deal I
first changed how I was working my old
work station it was a cheap ikea desk
and a really really cheap chair terrible
for positioning terrible for back sport
got from a friend for fifty dollars used
it for five years TV netflix coating
everything i did at that desk it wasn't
helpful my new desk is much better it's
a standing desk now standing by itself
is not that great it's the movement that
makes standing good because changing
position is what's necessary for blood
flow to keep muscles from being coming
stagnant cuz steady by itself is very
bad it causes joint compressive
thrombosis spider veins I know that
sounds out that much but I worked way
too hard on these legs to let them
become ugly with little spider veins and
you still get that posture you can still
slouch you can still cause a lot of
damage it's because they're standing
doesn't mean you have good posture of
course we use this without understanding
what good posture actually means good
posture is neutral spine it is bone over
boat it's your rib cage over your pelvic
bone over your kneecaps over your ankles
and it's not stagnant you need to move
you need a stretch
it's not just what it's what you go back
to because just standing up straight
with your chest out not moving for a
whole day would be awful it needs to be
dynamic I also start going to the gym a
lot an exercise is very complex
especially for people who don't normally
exercise I spent a lot of time
researching going over the diff stuff I
needed to learn by posture hours and
hours and the things I think are most
important is that you need to get a
trainer you need to go in with a game
plan a need to videotape yourself
because you do not have the body
awareness that's going to allow you to
do proper form and you can go with the
buddy but you really shouldn't because a
buddy is extra cognitive load it's extra
stuff you need to think about because
you need to match up your schedule I
started going them to my gym because of
my friend Anisha she has a gym right
next to her house and she told me that
we could be buddies and exercise
together every time I'm a 20 minute walk
from there guess how many times we
worked out together 0 you cannot wait
for somebody else to make you do this
you need to decide that this is
something you want to do and I'm still
learning and it's weird to be a job now
because I can talk about protein powders
and how to exercise correctly and all
this other stuff that we don't always
think about as hard because I get a lot
of pushback a ton so people don't want
to hear this don't want to think about
any of this but i found that progression
is key that you need to get stronger
that you need to think about that and
you need to get your pain to go down if
you're dealing with our zilog I and that
you
need to understand your body that you
cannot work through pain that is bad you
know what difference between the soy is
when I look at and tear you need to
respect that boundary and that you
cannot become intimidated I don't care
how you indentify if you're trans you're
female of your mail if your gender queer
this is for something this is something
that everybody should be doing you
shouldn't worry about poking up you
should be worrying about getting healthy
and strong I also start doing yoga if
you can't tell I do a lot of yoga I do a
ton of yoga and this is because
it's really good for ours I pain that
our Pilates because it forces you to
work the entire body not just the pain
points you really have to do everything
because it's your body not working as i
said before when your body is out of
alignment you need to work on the total
structure I hear you guys I really hear
you I do not have time for this I hate
exercise yes yes I hate an exercise
before this it's been six months now and
I might be doing this in front of you
but guess what people I hate exercise
still I rather do anything else but the
point is that you do it for the results
you do feel better while doing but like
I'd rather play a video game not going
to lie to you I goin up Dino this is not
going to change but I do this because I
feel better not perfect it's been nearly
eight or nine months i'm still not my
base level but i feel a lot better now
i'm able to go out i'm able to feel
normal I measure my I measure my sis
Kassadin small victories being able to
open doors without thinking about it
sitting in chairs and not being in pain
resting my arms on a table I know that
sounds so sap is true for months I
couldn't do this i would go to
restaurants and have to sit like this
because i was in so much pain when i
would rest this
apart on a table it was horrible and
made me feel really awkward because I
couldn't just like be normal I was like
being really stiff and weird but I had
to deal with it I found out the pain is
a really good motivator really good we
got it got me to like gain 10 pounds of
muscle but dame by itself is not useful
you need hope hope that the pain is
going to improve hope that you could do
more that you can do today because he is
great metal Vater but when you only have
pain you just spiral down to despair and
that's not fun we're getting older we're
getting really older and you have to
treat your body with respect you do the
apple tree with respect because if you
don't it's just going to get crusty and
old and nobody likes that because we're
not immortal maybe sub seconds I kind of
feel like the modules he makes my pee
vampirism like every time he makes a
module he like loses three days but
there I wish I could tell you there was
a shortcut I work out like four or five
hours every week there are nae shortcuts
at a standing desk is not going to be
the solution it helps with like getting
a little bit more weight off and a
little bit more energy but honestly you
need a density it's what matters now I'm
lucky I'm a freelancer I get to make my
own hours most people don't if you work
40 hours a week and have a family I see
you to do five hours of exercise a week
is a lot I mean you could lift your
children but i don't think the Milo
creative methods for everybody I like a
chai tea myself we need to make health
at what we do and mental health at any
other industry we need to make longevity
a tenant other industry now something we
do have to work
because it's not just about you it's
about your company you need to be there
for your company I don't understand why
you don't understand that if you can no
longer work they lose out on valuable
assets it should be something that's
symbiotic but they treat you like it
doesn't matter because at the people
your job is going to be gone before your
body is before your language is before
your company ipos or folds its with you
to the end of your life and you need to
treat it with respect and all that
knowledge all that wonderful things
they've you learn throughout your life
it doesn't matter if you can't actually
do it because you're in so much pain we
need to think more about stuff like this
my talk is imperfect I am imperfect as
you know as I kind of didn't set up the
timing right for my yoga I apologize for
that but this is important people we
need to think more about stuff thats
related to programming that isn't
programming we don't we treat frameworks
is more important as people that needs
to stop I know I could have done better
today but that doesn't matter we always
can do better I hate asking people to
join in with me but right now just take
a deep breath and think about something
that's important to your life be it
health be something else but something
that's not just related to the language
of JavaScript because we're better than
that we're more than that I want us to
start treating ourselves with that
respect because our community is special
because we act like people most of the
time
just breathe in and out I'm very honest
when I say this year has changed me it
will have changed me for 10 years from
now and that I will remember I will be
there for you if you're going through
this or anything else because we're
getting older and we're going to
struggle a lot with so many things we're
not even aware of I'm here for you I
mean that thank you they're also
references people come on if you if a
this is touch you look at these books
they have helped me a lot understanding
how to exercise how to think about
health and they're not perfect but
they're there and we thank you so much
guys for going with this little journey