I'd like to talk about html5 a little
bit what we're gonna do is talk about
what's in it a little bit but we're
focused here in this discussion around
what is actually well things that we can
put to use right now things that are not
really ready for cross-browser use and
kind of the techniques that we can
employ to make this stuff happen for
real so what is the stuff in html5 there
is a lot of things that people say are
in html5 my definition is a little
flexible you know geolocation share
let's call that html5 css3 probably not
but you know there's a lot of things
that are on the edge the orientation
events probably not in html5 but
probably pretty cool anyways so I'm fine
with that its kind of falling into the
pool shiny stuff a bucket at the last
James Caan I put out this site html5
readiness and the main idea here is that
we're not dealing with waiting for html5
to be ready we're waiting for features
with inside html5 to be ready all these
features are implemented incrementally
across browsers so think of it that way
instead of you know what are the big
things so for instance like at font-face
in css3 has had support in ie6 578
everything something like drag-and-drop
how support an IE because that's where
the spec came from same thing with
content editable but then you look at
something like the indexed index DB and
that doesn't really have great support
yet so yeah but if we take a look at all
of all of the html5 features kind of
what how can we break these up so I
think we can break them up like this so
here we have dependable features and
these are the things that we can use
across all the IES
pretty comfortably roughly usable might
take a little bit more work but you can
do it for real experimental are cool
things to play with and enhance the
experience with but might not be ready
for for prime time for everyone and edge
features and these are the things that
you know people are experimenting with
and there's a lot of cool stuff
happening there but certainly not going
to fly too well in a production
environment where you have a wide swath
of browsers and I play so I've kind of
broken up a lot of these things so
inside dependable features I think these
things these things you can feel
extremely confident using so the doctype
that's about it no big hairy thing its
case insensitive it can be all in caps
can be lower case it could be mixed case
if you like to go like the myspace style
of capitalizing that's cool too it'll
still keep it in standards mode
everywhere car set we used to have as
http-equiv content-type blah blah blah
sucky thing now we got medic are set
it's beautiful you just like an HTML for
you can self close your tags or not you
can throw quotes around things or not I
kind of like not throwing quotes around
things all the time makes me feel alive
it's good but it's fine if you don't
quote to make you feel safe makes you
feel good too I understand that that's
fine html5 is extremely flexible you
know you can kind of do whatever side
you want validators not going to
complain too much pipe attributes are
gone I six never needed them we don't
need them make it as get rid of all of
them new semantic tags article navin
section we've solved the problems with
them I didn't style them it couldn't
print them the html5 shim
has fixes for both those things the
entire html5 shim is in modernizer so
you can kind of like pick which one you
want to use it is the same thing so
those are a go the data attributes are
rad there yeah you know in HTML for the
spec says if e as a browser you
encounter an attribute that you're
unfamiliar with just ignore it you're
not going to have to worry about
anything breaking here of course in
html5 we also get a data set property on
Dom elements and that of course is
something that we have to wait for
support for but using like get attribute
for instance it's not too heavy of a
cost so we can kind of go ahead with
this one in content editable I love this
guy um oh yeah then I made it constant
edible because I was like all of these
such a good demo if I can just type in
here but then when i have a link i can't
actually click it that's genius ok you
want to correct the spelling on mine
oh alright we'll see that maybe
later
yeah okay I just got show this because
it's like the baddest-ass thing in the
world yeah okay here's a source the body
is totally empty in the head we just
have mostly a style tag that has content
editable on it but then the really crazy
is that head title and style are
all display block bodies display none so
when we're actually looking at this this
is the style tag that we're actually
editing so then you know I can change
the color of the text to white and I
like fuchsia because it's a challenge to
spell it's like yeah oh yeah so we
watch the uh uh yeah anyways it's good
one all right so now those are the
things you can feel really comfortable
using for my six and up you're good
these ones audion video was designed for
the fall back case we want to know if
there's not going to be support so it's
pretty pretty damn beautiful how this
works right so video for everyone back
rock came and kind of popularized this
technique we have the video tag the
source attribute is calling out are
three different codecs that we need to
support mp4 needs to be first because of
a bug in the ipad that is now fixed but
keep it first for now and then anyways
we we throw a flash object in there any
non supporting browser kind of ignores
the video tags or source tags and then
just dives right for that i will point
out of course though if let's say that
you like you only want to serve mp4 s if
you do this technique and you only
include the mp4 firefox for instance
which doesn't support that codec will
try and use the video tag it won't be
like Oh use the video tag but then I
can't use that code XO then I'll fall
back to the flash doesn't do that so you
actually have to use JavaScript and use
the can play type method to see can I
use this codec in this browser if not
then I'll just switch everything in for
the flash object but in general and this
sort of technique you get a get a good
amount of coverage yeah okay canvas
we've had X canvas from Eric Cartman's
in Google for a long time bringing
support through vml to the other
browsers I love this demo by tab Atkins
he's a standards guy it basically just
writes the each frame of the video tag
to a canvas writes the bright the
brightness levels and then converts that
into a ski on that side I thought that
was fun so I like kind of tweaked it and
you can adjust the resolution make a
little more fine or more rough and I was
like I think we could do this even
better so now we're gonna do the same
trick html5 video
but we're going to construct a 3d cube
using 2d transforms so that all the
sides are kind of all ascii i can still
manipulate and then we'll like pay the
edges for a nice little effect here but
the cool thing you know with using the
native things is no I just mean you know
flipped around to the back side you know
this is just an element and I can
manipulate it any way that I want and
that's where like the real power of
using you no html5 video in comparison
to flash pays off that these things just
like work together SVG SVG web is a
flash-based shim that provides support
for non-sporting browsers so that's
pretty good to go geo locations not too
hard web sockets socket i/o by guillermo
is a really nice library that provides
support from I think I five and up
through flash actually mimics the web
socket API through flash drag-and-drop
like I said it comes from an i spec
input auto focus in place older you know
placeholders kind of this interaction
it's you know easy trivial to to Nick
and JavaScript so we can just detect
support for that use it if it's their
fall back if it's not for experimental
the form input types so like input type
equals date will just give you a date
picker it's beautiful input type equals
color ideally would give you a color
picker these are not widely implemented
yet opera has the best support mobile
safari does a few key board tricks like
if you say it's a input type tell little
change the keyboard layout to be numbers
but we're getting there a metering
progress progress so these are just
elements on the page I'll just abuse
source
yeah so it's just the top one is an
indeterminate progress bar because
there's no value on it but you can set
values and meter works the same way it
kind of gives an indication of how full
things are you can kind of set the
optimum fullness it's pretty cool but
it's so far this is only in WebKit web
sequel database is most popularly used
by things like mobile gmail but the
support is going to be limited to Safari
and chrome Mobile Safari that's it I
believe I 9 IE eventually will implement
index database I don't believe it's
going into i9 Chrome will support index
database which is essentially competitor
Firefox will also add that an opera will
follow suit as well web storage so local
storage and session storage web workers
WebGL I show off this demo we released
this just a short bit ago and I think
it's badass I also like this is one of
my favorite parts of WebGL is that you
get all the polygons and things coming
in as the textures are loading in so
it's very like I just love that the
movement still continues as the
experience is loading in I think it's
really fun so always fun to look at
frame rates and increased numbers of
fishes 200 fish a change the view come
outside go I like I like to take let's
say you'll do take off the tank yeah
almost having float around inside there
take off add some lasers maybe on the
sharks
I think so smart l on the keyboard no
one knows all right let's roll file API
this is rad so actually a Googler just
put this out recently it was on a
unhappy news yeah okay so dropbox com
just drag a file into it so i'll drag in
a kool-aid man and childhood
embarrassing picture and so I'm just
dragging the files into the browser it
immediately absorbs it through the final
API and drag and drop then I can use a
html5 drag and drop in here to kind of
reorder the things to kind of go back
and forth and at the same time it was
uploading all these to the server and if
you notice the URL already changed to
something brand new and unique so that I
could send this to a friend so it uses
html5 history's push state to give me a
brand new URL without page changing
which out the page refreshing so then I
can send it to a friend and have all
these pictures so that's the file API
push say drag and drop kind of comboing
together networks now in chrome six and
firefox 36 i believe so yeah it's really
rad for more edges feature ishness I
know how do I accelerations it's kind of
a feature its landing in different
places at different times I definitely
got out of the game and accelerated
everything on on vista and 7 of course
chrome and firefox are doing a hardware
acceleration for nearly all the same
things you know 3d transforms
can 2d canvas all that on vista 7 XP you
know snow leopard linux indexdb i
already covered orientation we saw i
like lamentation it's it's a little
finicky so if you use it you know
especially on a mac you kind of want you
can add a little bit of dampening with a
WebKit transition and it will make so I
edit it here otherwise yeah you can kind
of like make it look drunk a little bit
so I can turn up the transition to like
one second yeah and then oh yeah drunk
if I your orientation protect device is
really rad and sony ericsson is is
really leading the charge here you know
this is a sane be on html5 devices
sometimes called html5 but it is so rad
it is HTML like 10 maybe you know so
basically just using a you know straight
up markup we can go into read a webcam
device element I can allow the web
application to access yeah Michael BAM
and then we can also connect
peer-to-peer to another user and go back
and forth I mean this is just like
straight up HTML that enables this now
is really exciting so I can't wait until
we started landing this the audio data
API I want to mention a Firefox is
shipping this in and Firefox 4 and it's
really exciting so not only can you
synthesize audio on the fly but you can
also read all the spectrum data and
essentially provide visualizations so
they did a really nice
demo showing all this stuff and but one
thing that's worth pointing out is that
the guy from google is writing a spec
for this and what's in the spec
currently doesn't match what Firefox is
implemented that's cool which is Firefox
is going to be changing their API to
match the spec later on so spectrum data
we're reading this just straight off
with it's on file we can do cool things
like that a little bit of this
visualization happy town is a really
javascript-based feet detector more that
then will like combo 2d canvas with
WebGL because that seems necessary and
beautiful
so awesome so Firefox a group there's an
experimental working group working on
their sniffing and ass a lot of the guys
from processing J is actually so WebKit
has an implementation of this with a
special WebKit audio build you can try
there's a bunch of demos out there to a
little different but like i said the api
is still kind of in flux input type
input not type speech just attribute
speech this is so going to work for my
demo i hope this works because that
would be embarrassing otherwise so it's
just an attribute on the on the tag so i
guess you could throw it on a text area
20 right what mmm yeah honestly i don't
know i don't think i don't know i don't
think that we put a speech like voice
recognition to the browser I think it
goes to google first like the like the
google iphone app hmm
and then SVG filters which are so
freakin rad and only firefox has support
for these right now well like I think
opera has a little bit of support but
it's not not as good so SVG filters in
html5 wish basically you can apply to
any element so I have an html5 video
with just a standard CSS border I can
blur it in verse that whatever some of
that some of that mm-hmm I don't know
what's going on there but this is really
exciting and I end up hoping that we're
gonna I know SVG filters is not going to
be an i-9 but but and I'm really hoping
that we can get into web gitsune so one
of the guys who actually a filter who
works on the audio data API and
processing Jas and a lot of things he
kind of combined a bunch of these things
so this little button here is a html5
video using the auto data API to read
the audio from it and create the
visualization on there we have a web
font coming in rounded corners oh yes
gratuitous WebGL um box shadow
yeah I mean this is like this is
extremely exciting to me it's like when
you combine all these different features
together like you see these demos and
it's like this feature in this feature
in this video but like being able to see
like seven features come together you're
like this is powerful you know this
is really cool that we have this stuff
in the grounds again all right okay um
let's say you've I'm gonna go through
these fast but come back to them with me
if you've kicked I you to the curb you
said I don't care about I a six just
let's recover let's cover over the
things that you have you can now play
with you have full ping support you
don't need to do ping eight anymore
position fixed things thank God hover
selectors first child adjacent attribute
and child selectors are good fixed
position backgrounds min with max with
good these are things we need clearly if
you said I seven instead which I think
we're going in the direction where we're
going to have six and eight and nine
plus for a long time so seven I think
might actually die before six in a way
postmessage you're good we haven't in
ie8 cross-domain xhr for the most part
Native Jason you don't need Jason to ejs
anymore dad you are eyes up to 32
kilobytes and I 84 after and focus looks
lords and such stories are both in ie8
even in compatibility mode like you're
viewing in ie7 but then it has parts of
ie8 a monster a lot of fun getters and
setters on Dom elements so we can
actually kind of recreate the html5 data
set attribute and kind of make it work
ni ate among other things Cory selection
Cory select are all badass easy element
selection and box sizing which Microsoft
was right in their original box sizing
when you combine wit and padding and
then it somehow is larger than the width
that you already specified here you just
do this
boy and from ie8 and everywhere else it
actually is the wit that you say which
is makes more sense to me but let's say
that you're a cross-browser warrior and
you will support all these browsers so
you probably do a feature detection
right probably something like modern
eyes right here it's awesome but you
want to support the older browsers and
you want to give them some of these
features and functionalities so you want
to employ something like you might call
it regressive enhancement because we're
going to give these features back to the
old browsers in a mostly consistent
fashion and this is not really like
doing it twice it's like doing it 1.1
times and most of the work has already
been done for you so what I did is I
pulled together all the different
scripts that people have done to kind of
do this thing and so we have a big happy
list of all the we're gonna calm
polyfills I think Remy sharp came up
with this I think it's a good term
polyfills to basically provide the
support the fall back to shim whatever
so we have the SVG web ex canvas shims
using either window dot name or cookies
or whatever to imitate session storage
and local storage the media element
jsuis throw in a flash object that
actually has the API of the html5 media
elements and you kind of use it like you
would want to mimicking all the the
input type date picker color picker
stuff so you're you're writing code
writing html5 code that is going to use
the native things when it's there and
then going to mimic that exact same
behavior in older browsers so there's a
lot of good stuff in here and I've also
added a lot of things where we don't
really have support for the progress and
meter elements no one's really made a
script that kind of give support to
older browsers for those but I'd love to
get your help and kind of filling in
these holes and you know one of the
challenges we want to provide these
scripts to older browsers and then it's
like a lot of these little scripts so we
have none a new thing from the author of
go to GIS
and co-author of a purge is Alex Sexton
we have yep nope yep nope is a
conditional script loader and so it uses
lab jass under the hood and so
essentially this is it so we're going to
just do a test so modernizer indexdb
this is going to return either true or
false yep if it does return true we're
going to include these files otherwise
we're going to chuck in these and we so
we can get the benefits of a dynamic
strip loader added with conditional in
this so we can do our future detect it's
on that and if that sounds like too much
work you could make money chrome web
store I hear it's pretty awesome so
basically you know you build a web app
you can throw it in the Chrome Web Store
you're going to have much higher
discoverability and you can make money
on it which is a novel idea you can also
play with all the cool things that are
in chrome that might not be in other
browsers or we might be implementing
them before other people you have a lot
more storage desktop-based notifications
the WebGL the dragon and drag out kind
of stuff the speech attribute which I
showed you orientation that's exciting
so next steps um like I said I'd love to
get some help with some of those
remaining polyfills I think this is a
this document right now is on the
moderniser wiki but I think I think
there's a lot of places where we can
kind of make html5 as cross-browser as
possible and it won't be like totally
possible and there's going to be
decisions where developers again you
have to choose adding this shim to add
consistency is just not worth the
performance hit and so we're not going
in cluding and that's fine but it's good
to have the option in addition to the
features of when I six and seven dies
the new features that you have there's a
lot of stuff like em
if you said that you know Firefox 3.8 to
you then you can use in line display
inline block Firefox 35 dies to you have
a lot more things available so I love
help kind of gathering those up so that
we can have a nice document to say when
you kill off this browser we can use all
this brand-new stuff also has that
jeaious that Pete Higgins announced
yesterday is going to kind of lay some
groundwork for doing a lot of this
testing as well I encourage you to throw
this in your pages so basically we're
going to always force the eyes latest
rendering mode this is a really smart
move there's I've been hearing reports
and I'd love to talk to Microsoft a
little bit more about this but it seems
like an i-9 it's a little bit more
aggressive about falling back into ice
ie8 mode then we were seeing in ie8 and
like something in your CSS might trigger
it and so if you want all the benefits
of I&I in which you do it's good to just
say I'm opting into this please give me
the best experience possible so the
second part is chrome frame this does
not prompt use you your users to install
it just says if they have it I want to
use it so this is a meta tag that you
can also just send this as an HTTP
header does the exact same thing for
both of them that's it for me thank you
for watching
don't know do we okay there's any
questions well attempt to suck well so I
mean you could build a web app package
it and phonegap throw it in the android
market and then adapt that web app to a
more desktop experience and throw it in
the Chrome Web Store to their kind of
two stores and it'll be interesting to
see how kind of you know where users use
it but you know for now at least the
mobile experience and a desktop
experience should kind of be a little
bit different so I think it makes sense
that they're they're kind of separated