the web forward and my what I want to
encourage everyone to do is to open up
your favorite projects on github or
wherever they're at and get pull
requests and issues ready because I'll
be discussing a common performance over
sites in popular libraries and possibly
in your own code so if you find
something that's useful tweet it there's
hashtag / forward and at the end of the
talk I'd like to see like a list of
hands of how many our show of hands to
see how many issues have been reported
or poor requests have been started so
cool all right a little bit about me I'm
co maintainer of Jasper com how many
people have used Jas perf com awesome
cool Wow I'm also the lead dev on lodash
solo dash is an underscore alternative
how many people have heard of allah desh
awesome sweet and then benchmark Jas and
benchmark Jas is what powers j/s perf
and it also allows you to do things on
knowed Ringo Rhino all the browsers and
then i'm also a perf p.m. at microsoft
so I helped make chakra the JavaScript
engine faster alright I'm back kind of
cool and by by looking at patterns
popular patterns on the web and helping
relay them to the C++ Java engine devs
and i am a javascript fanboy so before i
begin and talk about the specific
performance tweaks there's a couple of
themes that i'll be trying to reiterate
throughout the talk and that's optimized
for the common case optimized for the
common case whenever you're implementing
a API design or using a library if you
are a library author think about the
most common case for that API to be used
and and optimized for it everything else
is secondary at that point a lot of
mistakes I've seen when debs are doing
API is is they
they're putting things in their code
that slow things down for no for no
reason or for this edge case the
scenario next is is using natives wisely
last year I gave a talk at jfcom called
the hidden cost of natives and that was
looking at the performance of native
methods like array for each filter map
and then comparing them to alternatives
written with four loops also things like
bind as well and then avoid abstraction
one of the easiest ways to gain
performance in a JavaScript library or a
JavaScript project is to just peel back
a layer of abstraction reduce those
function calls you don't have to go
crazy you don't have to compile all the
things like method compilation but just
pulling back the layer of abstraction
can can help you with your perf and then
the balance the pros and the cons
everything I'm talking about here is is
just advice if you're not seeing a
performance issue then you certainly
don't have to refactor your code and run
out and do it I work with a lot of like
low-level library functions where they
have to be fast because you don't know
what's going to be built on top of it
it's the baseline for a lot of projects
and so keep that in mind when I show
like I'll show one way to implement
something and then I'll show another way
to implement it that gets a little bit
deeper and then you know code in kind of
increases in complexity increases so you
just have to judge for yourself do I
want to pre compile all things or do I
just want to maybe just remove one layer
of abstraction so cool now that that's
out of the way all right so I also hope
to blow some minds and I just love this
Jeff so I said let's just let's just
absorb this for a second how awesome it
repeats forever too I love it okay okay
so the first technique is to hoist out
dot call and apply from your iteration
functions and I put a little key down
here at the bottom that shows the
libraries that this applies to so if you
use any of these libraries this
technique applies to that and you can
create
patch for it or an issue for that
library so that's backbone dojo ember
jquery prime which is mu tools to and
then underscore and i'm sure there's
more every every library has some kind
of iteration utility every library has
some kind of event loop or event emitter
and this technique can be applied to
those so the general gist is we've all
seen code like this while loop call back
call and what it's doing is it's doing
the dot call for the this the disarm
your this context but if you don't pass
it this context it's still or this argh
it's still doing a dot call and that is
slower than just a straight function
call so one way to do it like we all
know like when you have loops you move
the the hard work out of the loop and in
this case you can move that call out of
the loop by doing something like this so
this create call back allows you to
evaluate and do the binding inside this
function here and then in your main loop
you've just got a straight function call
and so that increases your your
iteration performance and your event
emitter performance and the inside of
that function there that I've
highlighted looks like this AHA there it
is like this if you don't pass it this
arc it just returns the call back and if
you do it wraps the function and does
the call now this makes your common case
very very fast and I'll show you I'll
step back this is I applied this
optimization to backbone which already
has a very fast event system like they
go out of their way to really fine-tune
it and you're still able to get
performance gains in various browsers
because of this and I'll step back or
forward there's trade-offs for this this
makes your comment case very fast this
makes your case where you pass at this
argh very slow because it is having to
do a function rapper so there's there's
variations you can do on this
what you can do is you can check to see
if there is if this file show you here
if there is a this binding and then in
your loop do a conditional sure like a
ternary operator that says hey if
there's a binding do the call if not or
do the function call wit call if not
then dude alcohol and that will give you
a little bit better performance and not
as bad a big of a per penalty so it's
just up to you to weigh the pros and
cons of your approach one of the good
things about using create callback is
that with this approach you could then
add extra functionality without having
to modify this function you could just
modify create call back so I did this
with lodash for our map function usually
there's a function called pluck which
would then you you give it a collection
or an array of objects let's say and you
want to get the the name property value
off of all the objects there's a
function called pluck which would do
that well instead you could have map
which we all know whatever a map is you
could have map that accepts a string a
string for callback and it would pass
here it would automatically create the
callback that does the object property
retrieval for you and it's at zero perf
cost so you're able to extend your your
existing iteration function without any
extra perf cost and it's optimized for
the common case so you get win win win
win win out of that
all right before i get into the next one
i also want to touch on event systems
like jquery so if we looked at back at
this chart here you saw that so this is
higher is better so the longer the bar
the better backbone alt is my
implementation you'll see like jquery's
version here there there event system is
considerably slower but they're doing a
lot more they've got a more robust event
system it's for handling elements it's
not just generic objects and with this
technique you can improve jquery's event
iteration by like eighteen percent which
considering how much other stuff they
have around just removing that call and
dot apply is a pretty easy tweak so if
anyone digs jquery wants to optimize
that this would help their event system
this would help their dot each cool
alright i really like this this
technique and so I you'll see a lot of
this stuff is I've taken out of low dash
because I'm not just like coming up with
ideas for optimizations I use these in
my own projects and I've tested them
I've refined them to try to gain
performance and to offset the cost of
like bug fixes or compliance alright so
avoiding binding how many people know
that you can coerce a function to a
string and access its function source ok
cool you may also know that it's
non-standard technically but it's like a
de facto standard like everyone kind of
does it so I found a way to avoid the
this binding if you can detect that the
function isn't using the this keyword
and so so so so check this out you yeah
so it's so by the way this is going to
be in lodash as well so expected for
those that are like wow that's on stand
that's not standard I'm kind of scared
of it I in another slide I show you how
to do a feature detection for it so you
can get this benefit if it exists and
you can drop
it doesn't but the the the gist is and
this is me showing like a generic event
system but you could patch so you could
do this with jquery event system for
example or backbones of its system and
usually when you're registering an event
listener you you might pass intimated
that metadata so like right now I'm
passing in like the function and its
context but what I'm doing is I'm
testing to see if the function is using
this reference if it's not then I'm not
going to do a binding to it and so that
will let will speed up the iteration
there because it's not just doing this
implicit this binding if you're not
using this this also allows you to say
to your dad's that if they do care about
performance but you can you can actually
enforce a different coding pattern for
them and say all right well then just do
their that equals this which is you know
gross some people hate it but if you
need it your system will now allow for
it and actually have optimism
optimizations for it kind of backed into
it so that's that's this technique i'm
using functioned up prototype to string
because this avoids issues if the
function has a custom to string so like
I've seen charting libraries do that to
their instances and objects and
functions and so this way that even
avoids that gotcha there what this will
do is this may have false positives if
you have a comment that has dot this but
in that case the worst case scenario is
that it's treated like every every other
function and wrapped or bound so just if
you know that this could be a pattern
for you to increase performance so what
I'm doing is I'm adding this to my
iteration sugar in lodash so if you pass
at this binding but your callback isn't
using it it's not going to actually do
the bind so it's going to hit the fast
path because I showed you that that slow
path is considerably slower for me
because I do the create callback
technique all right so here's the
feature test for example that one up
there so I do an assignment I test to
see if i can find the this value if i
can then i return the value else it'll
be false then you can do something
similar this was just a cheap way to do
this what I've done in lodash is to use
the the running context method because
that's the method that wraps
everything so it's a it's a very big
function body and this allows me to
detect issues with mobile browsers that
may truncate function string function
body strings and so I reference this
like way down there in the bottom so
they can catch it then I know it's it's
probably safe to use all right let's see
this is me actually showing the inside
of the listener so before I showed how
to register it and this is an
implementation of it using that that
information now now that I know that I
can conditionally if there is a context
call it if not do a straight function
call and that is how you get your
performance now this is kind of like the
backbones implementation where they do a
switch statement on a number of
arguments I just did up to one but you
they do it like up to three you may
would do for it manuf eyes to almost
nothing so if you're totally grossed out
about that just say it's for perch and
and move on oh yeah okay all right so
the the next technique i have is reduce
your searches so a lot of people when
you they have a lot a large array or a
group of a race they want to do
operations like without or union or
unique on their arrays but that's doing
a lot of linear searches index of values
going through the collection every time
and that's very very slow and to fix
that you may think well i'll just use an
object cache so if the if the value in
this case turns the value into a
property name and they set its result to
true so then if it does exist as a
property then they know it's there and
they can they can continue on their way
they found the property or the value but
there's there's a couple of problems
with that it conflates things that look
like identical at strings so like the
number string are the number two and the
string to look the same and so
if you're doing something that's is like
a unique operation it's going to treat
them as equal when they are not or even
a function that coerced to the for some
reason course to a number it would with
two string would do it so that that
approach doesn't work well for generic
use now if that is your only use case
then maybe maybe you could do it but
this is how you could tweak that so
here's the first one where it's index of
and you'll also see that I've got a
little bit of something up here but I'll
talk about that later and then the the
tweak is what I've done is I've in this
example created a cache of that value
and then I just look to see if it's
contained in that cache or if it's not
contained in this case now I'm going to
go into actually showing you how i
create the object cache for that so this
is what the idea is is instead of doing
a long linear search you're breaking
that massive array into two smaller
buckets so you're taking all of the in
my previous example of two like values
so all of your number two's and string
tues and sticking them into a smaller
array so you have less of an array to
search so that should be faster and it
is it's considerably faster and so now
here's just a small code that shows you
an implementation of this what I do is I
detect if the array is large and what is
large it's an arbitrary number that I've
created based on research so in my case
my implementation the large array size
was at one time 200 so anything over 200
got this optimization now it's reduced
to 75 so now any array over 75 gets this
optimization but what it is is it's the
point at which your cost for doing this
actually gives you a perf win because
you're having to sit there and create an
object and populate it with properties
and if you if your array is for items
long then it's not going to be a big not
going to be a win so what this is doing
is I'm doing a prefix here for the
you to avoid issues with object
properties on objects of prototype so to
string has owned property it also avoids
issues with the magic proto property
double underscore proto double
underscore and that is the
implementation there I basically push
the values into their smaller buckets in
this cash and then in this function here
I check to see if it is in that smaller
array so instead of doing let's say 200
search over 200 items it's doing a
search over four so it makes it faster
now this is me zooming into that chunk
right there that that is what's actually
creating the cash but it was pretty
pretty clear before so there's an
alternative technique that you can do
that takes it another step further and
this is what I'm doing in the next
version of lodash and what this is is
instead of creating a bunch of smaller
arrays what it's doing a hybrid approach
of that the first naive approach which
was to do object properties and it's
also doing a race so object properties
for things like boolean values false and
true no undefined and I only do those
lookups if i'm looking for a value that
is one of those so it's not going to get
a false positive like with the number
two and string two and then I have an
object cash for anything else that's an
object so they'll get the their own
arrays there and this is just me
creating that cash again still you know
if it's an object it's getting pushed
into the smaller array if it's one of
the other primitive values it's being
set to true so that's the hybrid of the
naive approach and the the smaller
bucket approach and this gets
considerable ones this was this allowed
me to remove to reduce the size of my
large array limit from 200 down to 75 so
that means more arrays are impacted and
more you get better performance out of
it because the optimization kicks in
earlier
cool all right another another technique
is cool by the way that that
optimization can be used in underscore
and possibly jQuery another thing you
can do here is coerce values with care a
lot of times debs will get in the habit
of doing sliced call arguments all the
time just whether they need to or not
they're sliced up calling arguments and
in many cases you don't have two
arguments are an array-like object if
you're about to iterate over arguments
you don't have to convert them to an
array you can just iterate over them
straight up and many times you can avoid
slicing them if you just if your are
going to iterate over them just set your
eye index or your your index value to
one or something so you don't have to
slice them there's an example here where
I've done that where instead of instead
of slicing your arguments and doing an
index search actually I missed a value
there but use your imagination there's
about you the argument instead of that
I'm leveraging the the from index of
index of so index of an array index of
in this case the library index m allows
you to set a from index where you start
your linear search from so it doesn't
always have to start from zero we can
start forward so you don't have to slice
things there you can also avoid things
like concat so let's see
I have a typo which is lame but I'll
jump down to this example over here
instead of flattening a lot of times
Deb's will include a Lib to flatten
arrays and you don't have to you can use
native can cat concatenate so in this
case I'm having a variable reference to
concatenate anything that's me storing
their slice equals or rate up prototype
nestlings and instead you can use concat
to flatten your arrays and you don't
have to pass it an array as it's this
argh so I've seen many lives do this
where they're just creating garbage like
extra unneeded arrays there and you can
tidy that up the array dot prototype
itself is an array so you can use that
as the despot as that this value there
which is what i do in lodash too and i
believe it's been added to underscore
but this that pattern there is from
jQuery so if you're a jquery fans you
can go and patch that up and I'm sure
you could find it in all the other lips
too they all kind of do similar things
there and you can you can tighten up
their object creation and then the
bottom one is avoiding can cat when it's
not needed so in this case they were
doing food.com cat slice arrays /
arguments and you can you can avoid that
and do like push that apply and push
because push accepts more than just one
argument to push I don't know of many of
how many people knew that you could push
more than one argument okay cool well
you can and so you can leverage that
apply there and push all of your
arguments on to the array without having
the dukan cat and creating all these
intermediate arrays so try that instead
and that's me again having a reference
to array dot prototype top push assigned
to a variable push okay sugar in
moderation how many people use a jquery
straining syntax and not J queries
underscores changing syntax
okay a few if you're using a lib that's
optimized for the generic use you need
to be aware that the chaining syntax the
non-common syntax has a performance
penalty so if you have an animation
framework or tight loop try pulling it
back to the API that is is optimized for
that library before you even have to
roll it back to like four loops or go
crazy other optimizations and in this
case I've shown the the difference
between the two there you've got the the
chain version versus the generic version
and there's a trade-off there one is
pretty and in the chaining API is very
pretty but the other one is actually how
it was designed to be used from its core
so it's faster this way keep in mind the
differences underscore and lodash are
optimized for their generic use but mood
tools and anything but operates on a
prototype so that even means jQuery are
optimized for the chaining syntax so be
aware of the libs you're using be aware
of that in your own code to like if
you're doing something that's a
moderately performance intensive or
could be make sure you're using the API
that's appropriate for your your use all
right next I wanted to say is with the
chaining syntax if you do have a
chaining syntax there's an optimization
opportunity there and that is deferred
evaluation so just a week or two ago I
saw a library come out that was called
lazy j s which was boasting better
performance than lodash aha it caught my
attention
because uh because yeah I'm pretty
competitive in that in that space and
now normal usage normal usage you could
see I I beat them I'd be a beat
underscore two underscores the little
book I'm the big blue but but but as the
co as the complexity of the chain
functions increases this one starts to
win and win by a considerable amount and
that's because what they're doing is
instead of doing two hundred iterations
for map and then doing two hundred
iterations for filter and then doing
some other things in their collections
so iteration iteration iteration and
then at the end only getting build the
the last five values lazy evaluation at
that time doesn't execute that at all it
adds it to a queue and then whenever you
call to array or in this case like if
you're familiar with the underscore
lodash chaining syntax the value command
or the value method that's when it
flattens that down and instead of it
being 200 or 400 or 600 iterations since
you're only needing five values at the
end because you're saying like take the
last five values it only does five
iterations and so that gives you massive
performance wins so as you're chaining
gets longer you get better wins now i'm
experimenting with adding support for
this because i like this so much and i
like the performance opportunity my
chaining syntax is usually a perf hit
because it seemed like i said lodash and
underscore are optimized for the generic
use but i can back this in whoops hey
hey Matt no it's cool let's see Boop
someone's birthday all right yeah all
right and that's it questions yeah
mm-hmm
so general use case is the use case I've
seen promoted throughout like
documentation or through tutorials so in
my case I know that that most most
deaths aren't passing that this value
there so I know that the common case is
not to do that it's being familiar with
your own lib being familiar especially
if you're the lib author being familiar
with how you want your Deb's to use that
API and how you're promoting it through
your your evangelism and then you know
what the the common case would be so you
can optimize for what going back to the
themes again where I said optimized for
the common case jquery has an implicit
this binding in its event system because
if you know if you're doing each or
whatever you'll see this equals is is
the element that's currently being in
rated over something and that was baked
in from the beginning so it's hard to
kind of back in perf there because
they're always doing call or not apply
but if you want that eighteen percent
boost oh what you can do is do that that
function sniff inference where you can
detect if the dis binding is there and
in toggling but you wouldn't have to go
to that length if at the beginning you
said oh okay maybe not all going to use
this or maybe this will become an
anti-pattern or whatever and they get
instead have put that property on the
event object that they're already
passing down and so that would have
avoided it about call to begin with so
when you're doing like your event system
you could think oh maybe I don't need an
implicit this I could just add a
property to the event object that I'm
passing to every call back anyways so
that just kind of keep these things in
your head as you're developing your
libraries or your own code bases cool
yeah
so the question was have you looked at
any of these anti-patterns in
CoffeeScript I don't use coffee script
so no I haven't what's nice about copy
script is it just come boils down to
basic JavaScript and in many cases it's
sugar boils down to two for loops so
that's right up my alley like it doesn't
defer to native methods it turns it into
four loops and it has small utility
functions which are very nice also I'll
be positive about CoffeeScript and Sarah
like its class abstraction but yeah yes
I need to do more research there but I
do have a big function on line I only do
it once though for the future detect but
so far it's given perf games in the test
that I've done you could always do more
research dig into it I'm going to try it
I'm going to give it a shot because i
think it's relatively safe and stable
especially for modern builds so what I'm
doing is I'm opting that into just learn
so just ie9 up and modern modern
browsers will do this not old browsers
because if that just means bugs just
yeah man bugs get big but the idea is
that I'm doing that load that work
outside the loop so it's done once
outside the loop instead of like every
time inside the loop so it's again
hoisting things out of your loop cool
yes
yeah good good good good question so the
the the question was in create callback
which was the the code i have up here
and i'm going to get to it I can't speak
and move at the same time okay the
question was in create callback why not
use function dot prototype top bind
instead of wrapping and that's because
many times in most browser
implementations function dot prototype
that bind is actually slower especially
like in v8 it's considerably slower and
in lodash actually is aware of this and
will not use native bind in the eighth i
do an inference for its engine which is
really cool because i can detect the j s
engine through a little inference but
even in browsers where it's relatively
fast or faster than then then a fully
spec compliant buying alternative bind
is still slower than just wrapping it so
i thought i was going to get a perf
boost there too and i was really
surprised that it didn't it didn't do it
or else i would have yet done that
what's up yes
I for the purpose of this this
demonstration I kind of wanted it really
simple to just do word boundary this
word boundary you can experiment with
with other variations of it if you see
that as a problem I don't know if I'm
going to see a lot of people having that
issue but if it is and if it's a concern
I would I still kept it simple that way
it's just a quick reg ex that just finds
it or fails fast but yeah you could you
could modify the reg ex to detect
comments I don't know if I repeated the
question but it was could you modify the
this reg ex to look for comments instead
another any other questions yes
hit
yeah so I had a slide here that I
removed which was how to better how'd
the cab create call be better detected
for inlining because some engines have
an issue with that function call out
there and so what you would do is do a
check for if this is undefined don't do
the function call at all and just have
it do the habit do they have it be the
callback so a ternary operation of that
engines are tricky engines under the
hood are there doing all kinds of crazy
stuff to just get the result and get it
fast and jit and what what gets
optimized and what doesn't this is why I
said it's a balance of how deep you want
to go into it and I think this is a
decent trade off because it's not just
it's it's it's giving me win on top of
win here because it's optimizing for the
common case and allowing me to extend
functionality for each two and other
iteration methods to have like the
callback shorthand sugar of the property
access or partial object filtering so
that's that's what I dig a side note is
since we're talking about engines is
that I've noticed that minified code
will have different performance profiles
than your non minified code potentially
in different engines so if you're
developing a project and you have a
performance critical thing like an
animation lab or something you want to
test your men ified code in your
benchmarks as well as your non minify i
found issues with uglify j/s and closure
compiler where they because of their
patterns they're using when they minify
d optimize like safari and mobile safari
so again really really good to test that
and what I've done is in lodash I have a
min efficacious system where I run all
these many fires and then get the
smallest build but then I also go back
and I fix the the patterns that the
minnow fires are doing that slow down
the engine so I avoid the D ops but it's
something to do like if you're you don't
have a perf suite for your library you
should create one and
if you have a favorite library and they
don't have a perf sweet you should add
one and a perfect lib to do that is
benchmark Jas and you can look at low
dashes implementation of example of a
prick blood the other questions yes
no without you just had each engine is
different each engine has its own rules
with that minification issue what was
happening was I believe what was
happening was that the minified code was
not getting in line for some reason it
was passing some threshold of byte code
or whatever and it was missing the
inlining opportunity there and so it was
d it was reducing its performance by
thirty percent so it was pretty pretty
glaring but as to what gets in line and
what doesn't the the general rule is to
keep your functions small and then they
have a better chance of being in line
and that kind of goes at odds with my
other point which is reduce abstraction
because you're going to have all these
function calls so I would say profile
and then make your decision don't just
take my word for it that's why I also
didn't include a lot of performance
charts because all you see is these bars
with them being really big over here and
really small over there and I want you
to not take my word for it to actually
go out and use j/s perf and other
benchmarks in and verify that you get
these wins like don't don't if you do a
pull request back it up with a
performance benchmark so you can say hey
this actually does this and if it
doesn't then it's still good you've
learned something and you know not to do