so my name is thomas yang Chuck I work
for of zero with gum tow and during this
session will be talking about sin boxing
no dress code in multi-channel systems
so why would you even think about sin
boxing no dress code many multi-tenant
systems enable extensibility by allowing
users to write custom code that is then
running as part of the platform and
since you since you know very little
about what that code does and how it
behaves you cannot fully trust it so
that's why you need a sandbox to run it
in he not 0 we are offering identity as
a service and as part of the
authentication pipeline we allow people
to provide custom nodejs code that we
are executing as part of every
authentication transaction people can
basically customize the behavior the
authentication behavior for their
applications and users that way however
given that we don't have full control
over what that code can do we need a
sandbox to run that code in all custom
code in ode 0 right runs in the context
of an HTTP request so basically the code
must execute fully within the lifetime
for a single HTTP request which is the
like a time span of a single
authentication transaction given that
the sandbox model that we required also
was based on HTTP basically you were
sending an HTTP POST request to the
sandbox the body of the HTTP POST
request contains the node.js code to
execute the sandbox runs dovecote and
when the result is available it sends it
back to the color is Jason object in the
HTTP response so this is a very basic
sandbox model the program programming
model around that we have created is
also very simple you're basically
writing a node.js code that returns
javascript function closure that
function accepts a single callback
parameter when you're done executing
your code you're supposed to return the
result value to that callback that
result is then civilized into Jason and
returning to the color what kind of
properties that we require out of that
sandbox so first and foremost we require
data isolation if we r XZ
getting code of one tenant we expect
that code to be unable to affect
execution of code from other tenants in
any way or from accessing data of other
tenants so this is the kind of primary
security requirement that we had in
addition to that we also had a number of
resource governance requirements around
how memory CPU and networking is
allocated we wanted to prevent one
tenant from executing an authenticated
us attack against resources of our
sandbox that would prevent other tenants
from running code in the same time in
that sandbox so the very high level we
basically looked at what is available
out there in terms of sandbox in node.js
code and none of the of the shelf
components were meeting our requirement
so we decided to build our own high
level our sandbox is built on core OS
dockery tcd and fleet which is a great
set of technologies that help you write
container based distributed applications
however in themselves these technologies
are insufficient to provide the kind of
security guarantees we expected around
the sandbox so he had to enhance the
basic setup of chorus and docker with
additional sandboxing mechanisms so this
is the view of a single VM in a core OS
cluster that runs our sandbox the
primary mechanism by which we ensure
data isolation between tenants is
running every tenants code in their own
docker container in addition to that we
are creating an egress firewall around
that docker container so that the code
running in that container can only talk
to the public Internet it cannot talk to
other two endpoints exposed by other
docker containers running on behalf of
other tenants or two endpoints exposed
by our sandbox infrastructure like the
proxy the controller or etcd running on
that box so the way the system functions
is that when that HTTP POST request
containing the code to execute arrives
on the box it is first landing at the
proxy component the proxy consults etcd
which is a distributed configuration
system like zookeeper
to see if a container associated to the
particular tenant is already running if
it is that request is then reverse proxy
to that existing container if the
container doesn't exist in the proxy
will create a new one associated with a
tenant a creator registration etcd for
future requests and reverse proxy the
request to the newly created component
in terms of preventing authenticated us
attacks against memory CPU and other
operating system resources you are using
a number of mechanisms first and
foremost we are leveraging limits
imposed the see groups level so see
groups is a Linux mechanism that docker
also exposes that wasn't me the doctor
also expose issue which which unable to
put limits on the memory and CPU
consumption of individual docking docker
containers in addition to that within
the sandbox containers themselves we are
creating transient users basically
whenever we spin up a new docker
container we are creating a brand new
operating system user and then we are
imposing pam limits for that user so for
example you are saying that user cannot
create more than 50 processes or threads
or he cannot create more than 5000 files
in the file system so this provides us
with the very basic mechanisms to limit
what the code running in the sandbox
container can do so with that I want to
do a few demos and take our sandbox for
a spin you have seen one map during the
RabbitMQ presentation and I just
couldn't resist I'll show you another
one we also have a map about ours with
more dots on it so what we are seeing
here is basically eight places around
the world where we have deployed our
sandbox
cluster so each of these places can
execute custom code on our behalf during
this demo I'm going to use the one that
is just around the corner in Sao Paulo
in Brazil just because it is the closest
one latency wise so with that let's have
a look at some code so this is the very
basic hello world example we are
creating a JavaScript function that
accepts a call back in immediately turns
around and codes are called back with a
simple string as a result and that
string is pretty much saying hello from
Las Vegas and it's offending the version
of node.js to it so the way you run that
code i'm going to show you the organic
version first we are going to use curve
because this is just a simple HTTP POST
request so courage enough and so we are
using Colonel we are pointing it at our
sandbox deployed in Sao Paulo we are
saying that this code is to be executing
on behalf of 10 and Q 1 and this is just
an arbitrary string that denotes the
isolation boundary between containers
and then we are just providing the body
of the HTTP POST request which is that
not Jes code that we won't execute so we
are going to return a function that
takes a single callback parameter and
you immediately calls that callback
parameter with hello world and i hope i
didn't make and i did make what did i
miss here
no our sandbox also has a very simple
authentication mechanism so I have to
basically provide an authentication key
here this is a query parameter which is
what I missed so you're sending it over
to some Pablo our sandbox compilers that
code executes serializes the result and
here it comes back so let's run it again
it is not much faster because the second
time I run it the container is already
running in Sao Paulo for that tenant so
no extra provisioning is required so
with that let's move on to a slightly
more advanced example in this case the
only difference is that we have a
variation of the programming model which
allows URL query parameters of that HTTP
POST request to be propagated to the
JavaScript code as part of the context
object so what i'm doing here is i'm
prepending a name equals of 0 URL query
parameter to the URL i'm going to be
involved to be invoking and then i can
access that name parameter off of the
context object passed into the function
that I'm authoring so let's run this
game
oh hello of zero and just make sure
up against really well i'm going to
change the 02 jas cone and what comes
back is calories count so here is a
slightly more interesting example so
let's say now that we have the ability
to run arbitrary code in eight places in
the world one one way we can use it is
to measure latency of accessing a
particular end point from those eight
places around the world and this is what
that code does it will call in 20 20 com
basically to an HTTP GET against zero at
colleges our website measure the latency
of that call and return the latency in
the result so let's run it from Northern
California which is the other sandbox
lastly we have deployed and you'll
notice the latency to Northern
California is very long but once you are
in Northern California the latency of
calling ohdeedoh.com is just 26
milliseconds that is because our website
of zero dot com is hosted in Northern
California as well if we do the same
test and send that code to be executed
in Singapore that called take more time
than my flight here even not is the
latency from Singapore to of zero is 750
two milliseconds so that way you can
basically conduct very simple latency
measurements by having the code deploy
to different places around the world
with a sim simple HTTP POST request so
here comes something interesting that
that ghanta mentioned the beginning in
addition to running no dress code we
also have the ability to run c-sharp
code and you are doing this using the
eds module which allows you to host CLR
and v8 inside of a single process and
provides an interrupt mechanism between
these two so what happens here is that
the node.js code is creating a
JavaScript proxy around async lambda
expression in c-sharp and it's also
providing a marshalling capability such
a thing you can exchange data between
JavaScript and see
are and also you can sighs threading
models because see that is
multi-threaded and v8 is single threaded
so this code should effectively do the
very same hello world example that we
have done previously in purely non je s
basically the URL query parameter name
of zero is going to be first propagated
into that context object in not Jes from
there it is going to be propagated to
the JavaScript function which wraps the
sea shop is in lambda expression from
there hjs will actually propagate it
into the dynamic context parameter to
that acing lambda expression and c-sharp
will generate a response let's send it
over to Brazil hello world 0 just to
make sure that we have the entire
pipeline covered the fool and here comes
the phone so the interesting thing you
know you know you notice it was actually
pretty fast so what happened here is we
sent a JavaScript code with embedded c
sharp code to brazil the sandbox took
this thing extracted the seashore code
compiled it on the fly into an in-memory
assembly marshal the request in to c
sharp C sharp generated the response
JavaScript serialize it into Jason and
send back to us so that was pretty quick
so with that let's move into something
slightly more complex and let's see how
that sandbox preventing the different
provides the different isolation Gavitt
guarantees that I've been talking about
and also prevents different kinds of
attacks so what you see here is a code
that we are going to be executing on
behalf of two different tenants
sequentially what this code does it
first it looks if there is a secret
property in the global namespace of what
whatever context that code executes
saying if there is no secret object a
one will be created using math.random
and you know the second time you execute
that code the secret will already exist
so it will remain unchanged and then the
function that we are returning from the
snow dress code simply turns around and
returns the global secret so let's run
it on behalf of 10 and full in some Sao
Paulo so the first time we done it the
secret will be generated and will be
returned to to us and that secret is
0.56 to something something next time
you call it the secret is the same but
now if i go ahead and I change the
tenant named here to full 10 and 1 i'll
get an oosik
generated 0.35 if I call tenant one
again I will again get zero 3.5 but if i
go back to tenant I'll get back the old
secret so this is just a demonstration
that the data context in which the
requests on behalf of different tenants
execute is different so tenants do not
have access to their data let's have a
look
my favorite kind of attack on nodejs
very elaborate that I can CPU we are
basically going to run an infinite loop
while true so what this does in Dantes
it blocks the event loop the event loop
can process any any more requests but
the basic premise of our sandbox is that
it is fine to do so as long as it
doesn't prevent other tenants from
executing code in the sandbox if you are
writing bad cold it is okay if you
should you yourself in the food but you
shouldn't be able to affect how others
execute code so let's let's take a guy
who's actually in who actually knows how
to write good code and he will be
issuing request request to the sandbox
thousand requests sequentially will
basically be responding with hello one
two three and so on and now I'm going to
run the bed code in the same sandbox and
see if it affects the behavior of the
first tenant which is running the
well-behaved code so I'm not going to
take that wire through code that the
loop you are seeing here and I'm going
to run it from this console the Derby
the first of all take a moment is what
happens here is that we are starting to
execute the JavaScript code that does
the infinite loop and before our system
realizes that the event loop is blocked
it is like two seconds it is a
configurable time period but eventually
the our sandbox realizes okay this this
process is gone so we are going to
terminate it this results in that tenant
who wrote the bed code getting an HTTP
500 back but you'll notice that the code
who wrote the word written code is
running just fine so he remained
unaffected by the attempted CPU attack
to keep that well-behaved 10 and going
and we will do another kind of attack on
memory this time so here we have a
string evil and you are going to run a
very tight loop which basically doubles
the size of evil so eventually after a
few iterations we are going to run out
of memory so let's run this thing in the
same sandbox
as the tenant running the well executing
code so you'll notice that we got HTT if
I found it much faster however the the
tenant that is well behaved was
unaffected again and the last kind of
attack is a traditional fork bomb so we
are going to use spawn to basically keep
creating note processes child node
processes they're not processes are not
doing much but it is that is beside the
point the idea is that you know we are
trying to create a billion processes on
that machine and see that well behave
tonight is affected so let's do this
again I will take a moment until it is
it should be 500
and the world we hit tennis continues
running just fine so this just
demonstrated some very basic send boxing
capabilities of the technology that
we've created one last thing I really
want to talk about in this presentation
is logging because that in itself is
very interesting logging is a very basic
diagnostic mechanism that is very
frequently used in node in a distributed
system like that it is interesting how
to structure a collection of logs such
as it is actually usable to the
developer and other systems that consume
them so what we are doing here is we are
normalizing logs generated by all
components in the system both the
sandbox the proxy and the user code
using anything you write using
console.log now into Bunyan first such
that we have structured Jason locks then
we put those logs into Kafka we have a
Kafka cluster deployed across the car OS
cluster Kafka SMS messaging server that
is highly optimized for logging
scenarios and then we expose the logs
over HTTP so let's take it for a spin
again so what i'm doing here is
basically writing a single simple
function that the calls console.log ones
first I'm going to attach my streaming
logging endpoint that exposes the locks
from Kafka and I'm filtering Lee let me
actually filter the output through
Bunyan so that we get pretty printing
and then I'm going to invoke this code
that actually perform some some logging
here it is
all returned Monte is 0 10 30 which is
what this code did but you also notice
that there is a console.log statement
and that console log showed up here if I
run it again it will basically get a new
entry here down here so this gives you a
streaming logging capability real time
access to logs generated by the sandbox
code and you can post process it in
whatever way you want so this is this is
what we have built we are kind of we
built it primarily with a scenario in
mind of enabling our customers to run
custom code on a platform but once we
build it we are actually started
noticing certain scenarios and patterns
where the sandbox is very very usable
for example we've built our entire
health monitoring system around the
system we have these eight sandboxes
deployed around the world and every 30
seconds they are basically executing a
bunch of tests not just HTTP test but
you know you can contact Mongo you can
do anything you can do with no Jas in
those sand boxes around the world and
they are then consolidating results
across the world but such a technology
really we think the sweet spot it is
targeting multi-tenant systems or things
like if this than that things like
custom web hooks for example so the
possibilities are really quite quite