thank you very much thanks for having me
so I'm not going to do any live coding
i'm going to do live executing a fair
amount of it so when it works its it's
actually pretty cool when it doesn't
it's pretty uncomfortable so I think
either way it'll be entertaining for you
so so my name is Mark head and I work
for a company called box AO and we have
some telephony platforms that people
like to use so I men have a m head on
Twitter I'm just plain em head-on
everything else and couldn't get hub
I've been a telephone and voice
application developer for about 10 years
I've built voice applications on just
about everything you can build a voice
application on there are a whole host of
alphabet standards there that I I put
there i will talk about each of them in
probably painstaking detail I've built
voice over IP enabled phone applications
using asterisk and many other platforms
and I currently work as a developer
evangelist at boxer labs so who cares
about phones why do we care it's not a
rhetorical question why do we why do we
care about telephony yes throw it out
there yeah phones feel real and it turns
out that almost everyone has them the
telephone penetration rate in this
country's around ninety five percent
there have been a host of studies done
about people's preferences for
contacting businesses and governments
and consistently telephones ranked at
the top in terms of their choice for
communicating so we care about phones
because there are lots of them it's the
most ubiquitous communications device on
the planet and everyone knows how to use
one pretty much so I've made a submit to
you that the future of telephone
application development is JavaScript
and no jsx that pays a pretty important
part i believe so that's my contention
before
we can challenge that contention and I
would I would encourage you all to do
that if you don't believe me we we need
to understand how we got here and how
our telephone application is built
currently so there's a famous quote at
the top we want to be able to discover
the future by understanding the past
ducting out of famous quotes it's me I
made it look famous by enclosing it in
quotes let me give you a brief history
of telephone and voice application
development so in the late 90s telephone
application development usually meant
low-level programming against
proprietary API if you wanted to
initiate phone calls or take phone calls
you had a server with a telephony card
in it with either analog phone lines
plugged in or of channelize t1 and you
were writing low level code against a an
API that was for that specific telephony
card so in the mid to late 90s the big
telcos got together under the auspices
of the ww3 see each of them had some
flavor of a markup language for
telephony in the works and the w3c
brought them all together and there was
a very very great effort to standardize
markup languages for telephony so the
idea was let's make telephony
development like web development lots of
languages all languages can render
markup for consumption by a browser so
that was the idea so the main standards
are voicexml anybody ever heard of
voicexml all right cool anybody ever
built a voice XML app all right so
voicexml is a standard for dialogues the
interaction between a person and an
application CC XML is for call control
and the speech recognition grammar
specification are the rules for speech
recognition this is a just a quick
example of a voice XML application very
simple you'll notice a lot of JavaScript
in here I wanted to make the point that
along with these standard markup
languages the w3c and the working group
that created these languages saw fit to
include JavaScript support so really all
this does is you call it it says hello
and welcome to voice XML says the
alphabet and it hangs up but you can see
I can
I can split a raise i can use data
objects i can throw and catch events
this actually this disconnect element
here will actually throw a connection
disconnect event so pretty cool stuff
pretty cool stuff javascript lives here
so JavaScript was incorporated into
these standard telephone languages and
again the idea was to make telephony
development like web development the
large telcos very wisely realized that
on the late 90s early 2000s the number
of web developers was increasing rapidly
so they wanted to capitalize on that and
make telephony development just like web
development there are no Ajax calls but
there are ways you can actually get
external data into voicexml and CCX
malifesh ins this data element in
voicexml gives you a a read-only subset
of the of the Dom so you can traverse
over an XML document in CC XML some
platforms actually support acma script
for XML which is kind of cool on the way
to get data into a an executing voice
application since that time there's been
a lot of changes a lot of changes we
live in a time now where it's never
really been easier it's never been
easier to build a telephony application
and when I say telephony application
from now until the end of my talk I mean
it in its broadest sense I mean a DTMF
DTMF tones are the noises that your
phone makes when you press buttons on it
speech application text messaging
application basically anything you can
do with a standard that's a regular
phone or mobile phone there's been a lot
of change lots of options now and many
of those options are not standards-based
they are not these standards based
languages that were developed with great
effort by the w3c and a large telcos why
is that well there's a number of reasons
i would point chiefly to the observation
that a lot of people don't like to
program an xml voicexml and CC xml have
a very steep learning curve you get an
incredible amount of control over a
telephone call CC xml especially you get
a very granular level of control of the
phone call problem is the trade-off for
that is complexity
it's very complex I'm going to show you
a javascript application that will
transfer a phone call in one line of
code I've actually written transfer
logic for production voice applications
that were 65 lines of code doing
everything from you know connecting a
caller playing a ringtone to them
bridging call legs so these languages
have the benefit of being standard and
portable there are over 50
implementations of the standard fluffy
markup languages so portability is a big
selling point for them the problem is
they're very complex they're very hard
to use they have a steep learning curve
so something else has changed to that's
driving how tell f amps are built voice
over IP all telephone calls at some part
of their life cycle and this has been
true for actually a while spend time at
an IP network retail consumption of VoIP
services is large and growing you've
probably all heard the statistic about
skype being the largest telephone
company in the world it's true almost
all business class telephony systems are
now VoIP enabled and when I save way if
in that sense I mean sip the SIP
standard the lines between the different
modalities is is blurring or moving
towards what the consultants call
unified communications where
conversations will happen across the
modality is a phone call instant message
email all these sorts of things are
converging so to meet the needs that we
have now the development languages we
use to build communication applications
they have to be powerful if to be
flexible and have to be channel agnostic
they cannot be tied to a specific
channel so I don't want to bore anybody
anybody here know about sip the SIP
standard we feel comfortable with that
we just hit it real quick so sip is the
session initiation protocol it's a
signaling standard for VoIP telephony so
a sip exchange of sip requests and
responses is meant to set up a telephone
call so sip endpoints will have a
conversation and say what what what
voice decoder do you want to use what
channels are seeing what ports are we
going to exchange media on all these
sorts of things that are negotiated
before a phone call and then when that
negotiation is complete
call starts the conversation happens
step is used in concert with other VoIP
protocols like real time protocol which
is the actual protocol for streaming
media it's very similar to http in the
sense that it has a pretty simple to
understand request in response paradigm
and very importantly sip headers you can
set them just like HTTP header so you
can actually draped information on the
telephone call essentially and pass it
along a telephone network pretty
powerful idea and really something that
you need to have for next generation to
laughing so if your if your if your VoIP
or excuse me if your telephone provider
isn't sip interoperable then I don't
think they're going to be around for
very long so building communication apps
with JavaScript as I said before there
are more choices i'm going to go over
several of them there are a host of
different platforms out there that you
can use like I said it's it's a it's a
target-rich environment it's never been
easier to build the telephone
application there are very compelling
options i believe for javascript
developers we're going to talk about
three different kinds of telephone app
development i'm actually going to walk
you through a few of them i tell if any
app execution environment like troppo
which is the platform that we provide
where your javascript code is actually
executed in our environment there's
another company that does that as well
they were called soft IVR there are UK
company we're going to build a telephone
inside of a web browser using a jQuery
extension called for know and we're
going to use nodejs to do some really
cool stuff no Jas in particular my
contention is that it has some
properties that make it especially
attractive for next-generation telephony
and I believe that we will see nodejs
used more and more with telephony
applications okay so what does
JavaScript look like in troppo so this
is a this is the the functional
equivalent of the alphabet example that
I showed you a minute ago so this is
pretty straightforward pretty easy to
understand JavaScript i'm going to start
flipping around now I hope that doesn't
annoy everybody I'm going to try and at
least show you a few things i'm going to
give away all my stuff though
so what I want to do is actually oops
call this and see if we can get this to
work I have no idea what this will sound
like hello and welcome to track of a b c
d e f g h i j k l at the point n o p to
r s t u v w x y z now I know my ABC's
goodbye okay so there's actually another
standard for formatting our styling text
for text-to-speech engine I didn't want
to over complicate this though so I just
sort of used the phonetic text-to-speech
engine sometimes a little bit of help so
I wanted to give it that so that's a
basic JavaScript application intro fo
you can deliver that you can host this
remotely and deliver to troppo on
executed you can host it with us and
we'll execute it for you so here's a
very simple nodejs example this is this
is not the nodejs stuff i'm going to
show you in a minute which is actually
really really cool but we also have
another API where if you want to you
know if you need to integrate with
external systems we have a node module
this is the ubiquitous hello world web
server example for node with a little
bit of troppo flavor this is really nice
because if you want to use any one of
the growing number of get based
deployment options for your node you
know tap you can do that it's pretty
near so everything's sorted out in the
cloud ok so now I want to talk about
building browsers or excuse me building
telephones in your web browser and I'm
going to use a a jquery plugin called
phone oh I can find it here there it is
so phono is jQuery I have a I gave this
away a little bit but i actually have a
phono instance loaded in this browser
let's just reload it and what we'll do
here is we'll just check out the source
you all see that
so this should look pretty so I'm
referencing some external javascript
here but this should all look pretty
standard right I'm creating I've got a
funnel object here you'll see I'm
actually dialing something a nap colon
number i'll explain that in just one
second and you can see I've got on ring
unanswered on hang up I can handle an
incoming call I'm going to do all that
right now one of the things I real i
want to show you first is um let's do
this so actually wrote out to the
console the photo identifier so this is
a unique identifier that each photo
instance has every time is load in your
web browser and if it looks suspiciously
like a sip a dress that's because it is
a sip dress which means not only can I
make telephone calls from this photo
instance but I can receive telephone
calls at this instance the phone will
ring in my web browser so let me see so
I explain the second ago about this its
app colon in this identifier I can
actually put a regular 10 digit
telephone number in here and it will
call it right now we limit calls to real
telephones to 10 minutes and there's a
little speech you get before the phone
connects it says hey you're thanks for
trying photo you get 10 minutes of
calling time with this if you want to do
something else create an app on troppo
so what I did was I created a very
simple application on troppo looks like
this so this is the one line transfer I
was telling you about so what this will
do is this will transfer the call so far
no was going to call this app troppo is
going to call me on my cell phone it's
going to answer on media which means i
will hear the ring right away even
though it won't connect i'll give it a
60 second timeout i'm actually going to
set the caller ID to my home telephone
number so it will look like my wife is
calling me to find out what's going on
asking me how my demo is going so see
for work
hello can you hear me say goodbye it
gets cooler it gets cooler so I probably
shouldn't have closed that console I
needed that what's that make what bigger
sorry
I'll see that
alright so let me do this uh I have a
sip phone here sighs there's Michael now
I don't have any logic in here to
actually do anything with the call I
just kind of on to prove the point that
this is a this is a unique instance that
I can who's little down that I can
actually call now I wasn't going to do
this but I feel like I come on now
settle so I wasn't going to do this but
i wanted to because the Zeppo guys
something's ringing the sample guys
mentioned they're hiring for their for
their call center so call centers are
really interesting because they have a
lot of a lot of overhead to a call
center there's there's people you have
to staff it there's a lot of equipment
there's a lot of telephone switching
equipment there's there's automatic call
distributors there's there's there's um
dienes based routing you've got to know
what agents are on when they're on so
you can route calls to them so call
centers tend to be really really so
equipment intensive there's lots of
equipment so I've got this project that
I've been working on if you go to my get
a profile you see remote agent this is a
a couch app that's built with phone oh
so the way it works is when you go to
the couch app and you open up the index
page what you should get is a phone and
the anything about it being a cow Jap
remember I mentioned the unique
identifier since they are unique I can
then store them in CouchDB and I can
make the cipa dress which is unique my
document ID what it also means then is
that now that I know that I've got an
agent who is see here who is ready to
take a phone call so by doing a simple
HTTP query of CouchDB instance I can get
agents who are ready to take a phone
call these agents can be anywhere
doesn't matter where they are because
we're doing
telephony right and I know when they're
ready to take a phone call and I don't
need to work with them to install a sip
phone in their home and worry about you
know all sorts of crazy networking
issues and user issues with with people
trying to figure out how the phone works
because all they've got to do is open a
web browser so let's call this thing
it's got something of a unique ringtone
a a non call center ring Tim will get a
try let's make that go away that's kind
of knowing me every see ok you get a lot
of me ringtones with photo as well so
the interesting thing here is that I've
been able to attach to this this answer
event essentially and what I what I can
do with that is i can update my couch to
be instance and say this agent is not
ready now its agents on the phone so if
calls are coming in and I'm querying my
CouchDB instance to get agents who can
take a phone call I know that this agent
is now occupied so not to send a call to
them so just real quickly if you go into
this um this solution you'll see there's
others and there's a it runs with
asterisk so asterisk is a anybody ever
heard of a stress before okay it's an
open-source telephony platform nodejs is
actually a really good complement to
asterisk and one of the things I've
gotten here is a note script that
actually is a a TCP server that will
accept connections from asterisk and
then it will use an HTTP client to
connect to a CouchDB and because you can
build network applications so easily
with no tits it's a it's a really really
good fit for for this solution so if you
go to my my github repo and you check
out remote agent I think you'll like it
it's a pretty cool project and I'd love
to hear any feedback zappos call center
man right here okay so what I didn't
show you was the ability to send and
receive instant messages with a phono
instance as well you can do that in the
web browser
anything about that is if you want to
route calls to an agent you can give
them a screen pop and say we'll do a
quick color ID look up and say hey it's
Joe Smith calling here we can hit a CRM
system and say hey Joe Smith ordered x
y&z the last time he called so the agent
can answer a go hello mr. Smith I see
you I see you received a you received
your your your shoes or whatever
whatever we're buying too okay so I
mentioned just a second ago nodejs and
you know the ability to build network
applications so phone calls are
happening on networks happening on IP
network so the ability to build
something that can speak and consume
network based protocols is is really
important for telephones so this is this
is still sort of new there's a there's
actually a sip module four node the
author doesn't there's a lot of
documentation on it buddy he's very open
to conversation and email about it I and
one of my colleagues Chris Matthew who
was done in the middle there we have
actually a conversations this guy is
very helpful what I wanted to do was I
wanted to build a sip registrar so
except sip registrar is a component that
keeps track of supply ins because sip
clients can can exist anywhere their IP
addresses can change based on what
network their connection connecting to
so sip registrar basically a sip phone
will register and say Here I am I'm at
this location so all somebody has to do
to find that person and call them is
simply called the Registrar using the
registrar's address the Registrar will
tell that phone oh this person's over
here you need to redirect over here or
this person has now moved over here so I
wanted to build it with with no j/s I
also wanted to build it with with Redis
um because these registrations really
are sort of an extension number in a
separate dress so it's sort of name
value pairs seem like a really easy fit
for 44 ready I certainly could have
built it just using straight node you
know just using an array or something
and just storing up these things but I
wanted to sort of make it more real
world so I'm going to what I'm going to
do is I'm actually going to show you the
sip registrar than a bill and we'll see
if we need to work that won't work
because I don't
we're running ok so what I'm going to do
is first time I hang up the phone I want
to get this zip line this is a blink sip
client it's pretty nice I got no
complaints about it but I but what I
want to tell it to do is to register
with this machine the IP address that
I've been given by this network and I'm
just going to use an extension of 200 so
I told it to register and it didn't it
came back green and their day there's my
registration the actual code for this
see okay can everybody see this yes no
no can't see that are you for real so
all right well yeah yeah so this is
probably a little bit too much to
consume in this manner let me just let
me just let me just go and break it down
for you like this so there's this
awesome Redis module 4 4 4 node i
recommend it it's it's really easy to
use and as I mentioned before there's a
sip there's a sip module that I'm using
so I want to handle basically two kinds
of sip messages I want to handle a
registration or register so when a sip
request comes in that is a register
request I want to populate the IP
address basically the SIP fully
qualified sip address of where that
phone is in Redis and i also want to log
them off if they close their phone down
so that I don't have a record for them
the other thing I want to do is when i
get a sip invite which is what a sip
client will do when it wants to connect
to another client it will send a sip
invitation what i'll do is i'll send
back a an initial response with a 100
saying i'm trying i'm going to look up
this person and see if i can find them
now this is typically where you'll hear
a ringtone so your client has been told
ok the the other end is trying to find
where to route your call please hold
them will play a nice ringtone for you
and when I find them if I don't find
that mug in the 404 back you know this
this should look and feel a lot like
HTTP right if I do find them I'll give
them a sip 302 we
is a redirect so all I'm doing here is
saying I'm going to look up the person
that you're trying to contact and then
I'm going to tell your sip client to go
and find them where they've last
registered and then you're to sip
clients will negotiate the entire call
you'll exchange media you'll have this
great conversation it's all powered with
you no less than eighty five lines of
nodejs and that's probable I'm probably
being a little verbose here we could get
this down under 50 easy so if what I
just said to you was true I do have a
registration so I should be able to read
us and go get what did I register your
mat 200 yeah so there it is there it is
sitting in Redis now I should be able to
call that that's sip address at my local
host because that's where this is
running and if I do that actually let's
stick to the world my phone should i
phone rings I'm going to reject that cuz
I'm going to get a weird echo if I
answer the phone and trying to talk as
well so that seems sort of anticlimactic
compared to the last one but trust me on
that that is that is pretty awesome to
be able to write a sip registrar with
with no Jas and using using a database
like Redis there are some pretty
sophisticated and complicated sip
registrar us out there I mean while mine
does not do some of the things that they
do it's still pretty neat that you can
roll your own sip registrar with with
knows yes so it sort of underscores my
point my contention that nodejs I
believe going forward has a really
important rule to play in telephony
because increasingly tell F&E is
happening on IP networks okay
back to my okay here's the other thing
that no jess is really good at it's
really good at gluing disparate
components together to make a really
interesting application so sticking with
red us for a minute one of the really
neat things about red us is that and it
has nothing to do with red as being a
datastore is that red is can act as a
published subscribed framework basically
so clients can connect your reticence
and they can publish on a channel and
other clients can subscribe to a channel
and listen for messages on that channel
and everybody that's register excuse me
everybody that's subscribed to a channel
gets the message when a publisher
publishes to that channel so I wanted to
use a troppo app and I wanted to use
speech recognition and I wanted to have
reticence since out in the cloud so I
ended up going with red stratus to go
which they have a bunch of nice plans
and it's very easy to use so the tropo
app just to sort of I guess make the
point that Chris made it I think the
first day or early yesterday you said
you know this is even though we're here
to talk about JavaScript it's there's a
there's a there's a role to play in lots
of other languages so as a nod to that
that that notion I've coated this in PHP
that's a PHP application i'm going to
show you the code in just a second and
what it's going to do it's going to it's
going to publish information on a
channel that's in Redis Redis instance
running in a cloud so I want to be able
to do something with this information in
a web page and so I'm using nodejs as
sort of a proxy subscriber for a web
page I'm going to use again the node
Redis module which is really awesome and
socket i/o which is equally awesome and
just use some simple jQuery and web page
so oops oops oops
um there's a lot in this but this is the
meat of it right here I'm going to
connect to a reticence in someone who
authenticated i'm going to say welcome
to the Redis hello that actually makes
it sound better then I'm going to prompt
the user I'm just going to say tell me
the color you want to say tell me the
color you want to see and every time i
do that i'm going to i'm going to
publish on this troppo color channel and
when they say stop I'll just connect say
goodbye and hang up that's pretty much
it as I mentioned before regice to go
I'm using this free plan down here which
is very inconspicuously advertised so
let me see if I can run this yeah so
first let me show you the node
sorry let's do this
it's a really simple no script just
using the reddest module and socket i/o
let me also show you a secular
works in that running line serving it
let's do this so this is all on github
and I'm going to probably beg your
indulgence and point you to the github
repo it where it will be easier for you
to understand this but it's very simple
node scripts it's going to get it's
going to subscribe to a Redis channel
it's going to get information from that
channel and it's going to push it to a
web page that's through socket i/o let's
do this okay so I'm now connected and my
reddest client is subscribed to the
tropo color channel now we can look at
the so this is really easy I'm not
really doing much here I'm getting some
information and I'm modifying some CSS
that's pretty much all I'm doing but
actually turns out that's really kind of
cool so this is my troppo application
when you set up a troppo application you
get a lot of stuff for free you get a
skype address and a sip address that you
can use so I've given this demo a few
times I've actually gave it um a month
ago and in San Francisco so I've got a
San Francisco number and I've also got a
portland number that I've provisioned so
so I guess with all that lead up this
should really be this better be
something good right it's what you're
saying bear with me for just a second
ok
hey the color you want to see blue blue
yellow
okay I'm gonna hang it up now the other
neat thing about troppo is that I
mentioned before that the tools that we
use need to be channel agnostic right so
we need to be able to use one code base
and we need to be able to serve multiple
channels well troppo does that really
well so what I've done is I've gone
ahead and I've added a an instant
messaging just a simple jabber account
to this application and what that will
let me do is then interact with this
thing via I am same code base that's
just serving on a different Channel the
other neat thing I can do why don't we
do this since you've all set here very
patiently listen to me blather on about
all this we do this if you send a text
message through that number the choices
should be red green blue white and
yellow I think we should see Ruby got it
it's 5038 479 31 6 oops somewhere my OH
hold please let it go oh there is sorry
so if i send a text message to 5038 479
31 6 should get is a change in color
there we go somebody's textin keep going
come on send green i sent green so so
it's just sort of illustrates the point
that the tools we need to use going
forward are going to need to be need to
be agnostic to channel and this is one
way of addressing that need you guys are
going to keep texting are you all right
okay so before I don't know if people
have questions I'm not even sure where I
am on time but i just cannot underscore
a couple things so the way that we
develop telephone applications has
changed dramatically recently and it's
because web development has changed the
way we build things has changed and
there's a desire for easier ways to do
things so for javascript developers that
means we've got lots of choices now and
how we build powerful multi-channel
communication applications I believe
very strongly that going forward nodejs
will play a very important part in
telephony and in how we build and deploy
telephone applications because of the
things it does it's very easy to build
network applications with node we all
know that that is a perfect fit for
telephone applications because telephone
app telephones telephone calls happen on
networks the other thing is telephone
environments are very their their event
rich they're full of events connections
disconnections transfers the whole the
whole life cycle of call progress
analysis in terms of figuring out
whether you're talking to a human or a
machine very event rich in the nodes
event model is a really really good fit
for that I believe I don't know of
anybody that's doing CPA call progress
analysis with node I wouldn't be
surprised I didn't know there was
anybody doing a sip module until I went
out and looked
um so it's all good we have lots of
choices and there are lots of cool stuff
to build thank you very much Laura did
you remember to load the bacon oh I knew