everybody hopefully can you can hear me
okay uh yes I want to know we're okay
trust me I'm a professional so look uh
sadly I don't have any any code to show
you which honestly like makes me cry a
little bit on the inside there's nothing
more nothing I like more than then live
coding but I do have an interesting talk
that I hope you're all going to like but
I want to start it off with a magic
trick and actually need your
participation I need everybody here to
pull out their mobile phone and
presumably if you're using something
other than a motorola razr there will be
a calculator application on your mobile
phone so just go ahead and pull that out
and all we're going to do is I'm going
to ask you a bunch of questions that are
going to generate unique numbers for you
and I want we're going to add those
numbers together on the calculator and
I'm going to participate it right so I'm
going to I'm going to kind of come along
with you on this journey so the first
thing I want you to do is think of a
very important moment in your life it
can be any kind of moment but something
that is incredibly and deeply meaningful
for you for me I became a father in 2010
when my daughter catherine was born so i
am going to type in 2010 and hit plus so
just go ahead and type in that year and
hit plus the next thing I want you to
type in is your age either you're a diff
your birthday was in the past or in the
Peten you know this this year yeah sorry
if you're perth if your birthday was
earlier this year it's however old you
are if your birthday is going to be
before the end of the year it's however
old you're going to be before the end of
the year so go ahead and type that in
and press + now I want you to type in
the integer value of the current month
so October is 10 November's 11 type in
the integer value for December and hit
plus now whatever the number of your
mobile phone is I want you to think of
the last four digits of that number and
i want you to enter it in i have to kind
of think it think it through but ok yes
and then hit plus uh now this is easy
the year you were born I was born a
really long time ago i'm not going to
say it out loud I'm and hit plus and
lastly that really meaningful event in
your life whatever year it took place
just think how many years it's been
since that really important moment and
type it in and hit plus so I've got a
number hopefully you all have numbers I
would wager that they are all unique and
now I would like you to simply compose a
text message to the number that you see
on the screen I'll go ahead and read it
out 97 95 89 55 55 and ask the question
the very pertinent question what is my
number and I will go ahead and play
along myself what is my number okay cool
and hit Send now hopefully if everything
is working you'll get a response back
and you know compare that response to
the number that's in your calculator
okay now look if you know how this trick
works keep it to yourself you know for
at least the next 20 minutes but if you
don't know how it works you know how do
you feel right now do you feel surprised
do you feel a little bit of are you
astonished you know do you have a
feeling of wonder well I want you to
hold on to those feelings because that's
exactly how I feel that open source I
love this I love that I love that so
much open source is magic or at least it
evokes the same feelings to me for me
that magic does every time I go to the
console and I type in NPM install I take
a moment to think about the fact that
I've got over a hundred thousand things
that I could install and that's because
of open source we are all building
amazing things on the shoulders of other
people and frankly they in turn are
building their things on top of yet
other people and this is a this is a
remarkable world that we live in I'm not
entirely sure everyone in the node
community is sufficiently appreciative
or grateful of the remarkable ecosystem
that we operate in but I know I am this
past October a wonderful woman by the
name of Lena Reinhart gave a talk on
open source at jas confi you it was
about the future of open source if you
haven't seen this talk go to the JSP you
website all the videos are posted feel
free to watch it I thought it was
wonderful
and you know she reminded me that you
know virtually every transformative
technology that we all take for granted
at least in the past 10 to 20 years is
built on top of open source so you know
open source really is magical now I'm
going to kind of take a left turn I'm
going to get away from software i'm
going to talk about community and
community and that the IRL sense right
the in real life like right here like
we're all in the same room I got my
start in community back in January of
2012 that's when i joined twilio as a
developer evangelist i had never been a
developer evangelist before i had really
hadn't the foggiest notion what the job
entails it sounded pretty cool so I dove
in and for me I discovered very rapidly
that a massive component of my job was
going to be to support my local
developer community now I don't know if
I mentioned it but I live in Seattle but
I had a lot of agency in defining what
those words actually meant like what was
local like for me local wasn't just
Seattle like I wanted to make a
difference in Seattle and other
communities in the Pacific Northwest so
that includes obviously portland oregon
and vancouver british columbia and like
support right like I don't there are
many many ways you can support a
community and I had to kind of decide
for myself or figure out for myself what
that was going to be and by the end of
the year me and some really remarkable
people in that community put on a
conference called Cascadia jess and you
saw some hands go up and you've seen
some pretty awesome hoodies around the
room and yeah the Cascadia jess is a
conference for web developers that takes
place in the Pacific Northwest and we
put this on in November of 2012 and it's
just I love looking at this photo
because I have a lot of special memories
that came out of this event but also i'd
love to see the people right i mean
there's there's what Rick Waldron you
know minus the beard this is what I used
to look like there's a Dominic denticola
looking actually exactly the same after
three years ago oh wait there's a here
the guy that you didn't see today
there's Dominic tar he's right there
he's not here right now he's I guess he
got tear-gassed or something
anyway but you know this event was
special for me for a lot of reasons but
mostly because it made very tangible and
real my ability to make a difference in
a community it took something that was
abstract and made it real but the last
couple years I've had this nagging
question in my head like why aren't more
people doing this and it's been it's
very perplexing for me right because you
know I I get so much joy and pleasure
and satisfaction out of contributing to
the community and working on these
things but at the same time I go to all
these events and I just see a lot of the
same faces and a lot of the same people
it's almost like a click and it's
bizarre I don't understand why more
developers and more people aren't
getting more involved in the community
like the developer community in general
is growing you know like an exponential
rate right but i don't i don't believe
that the community of organizers is
growing as fast so this is very
perplexing for me and i think it's
actually like it's not just perplexing
it's incredibly problematic so i did you
know what any person does who sort of
cares about you know being data-driven i
sent out a survey to a lot of developers
that either i knew personally or whose
work I respected and it's very simple
survey it's like you know tell me about
how you involved you are in the
community tell me some things that you
like about being involved tell me some
things that you don't like about being
involved I wanted and I made sure I
didn't I didn't send the survey to
anybody who is an evangelist I just
wanted to talk to developers whose
community activities are not their
primary job and I got a lot of really
interesting responses and I asked for
permission to share some of them so
Justin Meyer I think you can read this
and you'll probably not your heads right
i mean this is this is something that's
unfortunate about both online community
and offline community but it's really
it's really it's really sad for me how
many people repeated that kind of a
comment because I feel like we've made a
lot of progress I think things are there
are I thought I thought there were fewer
assholes out there but maybe I'm maybe
there aren't maybe there aren't fewer
enough and I think I myself have
underestimated how how how much of a
barrier this can be for people wanting
to get involved
another comment which is actually really
interesting for me was from brenna
O'Brien is she here which is this was
really interesting for me because
because I don't consider myself to be an
intimidating person and I don't consider
the Cascadia Jazz community to be an
intimidating community but I have to
deal with the fact that I don't I may
not be I mean clearly not have any idea
like what is intimidating to other
people and this and this is this is this
was I'm really glad she shared this
because I think it's entirely possible
that despite my desire and my
community's desire to be approachable
we're not working hard enough so it's
really really good to hear that but
there was still a problem that I
couldn't figure out like why did I feel
so removed from this so those barriers
were like in or you know difficult
dispute but nonetheless like I myself
had overcome them like I do all this
stuff and so why did I feel so
personally removed from these problems
that other people were voicing it is not
because I'm special i promise you i'm
the least special person here so it's
all right so i had a real real sort of
you know a question about like why you
know why you know why i was having such
a different experience than others so in
order to answer that question let's
let's take that a right turn right back
into open source and let's talk about
something called a community of practice
so this is something that came up in
Lena's talk and there's a wonderful
ebook called the open-source way that
was written by the community
architecture team at Red Hat and they
talk about communities of practice so
this was popularized by a theorist and
attend winger and essentially a
community of practice you can read what
it is but the people at Red Hat feel
that the open-source way is just sort of
in an instance or an instantiation of
this larger idea of a community of
practice and in fact all professions are
ultimately can be thought of as a
community of practice and the ideas and
the communities of practice are just a
theory of social learning so you can
even go back to hunter-gatherers and you
can talk about how they learned to hunt
and gather among each other as a
community of practice and the reason I
bring this up to you is that if every
profession is a community of power can
be thought of as a community of
this then my profession can be thought
of as a community of practice like
evangelism or advocacy or develop
developer relations I apologize for the
word its kind of polarizing but I really
thought back like about what I've been
doing over the last three years and when
I really took stock of what I've been
doing it's kind of remarkable I've
probably been to over a hundred events
in the past three years I've met some of
the brightest and best event organizers
in the world I've met some of the worst
event organizers in the world I've seen
what works and I've seen what doesn't
work and I think I take for granted like
how what the insane amount of learning
that that I've experienced over this
time in addition I'm not alone I'm on a
team of a dozen other evangelists at
twilio who are having the same kinds of
experiences at the same pace and our
team has this culture of writing
everything down we write down everything
and we share it amongst the team either
in the form of email or updating a wiki
or what-have-you right there's this
culture of learning and sharing and I
you know it was sort of staggering to
really think about it and you know I
don't know how many of you read Michaels
blog post on creating a better note
community but this this part really
stuck out for me right you know because
when you make it clear and obvious what
people can do they'll do it well the
inverse is that when you don't make it
clear and you don't make it obvious
people won't do it like you are when you
don't write things down you are creating
either explicit or implicit barriers for
people to contribute to your community
which it's so obvious when you when you
when you think about it but you know
it's shocking how resistant people are
to writing things down this comes up
with codes of conduct I can't tell you
how many people have told me that they
don't need a code of conduct because
they're cool and they're organizers are
cool and everybody's cool and why do we
have to write it down happens all the
time super frustrating so we have a lot
of work to do and that's exactly what i
want to do you know with the spare time
that I have moving forward like I want
to you know i'm not the best developer
or engineer you know in this room but i
have i've learned a lot about community
over the last few years and i want to
start writing it down and that's what I
mean
open sourcing community publishing the
processes procedures and policies around
community events and this has already
started to happen I mean I'm certainly
not getting up here and you know
pounding my fist about we need to start
from scratch like it's not true chris
williams i'm the founder of JS comp you
know he wrote a blog post years ago i
think about how to run a jay s comp so
people have started to do this and in
bits and pieces but i think we need to
grossly accelerate the process for
Cascadia jess i started working on a
document about how to run an event
exactly like cascade ajs it's you know
it's up on our github repo it's very
incomplete it needs so much more work
but it's an order of magnitude more
detailed than Chris's blog post I mean
it gets into like really you know tough
questions like finances and sponsors and
speaker wrangling and stuff like that
like this is just stuff that this is
stuff that that is not written down
anywhere because I had to learn it
myself usually through incredibly you
know long tedious conversations too used
to other people you know like with
people like Michael and Chris you know
just sort of begging them to teach me
but I think we need to document more of
the stuff I was thrilled to discover a
node school a few months ago and I can't
believe how far they've come since sort
of creating this concept and I have to
believe that part of the reason that
it's grown as fast as it has is because
should you go to the website and click
on that little host button on the right
there is an incredibly thoughtful right
up on exactly how you can create a
chapter right like that like tweet me at
max Ogden and I'll like we'll talk on
the phone like no like serious and if
you've ever helped do a node school
meeting you've either attended or you've
helped host we stand up
give yourself a round of applause and I
but I think like once again like it
there are other things that are that I
think are actually just as cool as notes
cool but they they weren't as thoughtful
about making it clear how people can
participate and because of that they
they have their nichy and they haven't
grown so this is it's obvious but not
enough people do it and I'm glad that
that note school is doing it and you
know the last thing and this is
something I'm I'm sad about like how to
contribute right like this is
open-source 101 right like if you have
an open source project and you don't and
you don't have a contributing dot
markdown file you know shame on you
write like that is that's just so basic
but i think i think events need
something like this and i'm not going to
pretend to be super prescriptive or have
the answers but I'm we're starting to
think about this for Cascadia j/s right
like if you want to contribute to
cascade ajs I don't want you to feel
like you have to be friends with me or
you have to have a relationship with me
or one of the other organizers like
there should be a more transparent path
to contributing to an event that is not
my event it's it's the community's event
so we've started to write some of these
things down and you know I hope to get
feedback on what we're doing but I'll
walk you through some of them the first
thing is just be super explicit about
setting expectations like in written
form tell people clearly like what are
the amazing things about contributing to
a conference but be honest about the
things that are tough and aren't super
great be explicit about what you need
help with this was taught to me by Alex
Sexton you know he said like it is so
stupid when in this this applies to all
kinds of events but like if you run a
meet-up if you just sort of put your you
put sent an email out and say hey I need
help with the meetup like don't be
surprised if nobody responds to you but
if you do send an email out saying I
need help and specifically I need
someone to help videotape the meetups
like you'd be amazed at the people who
will be able to who will think to
themselves oh I know how to do that I
will now help you have to be explicit
about what you need help with facilitate
conversation as much as possible this is
tough like I literally just discovered
get er like a month ago kind of
late adopter but you know I think it's
important i think more conversation and
communication needs to be done in places
that are sort of publicly accessible so
that maybe even before someone is sure
whether or not they want to contribute
to your event they can kind of lurk and
just sort of get a feel for what kind of
community you are and what kind of
people you are and what you care about
encourage people as much as possible to
document and share their experiences I
was very happy when I went to the node
school page that on that host page is a
link of tons of write-ups from other
organizers about their experiences right
people sometimes people make the mistake
of thinking that everything has to be
canonical like this is not true like
everyone has their own reasons for
wanting to do a node school or their
their own experiences doing it they're
all different right and it's useful for
someone thinking about getting involved
to be able to read through all of those
things and create a fuller picture of
what's going on you know and lastly you
know a clear code of conduct code of
conduct aren't just for events at least
I don't think they are I think as we
start to as Cascadia gist or to
incorporate more people that we that we
don't have personal relationships with I
think we need to be super clear about
like what kind of conduct is expected
not just at the conference but you know
leading up to it and the last door I
want to share with you on so this is
Doug McKenzie he's a magician he did not
teach me the magic trick I showed you
figured it out all by myself but he has
a magician I met him about a month ago
he's an incredibly thoughtful person
he's also a developer so he's like a
magician / developer and he might be
like literally the only one in the world
he's also an incredibly thoughtful guy
and I was talking to Doug about open
source and he he had this to share he he
believed he knows that he couldn't have
become a magician without the generosity
of many other magicians kind of sharing
them some tips and some tricks and some
methods right but in that community
there's also the realization that
oftentimes like your secrets are your
livelihood there how you earn a living
so there's this tension between
wanting to share more but also wanting
to you know to pay the mortgage and i
think that you know i think that i think
india in the community event space
there's a similar dynamic there are
event organizers myself included who
feel like there's a little bit of magic
in the experiences that we create and
there's a little bit of reticence you
know to share the secrets because we
feel that's that's what makes our event
magical but uh but i think that we have
to we all have to reserve resist that
urge and share as much as we possibly
can because you know ultimately you know
community is magic right like i could
not have created cascade ejs if not for
the generosity of people like Michael
and chris williams and you know magical
things happen at these events this is a
picture of my daughter Catherine hanging
out to Rebecca Murphy and like I don't
know if she remembers this Ted of
experience or not but maybe she does
maybe that's why she grows up to be a
computer scientist someday like I don't
know right but I know that we need to
enable more people more kinds of people
to create and contribute to community
events because that's the only way that
we can sure that our ensure that our
community has a vibrant future right not
just for me and not just for you but for
the people who are coming later so I
hope you all will help me with this and
thank you for listening to my talk about