[Music]
I'm gonna do a quick intro we are using
create react app but then there was the
react license thing going on and then we
saw that for react 16 as you can see
here it's not gonna be very good for web
components and any external libraries
used so we were like hey what else can
we do so we stopped react and we try to
find a way to switch over to pre-act
which what priya compact can use the
same API as react but we might smaller
have nice support for external libraries
and web components and all this stuff so
I'm gonna show this to you and like five
steps start the step zero so first you
set up a project with create react app
and what you get is a hundred and twenty
three kilobyte javascript file which
does nothing it's a 38 after gzipping
but of course all of this has to be
parsed and it's quite big this is how it
looks
react just react Dom takes up 80% of the
whole thing so then I was looking at how
this whole thing is built up and and
well what I found you can do is you take
the scripts that react is using which is
this in react scripts build and real
scripts start and then you just hack web
pack to replace anything that's react
with pre-act compare and react down
would also create combat so this way
when you run build or run start then you
will actually get pre act in your code
for testing it's a bit trickier what
what you need to do is replace a bunch
of stuff in just you can check this repo
the URLs up there if you can read it and
I did need to hack it a bit
I take the module constructor of note to
resolve the just config to this replace
just config and you write test a little
bit differently but you have render and
shallow render and you can have snapshot
testing and run stuff there's also this
hack which is because of Babel pre-sale
react that itself and source but
basically you're still writing the same
code and it becomes 38 kilobytes before
gzipping and 13 afterwards so after this
I was looking at what else can I do so I
I was like okay we don't need ie 9 and
10 so you can patch be able to use ie 11
as a target I also made a really really
shitty less compiler with watch which
you just changed some stuff where is
thank you Jason it's gone here that you
build the CSS and wash the CSS when you
start or build or test or whatever then
our security guys were like hey we need
some resource integrity right now and I
still didn't want AJ because I just
don't want to maintain wet pad coffee
because it's all the same everywhere why
should you so you go in and you push to
the plugins to add the ESRI plug-in to
web pack and it just works out of the
box so yeah you can check the repo here
and still have one minute so here's a
picture of my cat
[Applause]