test testing yeah well better hmm
feedback good yeah awesome okay so uh
what makes something revolutionary all
right something is revolutionary if it
totally disrupts the established order
and it replaces this order with a new
order namely itself and it's going to
completely change the dynamics of
everything around it so we've been
witnessing this massive shift in
front-end development it's becoming one
of the most in-demand specializations
and we we have all these new tools and
frameworks that are really not only
changing our lives as developers and
designers but they're affecting how we
do things on a day-to-day basis and it's
this it's their effect on we do things
they're giving us these capabilities
that we can basically turn into new
opportunities so for example get comes
out in 2005 and then three years later
we get github and it's this
transformation that I actually believe
is revolutionary our tools are
transforming our behaviors and to quote
Clay Shirky revolutions don't happen
when society adopts new technologies
they happen when we adopt new behaviors
so what are these new behaviors that
we've adopted first let's make sure that
we're on the same page about what I mean
with the behavior and how behaviors come
to be so a behavior is the product of
three factors and this is fogs behavior
model he studies persuasive technology
at Stanford and in this model he states
that in order for a behavior to occur
you have to have sufficient motivation
sufficient ability and you have to be
triggered so motivation is pretty much
the worst thing should never rely on
motivation for trying to get someone to
change their behavior we all know how
well New Year's resolutions go you're
really motivated couple days later
are not so great ability as you can see
here can really be thought of as a
factor of how easy something is to do so
the more the easier it is the more able
one is and lastly trigger so dr. fog
actually really believes that we should
focus on triggers and simple triggers
will help us create habits and habits
are nothing more than automatic
behaviors so now we're going to walk
through and see how our tools basically
got us to change our behavior and they
did two things first we had to adopt the
tool which is a behavior change and then
as a consequence of adopting that tool
we gained some new behaviors and I'm
going to walk you through this so to
understand how this came to be we need
to back up a little bit and we need to
go back to the mid-aughts and there is a
lot happening in development and around
2004 we had the release of the rails and
Django frameworks 2005 we had get
frameworks and we also had this slew of
JavaScript frameworks that were that
were coming up and they were really
aimed at helping developers address the
inconsistencies across browsers because
it was a nightmare and so jQuery comes
out in 2006 and it wasn't the first
framework but it was the only one that
took into consideration three factors
that allowed it to succeed first jquery
itself was a simple solution to the
problem the code was really simple it
address one thing and it did it really
well and that was letting us this deal
with dom manipulation second from the
get-go jquery released with really good
documentation so prototype actually had
pretty much been adopted into rails by
that point and it kind of was the the
main one but it didn't have
documentation in fact it was like after
a year before it actually released
documentation and the last one that I
think is incredibly important
is John really understood the value of
community and so from the get-go he
issued this invitation to participate in
to collaborate and it took off the
second day someone released a plug-in
and this was this was incredible for us
I mean prior it was very difficult for
us to contribute back to JavaScript
interview back to our front-end
languages in fact it's sort of
JavaScript tumultuous the history that
got us into this browser war place in
the first place so really what jQuery
did is it created this environment where
people could get things done without any
barriers it made it incredibly simple to
get started and allowed anyone with
sufficient motivation to contribute and
it's a success arguably jQuery is the
number one framework and use on the web
to date but beyond its fame for me it's
these three simple design decisions that
have started to affect other languages
to date and I've really led to the rise
of like no Jas and our newer frameworks
and our new ways of doing things so
jQuery paved the road and set an example
of what to do and collaboration really
cannot be underestimated it means the
prospect for new ideas that can make our
tools better so because we're so steeped
in this culture it can be really hard to
forget that collaboration in front end
is a new thing it and for CSS this
ability is actually even more recent so
let's go back we're going to still stay
in about two thousand seven or CSS was
just a giant nightmare and around that
time we had decided that 960 pixels was
like the best way and the only way that
we should design we also had a bunch of
IE things to deal with
and while we had css3 and we were really
excited to stop all these hacky ways of
having to create border radius or like
load our our HTML with a ton of images
just for gradients all it did was
introduce a bunch of complexities and it
really just made us incredibly desperate
for a solution so and then additionally
this thing was about to come out and
completely flip how we thought of web
development and take our standards and
just turn them upside down so we were
clamoring for a way to deal with this
problem and really I see the rise of CSS
preprocessors as almost inevitable in a
way because CSS was so difficult we had
high motivation and were motivated
enough that we were going to seek out a
solution so much like what was happening
in JavaScript we had all these different
options but it really came down to two
these two and how did that come to be
first I've been much the same way as as
what happened in in the JavaScript
community sass and less did a really
good job at addressing the
inconsistencies less actually remained a
really powerful contender because it was
a lot easier to use and it gave us that
same power without the hurdles of having
to deal with like an indented syntax and
setting up Ruby and all these other
complications when all we wanted to do
with style and make our sites beautiful
granted the adoption in Twitter
bootstrap didn't help but I actually
think that now that Twitter bootstrap
has released an official passport we're
going to see much more focus on that and
less on left and before I go on I do
want to thank less for one thing if it
wasn't for less I don't believe that
sass would have would have adopted the S
CSS syntax as quickly as possible
and so the designers of SAS were really
aware that hey you know what by doing
this we're going to make it a lot easier
to get people to change their behavior
and to get people to adopt staff so
that's what they did but there was one
other major turning point that really
allowed SAS to edge out less and that
was compass compass was kind of like the
jQuery for SAS and in fact compass
really abided by the same three design
decisions that allowed jQuery to stake
its hold in front-end development SAS
was pluggable at first by design but we
weren't really sure what to do with it
so Chris releases compass and shows us
what we can do with these new
capabilities it's simple it's at this
get-go the most popular thing was
probably the css3 mixin so that we
didn't have to write all those crappy
border radiuses and vendor prefixes
second it had really good documentation
you could actually learn how these
mix-ins and these things were created
which helped you create new ones and
third Chris also issued a a call for
community and you could create your own
compass extensions and we learned how to
make Ruby gems and we release them why
because we really really really really
wanted to and to date there are over a
hundred and forty-two compass and SAS
extensions and it's growing those are
just the people that have registered so
we can see that we really wanted really
we're looking forward to this and we're
happy to share when that opportunity was
presented so our front-end tools are
really lowering the threshold for
finding good ideas as a result these
good ideas are getting incorporated back
into the parent language so you can see
CSS borrowing variable taking variables
and some of the things that the newer
stuff from SAS and also on JavaScript
the influence
of coffee script is really guiding the
newer decisions for the tc39 team and
harmony but what's really amazing is
that we are now empowered to do this
ourselves without having to rely on
these institutions I mean they're a
little slow moving and I know they have
rules in place but if we had waited for
them can you imagine where we'd be right
now not fun so our tools have triggered
this participatory cultural revolution
but really changing how we are able to
work together and to work around
obstacles and barriers it's really a
fundamental new way of thinking about
innovation it's bottom up it's
participatory its democratic it's a
little crazy and all these are great
phase our tools have enabled groups and
individuals to try radical things by
removing any barriers we've created
environments who people want to get
things done and they can and not only
that our environments are encouraging
and supportive and they're nurturing our
creativity and individuality these are
the necessary ingredients for change
collective participation plus collective
action
our ability to learn and work is growing
stronger and stronger in a relatively
short span of time we have completely
changed how we do things I mean we
wouldn't really dream of approaching a
project without any one of these new
tools so
what's the point of all of this right at
a certain point we're kind of like why
do we need so many things do we need yet
another build tool and yet another
static site generator and yet another
way to process or compile our CSS I mean
it may start to really seem redundant
but it's really not quite yet because
right now the best thing that we can do
is to continue to spur and encourage
this innovation our imagination or
creativity a lot of our life is sort of
spent focusing us down these paths and
the more that we can stay open and allow
ourselves to experiment the more new
ideas that we can keep generating so I
really predict that in the following
years we're going to start to see a
shift from technical problems to more
human problems it's going to be about
the human connection tech will be a part
of what we do but it's not going to be
that first solution that we should jump
to right so we really need to take care
right now to make sure that we are
building helpful welcoming communities
that are going to celebrate diversity
and difference let's continue to ensure
that we are open and supportive to
everyone no matter beliefs skill set
skill level or discipline remember to be
kind and in the words of Chris Epstein
let's not firm form cliques
so what's incredibly wonderful and
encouraging to me and should be to
everyone is that we are actually
succeeding look at us here today the
organizers of this conference value
community value diversity and they and
they put that first and it's incredible
the second thing that I also found
really interesting that we might not
know is that at the same time that we've
been changing our behaviors we've
actually done so in a way that's
designed for resilience so this is a
small world network and what it how it
works is that you have these tightly
small connected groups that then have
loose connections to a larger group so
here like this would be kind of our
larger group and within this I'm sure we
have like tightly smaller groups like
see some of my SAS people over there and
I'm sure there's no dl and every but and
despite that we have these tiny little
close connections and then we can branch
out and so small world networks are
actually incredibly advantageous they
first are resistant to damage which
makes us really strong and second they
transmit information really well we act
both as amplifiers and filters
so given that we are so skilled at
creating such a resilient network that
is based on valuing contributions and
the uniqueness of every community member
and the fact that we can do this in such
a short amount of time I really believe
that we have a lot to contribute back to
society beyond just beautiful websites
so citizens the world over are calling
for a change and I really believe along
with many others that this change is
only going to come to a participatory
revolution we're the same design
decisions that made our tools so great
and allowed them to succeed are applied
to other systems like urban planning and
education so we developers and designers
have an immensely valuable perspective
to share beyond just our tech
communities we are successful practicing
models of participatory culture I mean
we're more than just you I developers in
my mind we are leaders of one of the
largest movements in the world so being
a front-end developer means to hold this
immense power in your hand write code
literacy suddenly becomes more than just
a job or career change it's the ability
to contribute to this large human
network
so what
decide what we want to do with our new
capabilities what opportunities do we
want to create where do we want to
create these opportunities be it here
for our front-end communities or back
home for your neighborhoods remember
we're doing something right already so
as you create an experiment remember to
encourage and reward participation along
every step of the way don't worry
doesn't have to be a big thing make
up right now thank you Eric Suzanne and
if we can get he's right over there by
the way so I believe if we continue to
do this right if we continue to innovate
in the way that we've just observed our
innovations are going to certainly have
a really really high potential to
continue to be revolutionary thank you
very much