cool so I'm gonna talk about JavaScript
tooling uh this is a bit about kind of
what the ecosystem with tools are around
kind of rich web app development so i'll
be talking about the existing tooling
framework kind of contextualizing it
into the developer experience also be
demoing quite a few things some chrome
developer tools new features but yeah
okay so i think we'll start off with the
goal and i know this is my goal I I
think many of these people here share to
which is that we want rich web apps we
want powerful web apps that are fast fun
responsive awesome to use provide new
compelling unique experiences and the
problem that I think that we face a lot
or that I see is that well development
of course takes time but a lot of that
time we're spending on common tasks
things that not only that we've done
before like individually but also the
collective we has done before I don't
want to do the exact same thing that
Alex did two weeks ago and rewrite it in
my version so I want to be able to you
know take advantage of of the hive mind
the the community so no developer wants
to be operating on mundane tasks
spinning their wheels they want to
create and craft unique experiences so
tools allow a lot of power so I'm going
to talk a little bit about that
situation talking about tools is kind of
a abroad thing and to capture kind of
everything that encompassed I asked a
while ago kind of with the tools that
you use and I got responses like these
so this captures everything from CSS
preprocessors minification
concatenations of build tools templating
languages web frameworks your clients at
NBC I mean everything you could consider
all these things tools and I say that's
that's fair but this is quite a few
things and this is only a portion of
this and all of these projects
competitors so I want to kind of
contextualize this a little bit more so
here is my my attempt
this funny little infographic I think
tries to demonstrate that we can take
these tools and plot them along the life
cycle of a project and so you can view
the kind of Y axis is the amount of code
or something but we start off on a
project will have some boilerplate code
I don't think many of us start these
days a new significant project with like
a single empty text file but maybe you
do and that's that's cool so we start
off with like some code some structure
some skeleton we might use some
authoring abstractions and so I'm just
using that as a catch-all term to cover
CSS preprocessors templating languages
anything that compiles down to HTML CSS
and JavaScript essentially then we have
our frameworks in our client-side
application stack we have a workflow of
iteration of debugging a browser testing
after that performance tuning build an
optimization and then deployment so
we're going to walk through a few of
these sections and talk about what are
the tools in age so first I want to
touch on often abstractions and of
course the SS has provided people a lot
of pain but these days so show hands how
many people use something like SAS less
stylist cool enters your hands if you
did not raise your hand that's good ok
cool so that was a lot more than the
second one could so I think that that
situation has come along quite quite
considerably next when it comes to mark
up I see a lot of options here so Hamill
started out said we could take the
selector syntax of CSS and make markup
out of it and mark down is good for pros
not so much for the skeleton of HTML
Jade kind of takes what Hamill did and
makes it cool and the handlebars is also
awesome I think I wanted to show one of
the something that I think is beautiful
i remember a while ago James Pierce was
talking about he's like the
idea of my most beautiful the most
beautiful web page to me is it was like
this he's like I I can't imagine
anything more beautiful than that and I
remember when he said that I was like
that's crazy bro you don't have any
markup in there and and now I'm like I'm
totally into that that is awesome and
these days you know I also really like
this you know so this is this is a jade
file but then down in the middle I have
a section of markdown down at the bottom
I have coffee script so I'm able to you
know to develop any kind of these
abstractions not worried about my angle
brackets I am sick and tired of angle
brackets to be honest I just I hate them
so and this is really nice and you know
it just compiles to exactly what you
would want and it's all a piece of cake
so I like the kind of power that these
provide these days next when it comes to
scripting abstractions I over on the
CoffeeScript wiki is this enormous page
of languages that compile to JavaScript
there's quite a few of them some of them
just handle the ink Renee synchronicity
of JavaScript and adds a few keywords to
handle that others are more
comprehensive so of course the one that
most of us are familiar with with is
CoffeeScript dart you could consider so
it has a few different forums but it
does compiled down to acma script
version 5 and so if you like that you
could use that tracer which was
announced the last year's conf allows
you to write in Equus crypt next
compiles down to es5 as well so you kind
of have your choice so there's a few so
I like embracing the authoring
abstraction next going into iteration
workflow and I wanted to show a few
things when it comes to browser devtools
so one of the things that
I'm not going to be able to demo right
now but is extremely exciting is but we
just introduced with Google Chrome for
Android so on Google Chrome for Android
we have full remote debugging what this
means is that the the web inspector the
chrome developer tools is available so
this is a web app right it's all in
JavaScript and CSS and I can load this
up as just a page inside my browser
connecting to my phone have all the same
functionality so the winery if you've
used before has kind of a subset of
what's available and is awesome but
there's a lot of things coming in like
front since we just added indexdb is now
a first class citizen inside the storage
of chrome devtools but having the
ability to do scripta bugging and live
script editing is a pretty powerful
thing so we're excited to have that
ability to connect right to your phone
and show that but there's a few more
things inside the chrome dev tools that
I want to show this is a demo showing
multi-touch events and you can you can
paint with multi-touch on touch device
but it's only wired up for the touch
events so typically on a desktop it
would be quite annoying but nowadays so
in chrome devtools go down to the bottom
right is a settings panel and right here
is this little guy emulate touch events
I can check that and be like that's not
how you doing so you get your touch
events looks like my x and y is off it's
cool
I'm also pretty jazzed about a few other
things in here so when it comes to
mobile development it's been in quite a
pain but we now have override user agent
so this changes it at the network level
and I can just mask as an iphone 5 or
what have you disabled cash had been
brought up before but a new one that I
really like is dr. right so dr. Wright
does what it says and I like this for a
few reasons one is which I love to have
you know a full vertical view of my
scripts right side by side the other is
that I can now adjust this and let's say
that I was working with more of a
responsive web design so a doctor right
I can be able to test that out a little
bit more have my dev tools go side by
side with my with my code and and
manipulate it like that but we only have
this code up there's a few things that
that's worth showing its kind of new so
if you notice there's this little script
panel kind of hides away when you don't
need it it's really handy but if you
already know what file your opening
there's a few shortcuts command Oh
brings up a little file picker so I know
that I want the multi-touch I can just
type multi and just go through to that
and then I also know that perhaps I want
to go down and and make some changes and
I want to make some changes in pre draw
and I can type command shift oh it
brings up a list of all the functions
that are defined in this file and a
bigger file this would be much more
helpful and so I can jump right down to
pre draw and make my changes so in this
case i think probably i'm going to do a
few things i'm going to go over here
clear out the current painting and then
i'm going to go back and we are going to
inside pre draw just change these colors
to this so I'm just doing live editing
of my javascript and
it's cool emulate touch events thank you
cool nice so I just changed the colors
on the fly to be a little bit more j/s
confi but I have that complete ability
so that's the same sort of power we also
have in in the mobile debugging scenario
as well the next thing that I want to
show a source map so source Maps is
another feature inside chrome dev tools
and it just kind of manifest in the last
few months so I want to show it off a
little bit we have a full tutorial about
it on html5 rocks com that shows the
demos that i'm about to show in some
more but it has a lot of power so this
is just a basic little app with all the
colors and that's a hot pink as I didn't
know there's a hot pink as text that's
really that makes designing websites so
much easier okay good no more hex codes
super all right so now I'm gonna see it
looks like source Maps is already on I'm
going to turn that off just for a second
i'm going to refresh the page and now if
you look we have this compiled j oz i'm
going to view sorceress or a second just
to make sure basic page it looks like
there were some scripts but they're
commented out now and we're just dealing
with the compiled JavaScript we did have
a jquery and these two other files but
we ran it through closure compiler
announced the compiled and that's cool
but if i want to debug this well i can
go down and hit the pretty print and you
know at least it's indented and i can't
set breakpoints and that doesn't work
but still I'm dealing with variable
names like a and B so if I enables
source maps let's turn them on right
there and refresh the page and now yeah
so now we have a jquery
the original unmanned are two other
files here and so just to like verify a
view source the page is running compiled
jas but in the dev tools I have my
original source files and I still have
the same power so i can set breakpoints
let's say right there and as I click we
break I can even open the console and
interact with them interact down there
so it's mapping the identifiers of my
compiled code back to my original code
it's doing a little trick in there down
at the very bottom my compiled code is
oh sorry yeah there it is wouldn't not
the source mapping URL so this is just a
JSON file which does the the mapping so
that's pretty cool and really nice for
the the use case of debugging production
javascript but of course it does have
quite a bit more power of that source
maps were designed to kind of be a
language agnostic so I'm show off one
more demo with source maps so this right
here is 0 as page is gonna okay good
good good so this page here is showing
off I can script next so we have some
traits and setting up a class and so
this page is actually going to be using
tracer to do live evaluation of this so
i can edit this code and on the fly it
generates a source map which is this
what it looks like and the compiled down
i can script 5 code that it runs i can
open this up in chrome dev tools and
here you see this is this code is is
matching what i had in this text area
but if you look you know class mix in
you know this
not yes five but i can set breakpoints
in it and i'll just create a new guy a
new instance of my interval class and we
break right inside of it so chrome
devtools is doing the the magic to make
to make it allow me to allow me to write
and debug inside my abstracted i canna
script next and the browser's just
handling the mapping so really excited
about this the sort of power that we
have now with with source maps well
we're talking about iteration one touch
on linting just for a second a lot of
people use JSN jslint this closure
linter closure style sheets actually has
a CSS linter just for playing CSS pretty
powerful i did want to ask i'm just
going to assume that I one here uses a
linter just okay good but so everyone
how many people use have like immediate
feedback as you type your editor your
IDE is letting you know like if
something breaks against your linter
yeah okay on file save you get like a
report okay maybe like a build process
that tells you that like someone
committed something's been okay cool
good I asked around somewhat similar to
to the results here I know that when I
added in a real-time linting into my
editor I'd you know you don't have those
instances where there is that missing
comma or that semicolon that that was
actually a colon and all that stuff that
just drives you crazy so I'm really keen
on that's kind of setup but then I also
want to touch on equi script tooling
prima is is a project that is kind of
really exciting right now in this prima
if you're not familiar with it is a
parser for ECMO script we're in an echo
script itself and so this guy here is
it's just showing off so we're going to
take take this little segment we're
going to parse it so this is what is
prima can give you
kind of adjacent representation of the
AST or the absa abstract syntax tree
here's another way to look at it right
here so so that's kind of the base
functionality of what it does a more
flippant way of looking at it aria who
who wrote it who's also the author of
phantom Jas ran through all the common
popular JavaScript libraries and said
what are all the most popular keywords
and made this very pretty rainbow graph
but s prima is ushering in a lot of new
tools that are being built around it so
there's already code coverage tools code
generation tools documentation creation
tools just by parsing JavaScript files
even Anton who writes j/s hint is
creating a new version of days hint
based on as prima so it's offering a lot
more flexibility in parsing the original
JavaScript that a lot of other projects
that work with the language themselves
are documented on this very hidden away
tucked away page that's a jazz tools
resources page the so there is a chase
tools google group as well where this
kind of stuff is discussed but this guy
has put together a lot of the tools for
dealing with the language itself so
parser is an AST traversal source
implementation and so if I just turn on
all the tools there's quite a few of
them so I think you'd be surprised by
the amount of tools that people have
written already just to deal with the
language itself and it's pretty
interesting one of them that I want to
call out which is JSON it's a JavaScript
port of bison is actually used by
handlebars so handlebar stem bleedin
language uses JSON to compile your
template and the cool thing of that is
that it actually does create an AST from
the template that you had and we don't
have time to show it now but talk to
Alex exton later because he's had
devised some really cool way of working
with that AST directly and modifying the
AST
b-before before running against the data
that goes into it to make some good
changes testing I'm not going to spend
too much time on but I did want to point
out Tess Ling one of its authors might
be in the audience but there's certainly
a lot of fans to assess Ling is is a
really awesome service that I i use kind
of in a non-traditional way but I did
want to show kind of what it can do so
you essentially get to write a test that
run in browsers but in the cloud so you
know most a lot of people run max they
don't have internet explorer certainly
handy on here but it'd be nice to just
run my tests against it I actually use
Tesla ng2 to try out different feature
detection techniques so this one here I
was trying out how can we detect
xmlhttprequest level 2 and so there's a
few different techniques like these and
so I just kind of test them out and log
out how they go now I can just take this
small little test and say I want to run
this against every browser ever and so I
can just do that right here and then
running that against Tess lang here is I
sixes results I sevens results I ate
sighs and nines and I don't have to
worry about the browser set up at all
you know I just test throw my unit tests
right against it it's really really nice
all right so that's it for build and
build there's a lot of best practices
when it comes to things that we've heard
from Steve Souders and it's quite quite
a pain to keep track of them all but
there's a lot of tools that are that are
making this better so of course we have
our armineh fires
or concatenation techniques a lot of
people right tools to deal with that in
in ant make great call those or batch
Python scripts one of the things in the
html5 boilerplate build script that we
tried to do is we'll see if we could
generalize the process of getting a site
ready for production and and now we're
you've even took in that and put it into
node but one of the cool things that
we've done with that node thing is that
we're using grunt and so grunt if you're
very interested in it that you're
actually in the wrong room because Ben
almond is doing a talk about it over
there but so grunta is a JavaScript a
node-based tooling framework sorry build
process which i think is really good
right now a lot of people have kind of
their own different ways and I think we
could actually codify a lot of the best
practices and turn them into reusable
code so grunt is kind of a meeting place
for that I'm really excited about seeing
that grow lastly in deployment there's a
lot of Jenkins and Travis are the main
continuous integration frameworks and I
did want to show I think there's a lot
of projects now that are using Travis
hooked up to their github projects this
is what we did from modernizer so
moderniser after every commit it kicks
off Travis gets notified Travis pulls in
our newest code loads in our test suite
into Phantom j/s phantom runs our queue
unit tests and everything passes
and and we're good but I really you know
in its free and open source and awesome
I think I think this sort of setup of
you know having a continuous integration
tests for server that's running against
all your commits is is really powerful
in nowadays it's much easier than it's
ever been there's a quote from Kyle
neath of github here which i think is
really cool he says deployment is an art
and the style in which you deploy
impacts our company culture more than
you think deploy with style I remember
like five years ago there was a blog
post by dreamhost and they were like
they're like every time we push to
production we play salt-n-pepa's push it
mm-hmm and I was like that sounds
awesome but these days I think like you
know with ideas of continuous deployment
that might that song might get a little
old but I I do think that you know you
want to you want to find a deployment
mechanism that feels really good too
there's a few projects on the future to
lean side that I'm that I'm excited
about that I've seen things like it's
from Chris dip and this is a plug-in for
AMD called you a optimized which
basically says we can we can branch on
features but it'd be interesting to
branch based on user agent so that we
can optimize for our builds based on
what device it's going to and and built
up as an AMD module another approach on
a similar kind of idea
is this is by yen's arps a taxi boo who
wrote AMD feature and this is a similar
basic idea but we're just going to use a
feature detect and here is a drop-down
file for iOS here's the drop-down for
Android and we can just give one to the
two either based on a detect this is
also a kind of setup that I think is
really interesting if everyone if
anyone's used closure compiler advanced
optimization mode you really love it or
you hate it but setting up all those
annotations in your code is quite a bit
of work this is a this was a project to
generate those annotations for more
closure compiler advanced optimization
mode through coffeescript so essentially
right coffeescript and the annotations
are actually provided for you so these
are you know directions where I think
make a lot of sense and so I encourage
you to check out you know this project
and and certainly as library authors
what you can do to provide similar
usability in conclusion what web app
development is bumpy and it's tough and
cross browser certainly the first half
and mobile is is a whole nother mess but
I think tools give your development
vehicle a lot of suspension and kind of
smooth out that bumpy road into
something a little bit more reasonable I
also just want to say embrace
dependencies don't be afraid of abusing
dependencies not certainly not only on
the build side but also in the client
side a lot of people have done
significant work for you already and
take advantage of that and that's it for
me thank