okay hi guys um so here to talk to you
about SVG and more specifically like
some of the weirder stuff that maybe you
didn't know was kind of hiding inside
all that weird XML code so I won't go
into too much on like what we typically
use SVG for just like a little primer
lots of good resources that I can point
you to if you want like a beginner intro
but the basics of why SVG is catching on
in the community is first of all its
resolution independent so you have
graphics that are defined by a vector
path rather than a bunch of pixels so we
can scale them up and down and that
means they're really good for responsive
design icons and logos people are using
SVG a lot for they come out nice and
crisp wherever you're using them and
because they're XML based it's like code
if you look into the graphic you can
actually understand the code there you
can have really easy like like
manipulating States with SVG like a
one-line CSS rule can give you a hover
State on an icon without having to use a
sprite or anything so if you dig into
that little heart for example this is
kind of just like some typical SVG code
where you've got an SVG elements most
shapes are going to be this path element
and it's just a bunch of coordinates
that draw out that shape in vector space
and then you'll have like presentational
attributes like fill and Stroke that we
can fill out as well
something you might notice here that's
really important is there's no like
pixels or anything on anything in here
we are gonna actually everything all
these coordinates you see are all
relative to that view box attribute to
up at the top so that's 0 0 100 100 is a
hundred by a hundred like like canvas in
SVG light and so important thing to keep
in mind as we're moving around the view
box is like super super important when
you're dealing with SP
and you want to kind of scale everything
related to that and that's going to
ensure kind of ultimate responsiveness
and flexibility as we work with SVG so
what I want to talk about though is that
SVG is way more than just simple vector
shapes if you check out like some
resources on SVG barely even see that on
the screen I had to shrink it there are
80 valid SVG elements that you probably
didn't know about most of them 20
minutes doesn't give me time to cover
them all but these are a few of my
favorites that I found useful that we're
gonna look at there's even a switch
statement in SVG like that I found out
haven't found a use case for it but it's
there
okay so first example I wanted to move
through is SVG is really good at doing
editorialized text so what I mean by
that something like this where you know
you've got very specific placement and
sizing of of fonts that's something that
is kind of tricky to do you know with
just CSS to get that like right on and
the way that that's gonna work is like
we just have all these like SVG analogs
of stuff so there's a T span that acts
like a span to control individual
elements and you've got positioning
coordinates XY DX and dy and then the
love there to turn it a different color
you just throw a class on any SVG like
sub component to effect it with CSS and
say change the fill color so code looks
like that I won't go into like super
great details on the code examples but
these are kind of here for reference if
you guys want to look at the slides
later but you can kind of see what's
going on there there's a text element
and there's these T spans for every
single line the great thing about this
is that it's totally responsive because
we've sized this into the view box text
I find is one of like the most annoying
things to deal with when you're like
doing responsive stuff so if you have
something that's really specific like
this it's going to
well and it's better than an image
because SVG text is still like there on
the page and is still totally accessible
to search engines screen readers that
kind of thing so how do we make it
responsive remember the view box size
everything in your view box and then
you're just gonna put it in a flexible
container and let the container handle
at the same way like image max width
100% works another example of
editorialized text is text on like a
curved path you can do really easily
with SVG so the way we did this is I
just traced out a path like druid and
illustrator overtop it's kind of hard to
see there's a really faint red line
there you can really easily get SVG code
like by exporting it as SVG from vector
editing software and then so path this
path ID arc is what defines the that arc
and then what you're gonna do instead of
just using a text element here there's
this thing called text path and text
path is going to let you fit the text
along whatever vector path so you can do
pretty crazy stuff with that and another
kind of common pattern we're gonna see
path has an ID and then it's been linked
with this X link href equals hash arc so
we're linking these two SVG things
together another really important thing
that's going to come up often in here is
this depth
element so this you notice that that arc
doesn't actually get rendered on the
page anywhere so that's because we've
put it inside depths which is just a
place to define like reusable components
that you're gonna reference elsewhere
it's really handy yet combining
different SVG things together another
thing I have been really a fan of with
SVG is interesting fills so SVG has its
own gradient syntax nothing too crazy
they're different from CSS you're just
going to define your stop colors as
their own
kind of elements here and you can
control the direction with the X&Y
coordinates here we've got it going on a
gradient nothing exciting here when
you're just talking about putting it on
a rectangle what I think is cool is if
we're gonna put that gradient inside a
def settlement again so we're saying
we're not gonna just let this gradient
it actually won't do anything on its own
and then we're gonna link it to like
another shape you can start filling like
really weird unconventional shapes not
just like rectangles or what you're
limited to in CSS so like anything you
want can have a gradient field guys
another cool thing you can do in the
same vein you can fill any shape with an
image how cool is that
cropping images into weird shapes is
like kind of shitty as like far as like
labor overhead goes and also it's
expensive if you've got an image with
transparency on it so this one's a
little more like complex but it's gonna
use a lot of the same things we're going
to learn about a new element here called
pattern so it's kind of a bit of a hack
getting an image in here but what
pattern normally does is turns any SVG
element into like a tileable pattern so
if you were gonna like fill something
with polka dots in the background but i
think it's the most fun with using the
SVG image element and more specifically
i think it's the most fun when you start
putting gifts inside things you can fill
anything with a gift so code for that
looks like this we're just sort of
building up again again inside that
depths and then inside a pattern and
then you're just linking them together
with the idea again so the fill for this
path that heart-shaped path is going to
be filled with the image that was
defined as a pattern fill it's a lot to
kind of keep track of but it's all there
a few things to keep in mind when you're
working with images because it's
supposed to be a repeating pattern it
can sometimes be tricky to get the image
to completely fill your shape properly
but remember your view up
sighs everything to the view box if you
match the width and height of the
pattern so notice you can't see the view
box here but it is a hundred by a
hundred and the width and height of both
the pattern and the image are both set
to the entire view box space and then
this last preserve aspect ratio oh sorry
one more thing before you get to that
this pattern units user space on use
says size it to the view box not to any
like shape that's inside of it not just
to the thing it's filling SVG because
it's XML kind of quirky sometimes make
sure your images have both a width and a
height if you don't specify it's gonna
assume it's zero and then it just like
poof disappears so always specify a
width and height attribute and then
there's this cool preserve aspect ratio
attribute that you can do to kind of
it's sort of like a background size
cover one of the ways that you can set
it for SVG again to insure so this is
like if I didn't apply it see how it
doesn't fully fill the heart so it's
nice you don't have to worry about
cropping your image to the exact size
preserve aspect ratio if you give it the
right values um there's a link here to
check out it'll just fill it
automatically for you okay let's combine
two things that we've learned so far so
how about editorialized text and
gradient fills you get gradient text
awesome right that's something that's
been kind of tricky to do before most of
the examples I saw we're using this
WebKit background clip to make a
clipping path out of the text not super
cross browser friendly gradient text is
going to work almost across the board
with the exception of anything less than
ie 9 as a caveat to all of this SVG is
not going to do anything there hopefully
you're like on to supporting ie 9 and
above by now okay that was fun stood
again ready how
editorialize texts plus a gift bill what
s mean you can do that like I think
that's that's madness I've never seen
anything that can do that before and it
it's pretty straightforward
so I don't know exactly what you would
do with that on like a production
website but I really hope one of you
finds a use case please tell me if you
work that into a project so one other
area I wanted to cover too is
interesting image effects so we'll start
out with as an example of something you
can do with SVG these are my cats they
kind of hate each other sometimes and
fight so only way to get them in a
portrait together was to like do the
portrait studio thing but this is
actually using a few different SVG
techniques here so it's that image
element that we saw before combined with
a radial gradient to do the sort of
vignette shape and then something called
a mask so like who works in Nord knows a
bit about like you know Photoshop in
that area okay so a few of you so like
you might have encountered the concept
of a mask it basically kind of works
like a cookie cutter you can take one
shape and like stamp out any other thing
so in this example we've used like a an
elliptical shape and an oval shaped mask
to kind of stamp out that image and the
cool thing about a mask there's also
this thing called clip path which also
works like a cookie cutter but it'll
just stamp it out with hard edges with a
mask you can put gradients in to kind of
fade out the edges so a black fill is
going to give you an opaque mask a white
fill gives you a transparent mask so
this is really powerful with gradients
you put a basically it's an oval with a
radial gradient in it and that creates
the mask to cut out the image so again
sort of notice here with deaths we've
included two different like we defined
both the gradient
and the mask and then the mask is
referencing the gradient and then I've
messed up the yes sorry right here the
ellipse is actually being filled with
the gradient and then the image is using
the mask as a mask here so you can
really start like combining all these
SVG pieces together to get it super
creative and again look into like these
interesting attributes like object
bounding box mask units that help you
size things properly
another thing that SVG is pretty good at
is filter effects so here's a cool
example where they've got this sort of
like ios8 like gradient overlay thing
going on where if you take a look at
this on the live example it actually
like blurs the background as you scroll
down the page which is super cool so
there's an entire filter element and
this one's using a blur filter and also
like an RGB filter to alter some stuff
and then just as I've been showing you
guys primarily just linking stuff up
within the SVG directly but just just so
you know you can usually access most SVG
attributes from your CSS so in this case
it's being applied to every single
section element so if you don't want to
have to like you know repeat that in
your your markup you can sort of combine
defining things in SVG hooking them up
with HTML or sorry CSS rather usually
the attribute names just like the CSS
property if you go crazy with filters
you can essentially do like SVG
Instagram there's a whole filters get
kind of complex and you need a bit of
knowledge of image manipulation and how
that works but there's some good
tutorials here so the example that we're
looking at is like a combination of
there's a turbulent
filter and that creates like noise
effects the blur we saw already is going
to make a blur component transfer is one
that you can actually you get sub
elements to change our G and B
separately so you can kind of change the
color balance on stuff and then there's
actually like light source effects even
that you can do so you can do like
shadowing and and some interesting stuff
there if you if you dive into filter
effects another thing SVG is pretty good
at is animations so this is a really
popular thing that's been happening a
lot lately we've seen this before they
like line drawing thing okay so like a
few of you it's starting to show up more
and more and that is SVG down at the
bottom so if you like take a peek its
SVG's that essentially draw themselves
so this is actually I say almost like a
bit of a hack to with some interesting
attributes so this is going to rely on
you having a path with a stroke so
rather than a filled in shape and
there's these two attributes that all
SVG that you can apply to strokes one
called stroke - array and one called
stroke - offset check out the reference
for like an in-depth explanation it's
kind of beyond the what I have time for
but stroke - array allows you to specify
basically like a dashed line pattern but
be really precise with like the length
of the dashes and the lengths of the
gaps and then stroke - offset just sort
of shifts that around so you can control
where the dashes start so we're gonna
hack it by making basically a dash and a
gap that are both as long as the entire
shape and then we're just going to shift
it and it gives you that animation
effect so here's a really simple example
of just one line so we have a hundred
unit long walk like line and it has to
like - components each as long as the
line itself and then you just kind of
move it along you just move along the
gap and the filled in part
and you might notice here that I'm
animating this right inside the SVG SVG
actually has an animated element that
you can animate almost any SVG attribute
you might wonder though why not just
like animate with CSS or JavaScript
typically those are better and probably
more performant tools for achieving this
in the case of the line drawing that's
probably what I would have gone with
just kind of wanted to show you guys the
possibility there there is one case that
I've found that SVG animate is like like
kind of way better and like gets the job
done faster and that's tweens birthday
alright thank you didn't fashionable
wish I was that cool when I was between
so yeah SVG can like pretty easily morph
shapes from one to another so I think I
have time to show you guys this example
that I just kind of went to town with
these are just like a bunch of little
SVG shapes there's one circle that gets
like cloned with JavaScript but the main
animation of one-quarter morphing into
like an opposite shape quarter is all
done in SVG and then you can like play
around with it in j/s to get it to go
kind of like kaleidoscope II so that was
kind of fun yeah so a simpler example of
this the way that the morph works is
remember going back to that heart shape
how every single path was defined by a
series of points in coordinate space and
it's the D attribute I think it's like I
can't even remember what D stands for
right now but the path like definition
if you basically what you see here under
we're saying I'm going to animate
the D attribute and then the values that
I want to animate it kind of to and from
it's actually just to but in order that
it kind of like goes forward and
backwards nicely I've repeated the first
value but these are just two sets of
like coordinate points that SVG handles
the tween and the morph between one
shape and another so that's something
that you can't really do without like an
external library in in J s so kind of
neat that SVG can do that so there's
still like way more that I haven't
covered these are just some of like the
weird things that I've found hiding in
there and thought we're pretty cool so
you know sort of in the the vein of this
morning like just yeah go exploring make
stuff up like there's just so much that
I don't think like a lot of people
realize but it's all documented it's all
there these are some good resources that
I found helpful and you know I honestly
just been be reading through these and
say oh like there's that element like I
can do this sort of thing and go play
around with it and like produce some
some pretty cool results so I'd
encourage you guys to go try and do the
same and you know in a wider sense like
don't take any technology kind of for
granted don't you know really just like
dig into the details and and go
exploring and see what you find that's
all thanks