alright so you know this is the theme of
my talk and I like to start off with the
subtitle is why you know give me one
point though and when I when I say that
I guess I'm just really talking about
how do we stabilize something that is by
definition unstable right how many
people are familiar with Denver a little
bit heard of it that is way too few of
you that is unacceptable sember org you
all have laptops right now because the
fact that it is zero point four point
zero means that it is unstable anything
could change at any time the fact that
we have you know stable releases and
unstable releases just something nice
that ride does for us but it could just
change it anytime and so how do you deal
with that it's actually a complicated
problem let's start kind of small a
couple of I don't know caveats that I've
seen in terms of code usage that comes
up on the mailing list a lot and things
you should just generally not do right
or should do and just do them right this
is a great example right like oh if
something goes wrong I want to know
about it I want to say hey we're just
going to log that error I think that's
been a common theme overall today is
logging but the problem here is that
you're not exiting the process right
it's just like oh yeah no no did
something wrong and it'll probably work
itself out no it is not going to work
itself out you need to say stop exit
time restart the process all right let
everything reset it's important remember
this and so you really need to listen
for these errors and this is this
actually from the docs I mean how many
people have seen this snippet of code
you all should be raising your hands
okay that's sad but it's all right I'll
forgive you the thing is that there's
actually sort of a sneaky sneaky error
that's not trapped here and you would
probably see this in your code if you
use this in production and the reason
for that is that the underlying socket
can throw errors and that error will be
bubbled up to the request and so I will
give a node jitsu beta account to the
first person who changed
usage to this which is that you should
have the error event handler there and
if you don't believe me why I have the
source code line cited so I'm not
kidding and these are just sneaky things
right I think forgot who said it today
but it just just said assume you're
and that's totally true like you
never know what's going to go on I
solutely seen Ryan matt raney debugging
assess Scylla all week and like you just
never know the socket could just be like
oh you know the colonel just decided to
panic it's not notes fault but you got
to handle it next big one is event
emitters I mean a vented programming is
great but it's really dangerous and
we've seen this pop up a few times in a
library that we have written and
maintained for the last year called node
HTTP proxy that's a pretty full featured
reverse proxy and node kind of like the
sweet spot for fast asynchronous i/o but
the problem with that is that if you
start listening to events and don't
remove those listeners eventually you're
going to have some leaks and that's not
good right thankfully node will warn you
about this so maybe you'll see something
like this and by the way this this is
fixed so don't be afraid and you should
also upgrade to 5x so let's let's say we
had some code like this right you want
to do something and then notify the
person that you're done normal naive
approach would just say ok when I'm done
call this function but why are you using
dot on right event cardinality is
important if you're only expecting one
done event then only do this once right
and this gets important when you start
to think about closure scope because if
you're using something in the scope of
the callback and that event emitter that
event handler is never removed then that
can never be free because it still needs
to be kept around to maybe be used in
that function that will never be called
later on right seeing a lot of blank
stares I'm hoping I'm hoping this gets
through maybe not use a process monitor
you know I think most people do this
probably monitor upstart I wrote this
thing called forever that people use I
think I hope
I use it and you just start it and when
your app crashes you can restart it and
that's why that first slide that I
showed where you just eagerly exit the
process makes sense because I gots not a
big deal we're going to restart you
probably have your application states to
realize to some sort of remote database
like Redis or a file maybe if you're not
feeling that adventurous and you know
just do it and stabilize your
dependencies and this is this is a great
topic this has come up a couple of times
today I know Isaac talked about it and
this is kind of the power of node conf
this is stuff that I learned in the last
like 48 hours like I've actually been
doing this wrong for the last year up
until two days ago and the reason that
you want to stabilize your dependencies
is so you don't see things like this so
okay I have it installed on my local
machine and then I push your production
and whoops I forgot to put it in my
package about JSON and okay that's
whoops ok now it's not installed on my
production box and you know you start it
up with forever and all of a sudden you
see it's spin restarting because you
just don't have that module installed
and this local installation doesn't
solve this because the workflow that I
see it from a lot of people as they will
say hey I'm going to require this module
I'm going to try and run my program oh
my program doesn't run I'm not going to
do the smart thing and go update my
package.json and then use NPM install to
install it from there I'm just going to
do NPM install package name and not
update the relative dependencies in my
package.json and that's exactly why we
wrote this tool and so what this will do
is it will spawn up your child process
for your application figure out what the
dependencies are and update them for you
so this one's actually pretty neat
pretty useful but there's actually one
problem with this and it's a problem
that i found on the last 48 hours that
happens to be the dependencies that have
been listed here and i'm not even going
to ask for a show of hands here because
I didn't even know for two days ago so
the problem here is that I'm being
really really conservative and for a
ecosystem that moves as fast as the node
dutchess community you can't be this
conservative I'm saying I only want zero
point zero point three that's it nothing
nothing greater than that nothing
less than that has to be that version
alternatively you could be really really
optimistic and say anything greater than
or equal to zero point zero point three
neither of those are a really good
middle ground because you need to figure
out what semantic versioning really
means and so let's take a look at this
this is the incorrect way that I have
done this on every single one of my
modules or not necessarily incorrect
just overly optimistic and so you know
if one of these gets updated to say hits
a one point oh and there's a breaking
API a change in here you're not going to
know if you're going to deploy to
production and have five or six
application servers running that may
have been started up at different
periods of time they may have different
versions of that dependency installed on
each server if you do this and that's
really dangerous because you're back oh
I have six servers and now one in six
connections is failing and I don't know
why and i'm just going to log into the
first server i feel like and say oh the
dependency is installed here in the
correct one it's just not that easy what
you should be doing is this I was doing
it wrong do you you should be doing this
the X indicates that you will accept any
version of up to the greatest version at
that minor version level so in semantic
versioning your major minor patch the
second X or start of the last x is patch
versions so I basically say I know
there'll be no breaking changes in patch
versions that's by definition defined in
cember and I'm just going to accept any
of those but if there's anything greater
than that like a 0.24 eyes for example
not going to accept that because there
might be a breaking change in there and
I'm running this in production and that
could be really really dangerous but for
something like colors which has a
ridiculously simple API which is never
going to change and those major versions
or minor versions rather probably won't
affect the core API that I use I'm going
to be a little bit more optimistic there
and say I'm going to accept anything up
to a major version release
so just a little bit Isaac talked about
this earlier today you really should
just pop in and start playing with
sember it's really helpful really you
know package managers and package
writers out there you should know about
this and you should think about this
when you're determining versions for
your packages you know there are
nineteen hundred packages on NPM I
wonder how many of them are version
correctly considering the fact that like
my twenty were not versioned right and
I've been trying to do write her a year
so play with it use it love it let's
have better versioning find the best
tool for the job so this is kind of a
mini announcement we're going to be
putting this on all the projects that we
maintain later this week and so I think
it was Paul kerna who said earlier today
that you know be where the single module
authors you know that I'm just learning
node module authors it's not bad I'm
really happy that you're learning node
but just be aware that if that author
disappears or decides they don't like
node and goes back to PHP you're
maintaining that but anything that you
see with this seal we maintain I stay up
till six in the morning fixing that's
eastern time so you know now you know
why I am structure your code this came
up i think in md's talk one of the great
things about node is that it doesn't
enforce any code structure for you but
you really need to think about it this
is a pretty common template that i use
for most of my libraries and
applications you've got some sort of
tooling and your bin folder you've got
some sort of configuration / environment
you have some sort of lib maybe some
static files tests i do do integration
testing sorry Felix and then of course
any sort of sub modules you have there
of course some people are starting to
put things in node underscore modules as
per NPM one point oh that's something
that's still kind of experimentation I
some people do it I don't do it it could
be a good thing to do moving on but he
did just release that this week I decide
on a network architecture and what do I
mean by that if you're running something
that can run on one machine you probably
want to use cluster
and what that does is it uses shield
shared file descriptors to you know
basically open up a socket pass that to
the STD end of any child process this
has come up a few times today cluster
seems to be the best implementation of
it out there right now spark obviously
was the predecessor which still is a
good example in code reading you know
RTF see we're all here at a dev
conference the other one is to do some
sort of proxying and you know this is
what we do it no Jitsu this is an
extremely simple round-robin proxy
that's one of the great things about
node because this request handler in the
HTTP proxy creates or actually runs
synchronously right so you can just pop
it off and put it back on and you can be
assured that there is order here so you
know you're going to remove it and then
always add it to the end so there's no
need to worry about any sort of
threading or things like that you just
say remove it proxy to it put it back on
there and just cycle that set of servers
overall now you know what if there was
just some tool out there that did all of
this for you I mean wouldn't that be
great there's more so we have been
working on hibu for about a year now and
I'm pretty excited to announce that we
are releasing it today so what is it
right it is an application server for
nodejs that's based on the package JSON
format and so let's run through a little
demo so essentially it's two servers
right you have a basically the high
boost server which i'm going to start up
first after i do this so that's going to
run and i'm not going to show you a port
it's running on so nobody tries and gets
me over the network and everybody read
this is that good okay good great so
what this does is that this will respond
to incoming requests for a rest api if
anybody went to the cast talk today i
think there's definitely some overlap
there but we're definitely focused on
just note and not supporting everything
else so that gives us some flexibility
in that we can just say we only support
package.json formats
and so what would one of those look like
and so let's jump into an example is
this Oh drat I changed everything else
except for this sorry basic I don't even
know another one classic there we go so
here's a pretty simple package.json
right it has some sort of repository I
think this is actually the simplest node
application on the planet if you go to
it but it has a good package.json with
proper versions so essentially we're
going to say hey now that I want the API
client for hi boo on oh now you know my
port drat and I'm going to say hey I
want to start this application right
let's do that yes okay yeah its bond
okay and so you can sort of see from
this example that its bonds it using
forever so that means if it goes down
it's going to restart it and does all
that process management for you it
spawns it on a unique port for that IP
so you always have things isolated and
then you can actually start this up
again right so now I have two of these
things running now i have three of these
things running all from the same call
and you know now that i have them
running i might actually want to access
them and to do that I need to run the
load balancer and this uses a modified
version of the very simple load balancer
script that I show you before and this
will all be released in about nine
minutes so now the balance is running
and as we can see the domain of this
particular application happens to be dev
jitsu and what I have in my etsy hosts
file
is that I have a bunch of dev ji to
stuff set up so I'm just going to hit
one of those sites and I'm going to see
my app right good stuff but now I may
want to later on stop my app so I'm
going to stop my app right now
and now it stopped
well maybe it's not do it live and now
it started so Oh three two one file
descriptor reload now it's tough uses a
file watcher so it takes a split second
it could easily plugged out to use Redis
and be much faster so yeah we just
stopped a node.js application and
restart it and did all that stuff little
known fact in the node community is that
I actually wrote the programmatic
support for NPM or helped Isaac write it
I guess it since Isaac writes everything
so what this will do is actually install
all of your NPM dependencies for you
automatically get the right versions
this is why I harp so much on the
package.json dependencies because if you
don't have the right dependencies and
you decide to start multiple ones of
these overtime on different machines
that is a really difficult problem to
the bug and so I guess in closing before
I hit some questions I just was really
looking forward to doing this
yeah I've got I've got one more slide
which is another one of my favorite
lines you know why why you know make
questions trademark anybody cool man
that's great no questions I'm yeah
that's that's oh wait now I got 10
yeah yeah it's all round robin and just
oh I'm sorry the question was is that
load balancer doing rabid proxying and
the answer is yes and so the thing about
the stop request that came in when you
tell it to stop it will stop all
instances it's not really refined enough
to say oh I want to stop this one
particular drone or that one particular
drone and they're jitsu we generally
have multiple machines running and we'll
just say Oh turn off that machine which
might have two or three processes
running on it and scale in that way per
machine horizontally how much each
process uses so this is actually a
feature that I'm working on it forever
for the next version which is to just
monitor things by the OS module but
that's not in there yet so that the
question was is there an option in hibu
for doing rolling restarts so kind of
the way so I've got a few minutes left
let's just jump into the code so
essentially it all the way I like to say
about this this project is that it all
wraps this one function which is the
spawn function and this does a bunch of
stuff to figure out where your app is
and you know install the dependencies
and do all those sorts of things but at
the end of the day it just spawns this
thing called the carapace and it's fully
pluggable so I have a chroot plug-in
which is a good example like sometimes
you want to be in chroot sometimes you
don't depending on who you are and so
plugins can say oh I want to spawn with
these options and these can actually be
used by the carapace file so you know
because this is designed to spawn any
node application not necessarily a
server that's not baked in but one could
easily write a cluster plugin that
utilize cluster for particular HTTP
servers that does rolling restart
cluster does rolling restart for you so
if you are going to be running a lot of
HTTP servers you should write that
plugin because I haven't had the time to
yet but I plan on it all right anything
else