hi everybody I'm psyched to be here I'm
psyched to talk about this so let's see
I'm Adam Wolfe and today I'm gonna talk
about rebuilding facebook chat and
actually there was a big project going
on to rebuild all a facebook chat
including the back end but I gotta focus
on the front end and the JavaScript
rewrote it seems appropriate and you may
wonder why we felt like we needed to
rebuild facebook chat and you know the
answer is that it was pretty terrible
and I pulled something that I remembered
from about a year ago this was like a
blog post announcing our new subscribe
feature so you could follow people on
Facebook and the very first comment it
was posted a minute after this went up
says improve the chat system and there
are thousand likes on that comment so um
and actually this is a problem for us
because the complaints about chat just
drowned out our overall user feedback it
was like really hard to tell when we had
new bugs and stuff because you know
people are always complaining about chat
and facebook chats I think it's somewhat
unique as a client-side application
because it's embedded in this browse
experience you know Facebook is still
delivered very much as like a page to
page classic web application so we can't
afford to like load a bunch of code and
then go back to the server to build up a
bunch of state because you know we're
gonna get paged out quickly the other
thing is that the scale of facebook chat
is enormous it's you know at our peak
it's hundreds of millions of concurrent
users so every extra fetch to the
backend means extra latency and extra
servers you know more cost for us and
the worse experience so you know I think
it's kind of funny we've been doing
JavaScript and web apps for like for a
while now and it's still not obvious how
you build a feature like this you know
everyone like builds their own language
and their own servers for this and
everything so you know we kind of
approach this like not not sure um how
what we were going to do to to fix this
and I before we go into like what we did
I want to show a little bit about what
facebook chat does or do people here use
facebook chat on the web like some
people do I I figure this is like more
of a Twitter crab but no worries I'll
show you what it does okay so here I
have my alter-ego to be Co Jones his
Facebook page and I'm going to start a
chat with nan one of the Facebook
contingent who's here and you know the
very first thing I want to show is that
when one thing that we did is oh thanks
nan one thing that we did is let's try
that again when we when we merged chat
and messages you know we used to have
two different products there was this
there was this jewel at the top we call
this thing up here the messages jewel
and then we also have chat windows and
um we merged the backend for these
things because we felt like hey you're
talking to your friend you know in
either interface they should be the same
thing but we didn't merge the front end
of these applications so the jewel was
controlled by like one set of client
code and the chat window was controlled
by another and they would get out of
sync all the time that was actually like
the dominant form of angry feedback so
man will you send me another message so
now you'll see that when nan sends me
another thanks with nan sends me another
message you see they appear in both
interfaces at the same time and so like
fundamentally like this was what we had
to do you know we had to introduce a
model for what chat was doing and make
it more than just like a very simple app
it used to be just something that was
all about the UI um couple other
features I want to show here let me
minimize this window and maybe nan will
send me one more message I think he's
out of prepared comments so hopefully
yeah he has to type something on this
phone we'll wait for that to come in
okay there we go so now I have a new
message and I'm gonna actually reload
the page here before um before I do and
what you'll see now is what I wanted to
point out about this is that you know
even though people have messages when
they come to facebook chat is not the
most important feature on Facebook
obviously it's the newsfeed so like half
of our users don't engage with chat at
all in a given day um so we can't afford
to like load all the messages when the
page comes up and what that means is
that now when I raise this chat window
you'll see a little tiny delay where we
have to go fetch the the conversation
before we can show it and even though
we've done that we
haven't loaded all the data for the
model like when we go look at our list
of conversations you'll see that has to
get loaded in as well
so we very much have to emphasize
incremental loading they did take away
my shaving cream yes that's right
okay oh and I'm getting lots of messages
here hi everybody one last thing I want
to show is that there's a group chat
feature here and you know this makes
this much more complicated so tobiko
here is gonna add Adam to this chat and
this is a new group chat and maybe then
can add some people too and the thing I
want to point out about this is it you
know nan can add people who are his
friends to this chat that and these are
people that tobiko doesn't know so he
doesn't have information about these
participants and those need to be loaded
incrementally sort of as these messages
come in and in sort of real-time so
whoops I lost focus there we go
so you know that's actually something
that we had to contend with and I'm
gonna show a little bit of code that
kind of gives an example of how we dealt
with that okay so back to presentation
so um you know we did this we did this
rewrite and I you know I think we can
say it was a success you know one thing
that we really got to do is we really
got to focus on the technology and the
quality we didn't have a bunch of new
features to add it was pretty minor in
that regard so that was very helpful we
developed a new command-line JavaScript
test framework as part of this project
and it's been adopted across Facebook
and now we're working to open source it
so I'll talk a little bit more about
that the whole project took six months
most of the time it was just for
engineers working on it so you know that
it wasn't like a gigantic project and
what I'm showing here is the graph of
user tickets now unfortunately a
facebook like each individual user
report surfaces to us is like you know
thousands of users complaining about
things every day but we can tell we're
doing better when those those thousands
become hundreds and that's kind of what
happened here and it's gotten better
since so you can see that this was you
know really helped with the quality
there are other things we were doing
but you know the very first thing that I
want to talk about and the most
important thing and like the the thing
that I would sort of suggest you
remember from this talk if you're gonna
remember one thing is that we introduced
modularity into the Facebook JavaScript
code base in order to deliver this
feature and that was like the single
best thing we did cuz like if you even
if you have a big steaming pile like if
you have a steaming pile that's like in
little buckets then you can fix them one
at a time and so that you know that's
like the single best thing that we did
so when I joined Facebook like a little
over two years ago all of our JavaScript
was effectively in a global namespace so
you know you just write like var blah
equals blah you know and then and that
would just like kind of run whenever it
ran you could you could give directives
that say like hey when you load this
file you also need to load these other
files but there's no guarantee about
what order that would happen so it made
it really really complicated and any any
JavaScript code could break any other
JavaScript code so it's like really easy
to cause a problem and then really hard
to figure out what who had done what and
the other thing was that like we had
this we have this stochastic packager
that actually takes data from production
and tries to do the most efficient job
it can like putting JavaScript files
together
so the packager would like change what
javascript with was delivered in what
bundle and that would cause bugs even
though no code had changed that makes it
really hard to figure out what's going
on and the last thing this is leads to
is like just layers and layers of
initialization because you kind of like
it's really hard to know when
everything's ready just everything sends
in an it event you know and you like end
up depending on like 20 init events
before you are ready to do anything so
we fixed that with you know common KS
effectively so now at Facebook when you
write a file you can require resources
and then you know you just can export
something this gets transformed into
like something like a defined function
along the lines of requirejs
we didn't actually pull in requirejs
because you know it's kind of easier
Facebook to just do it
unfortunately often but we're definitely
inspired by requirejs
so you can see that now like the
contents of a given file get run inside
a function you get you know global
namespace protection all kinds of good
stuff and you get this like
initialization guarantee you know
there's only one module named foo and
you kind of know know when it's ready
now um that ideally that would have been
enough but for our application it wasn't
and the problem that we had was that
most dependency chains in our app
actually start on the server so if you
think about like I'm gonna talk about
that chat tab window that appears at the
bottom of the screen and just like
imagine the control that renders that
right so in addition to all the data it
needs it needs a couple other things
like a like a configuration from the
server and also the templates we
actually deliver from the server as well
and you may wonder like why in a
client-side app we're delivering
templates from the server the best
answer is that initial is a
internationalization is really really
hard and we have a big legacy stack for
D not on the server so we
internationalized a template on the
server and then deliver it to the client
there are other things that we do in
these templates that are also helpful
but then you're back to this multi pass
initialization thing where you know you
have a module called chat tab view but
you can't use it right away
you know requiring it is not enough and
instead you also and the other thing
that you have is like when you want to
deliver these resources to the client
you have this like gross interconnect
between PHP and JavaScript where PHP in
our case sorry where you have to like
require this module and call a method on
it and you know this is a really hard
dependency to track like it's
effectively a string in PHP so if you
want to refactor that method it's a pain
also if you want to share this config
you know you end up doing this like 50
times so the way we fix this is we
introduce this idea of dynamic
dependencies where you can define
modules on the server so you just sort
of export like a bunch of configuration
as a dictionary or a template as even
just like a string and then you can
require these templates and now we don't
use the require keyword even though to
the client these things look the same
regular modules we use require dynamic
because you know the one thing about
this approach is that it is a little bit
fragile right like you can end up with a
client in a state where it needs a
module that the server forgot to prepare
for it so by using a required dynamic we
can kind of keep better track of what
the client needs in order to be able to
initialize but you can freely mix
require dynamic statements with regular
require statements and then go about
your business so you know this worked
really well and as I said like if
there's one thing that made this project
work it was the fact that we could put
our chat code our new shiny chat code in
modules that would not be broken by the
rest of the JavaScript at Facebook um
there's a couple things I feel like we
didn't quite get right so you know if
you go down this road there are things I
would do differently the very first
thing I would say is I I really wish we
hadn't allowed circular dependencies I
know that's part of the common Jas spec
and I'm I'd be fine allowing it for
third-party code but in our code you
know it leads to all kinds of problems
it's really hard to reason about these
circular dependencies and it's really
hard to know when you're looking at one
module that like it it's part of a
circular dependency chain the other
thing about it is that like anytime you
have something that can execute an
arbitrary order you almost always end up
with bugs when that order switches for
whatever reason um the other thing I
wish we'd done like while we were at it
I wish we had modularized JavaScript
codes access to the window and the
document in that window because just
being able to freely refer to the window
as a global basically means that you can
only have one window in your context and
I think like the destiny of all
JavaScript code is to run on the server
and when you move this code to the
server you have to context to fie it you
know you have to say like there's
there's one VM sort of per request and
then the last thing was just dumb we in
you know instead of doing like straight
common J ass where you can give file
names we did this thing where you kind
of like name your file using a comment
and that was just like it's unnecessary
garbage now in the system but overall
you know big success okay
the other side of modularity I think is
unit testing and I'm presenting these
things as if they're different but I see
them as very much the same like you can
build a module system but you don't know
you actually have modules unless you
have an expression for the seams between
these modules and that's what I see is
unit testing being about so you know I
feel like a lot of people feel like okay
we I know we need to do unit testing
yeah I know that it really helps
especially an environment like Facebook
where you have hundreds of Engineers
committing to the same codebase but you
know I think like one thing that people
don't talk about too much is like just
the workflow benefit of unit testing
like I think most developers I certainly
would rather interact with my console
and my keyboard then with the browser
and the mouse but in order to make that
really work you need to make the unit
testing really fast so you know when we
we had some unit testing for JavaScript
but it was actually slower to run the
unit test and it was to reload the
webpage and click on things so like you
know that's like the wrong set of
rewards there um
the other benefit of unit testing is is
this design benefit so you know if you
have a unit test like you're forced to
consider what is this unit you know what
are the guarantees that it provides and
what are the invariants so in order to
like really capture that design benefit
you need to setup your unit test system
so that it um
by default it isolates modules you know
you sort of encourage to test one thing
at a time I mean then then the last
thing and I think this is like really
common understanding of what unit
testing is for us is the idea that like
it's a signpost you know if you come
back or someone else comes back and
wants to change something like there's a
big long list of like well this is what
it does now you know if you're gonna
change it you need to like think about
the current spec but in order to make
that read well as a specification you
need to make sure your unit test
framework is really expressive and to
this end I think you need to make your
unit test framework hack hackable you
know you need to make it so that like
developers on the team think of
committing to the unit test framework
and the unit test as like just as
important as committing to the
production code and you know like
packing on the unit test stuff is fun
cuz like you know if you break it that's
really good
and and it's also like it's much more
abstract you know it only
runs in your dev environment one thing
unit testing I think is not for is like
as a wall you know and so people new to
unit testing sort of say like well I can
write this unit test but that doesn't
prevent you from like you know writing
some other module that mocks this
interface and does the wrong thing with
it and yeah you know absolutely and you
can write integration tests if you're
really worried about that but you know
this is unit testing is about other
thoughtful developers coming along and
like sincerely trying to do to do their
best to like keep things working you
know which I think most developers
that's what they want to do so this is
what it looks like and you know that we
we integrated j/s Dom so that you can
run browser code at the console it works
great you can see this is like a trivial
test it takes about under two tenths of
a second to run I still wish it were
faster but we made some trade-offs at
all that I'll describe now so the test
environment is written in nodejs
and that alone gives us like a lot of
speed benefit so you know before we
start we actually kind of have to scan
all the JavaScript files it's really
easy to do that in parallel and notes oh
that's great we also had to integrate
j/s dom and could text fi in order to
support browser code and that slows us
down you know and again like I wish we
didn't need context to Phi that I think
was a mistake we made for isolation we
did a couple things one is we made it so
that the each test runs in its own VM
and that prevents cascading failures
because I think like if developers get
used to the idea that you know unit test
breakage doesn't necessarily mean that
something's broken they'll start to
ignore it and then you know the tests
rot really quickly the other thing that
we did is we made is that by default you
get a mock when you require something
and this was actually inspired by Felix
goose and darf who's I think he's here
at he presented at node Kampf like over
a year ago his micro test framework and
you know it's the idea of using a
require as a seam to inject test doubles
and it's great it works really well that
was pretty awesome than looking for that
guy but you know I can talk a little
more about that but I don't have a lot
of time okay and then the last thing is
you know this hack ability idea and
they're the best thing working for us
so at Facebook we don't have production
systems that run node but there are a
lot of people who do want to hack on
nodes so the very fact that it's all
written a note is great and then the
other thing that we did is instead of
integrating with crappy old legacy
systems we rewrote them you know even
though it was extra work it makes it
like all the code is shiny and new you
know when you go track down a dependency
chain like you're looking at JavaScript
code and not crazy legacy PHP okay the
last thing and this is like kind of
where it gets weird so come with me you
know we we sort of abandoned like
object-oriented programming for this or
at least like sort of the framework
style MVC I mean I want yeah and I want
to talk about you know why why we did
that so here let's again we'll consider
that chat tab view that window and you
know here's like a classic MVC
constructor for that thing we're gonna
take a thread object and the Dom node
and what we're gonna do is like attach
our template for the window to that Dom
node and like let's just think about
what we need to do to fill out the top
bar of that chat window that needs to
say like you know Adam man and two
others or whatever um so you know when
you start off and it's like a sunny day
and you know it's the first file of your
new project you write something like
this you say oh yeah the thread has
participants so we'll just get those
participants and we'll like map over all
the names of the participants and use
that to generate the title and you know
this works this is great toy program you
like go show it to the product manager
he's all excited you know keep going so
but then you realize that you know you
get sometimes you get a message and you
don't have the data for the thread you
need to be able to talk about this
thread just as an ID before you really
know what's in it so cross that out and
replace it with like some evented thing
where you know the the thread has a load
event that distinguishes between the
case where it's got data in it and it
doesn't and then you know you have to
kind of wring your hands a little bit
about like okay but what if it already
loaded by the time I get here you know
what does that mean but you know there
are answers to that question
so now you know you sort of wait for
this load event you register your
callback and then you get the
participants for this
red and that works for a little while
until you know you get to this group cap
feature where you realize that like you
may end up on the thread with
participants who you don't know about
yet and what are we gonna do about that
you know and this is where I you see two
approaches you know one is people try to
like have this invariant that we never
have threads that don't have
participants at the best case that leads
to over fetching right cuz like that
means that every time you find out about
a thread you have to reef a CH all the
participants um
worst case is like you have a bug or you
you know you've failed to capture this
untracked dependency and you get to the
client and you're you're trying to do
this render a thread you're missing
participant data and the only thing you
can do is error you've got no you know
you've got no way out of that so you
know probably the best thing to do is to
not do this and do the same thing to
participants that we did the threads so
we wait for the load of the thread and
then we have to wait for all the
participants to load and then we can
finally render the chat window and you
know by the time we get here like this
is no longer shiny and simple it's like
now really complicated and you've got
this sort of spaghetti evented system
you've got like subtle ordering
dependencies like if participants load
before threads that make aynd of change
the behavior here it's it's not obvious
what's going to happen so um you know
there there are two things that like I
really don't like about this style I'll
try to point them out quickly the first
one is you know let's just be okay with
constructors and initializers and like
you know class keyword thank you but but
you know we have two different kinds of
api's that don't look different right
like the thread knows it's ID and you
can always call get ID that's fine but
to call get participants you have to
wait for the load event and like there's
nothing obvious in the API that says
this you have to kind of like read
through the code or keep the
documentation up-to-date or whatever to
really know this and new developers will
come along and you know it works
sometime so it's like really confusing
um the other thing that really hurts is
testability right so like consider our
test for the participants behaviors
around threads
what we're gonna do is you know we can
make a new thread that's easy but when
we call get participants in the context
of a test it's like unclear what we need
to test here you know like we can do two
things one thing one thing we can do is
we can sort of return real participants
from this call in which case like now we
don't have a unit test we've got an
integration test of threads and
participants or we can return mock
participants from here in which case
like the mock four participants needs to
be really clear about like what what is
done by participants code and what is
done by thread code so you know you you
still bundled these things together and
pulling them apart again is pretty hard
um and you know this makes me wonder
like why do we do this whole
object-oriented programming thing like
what what got us here and you know the
first part that like the ones we're all
programmers you know the one thing I
think we're all good with is abstraction
right like you wouldn't you wouldn't
write code if you didn't like
abstraction and I think that's you know
that's something we can keep so in the
chat code they're definitely like
function constructors and function
prototypes they tend to be for like UI
controls you know like that menu or just
or the chat tab view things that we're
gonna have a few of but um but that's
where I would say it stops you know like
inheritance that you know that's when
we're like even in languages that are
built around inheritance like Java like
the best directive there is to use
delegation rather than inheritance
because you know it's just so brittle
like once you've put something in an
inheritance tree then you can't get it
from anywhere else except subclasses and
you know no one really does a good job
of like designing for inheritance like
designing an API is hard and then
designing a class that can be inherited
is like you know ten times harder
polymorphism is another one where like
if you have a language that has
first-class functions and callbacks I
just don't get why you'd have this crazy
contract that says like by naming this
function show I am participating in the
show able interface you know which is
like again this like super untracked
dependency in JavaScript and a callback
totally suffices there and is much more
flexible it means that you can have sort
of pieces of code that don't really that
aren't expressed as objects but can
still connect to
opponents that are um and then the last
one this is the worst one I don't even
get why this was a benefit in the first
place like data that is hidden is data
that you know is not serializable so
like you know when the browser page
unloads when the machine crashes when
you migrate data this is the stuff that
you lose and you know in facebook chat
what we found is it like we had to
externalise everything you know we have
to account for multiple clients marking
things as red or opening chat tabs or
whatever it's gonna be so like all of
our data ended up externalized and we
sort of now I think of like application
data should always just be JSON of old
data like it it should never be hidden
in this way okay so that's my little
rant what did we replace it with so you
know I have to scare quote this cuz like
we used a functional style not strict
functional at all and you know there are
places where we have objects and you
know it's it's intermixed but like in
general I would say you know modules are
connected by functions and not by events
or named interfaces instead of like
class instances so instead of a thread
instance we use a singleton to represent
like all the threads and then this last
thing is the thing I just talked about
we're like application data is generally
sort of thought of as always
serializable so let's go back and look
at that chat tab view example now and
you know the first thing you'll see is
that like the signature for this
constructor is different instead of
getting past a thread object it gets
past a thread ID which is just a string
and now to go get the data about that
thread sorry first we're gonna attach a
template that doesn't change we're gonna
pick out the title just so that we can
close over that it makes it code look
better but then when we want the data
about that we pass that ID back to the
threads singleton and go and pass a
continuation that will get handed the
data for about that Fred once we have it
and that means that like if we have it
great you get called back right away if
we don't we can go back to the server
and get it for you
so this continuation then gets the
thread metadata and we do the same trick
with participants and you'll notice that
thread and participants are completely
coupled in this case so you know this
changes the API it makes it simpler
right threads is just a singleton and
you can obviously tell like what things
support direct returns are like you know
let's say there's some trivial ID
transformation that we can do on the
client obviously you just pass in an ID
get back the normalized ID but the get
function here takes a continuation so
you know that you have to pass that
along with your call for testability
it's like a similar thing where you know
instead of being bound to the
participants data we can use like a mock
function here that we just made this
like utility knife function that can be
called as a constructor or an instance
method or raw function that captures the
calls and can also be used to inject
return data so here we just pass a mock
function to this callback and then we
can poke it off you know do various
things with the mocks make sure that
threads made an async request if we
expect it to whatever that's going to be
and then when we want to verify the data
again it can be expressed in JSON so we
just have like this simple equality
check to be able to talk about our
expectations there you know I do want to
at least build up a straw man and tear
it down about this functional style so
what are the what are some of the things
that I hear objections to you know I
think that most common ones like this is
too hard you know like four layers of
nested callbacks is like it's too hard
to follow the code it's hard to write
the code and and people usually talk
about this is like I get it but someone
else wouldn't and you know I guess what
I say is like yeah coatings hard you
know that's that's just the way it goes
buddy you know writing these apps are
like if they weren't hard to build then
everyone would build them and you know
we'd be out of a job
the the other side of this is that it's
like hard to follow you know it's like
kind of it can be like really and you
know this is related to the like super
indenting thing I guess what I would say
is I think it's clearer than the than
the tangle of events you get in a lot of
OOP code and so I like it better that
way
another thing you see is like there are
too many includes in these files and
it's true like at the bottom of our
dependency chains like I was looking at
chat tab
to prepare for this presentation and at
this point they're like forty includes
at the top of that file I guess the
thing I would say is like at least the
dependencies are tracked and not and not
on track the way they are in that
threads participants example and then
the last one is like this is legit like
you end up using bind a lot when you use
this style and that can be really
inefficient like if you bind at every
call site like every time you call a
method on another module and pass a
callback if you bind every time that
uses memory so you do have to watch out
for that one I hoped I'd have time for
questions but I don't you'll just have
to find me and I'd love to talk about
functional and OOP or chat or and
anything else but I guess here's what I
have to say modularity that's the big
win you know that that's what you
absolutely need to do unit testing goes
right with it I highly recommend it and