[Music]
hey everyone so my name is Claudia I'm a
Mexican software engineer currently
working for NPM so um a little bit of
context I'm actually from this city kaul
Monterrey Mexico and in case you don't
know where that is that's actually just
in the north of Mexico very near the
States so what was happening in my life
in 2014 so in 2014 I was getting my
degree in computer science and being out
of school I asked myself how can I
continue learning so that's when I
actually came across conference talks
online so this really sparked my
interest in tech meetups in my local
area the thing is that I realized they
were not local meetups happening at all
actually there was only one so in 2015 I
gave my first talk ever in this very
very small meetup in Monterrey called
JavaScript Monterrey and as you might
notice it was a small it was normally 10
to 15 people um this made me realize
something very important I was missing
out a lot of things but why and I really
really want to highlight three reasons
why I believe he was very inconvenient
for me to stay in this city in Monterrey
so the first reason is this one Loeb
community involvement so this is a graph
of all the conference's that are more or
less happening in 2018 and 2020 in the
graph speaks by itself
there are way more conferences happen in
Europe and in the u.s. than the rest of
the world
this is JS JS JavaScript conference is
happening so the second reason is non
competitive salaries in Latin America so
the average monthly salary in Mexico is
$745 this is what I what I was actually
making in my first job and these are
very I open or tweet by Juan Pablo
Radhika he's one of the leaders of the
Colombian community and his
a hundred ticket $100 ticket is a 10% of
a Colombian developers monthly income
sometimes even more sponsors really help
in developing nations events so in that
fashion $100 ticket is 13% of Mexican
developers monthly income so I already
mentioned that there are not a lot of
things happening in Latin America so on
top of that if you won't actually go to
a conference you have to pay
accomodation you have to pay the ticket
and you have to pay the flights so you
know we don't have a lot of options and
the third one it's expensive
infrastructure in Latin America so long
story short this means is that we're
paying more for slower services so now
that we have this three reasons in 2015
I decided to move from Mexico and in
2015 I moved to Paris an incredible
thing that happened once I moved to
Europe is diversity scholarships so in
2015 I got a scholarship for J's
computer and this is a quote that I
really really love from Yoona that says
scholarships aren't just about
increasing diversity numbers or
financial assistance they can change and
attend in life they do they change mine
so in this computer up 2015 I met an
amazing human being that really inspired
me and really motivated me to pursue my
public speaking dreams so this led to
this in 2016 16 I gave my first
international talk at Jes come Budapest
and shout out to the descon organizers
because they believed in me I love them
so funny stories well the edition after
the one in which I was in first with a
scholarship I came back as a speaker
this time so it was a mind-blowing
experience to be sharing the same stage
with the same person that the previous
year actually inspired me to be in the
stage in the first place amazing
experience in the rest the rest is
history
after this opportunity that I got which
is calm Yura I attended more meet ups
and stuff but all of these wouldn't have
been possible without the help of that
community without the meetups that I
attended and the conference's that I've
been to
what I really really just want to ask to
you is to help create these communities
for people that aren't as lucky as I was
to literally switch countries to sort of
search for these opportunities so what
can we actually do we cannot change in
tahrir bills we cannot change salaries
but we can help organizing and funding
meetups and conferences around the world
so please get involved attend your local
meetups help the organizers give back to
the community and this is just one of
the examples this is limit is you can
actually sponsor the Meetup Lima is in
Peru
one of the South American meetups and
spread the word help other communities
be built and with that being said I want
to make an announcement I want to
announce a new member of the JSF family
Jace comes Mexico 4th and 5th of May
Cinco de Mayo next year Mexico City you
are all welcome to go please I really
really want to see you all there and
with that being said thank you very much
[Applause]