hi well that's weird okay hi I'm
Sebastian I work at some web service
agency code dank vector and Germany most
of you won't know this one actually I
consider myself as the average
JavaScript deaf from the next door so
nothing special most people then from
the internets know me as a ski disco if
they know me and yeah I actually love
coffee and 80s movies and multicolored
sucks so these are my favorites I'm
wearing them right now and if you have
any any cool online stock online shops
or something like this where i can buy
socks that look like this just give me
ping on twitter please thanks ok now for
sure and i also love javascript so yeah
a bit of history um my this looks a bit
word i know but when i was a kid like
six or seven years old i always imagined
it later when i'm working in my working
life that i will be in some lab and
actually looking like this every day and
doing some weird stuff building cool
things yeah but then I discovered our
script and after a while I thought yeah
actually I'm doing exactly that what I
dreamt of when I was kid so like
building all these crazy things here and
yeah so let's start the actual talk I
brought three kind of examples things I
build at home um I just figure out the
first one won't work because of some
network issues but I still tell you a
bit about it so actually um about
something called the trial detector so
the actual quest was that I'm spotting
the trolls here in the room
that tweet bath stuff during the talk
but yeah let's come to that later but
you're due to some network issues that
won't work because the actual setup boss
you see this this lamp here maybe and
this is attached to wireless power
plaque you can buy on Amazon and this
book's if I turn it on here no yeah so
you can see ok works manually and I'm
actually this works through the zigbee
wireless protocol is some kind of
standard protocol and I rode a node
library that you can that abstracts this
protocol this is not like it because
it's pretty unstable and well so you see
it's not working yet so it's really
unstable and I will work a bit on it and
then I will release it but yeah ZigBee
protocol is like a wireless
communication protocol and it's
standardized and open protocol so
everybody can just like grabbed it and
builds devil it works like bluetooth
kind of 16 communication channels can
fool duplex and you can do a scene
communication also there are you know
connectors i'm currently working with
the XP shields but this is kind of hard
to get around yeah there are also like
devices are standardized so you can buy
like this wireless power plaques on
amazon for like 20 euros or something
and then use them with any environment
you want that speaks the ZigBee protocol
and by the way when I'm when I did this
like kind of library abstraction I just
find thought that the guys who went to
the protocol must be on crack or
something because this is so weird
standing like packages with hex values
around and not good at math and just
really sucks when
you're not good at math so but I built
this library that will be released
somewhere in the future yeah that I
think it has some easy API so you can
just like discover the wireless
controller that you will connect with
your devices that you have you can start
a device discovery and actually like
getting to know these both so let's ddu
the wireless control speak with the
device and yeah so the device is called
will return all available devices these
have some common types like this one
will say hi I'm a binary switch and the
other one will and also it will say like
a are the status currently I'm turned on
and then you will have some easy actions
like turning things on and off hood when
it works then it works with these binary
switch things only but I will implement
some more drivers soon when I release a
library okay yeah sad that i discovered
that that won't work because there would
be a cool thing to show but let's move
on to another thing abroad here actually
uh-huh i have a connect here these
things i just type here is not like
comin fer to connect because when i
arrived in berlin on friday i just like
set up everything in my hotel room to
test if it works and to connect connect
gotta serio got a serious damage during
the fight and so a friday morning free i
am I like saturday morning for um I just
my last chance was to open it and I only
had a Swiss Army knife carrying with me
so I will never ever do that do that
again not in a hotel room not at three
o'clock in the morning opening a connect
but it kind of worked after this surgery
and so hopefully this will work so the
quest is make you're a proud of me and
actually what I'm trying to do is let
the kinect recognize a gesture i'm doing
then brought the kinect will give all
that stream to this Windows PC which has
to connect SDK installed and there's
some library running which will then
broadcast some broadcast some WebSocket
event which I'm catching in a browser
here on this computer and this computer
actually then we'll go and say hey
arduino please just let these tin cans
flip over okay and let's see if that one
we work huh it's running okay so after
this connector Udrih it worked like in
sixty percent of the things that drive
so hopefully so the bad way the infrared
sensor is gone so let's see how come on
come on come on
okay maybe will someone come over and
try his jedi force on the second one any
volunteer no I just come over just like
try to position some around here because
the kinect has some damage you won't see
yourself here normally you would see
yourself here and it's kind of hard
because no you don't know what to do but
still stand here and try um just give
just stay here for like two or three
seconds and I hope they're just do it a
couple of times just thank you
yeah I actually I just like did
something that was way cooler than this
like a shooting game so hopefully that
if the internet works uh-huh I did
something enter user group like a couple
of months ago and you see actually you
can really control this little rat
cursor inside of your browser window and
this is way more cool than what I showed
here and actually had this cool example
we're just like point on things and take
your other hand and shoot and shoot and
when you hit the virtual tin can I would
just flip this one over but damage
connect and a failure but hope you
enjoyed it what the other one too okay
so let's see how that works ok meet
connect Jess connect us is a library
that some I think some guys from Norway
build like half a year ago and this
one's super cool as a it uses the kinect
sdk so this is why I have this windows
laptop here and it's a little program
that runs on on this computer which
dispatches like you ends why sockets and
broadcast em to the network also they've
built some neat client-side JavaScript
library and it which introduces new
events so you can do like at evangelist
interconnect touch start to a need um
alum and and then react on that this is
so cool and you can set this up in like
15 to 20 minutes to do something in your
browser it can handle two players
actually so they also have a nice demo
with a pong game to place the two
players playing against each other and
it also has some predefined gestures one
we saw there to swipe gesture and they
also have something like a jump Chester
when you jump
up and down and this is pretty pretty
cool okay for my next project that I
call the Dancy Dancy I need another
volunteer out of the audience somebody
is willing to dance in front of okay
maybe maybe you will you would trust me
that nothing bad will happen as I just
ruined my street credibility on my own
and dance barefoot in the front of all
of you so let's try that yeah looks
beautiful or and I should turn on the
audio okay that sounds good so mm-hmm
looks like it's wicker so okay I really
never thought i would do this but I'm
doing it oh by the way this hook stuff I
read them right now yeah i did because
these are my favorites at the moment for
those behind who don't see why I'm
sitting here there's some flights on the
ground with foil and I rican belief that
I'm doing this so that's try
okay and also there's a pier lying here
on the ground when I touch it it will
start the game was the first one okay
let's gooo that so
that's good it back on because I'm not
Jake Archibald ok so now any volunteer
any audience I'll come on guys one
person dancing in front of all so come
over because yeah I need to show that
I'm not cheating so yeah so it's always
good to cut someone off the audience
applause hi ha I'm Sebastian so let's
just get rid of your shoes and socks
actually once enough but ok ok good and
go over here here's your keyboard you
need to take this in your hands and then
touch it appear on the ground with your
food or with your hand ok and play so
was the right one
last round such as we have a winner
by the way so we're at one yeah some
goodie pack for you thanks for coming
over and helping me out yeah take this
with you I think you need it okay what
happened just here well I don't know for
sure I know does any one of you have
heard of this cool thing called Mikey
Mikey okay after this you will just like
directly order one on your own so make
you make it for me is the best damn
thing since sliced bread it's like this
little controller it actually was a
Kickstarter project like four months ago
and this little controller you can just
pluck them a plug it in via USB and it
acts like a normal keyboard so you get
some alligator clips with it and
actually that's the back of it so you
can map keyboard keys so you see W ASDF
these are actually normal keyboard keys
you can just clip alligator clips and
and connect it with everything that at
least transports a bit of energy like
your skin or some foil or appear a
banana they actually built some really
cool banana a keyboard that's awesome
but it is a cheap trick so as a toll it
acts like a normal keyboard and you can
just like grab it in your browser like
normal with a normal event listener and
as I told you an immaterial that conduct
at least bit of energy will work and
should really really get one for you on
your own at home okay so unlikely first
example won't work maybe I'm showing
that off later over there let's see but
you may ask yourself why is this guy on
stage showing us all this weird stuff
connecting you know
and actually it all started after last
year's Jays convey you so we had this
cool talks about the coder dojo and this
really cool talk by Chris Williams who
encouraged at least me to step up and do
some practice talking and also because
in a company i'm working there we work
together with some schools and
universities and select students coming
over and we tell them what we do here
and before i discovered all this cool
hat worst of they were like design
students that came over and asked you
here a developer do presentation on what
you're doing and I was like I was here I
built this website and you can buy
flights with it and every one of them
was like oh yeah ok this guy bills
website mmm but then I thought okay
maybe the job as a developer needs a bit
polish and I started building those
little things so I build a couple of
more which I just like for a way after
time when I'm bored of it and now I'm
showing this all to students and school
kids who come over to your company and
wanted to know what a developer does for
me and now i can say i'm okay i'm a
developer a boat key words you can make
music with your feet and i can make you
a real Jedi warrior night whatever
they're called and also I have some very
little cousins like beginning from the
age of six or seven I guess yeah and
this is this is the stuff if you want to
get someone into programming or want to
make somebody have fun doing starting
with programming that's the stuff you
should show them so and also if you're
some kind of a CTO
CFO run a known company that employs
some developers just buy them a couple
of rdu nose just buy them like a connect
to play around or just make you my key
thing and give them like two or three
hours in a week in a month maybe two
just and say just go and play so they
will have more fun when they go to work
because they can really do something and
actually just building thinks of
javascript is fun so yeah I guess that's
it a bit shorter because the first
example was screwed but first of all