cham interviews myself basically she wheelies
picture of project manager at talk about the next minute made die
presentation the performance july korn with we thought we are going to laughter
lounge of the protect source project itself basically a business translation
because of you do something like the factory important that i always on zu
know translate uhs i management rod is basically do in the background of
systems starts in the beginning of last year to date up at the event started
quaid design system trivago because frontend let's say the historical and i
had some issues that takes you later tobi enterprise ihe still would have
created the the spirit that the trainer knows the task force created to end
Task force one man's later the important for you project reset flowed
at innside by how would it be like the newspaper tuttosport first of all it will be
import almost like herbert of applications like music like hip hop or
with is the trivago hotel cert wilkens becomes spoiler old hotel europa league
finds either lot of other applications and lots of different
department of it is won in leipzig in palma and in amsterdam and like never
had consistent style guide design system of course on inconsistent code and
design one other important giant baby this project would have something to
improve quality and maintain ability to let the example momentane bielecki and
quality superdome as well as in the new system design system and increases and of
course i want to be faster in building modern sustainable user interfaces for
our products as i said i starts developing creating peter lambert
trivago and we've always on our corp the day before with business critical to the test
as to work centered design development process leike tomic design is much more
efficiently sets company pages
if it was said 14 this is combi on average
night and want to have the page book
Saturday lotto was basically barry peace and our company
and assessing mixture from the bronx like a buffer frameworks basically back and
dad says it to better
it is what the first sight will be like monsters of september the back and for
the perfect but you can't see sepsis ortsbild becomes design thinking
tomic design just changes external websites of courage as far as we do
table to do looks like the science buddys screens put a consistent one year
design has coming back to our core products, trivago starts and off
2011 first time open text css celebrates hard there in Katowice we started to
produce and the city in cs smz-ost basically elektro call it the city that
happens if you don't have design system system and trust open file and select
the bottom of fire is called the workcentre so basically here
application looked like system at the end of 2011 as always as came to
Started in 2011 to create better way to face lift off the website like at apple
to improve code is not having design systems is what you do on ms project
related to conversion way treated in 2014 15 cent and conversion bicc dosis
looks at least a bit modern than in 2015
like image of an adaptive on the scales basically desktop forester would have percent
uhwiesen resource manager resources and able to do a completely picture sony wo
able to do is basically mobile and desktop site kibiz is super big wall
for basically body dead 2 4 down the sword as snappy as before this started
is how you look like you remember this way we showed you before this das much
better she horny simons of you that more bodies it wants the bitterest pink since
the beginning of the end of the world as we had a specific looks like starting to
go up here but if you have been you start off is the peaks because
this might be 6 is elektro here in the beginning of the state is already source
to have to wait a place for mobility and scalability office space so basically
it has small capital over here as well as the able to the bone and president
ist coldplays which would like to show you know what we build basically
frankenstein to 11 itself but there will be designs
pride with space to better as head of sales management director page up
we would be able to drink lots of alcohol desktops
critically the icons videos
this lot of the decade with travel time to remove bahnhofs icon centers workout
how also had some people in the box for example is present from our politicians
department fought michael küster household has ended you have one
renaissance is fetching process crashes it was said to be complex and
today you like the dom and structures the baby the guests the upper hand again
the new photos of jesse hughes troll
basically it is what wooden stairs it said then let you like person kempkes
dorf in 1 1 internet explorer hesse limit inspectors reebok it and so are
watching and asset how would desktop first thought you might not especially
mobile device first has to the desktops partly removed mobile
star of topic witches of course i shot cupid mobile first to basic ran first
mobile styles the desktop starter without playback samples leaves the said we had
in consistency and the missing style guide
now basically found everybody happy with what they could look like like css
chair tour ends world tools to show for example people what about to
understand the people how did he overlay complex smc s and don structure
coming back to protect the basic i had to decide who his team is too
engineering team how to protect and how to explain the management fleet
management tlm rbi human factors could i
have to make it more transparent what you get me you are some say we came up
with three steps the cost of his project on site
christoph becker steps we had to do to review the witcher basically creative
lab one thing is still had we said css code and especially reset cssr be heard
that again that matter in fixing if you stayed browsers and wood as well
used content box and one of europe plc assessment of use content box basic
like paclet volks ampel view, you only have browser zoom center browsers
do you have the kecke late service of the border and have spent the case of use
enormous achievement of this thing to explore the word crisis mobile
first suite robert boers list password rbb hat werder will be a sweet forest
basically very easy to explain the third place to be mobile first to replace him
is great because they say never let me sign end beforehand educated people don't
change the existing layout despite basically has challenge because the view
of the year is the notebook or changes that but he couldn't because we would
have we had an impact because i never change we have just live retail things
button color can can lead to flash converter to the example of amazon don't
know how often the test win everyone on whether you click on the techart button hessin
fuentes so boeing would have stayed in that the architecture us out ending the
prince of this time we can give you some more technical details what i basically
but if you had the sts essebsi 50001 of code becomes head of course i spg
how did you get jane seymour to remove she paints glass called o2 world
of possible and changing the appearance to reduce the complexity set in them
Seeing harmful as in the ghetto kid support relieves stress like kurt f cell
future is what would have captured support at cis point important
boxee box half time frame
the risk of technical people to understand why you have basically
constantly space and live from time to time through factoring basically
force one of our challenges to explain the management fleet feature freeze dual
as well as four background an sie core products waage hotels working as think
about trade people see it right to build features and trust of our users
and to basic i have to say i has the top four weeks because of the factors and
space is concerto management vw holds well so wood is a classic style
a new project is being built on whether she's gone learning centers porta
q-cells are user management just understand what would you do i do
it for the evaluation of display consistent but case it is up to the city
that may be does not have it initially 50 sms is north korean to something
Fall is just like faster than people will love you to try to be faster
Its posted very much like Germany would have bit of minders in
but new existence people become ill with full liter and all very important luca
tonis ink technik should so understand the third person servers demanded just can't
go then tony iommi come up with respect yourself do to understand that important
that the company is money removes half of the wittler business
processing potatoes and interesting talent for the car
especially imports is there and it is the set and have sex is in process and
don't stop loss something with a very important car dealer management
expectation especially asset management kenneth klev things like the fact the
great and very happy few ken gibson update every day is worked out of work
out to play mmo s ms tablet crisis best and maybe you and i think we
just do to access the work out one thing that people process which was very
important that what about having process of the processor moore last people die
time home expected
romy very important commitment over estimation lately anti-virus molly
factoring the child almost blows apse like factoring test in small but as the
people the better visibility and salt on the splitting from wars at last las
the bishops' conference asks liebert and ticket system time because it's very
hard fact that won't you very hard user interface because you had so much
dependency battle los angeles electro here a good ride informs what more
important than the technical support act has a know put people are committed
to that i want to get it done as fast as possible to create a possible you're
interested justin long tax and asset management as well as internal social
ksv am 3 update the people and side hedia wir gut in time and very important
that one point where we didn't how come you gotta get your hand special
for the finest is a widget for us the first problem means the band offers
connections because if you like for johannes to the people are the new ones
president of nok there are only problems in the lakers team is motivated people and
let there be awesome is not about special effects projects from we forget
to be for is not about my key management people
controlling people is about what people
and difficult explained that are coming back tour tour for mom's process one
people we had this post basically but you can there instead of having to what
ever be used cars on energy and the search for mathias hain l 222 visual
process which have thought it simple and coming to protect him the kof system
basically no counters developers designers to create people and the other
supporters so basically back and tax
justice has to be done in the same horn hands out release and any and of course
to know the performance of very happy ending in the power performance
insiders like hefty june were able to manage these processes as well as head of the meeting and
seventeen stand up center can be murder as basic i needed to music and outcomes
and we have some numbers to see what
the basic element that was nine hundred things we do incredible of the baby part
goalkeeper or less like to talk swan kolleg at main event watch conference
Interested parties with something that they said no beer are they office bust
committing tutower feature brings thorsten so smashing could
support and most basically committing and contributing to the project and if
I should have stopped my playlist gaming series finally a can do x change
is out like basica vital ten minister would like base again and display the
state and i was sitting and assembly and combating the band 2000 lines of
code of the post basically newco change code review before these lines of code
javascript and had cssb is the lines of code of 25 percent from the asc space
and replace the existing icon service present die man with of course a too
much amazing to the hundred acre wood christina user interface bad es aber die
saints of my different ways to you don't have any impact on and conversion
negative impact on conversion also like change would end to files
dancing stars of the ssc lecturer as before the iss select fund again on that
it is probably like before eighth estg knows the fair reduce coming up coming
use on saturday a highlight for basically first what the desktops applied
sciences master host mcquarrie from mobile devices and inconsistent wars like
come you mobile stylesheet a complete history click to basic changing
horses and positive impact on and racing performance the topic is get what
you pay to play version bettina most retina display will time until the
norm is wide and eight before
requests games wide we can take 126 out of the
after what we saw at the colors like tablet introduce the color palette
trivago lux 0 exists on legacy code in bad ems in operation picture new from 9
picture franziska ballet and how it should be a mess as well as the hesse-spd icon
set is like news and can easily be given to people who cost it de facto too
very positive become better overview of which were used to end that becomes very
difficult if i had before and after you like basic thinking about the foundation
of a completely god in vom supertalent is basically broadway basically sie
mobile first you know you've got components like like to do
testing value on course dual speed test is it is is the presence of the
user space education and 50 percent to much magic basically what you see here
is something is significantly negative
indication is different matthew campbell imagine that for example with that
people search or trivago look at the advertiser and sent buchsi hotels first
medical hot saw some other things like build second session duration witcher
importing fast and costing something new boss is what was expected to
the event with crazy on it's corners june could longboard changing must
unicorn the osi office offers unicorns and twitter account sales
big project ends giving you some of which is refactoring project like
bild.de foundation to move right to the next level with roger moore business from
Basically but foundation is much more stable relieves ovations
gentlemen example the very end of mine presentation how better if
performance on mobile rich wars episode i costs lotteries something around 550
millions will not really like but at least like cookies and especially box
is like ethanol devices disappeared and all things very important that we have
much better understanding of power user interface works photo mig designers and
white christmas is important and prices do you love well knows how coldplay
keyboard in building new web pages it is the satin optimal design
development process and be introduced a lot of you guidelines css bento css
coming to move it pastor you time after sales business critical elements like
coliseum element itself the ott version until it is stable 1 in between systems and
i can't see is super class is the price but here it is content is not
what really user friendly motor show the next one nine months to develop and the
dead end after we moved to willi peter lapp holding wie bild in east and
human services testing of developing prototyping inside the pattern matching
started with lily cole like the business metvix which started
longines new elements that present integrates what the 19 percent conversion
but the cross eyed possum much more modules and much more structure like wait
to do incredible fast september basically days of work out to maintain
the date of design kallas basic and ever
wanted to mars return to basics in the business week which was just positive