hey everybody how's it going hi hi hi hi
hey hi hi so this is a talk called
making modern web sites my name is
Patrick Kettner this is me if you ever
see me online i'm pretty much ease that
appetite everywhere i like to take
pictures of cakes my girlfriend makes
them for me she's over there she's
really cool she want to say hi I also
work at Microsoft and I work
specifically on edge I'm a program
manager for interop so basically if
something in edge is shitty it's
probably my fault or my problem to get
it fixed so feel free to complain to me
either in person or online that being
said edges and shitty it's a really
great browser to check it out so anyway
I don't here to talk about I jumping to
talk about website specifically making
websites and specifically help making
websites is hard at least to make good
websites and it really really hard and
it didn't used to be when I was a kid so
my first websites looked a lot like this
this not quite this very first website
but it was you know throw up some stuff
HTML on a page and it's done and it's
better than most things in the world is
most of the things websites in the world
didn't exist yet um but now there's just
a ton of new features that get added to
the web platform every single day and
it's kind of overwhelming and you just
kind of feel like you have to know
everything and it sucks and you just
kind of want to make it stop but you
don't though you don't want to make it
stop you want to make it better and we
make it better by using tools there's a
lot of tools out there because there's a
lot of different feature sets I actually
work on one specifically on the lead
maintainer for moderniser it's the most
second use JavaScript library on the web
after jquery if you don't know it's
basically like a feature detection
library rather than do like you a sniff
user agent sniffing you're able to check
to see if a feature exists and if it
does do something it's cool um it's
really popular justin bieber actually
hasn't moderniser hoodie for some reason
this is an actual photo he really owns
that it costs like five hundred dollars
it's from France I don't know why they
have it but modernizes on it but that
was fine um yeah anyway so moderniser
actually came out with version 3
recently version 2 was in 2011 so
version 3 getting shipped finally was
kind of a big deal for me I was a very
prolonged pregnancy um we just shipped
it and if you haven't looked at
moderniser since we shipped it in
September
you might be familiar with this this is
the website it served as well since 2011
it was you know it was fine at the time
it got kind of aged so we ended up
spending a lot of time wanting to update
this and make it better we did a whole
lot of work that old team did a whole
bunch of work and eventually we came up
with this which is the new website and
it was cool it took a lot of energy took
a lot of work and no one gives a
about it other than me um no one really
cares at best modernizer just doesn't
get in the way like if you're wanting a
new fee if somebody's no one's going to
modernize accom every morning when they
wake up they're only doing it because
they want to make better websites they
want to get a tool and get out of the
way we're up pit stop at best along
their way but we still want to make our
users happy and we do that by making it
really really fast and having a whole
lot of fun features in it so like I said
this was the website but what I'm going
to be talking about mostly the download
page which is a kind of a complicated
app which looks like this so um this is
the new website and this is the
gentleman who designed the new website
guy named Joe critchley out of England
he's great and like most designers when
he went and created a new website he
wanted to make it look pretty with the
thoughts because a lot of the website
fonts are kind of boring and so he used
the fun face API palm faces you know
loads got some phones is great and makes
your website look called news and fancy
unless you have a slow internet
connection like I'm sure all of you are
aware right now in which case the
website looks like this which sucks
because the websites completely broken
you can't do anything on it but it
actually does work it's just looks
broken everything functions you just
have to be a mind reader or use like the
accessibility API to be able to access
it and so the way to get around that is
uh there's a great new API called the
font loading module if you're not aware
this is a new JavaScript API that's been
added a while back in chrome and what it
looks like is this you have a new
document fonts property that has a dot
ready method and that gives you a
promise that promise gets fired with the
results once the fonts have been loaded
previously if you wanted to know if a
font had been loaded you had to wait
until the actual load event fired then
you had to wait for it to partisan the
only we could know that is if you like
injected into canvas and check the width
of the character length in campus by
pixels it was terrible this is great
this is God's end and so
the only problem with it oh so sorry so
rather than having a font definition
that looks like this where you define
your web site your website fonts after
your custom fonts you end up having two
different declarations like this one
with your body at the top where you have
your website plants website fonts rather
and then underneath it you have the
fonts loaded class which is where what
gets added when the fonts loaded so
instead of this it looks like this and
then after a couple seconds it look goes
like that a little clot dance and
otherwise it's great it's great API
makes your website's load a lot faster
the only problem is the support it's
only supported in chrome and firefox
right now and working at Microsoft I
can't really ship something that doesn't
work good in the browser or at least
work in the browser it also doesn't work
in Safari or mobile iOS so it's not
really ideal but there is a thing a
polyfill called font face observer by
Bram Stein it's great rather than your
code look like this you just make a
minor change and you import the font
face observer and otherwise your code
books the same we just add a class at
the bottom inside of once the fonts been
loaded we had class to the body and
you're good but breaking news
visit it breaking news um so there's
actually a new CSS property called font
display it does the exact same thing
it'll swap out your fonts as soon as the
fonts Brett loaded rather then you know
like blocking or waiting till the next
red light or anything it's a great API
it's brand new like literally brand new
it's December first like a couple of
days ago we just gotta do Chrome Canary
so probably a year from now everything I
just said is complete nonsense you won't
need to do it but this is great best
feature anyway back to what I was saying
so uh this is what like I said this is
kind of this weird Dancy thing that
happens when the fonts load it's not
ideal especially if you have real design
focus people um so rather than setting a
class you also the option to do like set
a property and local storage then the
next time it loads you can check if that
local storage is already there at the
very top your body it's at the class
immediately and your fonts are
constantly that one fun it's better and
if it's cash properly and the user in
clear part of the cash or the browser
and clear part of the cash and the point
being this is always basically an
educated guess we don't know for a fact
whether or not that fonts going to be
there without that skip unless we use
something like service worker so service
workers are really cool they're kind of
a big deal if you've never heard of them
as anybody not heard of service workers
before no great cool so it's gives you
adds a whole lot of new features to the
web platform stuff like offline
experiences push notifications
background sync and much much more but
the two parts that I'm going to be
discussing our kind of more fundamental
pieces fetch in cash so they're both New
api's fetches sort of network proxy any
network requests that goes out through
the browser whether it be from CSS xhr
JavaScript anything at all as long as
it's from your same domain it'll go
through fetch you have the opportunity
to catch that request modify it send it
on do whatever you want cash is like the
browser cache only it's completely
programmable so you're able to control
what goes into it so we avoid that whole
is it or is it not cached thing so
modernizer the website was completely
built on requirejs modules because it's
old and so every one of these like check
boxy things and anything that is
anything you can click on pretty much is
its own module there's 259 modules today
though probably like 262 once I start
getting back to my house and merging
commits that came in and any single one
of those modules could end up being
dozens of requests
and as a result we have to we want to
add it to our service worker and the way
we do that is like this we do navigator
that service worker dot register a new
API you pass it a string that represents
the path to a JavaScript file that
javascript file looks something like
this this is an example of us
prefetching are Totally Rad sans font we
have we set up a cash up here which is
just an object with the name space
because you can have multiple caches if
you want to delete one and keep another
then we add an event listener for the
install event the uninstall is when the
service worker has been installed into
the browser then we go out and we
prefetch each one of these URLs so you
can pre straightforward and so later on
we'll have this which is the fetch event
and the fetch event is that network
proxy thing that I mentioned before
every time that a fetch event happens
which is any network request it goes
through here we check to see if the
response is already cached if it is we
respond with that so it happens
immediately rather than going you know
over to server farm somewhere in coming
back to a computer and just read it
straight off the disk and if it's not
there we go and we fetch it and then we
cash the response so that if requested
again in the future it's there it's
great it's simple um the problem again
the support is not very great it's
pretty much only in Chrome it's going to
be in Firefox in a couple of weeks in
early January so we need it sucks we
need like some kind of hero we need some
kind of Savior we need a douchebag and
we need app cache um so a couple of
years ago Jake Archibald gave a talk at
jas comp called app cache is a douchebag
it's a awesome talk if you've never seen
it it gives a lot of background into
what app cache is that was the original
kind of fork off of Google gears that
was supposed to be how we were going to
make offline applications the problem
was it's a douche bag and it sucks a lot
um service workers way better if you
have the opportunity to only make
something for cromer to make something
specifically using a service worker
don't even look at app cache it's
horrible but it is supported everywhere
pretty much any browser you'd want to
develop something for supports it and so
it come and it happens to cover our use
which is basically caching everything
and then returning it immediately if
it's there so the way that it works is
you just have a plain text file that's a
manifest looks something like this
you'll have a comment up at the top
do cash and validation because it app
cat the browser will check to see if any
new version of the manifest is byte for
byte the same and if it isn't it will
redownload everything which is what we
want to have happen when we do releases
we list a couple of static files you
want to have downloaded and then I have
this double under assets thing that's
something that gets programmatically
addict we're injecting a whole bunch of
like the individual modules that we're
creating for the website that way we
don't have to maintain a list of them in
multiple places it just gets added in
like a gulp script then the only other
important thing is down here the network
asterisk what that means is that as
you're browsing everything that comes
from your domain gets added to the app
cache automatically so um it looks
something like this you just have a
manifest attribute on your browser and
right there and it's OOP sorry again
service worker is much better than app
cache though so we don't want to have to
inject it unless we need it app cache is
a douche bag it completely takes over
your entire page you're certain all your
serviceworker responses would be
confusing a lot more difficult to reason
about you get into a weird state that
you'll run do so yo news app cache if
service worker isn't there we do this
registration like this if service worker
isn't navigator then we register it and
if it isn't we check to see if app cache
I was on the window and if it is we at
the app cache the problem is you can't
add it by JavaScript to that page you
have to UM the manifest file has to be
there on page load and so what we can do
to get around this is load it in an
iframe we create another basically a
dummy page and add a that has an app
cache on it we load that I frame on the
page and we inject it into the page and
then everything's loaded it's great so
this is a duck like an example dummy
file it's all that's doing is loading
the app cache and it's injected to it
and we go from loading the moderniser
website on the wonderful provided Wi-Fi
here went from 20 seconds to 190
milliseconds on reload so it's
substantial savings anytime I'm on an
airplane anytime and i'm on a train or
at Amelia Island at jjs conf it's always
wonderful if the websites properly using
this stuff so check it out if you
haven't but again service workers are
much better than app cache service
workers are the future web workers are
the future um that's web workers if
you're not familiar with web workers
they've been around actually for a long
time November of 2008 they shipped in
chrome version 2 in 2009 when it looked
like that
it's been around for a very long time
they're they're pretty similar web
worker sorry to service workers in the
way that you interact with them but the
purpose for them are completely
different web workers are a solution to
the problem with the browser that
everything is single threaded because
layout is constantly fighting for
resources on top of all of your logic if
you have a whole lot of different stuff
going on at once it creates this really
ugly janky experience that sucks and
it's not a good website in a tux so what
you're able to do is you're able to take
tasks and offload them to a background
thread so that your uh your UI is able
to constantly update in the way that you
want it to but you can still do those
heavy crunching things it's great so
super expensive functions become really
cheap and one of the things that we
ended up doing with it was creating
dynamic file size calculation so if you
look again this is that website that
I've shown you a number of times up in
the left hand corner it actually says
the number of kilobytes and bites of
every file that you have that's been
created so as you check stuff it updates
with those values now this is a hundred
percent client-side there's nothing
talking to a server because I want this
to work completely offline the way that
we do that was through a web worker we
register that web worker with a little
we call gzip worker and it's just a
basic function that gets a JSON object
and that passes it to that JSON object
to a worker and in father's a call back
to update the UI later on inside the
gzip file we import a couple of node
modules Packo which is a javascript
implementation of the deflate algorithm
for g zipping and then pretty bytes
which takes something like a hundred
bytes and makes it into point zero zero
point one kilobytes and makes it more
human readable and pretty so we just
listen to the message we parse the build
out of it we so we would pass the entire
build of moderniser to this function and
then we would take that string we pass
it into pretty bytes pretty by its
figures out how small or sorry we get
the original size of it through pretty
bytes then we also pass pretty bites the
gzipped and pack o deflate which is a
gzipped minified version of it with the
average server level which is six and
that gives us the size of the files so
you see originally was to point 64
kilobytes gzip it's down to 1.18 for
these first three things that are
clicked um
now there is not that's not the only
other worker we because we want to be
able to update that on the fly we have
to build stuff constantly which means we
can't wait for someone to click on the
build button we want to be able to build
in the background and what we the way we
do that again is through a web worker so
we have a separate worker for building
it's very similar registered the exact
same way and we post a message with the
config file that config so all of the
modernizer require modules are built
through one big Jason config um that
gets passed into the worker and the
worker loads up the moderniser requires
a s based builder and then that does the
on it then it registers for on message
and then that does the building of
moderniser and it reports back with the
final string so basically you're just
passing this along it's exactly like you
would imagine use pass on a config file
you get out of string the only
difference is that it's on a background
thread so we can be doing this
constantly in the background and you
wouldn't even notice so by the time that
somebody actually clicks that big pink
build button in the corner it's already
been built usually for several seconds
but they might be asking what if their
browser doesn't support web workers
first of all it's been around forever so
pretty much all browsers support them
they're all so many should use them if
they don't it's not that a good deal
they click on the build button and then
we just build then that's you know it's
fine there are not older browser they're
used to shitty experiences you know we
can just click on the button and go on
so that bill button actually doesn't
give you a file it opens up a pop-up
most of the time um with a couple of
options one of them is to copy to
clipboard there is to download copy to
clipboard again is something that has
been really difficult to do right on the
web for a very long time leaves a thing
called zero clipboard it's a pretty
simple API you just load it up and you
give it a listen for click event it
gives you the clipboard data you add it
to sorry you add your own data to a
clipboard and it's done it's pretty
straightforward the only crappy thing
the really crappy thing is it's built by
it's powered by flash it's one little
flash control that's put on anything you
want copy and that's how it works that's
how github stuff works that's how the
monitors are set work's currently and it
sucks flash sucks you don't want to use
flash because who wants to have flash
installed in my machine so we have a
modernized detective to see whether or
not flash is installed and working as a
not blocked or click to play and if it
isn't then we load zero clipboard and if
it isn't if it is being blocked then we
it's something else and it's something
else is just a textarea box we just load
up as plain old Texas Reeboks inject the
values into it and then automatically
select it then that kind of command to
copy Club to copy to clipboard just
becomes a request to go ahead and copy
this to clipboard later on if degrades
pretty gracefully but another breaking
news did it because the video doesn't
work clipboard j/s is a new way to do
this that was added after I started
writing this it doesn't use flash it
uses some of the exec command stuff
that's been built in the browser forever
that actually started working in chrome
recently and it does the fall backs
automatically for you if i were to
rebuild this I'd probably just use this
that being said zero clipboard can be
great if you need more browser support
especially on older browsers excuse me
um the other option after copy to
clipboard is download download is
something obviously most of the people
probably just to get a file they don't
really want to copy it or pace at
themselves and so since this is a
hundred percent client-side we view this
using a couple different api's file
blobs URLs and the download attribute
now file blobs are pretty
straightforward you just give it a
string and it gives it creates a binary
representation in memory that you're
able to pass into a another API called
create object URL which turns it into a
blob URI so those instead of like HTTP
colon forward slash words has something
its blob colon forward slash where says
something and you get a reference to
that file that's been created on the
client side and then finally we have a
download attribute that lets it download
with instead of a random gibberish
looking string it gives it a nice pretty
moderniser got custom jas name so it
ends up looking like this in our
template we set an HR up to that href
downloaded download and a download works
you should get a pop-up and it says
moderniser custom download without ever
talking to the server it's great so blob
constructing is really well supported
blob URLs are pretty well supported
download attributes aren't and that
makes it a really kind of crappy
experience so for us we considered it a
no-go if they don't support it otherwise
they get this really random gibberish
file it doesn't work on certain versions
or older versions of websites oh sorry
up browsers specifically ie it makes a
lot more confusing experience and a lot
of people that are using our website are
for newer web developers and so we
wanted to try to avoid that so what we
ended up doing was kind of thinking
about how we structure this page
if you'll notice this pretty much is a
giant list of check boxes and a submit
button this is really just a form when
you get down to it even though it was
kind of a web application so we decided
to just people just let people post the
form what that so basically what we do
is we instead of having this template
anger peg we end up checking to see if
it supports everything if it is we set
it to that anchor tag and if it isn't we
just changed that download button to a
input type submit and that becomes a
form that just submit and they submit
that form and they get a post it post to
the server and the server itself
processes the file sends it back it all
works this is a possible because we're
using decent markup decent markup is
actually supported in all browsers for
the most part it's when you use HTML
properly and what's cool about using the
decent markup is that when you use we
like we have a whole lot of CSS on the
site but you don't actually need to use
it websites that works completely
without CSS like completely without CSS
everything functions you can check off
new stuff and it calculates the new
values and everything functions
completely right it's great um then on
top of that not is since we're doing all
this stuff and basically just a form we
don't even need JavaScript anymore it
actually functions completely in links
the old text based browser um so you can
actually have this web so sorry oh god
um yeah you can have the browser do
stuff and you don't get the file size
calculations you don't get the dynamic
counting but you're not really expecting
to have that experience on here you just
hit you hit the build button once you're
done download it save to disk save the
file and there we go cat moderniser and
it's there in gzip and my terminal
broken it's there it works it's great so
it's awesome it's a hundred percent
client-side unless it can't then it can
fall back and it still works it works
pretty much all browsers because we have
a couple of little tiny pieces in the
server side even though it's mostly
static files like this is basically our
entire server config we use happy it's
like 20 lines plus a couple other little
cleanup things but all we're doing is
reading out of the distribution
directory and getting your path applying
it to that in serving that file and
that's it it's
clean its I've everything works since
wonderful but again it's almost one
hundred percent because we wanted to
support that post environment so what we
end up doing is creating a little
function that we build from a posted
query we grab the payload of the post
and we send it through the moderniser
API on the server side apply the contact
contact just that header Jesus Creek to
it to get the file back and then add
that to the route config and we're good
it works for all browsers like really
all browsers it literally works in
mosaic if you open it in mosaic I tried
it today it's awesome it's really cool
um the internet is awesome HTML is
awesome you able to make some really
cool stuff but again no one cares we
have all these tools they don't really
care whether or not the website is great
or held it work went into it if it
doesn't fit their workflow they don't
want to go out of their way saving
developers to download a new website or
to download your site to see the site to
get the build every single time they
want to make a change they just want it
to work for their tool chain to get out
of the way so one of the biggest
requests we had was to make it work for
NPM and Bower and people always said you
know I want a bower install we had
dozens of issues on github with people
saying that why can't we Bower install
it I want NPM install it and the problem
is that there isn't a file everything's
modular there used to be one single
moderniser file that's not been the case
for years and so we say you can't and
they say but I want to and so again no
one cares um it's the problem is that we
can't really like art process the reason
why pushing back against it is we can't
really precompile these things and push
it because again they're 259 modules you
figure out the math it's like sick yeah
it's there's not real I don't think
there's a name for how big that number
is it's ridiculously big 616 decimal
places yeah we would blow up n p.m. we
would take it all down if we tried to
publish everything to it but no one
cares that we can't do that they just
wanted to work they just want it to do
it because it works so we're like we
have to solve this we figure the server
is already building polls that doing
builds for posts posted things and
there's already a unique way to identify
individual you build the moderniser
using the header that's at the top of
any file that's ever been built so we
ended up doing is making it so that you
can NPM install that URL and the same
server that serves the HTTP HTML for
moderniser actually will respond with a
tarball for Bauer or for NP
and so that again 99.99 static files
this is the one other edge case if we
get to the handler for the download page
it checks the safer user agent is Bauer
if it does it builds for Bauer check to
save your user agents NPM it builds from
p.m. otherwise it serves the HTML for
the page so modernizer is using a user
agent sniff to give you a good feature
and that's embarrassing but it works and
there's no other better way so um yeah
so this is it really all that's in there
for a build for Bauer we just grab this
a great node a package called archiver
create a tarball and then create the
bower jason file which is just like a
static file with a couple little pieces
in it the name if you've ever used Bauer
it's like a it's like it's package.json
you know the name of the file stuff like
that where it came from and then we
append the actual build and we reply
with a big target and so if you Bower
install that you get a tarball back it
works same thing with NPM there's as you
can tell there's basically no difference
the only difference is inside of this
package ace of a creation of the JSON
file and it's a little bit different and
the name spacing is actually different
on NPM these are in not accurate but
otherwise it's the same and so you might
have noticed that we're actually loading
the moderniser module in there and it's
kind of confusing where it's like I
thought you said it was an on NPM and
the problem is that there is a
moderniser module but it's actually for
the CLI command line tool so most of the
time when people are talking about we're
wanting to require moderniser they don't
actually mean the command line tool they
mean a build-up moderniser but they can
load on their website and just get it to
work and get their day done and get over
it so this is what the command line
thing looks like and it's useful for us
because we've been able to build all
these tools off of it it works great you
just can end up creating a file and blah
it's very flexible but it's not super
friendly especially if you are new to
web browsers like a lot of people are
they're not familiar with the CLI they
don't want to use the CLI one of the two
and so we were like let's try to make
this better rather than passing a lot of
flags we had an interface that we liked
and so we want to reuse it and so we did
I created a command line version of our
website that works completely in the
browser or sorry in the command line you
do all that stuff you can it build and
you can open it on code pen and it opens
in the browser and yeah you can check to
see if it works it works
it's cool and what's cool about that is
that so if people are necessarily
comfortable with building in the browser
or sorry building on the command line we
can give them basically the exact same
experience and it's a great kind of
introduction to it it's cool we're able
to basically use the vast majority of
our code because react is cool rape is
awesome it makes it via the reuse the
stuff and were able to port it directly
to react blessed which is a the
command-line API that we're using and
it's a really cool hack it really works
really well and yeah so that's pretty
much what I have to say but just want to
leave with this no one really cares how
cool your website is if it doesn't work
or if it takes a long time to get there
if you have really slow animations if
you do all these things people just
wanna get their work done most of the
time especially when you're working on a
tool but so what our goal is to get out
of the way in the best way possible make
it the most enjoyable experiences but as
possible to get out of the way quickly
don't let that stop you from making
awesome stuff and don't let that stop
you from using new shiny features you
can use a lot of really cool stuff and
still make it really fast and work
really well and just have a lot of fun