okay i want to start with a similar
question who of you in this room is
working on JavaScript frameworks as
developers awesome so this is a talk I
did to to show some of the design
decisions we made and I think this is
something pretty interesting for anyone
writing JavaScript frameworks but should
be interesting for anybody else so what
kind of frameworks am I talking about so
my background is bored what we are doing
I'm working for for cooks ooh and it is
a rich gooey JavaScript framework and
we're doing a similar single piece of
page applications so what you're seeing
here is gmx com make lined which is
written totally and cook soup and we
have widgets like the toolbars the tabs
the menus like the search bar of the
tree and what I'm talking talking about
today is how we actually implement these
widgets so which it is not in the sense
of a these mobile widget w-we w3c widget
it's in the sense of your I components
so what you're basically doing is we
treating the browser as rendering engine
so native applications like java
applications windows applications use
native api's we use the browser as
rendering engine and
what we have in the browser so I was
glad Dion put up this this slide only in
his keynote yesterday it's basically we
have three primitives we have images as
single entities or as background and
images we have text with some ways to to
define the font and colors and things
like this and have rectangles things
like this is the only primitives we have
if we want to support all browsers of
course we can use canvas but then it's
hard to this is not available in IE so
this is what we need to stick to well
and then these primitives are arranged
in a tree so we have a scene graph of
all those of all those elements which is
the Dom tree and the don't worry is
pretty nice it provides us stuff like
events bubbling through the tree and
propagating through the tree and we know
exactly for example click events on
which element the cliq occurred unlike
if you have the canvas where you have
just the opaque rectangle and you it's
hard to match what is actually the
element behind the pixel you are
clicking on and then we have CSS for
styling and of course JavaScript so
javascript is pretty much the thing
which ties it all together so let me
present you in the body this is the
widget I'm trying to open right now
spinner cool
it's pretty simple the the code you see
there is cook sous demo code it's
actually working code and spinners nice
because it's not too complex still it's
something you compose out of other more
more basic widgets it's simply used as
as an input for text and this is the
widget I want to talk about today so the
first step is I said the spinner is a
composed switches let's take a look how
the spinners compose out of other
widgets ok our goal is to create widget
by composition we want to create complex
widgets by composing simple widgets and
like the spinner basically is composed
of three four widget one container one
input field and two buttons for the up
and the down what we want to do is use
known glee concepts to do this like we
want to use layout managers to say how
the witches should be arranged or we
want to use a rich set of basic widgets
to compose it from and of course we want
to have some basic things like events
and the other thing is at this level I
really don't want to hassle with the
browser I don't want to know which
browser I'm in or I use any low level
browser api's because this is code that
letter right found it much more abstract
level
let's take a little look at the source
code in cook sous so this is cook soon
saw Scott a little bit like the juice I
talked we've seen yesterday or object
model so in cook sous widgets inherit
from our widget so we define a spinner
with your hair from widget and then we
provide a constructor and all we do is
called the base call are called the
constructor of the base class so this
basically just nothing it's just a
widget so the next step is we want to
lay out of the lease up witches and for
the spinner it's basically it's a grid
and the input field should have a row
span of two and and the the spacing of
the resize behavior should be that if
you resize it horizontally only the text
field should resize if I resize it
vertically both rose so should resize
equally and that weather is what I'm
saying there I create a layout which
nope layouts are not widget I create a
layout manager it's a grid and then I
say the growth legs that is the resizing
behavior of the first and second row
here equals 1 so it's resizable and the
first column well it's a type of way
sorry it should be the column should be
0 because the first first column is
starting with 0 so the first column
should be should be flexible well and
then I want to add the widget so I want
to add the text field widgets and I pass
in the value a string and then I simply
want to add this text feed widget to the
parent which is the spinner and then I
configure some some layout properties
like the row where it should be placed
column and the Rose bear and the same is
true for for the buttons as well
additionally
i define the images for the up and down
arrow so this actually is working code
and this is something that what we had
in mind so we want to write widgets on a
very high level just like and swing our
q te or any other widget toolkit and let
me switch to firefox just to show it a
little bit so that what i have here is
the cooks to demo browser no the cooks a
playground and i can type in code on the
left and run it on the right and what
you see here this was the first step
just inherent from from widget and then
I said background color because
otherwise you can see anything then we
have the next step that's pretty
interesting I add a layout and suddenly
the which it disappears that's why the
layout manager uses the sizes of the
child witches and since I don't have any
child widgets adjust the size collapse
still and then I add the text field
again with the row column and you and
the row span i can add the the first
button and the second button and voila
this is pretty much looking like a
spinner it's not nice should some
tweaking us is needed but this is pretty
much the api we had in mind how we want
to to create complex compose switches
okay let's get big
so now that we have the composition of
of widgets the question is if we have
basic widgets like a label or and image
which are not composed how does it map
to the dome what is the dome generated
or needed for this widget so let's take
this text field and this is
approximately the HTML generated by by
the framework for this widget basically
we have our three two to three diff
elements and I will go to third to this
in a moment so first we have the
container in our case the container is
the Dom element added to the parent
widget we use absolute positioning and
we use fixed sizes why we do this a
little bit later then you have a
decorator element this is I think this
is a pretty interesting concept the
decorator element arm basically is a
container for any background decoration
so i can add an image to this i can add
our complex HTML to render the
background of the of the widget and we
have custom classes which are simply
there to to render the background of the
widget and then we have the actual
content on the content the decorator are
at the same level of the year Dom
hierarchy just a difference z-index and
the content overlays the decorator and I
can change the decorator on the fly
without changing anything else on the
widget so it doesn't influence the
layout in our stuff like this and the
content actually is the element we want
to display in this case it's the input
element
the little dots we do set some starts to
reset the input element so the input
element itself doesn't have any chrome
so small summary of the of the dome
structure we do have two to three dom
elements it's two to three because the
decorators optional if I don't want to
render any day any background there is
no need for me to have this element we
use absolute positioning and fixed sizes
that's easy because if we do fix
cézanne's absolute positioning that's
the easiest staff browsers can do so
there is no cross browser issues in
these two features so cross browser
issues are just gone and then we have
something like no explicit heading and
no borders does anybody have an idea
where this is an advantage no borders no
pettings okay the advantage is that this
is box model independent this works in
COEX mode and in standard mode exactly
the same way because in a sentence mode
if you specify the size it will add to
the size the padding and the border and
you will get something different 22
quirks mode where the size is just the
size and if we remove in our our set our
borders and padding's from the widget we
gain box model independence out of the
box second
can show you how this maps to the dome
like
ok
well doesn't look nice okay so you can
see here this is the container element
it's a div it has absolute two positions
then this is the input element this
looks weird but most of these styles are
generated by by the browser so we you
use some of these these starts to to
make sure that the input element itself
is basically invisible so it doesn't
have this border and the inside and
background color and stuff like this and
then we have this one is the decorator
and this decorator is actually a little
bit more complex because it's rendering
these slightly rounded borders and it's
using its using diff elements to do this
and leaving the edge pixels empty and
then it has a skate background image and
that's something we can do without
interfering with any of the the rest of
the widget
okay what are the pros what are the cons
of these these decisions first of all we
have box model independence we have very
flex flexible styling because we can do
almost anything we could even do a
canvas element there and draw something
weird on the background and we don't
have any cross browser issues because
it's stupid sim the negative side is
that we do have to use more dom elements
than with the basic basic approach where
the element is the widget like the input
element is the text field widget and we
do sighs computation in javascript
because we have these fixed sizes we do
have to do some loyalty and this is of
course lower than the built-in layout
engine okay next a little bit on
steaming this is only a teaser I like
this image okay we put the skin over the
scalp so just a teaser this is a very
little calculator application I've
written some time ago and these two
applications are exactly the same the
application source code is exactly the
same the only difference is that i use
different decorator renders so all I do
is I swept swap the decorators used to
render all these widgets so none of the
UI composition codes also is affected to
do this
let's get to the guys now somehow we
have to work with the Dom so there's no
no way around working with the dome when
we want to build a browser well we took
it so how how does this text via mid
widget map to this HTML so what code is
required to do this first of all this is
I think this should be familiar to all
of you so working with the Dom without
any library is not fun at all like we
have cross browser issues simple things
like setting opacity of an element is
very different in IE then in all other
browsers and there's many little things
so there are many cross browser issues
small mistake can degrade performance
enormously like in this little snippet
of code I create an element append the
element to the body and then I do a
change the style of the element and this
is slow because every change to the
style will update the layout of the
would trigger the layered engine of the
browser so don't do this the simple
change is to first create the element
set all the styles and then append it to
the document this way the Laird engine
is triggered only once and this can make
a huge difference just putting the line
a little bit further down and then
simple things like reading styles and
attributes from the Dom are depending on
the browser can be very expensive so
reading from the DOM is expensive so
what we do is we try to wrap the door so
we creep we create dumb wrappers for the
elements we use for the widget we do
lazy Dom element creation because
creating elements
so expensive and we batch dumb
operations additionally we start we
cache style and attributes so in the in
the code you see here let's focus on
this one this is how the widget the very
simplified widget could create its
element and what you see is that we
creating QX HTML element instance and
this is the wrapper and at this point no
Dom element is created just the
JavaScript instance and the Dom element
is only created when we actually add
this widget to the document and all this
is a decorator you see that it has a
unified API to set styles like if I had
this opacity here it would be normalized
and by ie the filter style would be said
and for all other browsers the opacity
style would be said the same for the
decorator and all all changes to these
elements are not applied immediately to
the Dom but they are queued and then in
in an asynchronous flush all of these
changes are pushed to the dome in one in
one batch which reduces the number of
relay on the browser has to do and
additionally the values I've said there
when I read these values they are cached
and that it doesn't hit the Dom it
actually returned the cash values so the
dumb rapper is a mixed bag so it does
provide a cross-browser API it can
increase performance in many ways as I
said inserting nodes can be can be
critical and we can since we know all
the dumb operations which are going to
happen we can order the Dom operations
in a way that are avoid these pitfalls
and it keeps the widget code clean and
working with a dom is very
very streamlined at Richard level well
obviously the drawback is that it does
cause more memory and the complexity of
doing this is of course higher basically
what we are doing is we are trading
memory to runtime performance we do use
more memory and get a little bit more
runtime performance ok so I said before
that layouts or that we use fixed sizes
for the images and absolute positioning
but the sizes must come from somewhere
and that in our case that's our layout
managers so and the layered measure has
basically two two tasks to do the first
is to render the initial layout to give
all the widgets the initial position and
sizes and for the spinner measuring
where the buttons should be and where
the input field should be placed like
this and the other task is what you do
when something resize when the browser
window resizes Owen I said with value
and the child nodes have to be resized
so that is a two tasks for for the
layout manager so basically it has to
compute widget sizes based on the
available space layout constraints like
it has to be in this cell and this
column and this row preferred widget
sizes like the label has a preferred
Richard size which is the size of the
label and widget size constraints that
is widget could have configured minimum
size or coffee configured maximum size
so all of this has to be taken into
account to compute the sizes basically
this is what the browser does as well
and the algorithm that does is basically
a two-pass algorithm we took compute we
first compute the preferred size the
preferred size of the spinner basically
is the preferred size of all of its
children and then combined with the
later information the layout manager in
this case the grid provides and once we
know the size of the of the route widget
and the available space we can then
render every widget from top to bottom
given the the known size that we have so
that's the second part pass the
following slides will be a little bit
complicated not complicated i will show
a little bit of code so let me know if
you have any questions there ok so first
person said I want to complete compute
the preferred size of the spinner simply
what I'm doing is I asked the layout
manager the spinner has a layout manager
asked the state layout manager what is
the preferred size of all of my children
given this layout well and the late
major says ok give me all the preferred
sizes of the children and then I apply
my complex or simple layout algorithm
and compute the preferred size of the
aggregate and the preferred size of the
children again the text field has the
preferred height is the text height we
can measure the height of the of the
text and I just have a fixed fixed with
because there's no intrinsic preferred
with often text field and for the button
it's even easier it's just the image
size
so once we know the preferred size of
the spinner we can then go top down from
the spinner to all of its children and
say okay I have the available space and
tells I and update the Dom elements
required for the switcher so it will
update the content element the decorator
element the container element and then
tear the layout manager to do the same
for all the children and the layout
manager does its size computation metric
iterates over all the children and then
tells called the render layout on all of
the children and the children again just
update their Dom positions and don't
sighs well that's not too easy so we do
all the reflow computation in JavaScript
the great benefit is that we can do
anything we have a large collection of
layout managers not just grid layouts of
the box layout and flow layouts and
other stuff but it has to be highly
optimized since we are doing this in
JavaScript and there are some browsers
which are not so fast in JavaScript we
have to optimize this a lot so this is
not so easy to do but if a feature is
missing we can implement it we don't
have to wait for any browser vendor to
implement a feature for us we can
basically implement any layout in
behavior we wanted that's a big win for
us so layout in summary this layering
mechanism is cross browser so it's all
JavaScript and it's the layout managers
itself have no references to any low
level code or widget code or whatsoever
we can do custom layout managers we can
do set anything can customize it we can
have default sizes for all of our
widgets but of course the drawing is
this is not native CSS layout in and you
feel the difference you feel the
difference because if I resize I can
show it so this
let's just say I edit I at this one in a
different way I say h20 that's Wow ok
ok so the resizing of the text field
doesn't doesn't work very well but it
just says 20 pixels from the border and
when I resize this one you will notice a
little leg and that's because the
JavaScript engine has to update the the
positions in Safari and chrome actually
you don't really notice this anymore but
of course that's the drawback of this
approach and implementation is not so
trivial actually I think GWT 2.0 has
implemented a layout engine purely with
CSS layout but the problem with it and
it's very snappy fury sighs but the
problem is adding features to this one
is really rocket science that's nothing
you want to do so now to the last topic
events like what can be so hard with
events let's just click and mouse down
and mouse up and key press but actually
Dom events are stinking it's not
javascript is a mess and not the dumb
SMS but Dom events are even worse so
first of all their different api's ie
has a complete different set of api's
than at any other browser that's fine if
the behavior is similar we can add
wrapper on this standard stuff but it's
not nice it's getting worse features
there are some features which are only
in IE there are some features which are
not in IE basically it's always IE and
not a one feature which is not in IE as
the event capturing face the normal
behavior for an event is to bubble from
the target
to the document body that's a bubbling
face but the w3c events also define a
capturing phase where the events starts
at the root bubbles through the target
and then bubbles back to the root that's
a capturing face that's not an ie ie has
on the other hand most capturing
completely unrelated just a similar name
and mouse capturing is if you turn on
Mouse capturing on an element all Mouse
events will be dispatched on this
element regardless where the mouse
cursor is at the given moment it's very
useful to do things like drag and drop
where the mouse cursor can leave the
direct element and the mouse event will
still be dispatched on the element and
not on the unrelated element below the
mouse cursor so both both features are
nice to have but very hard to to get
this cross browser and then even worse
they have different behavior they have
different mouse event sequences like
double click event sequence in IE is
different to double click event sequence
in Firefox where it is mousedown most up
click hasta almost up click double click
and I think IE doesn't fire two of those
don't remember exactly which one but
that can can be a problem should depend
on things like this and key code char
code are very very nasty they depend on
the browser on the operating system and
even on the locale the user has said so
that's not nice so our goal would be for
this little spinner widget to just
specify button up widget at listen I
click and then a function and this will
handle all of this in the background for
us so the native implementation is just
to add the listeners to all the elements
and then you have all these issues are
just
then that's not so now we'll tell you
that how our event implementation works
first of all we don't attach event
handlers directly to the elements we
have a generic mouse event handler and
what this mouse event handler does it
listens on the document body and all
mouse events bubble up to the body and
finally we'll arrive at the mouse event
handler then we have an event
registration the event registration
keeps a mapping of all listeners and all
elements so basically the event
registration does the same as a browser
it remembers all event listeners and of
course the most event handler has a
handle on this registration and then we
have code like this it's very low level
code where we call a net listener on the
registration this will store this
information about the element way we
want to listen the event type we want to
have and the callback function so now
it's a funny funny
okay what happens if I click on this
image obviously this is the event the
Dom event and the Dom event will well
bubble up to the root as you see it will
when it passes the element where the
listener is nothing happens because the
listener isn't attached directly to this
one then it arrives at the body and
there the mouse event handler will
listen for this event and we'll get this
event and now the event handler the
mouse event handler can do anything with
it it can wrap it into a custom event
object which normalizes all the API
calls it can even fire synthesized
events to fill up the event sequences
and all fancy stuff and when it has done
this it can just push it to the event
registration and tell the event
registration he is a mouse event this is
the event target for which can be read
from the Dom event do whatever you want
with it at this point we can handle the
dispatch of the event totally on our own
so we can now go ahead and say okay we
want to implement a capturing face so we
traverse all the Dom elements between
the target and the body and dispatch all
the handlers first or we can do mouse
capturing we can always dispatch this
event to the same element and then
finally the callback function is called
so to solve all these browser issues we
simply don't attach event listeners to
to the dome directly anymore we do this
all through to an Eric handlers there's
not only a mal Sandler there's a focus
on floor there's a keyboard handler
which does similar things yeah like
we have a standard compliance API we
have mouse capturing support we have the
capturing event capturing phase and we
have a unified behavior where it's
possible well like always we trade this
for a little bit loss in performance and
increased code size especially keyboard
handling is not the smallest class in
our framework because this only shows
how broken keyboard handling is in the
browsers okay let's come to the end sum
up we had this widget we've seen how
this complex which it can be composed
out of other simpler widgets we've seen
how simple widgets map to the Dom with
the container element the content
element and the decorator element then
I've shown a little teaser how theming
could look like why we use the dumb
rapper how we interact with the Dom
haole your team works how sizes are
computed and as last thing events how we
deal with events and in the beginning I
asked you who is framework developer
this is because this is why you want to
use a framework if you want to write a
GUI application this is stuff users
shouldn't have to bother with and that's
why they are just frameworks so thank
so now it's time to take questions are
there any questions yeah please
yes
in theory this shouldn't be a problem
and practice it still is if the browser
if the user increases the font size what
you could do is pull in the background
for font size changes and then trigger a
relay out of the of the interface in our
case it we don't do this falling yet but
what we can do we can increase the font
size and then reload and then the
measurement of the labels get the new
sizes and the interface will be will be
adopted like in this in this screen I
have increase increase the font size to
to make it more readable and the layout
mansions will get this but not yet at
one time yes
okay let me let me show you the the the
the HTML like this one if you look
closely there's no styling information
in this this is only positioning
positioning is things computed by the
layout engine and the layout engine has
to set it directly on the element so yes
you could do styling with external
classes and with CSS we have a little
different approach to styling because we
want to style widgets on the widget
level and not on the Dom element level
so we want to keep the abstraction and
we have a different approach to sort to
starting but in theory you could of
course apply styling or CSS classes to
the widgets like you can all your
buttons can have the button class then
you have some CSS which defines the
sides of the buttons what you cannot do
is externalize the size and position
information in this approach okay