just a quick content warning this talk
mentions open ography and chopra graffia
in the fifth part so anyway this is a
story of
J spin I've given one talked before
about Jay has been and how it went from
PHP to to know it was a cool story and I
was high-fiving myself fish thing this
is the b-side this is the the bad
stories and everything I share with you
today Jo spin is the longest-running
live paste bin it's it won't it's not
going anywhere and will continue to
serve its users including the scumbags
so I've broken this up into five
sections just to touch on each kind of
area that kind of focus into so denial
of service different types of spam that
i found on j spin havoc from my own
registered users the costs of running j
spin and a few incidents that were the
police yeah so just a very brief
backstory Jay's been originally was a
four-hour PHP hack it was out of my
bedroom office and it was 2008
September's he doesn't eat it was
released it was the first to suffer any
real abuse I know jsfiddle was offered
quite a bit of abuse in the last couple
of years I'm not sure if Co pen has so
much in terms of kind of you know people
websites in the same space so this is
not a particularly happy story it's left
me with a bit of a toxic taste in my
mouth for the the open source project
please bear in mind i am the solstice
admin for this project my knowledge is
limited there are no you know big load
balancer servers my pockets are not
infinitely deep with cash there's no
central machines it's just me so do I
service so this is what denial of
service looks like four J's bin and
there's there's different forms like
they're not generally trying to attack
jsb in the the users but this is what
happens when node Goes Down and engine X
is the front you get to see this page
and like so there's different types of
attacks that I've seen and one of the
one of the popular ones is the self
attack by
the the morons so script kiddies are
basically taking their there you know
copy and paste HTML and Java scripts me
put it into J's bin and the idea is you
point it to a domain like Jas comp and
you hit go and it launches like a
thousand xhr requests or a thousand
image requests and it just you know all
attacks at once the April May is being
script kiddies they've copied and pasted
I only thought about what they're doing
so they forget to type HTTP / / J's bin
je s conf put us and they type just jazz
comp us there's no validation the hit go
and it attacks HTTP Jess been calm /url
/ Jess comptia us goes through the full
subsystem of jet fjs been looking for
the bin with that name and it comes back
saying no it's not here and they just
hammer the out J has been and you
know I end up with this which is which
is cool and generally I mean I'm based
in the UK most of my my script kiddie
friends are in the US so I tend to wake
up to this so you know Twitter being a
metric for you know how queer products
is it is jasmine's down you where
there's SS problem five or four errors
just over and over again now some of
this actually comes from the Status page
they're just kind of clicking on the
link and it says tweet me if you think
it's down this is the kind of love I
getting in Twitter which kind of sucks
to wake up to this first thing in the
morning and i do have run books for this
kind of thing so i use cloud watch on
AWS to tell me when the cpu is high but
when it's happening a lot it's kind of
like the alert that you just eventually
just ignore you like yeah it's high
again and one night it got so bad that
so what I normally do is I go the run
book tells me to look the the engine
text logs and like take the last 200
lines and find me the unique IPS and
gimmick count those ip's and if there's
one there's only one it has like three
hundred quests and last couple of
seconds and a restaurant normal numbers
so I'll just IP table block that I
and one evening it was just going
bananas and I was just getting I
constantly different IP addresses
turning up in this big range of kind of
a requests so I was like this is 10pm
I've kids so that's kind of my bedtime
and so I wrote cron job that would just
repeatedly look at the logs and just
keep IP table block at blacklisting
these IP addresses and a head off the
bed kind of like this will be alright
and woke up to pretty much everyone
using Jer spin has been blocked but the
server was fine again which is good yes
I got real the cron job and yeah a lot
of people kind of got hit in the
crossfire it did calm down it on a war
caused it but eventually discovered a
fail to ban like I found this about two
years ago now I think so fail2ban
basically does the same kind of thing
but is a lit we're more intelligent
about it so it'll jail the IP address of
five minutes and stop them from
basically heading the the node server
which is good the only problem is it
then catches workshops and like when
teachers of state teaching students and
I workshop they're all coming from the
same IP address and they get hit by this
this belt ban so like people trying to
learn inside the classroom environment
get caught by this thing I've had to
create I can whitelist people but they
have to know that they've been
blacklisted in the first place
automatically I've had people send me
tweets just like Jasmine of shits down
like that get I get sense that you're
all coming from the same classroom maybe
start with is there a problem with Jay
has been rather than just saying it
and then I whitelist them and that you
know that less angry at me yeah that's
one of the the fun bit server chespin
and who doesn't love a filthy amount
spam in their products so Jay has been
what it is exactly is a website that
people can anonymously create anything
they want so yeah it's basically I was
asking for trouble alright so
Jeff spin as of say April 2015 yeah as
of April 2015 this year had well over 15
million bins and I looked at a few
minutes ago actually it's 21 million in
there now and across 10 million bins in
2014 so it took like five years or six
years to get to 10 million but I got a
15 million a year later I should have
twigged that something was up like
having gotten fifty percent more content
in the database in a year and I mean
maybe that's growth hacking but I don't
think there's yeah there's definitely
span going on so I have different types
of spam lots of different types of spam
i have like affiliate spam SEO spam i'm
just going to work a couple of them
fishing was the first kind of the real
first kind of abuse that I ever found in
Jay spin and if you actually look at the
source code for a spin in github you'll
see that the config says it's blocking
habbo com so someone had taken the login
page Harbor com put on a spin and so if
anyone remembers having a calm is like a
nice more thick game from the other node
two thousand mid-2000 something like
that and it they put the login page
there so I got an email saying someone's
fishing the logins even though like it
says chance been in url you'd think that
people would see this but apparently
they don't and the code today that
Sanjay has been it currently blacklists
habit or common and I think the process
formed what CGI a like the old thing for
capturing data and there's there's
simple blacklisting tech inside a JSP I
have a private config that's not in
github that blocks a whole lot of things
things like clickbank and random bits
and Narcy code kim kardashian spelt
wrong consistently wrong Kardashian some
of that there's a lot of spam with her
name in it so it but it's a whack-a-mole
situation like you you be blacklist one
thing and then
a tweak the spam a bit more and it just
starts appearing again the biggest kind
of spam the biggest problem actually
turn out to be linked hiding so this
would be where I want to get you to my
ass hat website so i run a skeptic calm
and i sell bad stuff and i put the links
out on social media networks like
Twitter and Facebook and you end up
going to this website like oh no it's
bad so Twitter and Facebook get savvy to
this and they block any links to ours
hat com so like okay you know what gonna
put inside a bit ly and I'm gonna put
bitly link inside of twitter com and
your bounced and hit bit be and go off
to our SATCOM but now Twitter or
following redirects so they can trace
the redirect down and see that i'm still
linking through to our SATCOM so they
take j spin and they do window dot top
location or window de location equals us
out so calm and they put j spin in
twitter and there's no like you know
header redirect so you get redirected
off to at the bad website and there are
a hundred different ways to do a
redirect in javascript it's like you
know window dot location equals top
delegation equals top square bracket loc
plus okay occasion like that I can't
black list it's just impossible short of
I don't know I don't know how to there's
no way blacklisting at all to the point
where eventually Facebook were just like
yep we blocked jasmine so I was breeding
blog post about how jet Jasmine was
being used for some react demos having
known that Jer spins completely blocked
in like those posts or coming out of
Facebook having Facebook blocking Jay
has been the same time now they've
stopped blocking Jeff spin but them yeah
basically was being abused so and and
the thing is with the redirect it it
doesn't happen when you're inside of the
chair spin window only happens when you
get rid of the editor so I had to like
limit the ability to create an anonymous
bins like what it what it does so if you
are not signed in to Jay I spin when you
look at the full output it can still do
that rewrite but it'll only do it for 90
minutes
after you your last save so when they
you know they put those links into
Twitter or Facebook eventually they
expire this that 19 minutes and it goes
inside of the chair spin editor and the
redirect doesn't work because it's in an
iframe that has a sandbox property that
doesn't allow you to a redirect but it
means now that I've limited this
anonymous functionality in the free
functionality that I offered to to users
because of people just abusing J spin
but at least I kind of solved that
problem and the anonymous users abusers
it instead so yeah riginal EJ has been
the very first version had no sign in no
concept of accounts or anything with
that it was a hundred percent anonymous
I wanted it be I try for a very long
time to keep it like that and I didn't
want user accounts I thought it was cool
that you could just kind of go up there
do a thing walk away from it it was lost
forever and that lost forever was a
problem because eventually people coming
back saying yeah I make like 30 pins on
jasmine and where are they how do I get
them back like there's no user counselor
yeah no I want the back though I want to
be able to find them again so there was
a complete refactor from PHP to nose in
that refactor version 3 or very clean
but we also added user account
registration password reminder so you
can actually get those those bins back
there's just one floor there was zero
checks on the account like I don't like
captures so I didn't put one there and I
don't like the email authentication loop
so I didn't put that there either which
means that you can literally just say my
username is a if actually we have a user
with the username space so you can have
a space for your username and your
password can be a space if you choose
just possible to his place so yeah my um
my registrations went up and unbeknownst
to me yeah my my users were going up and
I hadn't noticed basically until this
day so this is the day that everything
round two
at almost a 100 percent halt so it's
March 2015 this year I'm solo parenting
my wife my daughter being born earlier
on that year yeah she's like almost one
at this point my wife has never gone out
by herself like this is the first time
that you I like she's gone out by but
like for the day so i'm i'm babysitting
babysit I'm solar parenting for the day
for the first time since she gave birth
to a daughter so like it's a big deal to
her that I don't kind of go yeah can you
come back because Jasmine's broken see
ya that morning I woke up and people who
have sending me tweets as they do about
Jay has been there was you know
something's on something it wasn't the
fibro force but something was off it
wasn't quite working the way they wanted
it to like saving didn't seem to work
and I had a chance to have a look at it
and I mentioned the bins had gone up
they've gone up from 10 million to 15
million at quite a rate a storage is
pretty cheap right so jess pins database
is completely isolated on one ABS drive
and it's 100 gig and all it stores is
like text HTML CSS JavaScript and a bit
of metadata that hundred gig at all gone
by completely empty and I managed to
jump on the server and try and delete
some rows of data but in in writing an
SQL query to delete rows of data at
nasik like create a temporary table to
be able to work out what rose to delete
I by the time I delete rows more data
came in filling the remaining space
until I had 0 bytes left it couldn't I
couldn't run the query to delete rows
from the database like ran out of space
entirely there was zero bytes left and
the thing is it's like I'm I'm so
apparently and I feel this
responsibility to to J's bin and the
users who aren't paying me for it like
it's just a service that's there and you
just have to I just had two basic say
okay close laptop
so it's not going to fix itself but it
will have to stay broken and Jasmine was
still low like you can still bring
things up and see your data you just
couldn't save anything and I just had to
focus on my kids until my wife came home
I was like can I get just quickly grab
the computer and increase the displaced
from 100 Gig to 400 geek I did manage to
get a github issue up saying please help
describe the situation but the bottom
line is like the actual drive on a DBS
had to be changed and no one could do
that for me that no no amount debugging
would have fixed that problem so
upgraded to a 400 gig drive that's
enough space for a while right I've
another a year until this happens again
but the downside is I had to close the
like free sign in process so I had
register with your email and password or
use github and now you can only use
github to get into jf in which is
totally reasonable for you know this
kind of audience like I'm sure most of
you have a github account and it's not
problem just click the button and you're
you're in but a classroom full of
students or you know kids they won't
have a github account and I've closed
the door on them now which kind of bums
me out because it was supposed to be you
know free but making it completely
anonymous is ultimately a stupid idea
like it ends up you know getting abused
and this kind of thing happening
basically so in 2014 I was doing a lot
of traveling and going to lock
conferences and I think I was here what
year is it 2015 2013 no 2013 2013 i was
doing traveling i was here and I spoke
to other people that spelling people
during the conference and other
conferences and had a lot of people
saying how we give you money for ji spin
I was like no no no Jasmine's free I
don't money this is stupid by the way
people say you want to give you money
take money and
yeah I up to that point I've been
working on it since 2008 entirely all my
development a friend of mine Danny hope
had been doing the UX on the website
since 2009 and the more people I met
that said they wanted somehow support
the project I realized that there was an
opportunity to try and add profi like a
pro account and make it try and make it
self sustaining so the beginning of 2014
I hired to developers to work full-time
on Jo spinning clear and then added
myself to welcome Jeff in full time and
I would create the pro offering of
Jeff's been so the end of yes the end of
it launched in May 2014 or may or may
july or some middle of the year and the
income from the pro subscriptions just
about covers the operating costs of the
servers so i am not doing scrooge mcduck
nose dives into piles of cash and if
anyone doesn't know who that is go
google it you can watch some screws
McDuck but the upside is before pro
chair swing was making a hundred percent
loss now it's just not making hundreds
in Los I'm just not making any good
money from it so that's kind of good
there was also a huge cost to taking
money through a cycle VAT moss which I
can run about for ages which is why I've
taken it out of this talk but it's a
European legislation thing which i'll
happily talk to anyone about in the bar
for about an hour because it makes me
angry but there were other costs to two
chairs been like it turns out i actually
created a website for testing stolen
credit cards didn't realize but um yeah
because the pro accounts was initially
so cheap it meant that you could take a
stolen credit card and test that stolen
credit card in jay has been because the
the cost is so low dozen
set up a red flag there goes through
like yeah I've got a stolen card that
works so i can go ahead and you know use
it for more transactions yeah so Joe has
been being used as a test bed for stolen
credit cards I would be like yay new pro
user and they'll be like yeah this card
works going by TV and then eventually
the owner of the card will get like work
out what's this Jer spending on my
account I mean it should produce about
the TV but they they get in touch with a
bank and I say I didn't buy this I would
like it kind of refunded and they have
protections so the bank gets in touch
with stripe and stripes say we have a
dispute on this this account and I look
at the account I'm like oh yeah they
made like one bin yeah that looks like a
stolen here's your money back like no no
no we need money back and because you
lost the dispute you have to pay 15
pound 34 so for the refund for a stolen
to test the stolen card success and be
successful it cost me 21 pounds so like
twenty eight dollars twenty thirty
dollars something dollars but like money
it costing me money for people to test
their credit cards and successes like
succeed stolen solid credit card so
there's there's that's not a business
but it's like a negative business there
right and Stripes pretty good at
catching some of the stuff but still
there are some stolen cars to get
through basically and there's no there's
no avoiding it so i have a new process
which is every single pro user that
comes through and it's it's not a lot
like there's one every day or every
other day and I go in and I look at
their account and if they have some bit
like some bins with like react
surrounded or whatever they choose to do
I'm like okay that seems legit and I got
one recently I think that part they use
name was like anti security and there
was one bin which was just it was
obviously i think was like a script
kiddie style thing and looks at the
credit card the credit card was from
russia but they were based in america so
like you know what I'm just going to
refund you and Mark that's possibly
fraudulent and I did
get fined so ya caught 11 stolen credit
card he gave me yeah so when I was
meeting these people saying like we want
to give you money like do you have a pro
thing or a donation thing or anything
like that I ran some numbers on the
database looks at the registered users i
factored in like twenty percent Idol
spam users having not thought about like
you know when they're going to come an
attack and just start registering
bye-bye bananas going nuts and
restorations but I figured I aim for one
percent conversion rate if I get 1% user
used to go pro then this would make the
project sustain sustaining
self-sustaining enough that I could put
at least a full-time developer honor and
I could then kind of get income from
client work at the same time that's all
I did though there was no business plan
beyond that there was no development
plan there was no marketing plan there
were no deadlines there were no Eames
really beyond that I just had kind of
looks and when what could we offer for
pro a couple of private things and there
wasn't there wasn't a great deal more I
mean we looked at teams briefly and we
kind of end up going down the wrong path
and ditched a month's worth of work and
kind of backed up to just try and go for
simple and get something that's launched
and it got to the point where I was
chasing the end of the rainbow like I
was trying to get that last like five
percent done and like all this work was
done I was ready for pro but I just
wanted a polished off the last little
bits of work and it took like well over
a month just to get to that point where
I was happy to kind of turn on and say
yes we can start taking money and it
seemed to drag on and all the time that
I'm like investing full time in Jay spin
and I'm putting my own money into paying
that my developers well it meant that my
company wasn't making any money from
consultancy so it's basically just money
out and no money in so eventually
jasmine went pro at july twenty third we
had 42 upgrades in the first
week 26 from the first day like I said I
was hardly doing kind of nosedive into
cash I was very pleased but those
numbers are actually reasonably low so
the bottom line is I needed that there
was no plan asshole if I'd had some kind
of business development plan I think
things would have gone differently I
mean Jasmine gets a decent amount of
traffic there's still something that's
monetizable there I just don't know what
it is and once it gone live as soon as I
would think about new features or
significant changes the Jay has been had
to be justified I I couldn't do that
work without if it couldn't justify the
cost of the work on Jeff's been then I
couldn't do it because did it get me
more like paying users did it just add
cost to the server ID it it kind of left
me feeling like I had to IIE I didn't
like kind of being tied to has been this
way it wasn't fun anymore basically and
one of the other biggest problems I had
was that Jasmine gave everything away
for free start off with like we had when
copan launched we had four of their six
Pro features as free and open-source
features in Jay has been like like live
reload and co casting all this office is
free it still is free but I pay for my
github account because they need private
repos I pay for my google account
because I needed the space I pay for
dropbox because I needed the space as
soon as I put the word need in the
sentence I realized that I'm willing to
hand over money and with Jay has been I
couldn't even say I needed anything that
was offered by the Pro features so if I
can't get to the point where I need
something in Jay has been I found it
hard to see why people just start
throwing money at me you know so as much
as giving everything away for free is
honorable it doesn't pay the mortgage at
all which kind of sucked so
geben suck some of the life at me the
bat moss actually the thing I didn't
talk about is it's probably the the one
thing that made me consider quitting
entirely the police interactions I've
have been a mix of emotions and over the
years I've had could have a decent share
of cease and desist emails either kind
of stolen content put on Jo spin or
actually has someone recently saying
someone posted up all their personal
details on ji spin which you know I take
down immediately it's something someone
tells me something's breaking the law or
even like that kind of stuff that is I
don't know anyway I take it down so that
isn't my phone by the way hello one
pointing up but so early 2010 I've been
doing a lot client work and it was in
the evening like seven or eight pm the
phone rings and Julie my wife took the
call and she comes fine Mitch named find
me I think I might been on the throne
she's like you need to take this it's
the police it's like okay why the police
phoning me like on my phone rather than
I know how people communicate replace
any way yeah so the police officer I
spoke to he was like so people are using
J's bin to coordinate attack on I think
was a bank and they have they using Jay
has been there planning to attack like a
denial-of-service this Bank in a couple
of days and because his English she was
like could you possibly maybe if you
could possibly take those bins down if
it was possible because I'm ENGLISH I
was like I'm sorry yep I can but he
understood what Jay has been was he
worth he didn't say like take the whole
thing down he'd actually taken the time
to look at what Jay has been worsened
and he could see that I should be able
to possibly take down those those bins
which I did immediately like it was it
was totally cool I didn't hear from him
again
but it kind of bummed me out that these
these people are using Jo spin is the
place to share the the webpage I could
just email each other a web page and
attack a bank see ya that's true right
so this is the worst email I ever
received I got an email from the Spanish
police as a sort of cease and desist it
included two links to Jay has been
asking for immediate takedown and I'd
had issues in the past where monographie
even put on Jay has been made I tried to
block it with the blacklist and so on
but the email from the Spanish police
didn't tell me what was behind the links
and I have to check them before actually
just delete them so I clicks on one of
the links starts loading and very
quickly I realized actually what I was
about to see was child nog raphy I
didn't I mean I didn't get to see what
I'd never want to see and obviously you
know it's terrible for the people
involved it it was yeah it's harrowing
it's really horrible I close the browser
fast enough and what I did was curl the
URLs down and look for commonalities
between those two between the two
sources and found a website where we
could see the website the images being
hosted on and just immediately deleted
everything in the database put in the
black list destroyed everything in a
database that was had that n and
actually from doing the research for
this I deleted all the emails to do with
this and I just did not want to ever
think about it again it was I thought
the worst because I'm building this
thing for to help people and eventually
like the the worst thing turns up on
this website that you give crafted and
yeah absolutely worst so enlighten note
terrorism this was a bin that was an
issue that was raised on j/s bin j spin
is being used for terrorism okay cool
I've made my way into all the way up to
that
and it was being used Jasmine was being
used to attack the Madison Police
website apparently organized by these
guys and I took down a bin straightaway
as requested I then did find the
original source of the tweet that had
the been in it and it was 10 days before
the issue is raised so whatever happened
at being done and dusted I did put out
tweet saying that jasmine is open source
so if anonymous want to actually clone
their own copy they should go ahead save
me from being you know the single point
of failure for some of those attacks see
ya that was that was fun and I've tried
to kind of end each section with like
this is how I would make it better I'm
from with this is that like I don't know
I don't have a parting advice for how to
like deal with the absolute worst
that kind of comes down obviously Jay
has been is open for all its that
includes kids wanting to learn but also
includes people wanting to absolutely
destroy things on the web as well but in
going through all of this I was worried
that I'd have this really bitter tale
sure it's not kind of a happy kind of
like who at the end but in kind of like
writing out this talk and I end up
putting a like a 6000 block 6,000 word
blog post together end up being a really
cathartic process I got a lot of the
poison out my blood I felt like I kind
of cleaned out and got it off my chest
and shared some of the stories and since
kind of getting this all down on paper
as it were I've since gone back to ji
spin and added new features added HPS to
giving away for free for everyone added
another pro use or a pro user feature
looking at things like service workers
on jspn and and trying to kind of find
that love again in the project and it's
not my fault I'm focus anymore it's gone
back to side project it's not going
anywhere but I'm starting to find the
love again I have a bunch sick is over
there if people want them I don't want
to go back to the UK with them please
and I'm done