hi
yeah so I'm here today to talk about
something that happened to me I arrived
within five months ago were for sample
and I mean while I was attended a
conference called Berlin music hack day
which the purpose of it is to hack on
audio on the web or not but my purpose
was to actually find what could be done
the boundaries of what can be done on
the web in what's related to audio so
Berlin music egg they happened I think
three months ago and I just sent my
purpose to do some crazy as long as
it was related to audio so that was my
goal what did I do well I did an idea
about sorry I'm a bit too fast for my
slides but I came ketchup so what I
wanted it was this is what we have
currently on the web we have pretty
recently html5 audio and by the way
still a bit buggy on many browsers and i
wondered so we have all these audio
capability all these graphics
capabilities on the web which is like
canvas css3 and WebGL and the SVG
and low whatsoever what's why is the
audio even on personal computers we have
such advanced graphic cards and we have
16 beach 16 beats audio card on most of
them it's it's like it's treated like do
back it it's I don't know why well
I want this you know I want to be able
to have this from the web browser and
it's too far French maybe I don't know
but why not so we have WebGL on the
browser now who could have a manager
imagine that
so you know this this is who knows this
whoever use this put your hand in there
one person man okay so this is adult
life it's it's a digital audio
workstation pretty good one and and yeah
and so I wanted to knock or so I'm not
going to do this in 12 hours that was
the time of the competition and music
out there but I wanted to do something
that resembled some advanced audio I
said to to search what was available on
the web what could we do more than just
play pause seek that's boring I
discovered some blog posts and some
things one of those was that we can
actually like Romani played audio data
in this case we're off and put him as a
data URI on on the other tag so you can
actually do all the synthesis in this
way he just if you know to some DSP
digital signal processing you can do
that pretty easily but it's not
versatile it's not flexible you can't go
much further this was one of the things
that I found that I could use to do this
I don't know what projects i just wanted
to build something cool next thing i
found was the mozilla audio data API
which is still a work in progress but
like the lead the the staff that had to
give to actually do something to have
feedback the distance between starting
to guard and having that feeling oh this
is cool you know like the feedback loop
is was too big it has it expects that we
developers not like DSP programmers
implement everything on top of
JavaScript API so
after that I had something very no flesh
so I flesh without an option for me as
that's not a standard way of doing
things for me it's just avoid it
completely I don't know about you but I
think you're just gonna fight it I hope
you do so I found lost sorry
there's water to ring the wrong I found
a Google Web Audio API so this was like
instantly kind of the solution I thought
it was good for my problem and it
basically provides a way for you to
manipulate audio on a web browser with a
very well-defined API and the main
advantage of this epi over the Mozilla
one as I view it I'm not just advocating
by advocate just it solve my problems
quickly quicker it was that the common
things that you want to do with audio it
already implements it it already has api
methods written in c++ really fast for
you to do common things so the feedback
loop that i was talking about was
reduced to this size really small but i
forgot to tell it is it still has the
option to actually implement your own
DSP algorithms on top of it so it has
all the advantages i really didn't need
it and i don't want to get knee deep on
that but that's that's what I went for
so that was it it was love at first
sight uh yeah it was really love at
first sight I got really amazed we did
and I for around 15 minutes I tried to
understand it as a whole but there was
some problems it is experimental you
know and as you know an experimental API
which is still not a standard it's a
mess to understand and there's a dog
there is nothing well yeah that's the
hacking started ah and we're talking to
fuss so opinions please yes yeah okay
it's cool thank you sir okay ah well I
tried yeah when I got angry I got
frustrated because i was on a rush right
I was only kind of programming contests
I wanted to do something quick and fast
I didn't want to do something well it's
like the difference between engineering
and hacking so like we have Felix
somewhere that you gave a talk on
rejections but that like when you don't
have time you have to hack you don't
have to engineer and I got really angry
because it was so undocumented it was so
buggy it was really unstable in some
points and it was not it was difficult
to understand if you want to just to
jump in just something uh well I was
really really really almost quitting I
was hangry yeah but what I did was
thinking about what I was doing and I
had set his purpose of doing some crazy
or anything so I just okay I'm gonna
read this back for the fact i never read
the whole spec in my life at that point
it was kind of daunting to do it but I
did it it was damn it was really hard I
read the spec and it was really huge and
uh and complex and it was more than I
needed and
but in the end guess what it was good
for me I had a reference point of
behavior I knew that when something went
wrong and it shouldn't I had that
reference that's what specs are for
right sometimes browser vendors don't
read them all right ah so I started
hacking again after reading this Bank I
more successfully this time got really
productive I got really building and
trying ideas and what could be done so
after 12 hours of non-stop coding 12 red
bulls one night pain when back pain and
like infinite size of frustration yeah I
got some feeling of satisfaction and
well I built this yeah it's called
outage at it and it was born he matured
the version that I'm showing you today
it's a bit more polished I was
committing until like some 15 minutes
ago but i'm going to show you what I
built what I this API in 12 hours of
hiking I could be this so as adults I
where I also for some calls so probably
every hack that I do it includes the API
arica these loads sounds from SoundCloud
that's the waveform and you can crop
parts of the waveform into a new sound
and upload it directly to SoundCloud
without any fuss just native API so I'm
going to demo that I hope we are sound
but let's see you
okay I'm gonna play a bit of the first
part for you to the central solides
seafood Omar think you understood that
why I talks a good signal on Star Wars
and research it the news more small
thing this is a result of course it's
not a music creation it's just sound are
not attending to the creativity part but
this is showing off what you can do with
Monica thank you
David last but not least I wanted to go
further I want it to be able to upload
these results to save it so I set up
that extra mile to actually put it out
to SoundCloud that involves sex I xhr to
and generating your wave file with blobs
which was kind of a pain yeah for
someone that never messed some so low
level it was a pain but at some point I
got it right yeah I'm gonna do it got a
bloated sound out first gotta connect my
count it's connected uploading should be
there now let's check it out on my count
it is
it's the same unfun
so after let me go back to my slides so
after this experience I really enjoyed
it and I wanted to contribute to it I
wanted to actually tell you everyone
that we can do more with audio in the
web so I was in contacts for since since
then to do with the creator of the Web
Audio API Chris Rogers from google the
very very open to communication guy in
very nice and he's working like crazy on
it to make it really really good for us
use it so that thing that I was telling
the frustration from starting out from
no dogs from everything it's actually
much lower now DVI is much better it's a
more stable it's enabled by default in
google chrome now and i think you should
actually try to alright so wrapping up
is this how do you on the web is no
longer ghetto it was until very recently
people don't just don't care about it
it's all about the visuals and graphics
which are really good but we have more
senses than vision and once this is in
place we have endless possibilities to
do a lot of things so for example from
the single guys that were here before
with this api you could actually
implement something which is 3d space
Alicia are this worthless if you three
displacement sound so we
on sun on games you can actually
localize what this sound comes from and
objects in these each other's prepared
for that and it should be standardized
it should be cross browser so that we
don't we don't want more API wars we
just want something that we can use its
radiance fast and it's available and
there is some kind of a rumor I heard
that this API really really soon he's
going to be may be available on Safari
and on mobile safari these rumor i read
in peterborough new blog so let's hope
that that happens because if that
happens it leaves Mozilla to actually
implement it as well and we have all
this power everywhere so but still have
order yeah as you know the we don't have
access two microphones and then camera
as right now from a web browser that's
the web RTC API which is being developed
and that's not us guys imagine that you
have a microphone we have a stream of
audio and you can no longer just
manipulate the images you can manipulate
sound live on any device if this inner
if this guy gets analized sorry this
went into
all right the one message that I want
you to take from this talk is that stop
thinking only in one sense of your body
we have more and need the web make it
loud make it creative on the outer side
just unleash your creative potential not
only on what we already know but go out
there heck around just do it as you've
been doing until now but applied to
other senses the mat the web has been
too silent until now George Lucas I
think it would be really really happy
with this okay this is it I don't know
if I went too fast or too slow but i
want to thank to music and I'm willing
they certainly in this path of actually
appreciating that we can meet the web
and Chris Rogers create a web addict guy
not just by creating it but by being
really really open to communication so
every problem that I had I could discuss
with him with a very different time zone
which is difficult but can handle it to
chance come to let me tell you my
concerns about what's happening on this
field and to every one of you to hear me
thank you
yeah questions silver value yeah just
one thing so yeah this is available
these are URLs this talk the audio chat
it up the source about me you can access
it if you want yeah questions anyone
Joanna all right okay then I told really
clearly thank you very much sky no
there's a guy yeah wait wait wait my
girlfriend's coming so high I like a
comment so you had very good ideas how
to evolve this this API so idea I'll to
be bold you said you had very good ideas
but I think you should you know
standardization community is really open
so there are open mailing list as w3c so
so you should really you know push your
ideas true w3c to actually make a
standard yes so yeah the standardization
communities open to all the developers
out there so I mean we're all the same
yes exactly yeah let me let me tell you
my this water so standardization on I'm
just going to talk about salvation of
this topic I think it should go rly
through a very simple way which you guys
should try what best suits you it
shouldn't just like listen to me and
saying this is the best one I'm agnostic
every time i see i know i've enjoyed it
seems to try selling something but this
solves my problem in
in really short time this was a solution
to my bro it maybe not for yours but it
maybe not for yours but what I want you
to do that that's what i said it's you
should go out there should hack you
should try out experimental API as it
should move the web ford push the
boundaries try and documented things try
out what's really brand new and
contribute to its development because
this is still being developed so if you
have an opinion on it you can actually
change the course of it so yeah that's
my opinion on this oh man yes oh man
dude that okay thank you another
question there's a question here
do you do you intend to have a tool for
mixing on some clouds too well dis dis
that I sure did this was a hack no it's
was built just to impress people to that
was a part of it but this is independent
from soundcloud i may develop this
further but just for the fun of it it's
not going to be a product in the anytime
soon yeah does that answer a question
what's your favorite song okay don't ask
me I'm a techno DJ I don't have a
threesome the other fun tonight then