technical problems all right excellent
why are you guys here let's go a little
meta for a moment here why are you here
in this room with me now cats cats are
pretty pretty pretty good answer you
might also say that you're here because
you want to learn more about node and
that's a pretty great answer I'm going
to persuade you I hope that that's not
the only answer you can have to that
question it's not everything you could
be getting from node comp or Jas vests
in general and to tell you why I'm here
I'm here because I get something here
that I can't get anywhere else cats I
can get cats anywhere I got to confess
this to you i have i have cats at home
there are cat slides on every single
slide deck in the universe right I get
to tell you a story about me in the node
community and why I get something here
that I don't get anywhere else I'm going
to start by telling you who I am why
does Michael think I'm a node badass I
don't know why he thinks I'm a noted
badass I look like I do DevOps a 10pm
every time you install a package or
publish a package your work goes through
my code I have the responsibility of
keeping that flowing I am plugged in
very deeply to the heart of the node
community but it wasn't always like that
for me I have not been plugged into the
heart of known community for very long
we had to tell you about what my life
was like before I was a part of this
community when I was a solo cat I've
been writing software professionally for
a long time possibly longer than some of
you in this audience have been alive
literally I first got paid for it in
1996 but I've been writing code for a
lot longer than that at the time that I
got started my community of practice
the the phrase that Carter used earlier
is was myself and my coworkers I learned
how to program more or less on my own
and for my coworkers I did not
participate in any communities at all I
didn't go to events like this if events
like this existed I didn't know about
them and that was that was pretty good
actually I have had a great career I've
worked on a lot of great things I've had
a lot of fun I found node completely on
my own I was as a friend shot said i was
i was interested in the async nature of
things i found node around 04 i taught
myself how to program node using the
code examples in the node node source
and from the code examples with express
i did not seek out anybody's help
learning knowed I was may be aware that
there was a community of people using
node but it didn't occur to me that you
all or somebody I should or could talk
to to get anything from I did this all
on my own
and then I did a really really scary
thing I published a package on NPM this
is the first time in my life that I had
ever participated and what I would call
a programming community and this is the
safest of all possible ways to
participate in a programming community
to it's it's it's almost completely
anonymous right no one knows to know who
you are you use a handle but you know
that's divorced from everything else
like CG bot do you know who siege bot is
you probably don't know who sees bot is
my my my icon on github is of a rocket
launch at Cape Canaveral that's you
don't know that that's a woman or not
like it's just so putting that toe in
the water ever so gently right but I was
still terrified it was this was you guys
probably published packages on NPM all
the time and don't even think about it
that's that's actually a triumph I was
scared about this there were maybe a few
thousand packages on NPM what if
somebody noticed mine what if I had bugs
what if i was using node wrong it just
is a spoiler my first package had bugs I
almost I pitched I published a patch
release like half an hour after
publishing it because I found a bug he
was very embarrassing I probably was
using node wrong because I'd always
known for who knew what was going on but
I was scared that people would yell at
me or laugh at me which is a thing that
happens right I've seen people's code
get eviscerated on Twitter right people
have github repos other people mock them
why would you do that I was really
nervous about that in fact nothing bad
happened nobody commented on my bug
nobody made fun of me for publishing a
package on NPM I did it again
but this is the thing that happens when
you participate in community even in a
simple tiny way like publishing a
package on NPM you make yourself
vulnerable I made myself vulnerable by
putting a little bit of myself out into
public in the form of a little bit of
code and any participation in a
community requires this it's a side
effect it's what happens when you do it
you're all here sitting here in front of
me I can I could look at you I see you I
can make fun of primes t-shirt if I felt
like it he's made himself vulnerable
just by being the same room as me so
participation entails risk humans are
spiky and dangerous sometimes except
that a lot of the time they're not as I
discovered with this community with you
guys this community welcome to me that
was actually it for me for a long time I
got going on NPM I got going with node i
did a bunch of stuff i published the
modules I got a node job I met some
people and then I went to node
conference this was a big mode move for
me I'd never done this before I was like
well I'm not sure what I'm going to get
out of this but it seems really exciting
and I've seen these peoples names on
modules that i use and I'm kind of kind
of really excited to maybe meet some of
them even though that was really scary
this is not my first conference I went
to sig chi and 99 that was giant I hated
it was miserable I didn't try to repeat
that experience so I went to node cough
I knew one person there my coworker kit
that was it I did a lot of sitting on my
own at lunch and meals because I didn't
know anybody right meanwhile this
community is happening all around me
does it sound sort of depressing but
like I I didn't know anybody and i sat
on my own at lunch it wasn't
no cough 2013 was amazing for me it
changed everything for me it was though
I got to sit in the very first node
school experience the stream adventure
which was fantastic and then something
really wild happened I met people Bryce
you're in here right yeah there you are
you and I we met each other at node cop
2013 and we both didn't know anybody
right and now we know people it's
amazing I talked to rod bag because he
had noticed that I had published modules
on NPM that used level up and he wanted
you is really excited about that and he
wanted to talk to me about level up I
said oh whoa that was that was wild i
just talked to rod bag I wrote this
level up thing this is so awesome and
then another thing happened I'm still on
node comp 2013 here I there was this
another session that was live coding
with Dominic thar mr. got to your gassed
and isn't here and rhinos they they did
this live coded distributed chat service
thing and my mind just went kaboom I
went home I wrote three modules on NPM
using scuttlebutt and consistent
replicated documents and they're
completely frivolous modules no one
should use them for anything but I was
so excited about that I it was it was
this just massive inspiration thing I
went home excited about node excited
about programming excited about
everything around me I want you guys to
go hope you're that excited about monkey
patching or about building wearable
clothing or about that guy named check
Dominic tar a little bit more so said
that he's not here because because he's
he's somebody he doesn't know he's the
star of this little story but he's my
mad science at conferences inspiration
he I see him only at conferences boring
bars surrounding conferences every time
I see him I talked to him about
something that completely blows my mind
we talked about encrypted Merkel trees
was stuck with cryptographic hashes that
you can trust so you can have secure
distributed databases he asked me to do
some things about like making content on
NPM addressable via its hash so that he
can always get at stuff and this is like
the coolest thing ever i would never
think about cryptographically signing
merkel trees unless Dominic tar was
there to tell me all about it and it
doesn't need to know that he inspires me
this way all he has to do is be himself
and talk guess what you're mad slides
inspiration might be in this room right
now it might be well Dominic isn't here
so he can't be your inspiration right
now the sub stack might be our node
botanist might be um max I'm a fan Tosh
blew my mind earlier today with that I
am going to go home this weekend I'm
going to write I'm going to have the
equivalent of like this explosion of
modules because i'm going to use that
for something i'm going to figure out
what that is good for i'm going to play
with it all weekend i am so excited
right now here's another flip side you
yes you might be somebody's mad science
inspiration Cassandra you're mad sizes
for inspiration guaranteed all right
touchy feely right here's another wacky
thing that happened at node comp 2013
because i'm still in how one stupid
conference changed my life right now
okay I met Rick waldron he did it the
the node BOTS session at node call 2013
and you know he threw me a leap motion
controller before that these things have
been released and I made my little crazy
fly copter go up and down and land and
crash into people and responses elite
motion commands and then he did this
this really nasty nasty thing to me he
volunteered me to give a talk at
cascadia j/s and somehow talked me into
giving an intro to robotics talk at
cascadia Jas and this was literally the
first time I had ever gotten it in front
of a room of people had talked about
something he met me at a conference I
decided I could do that and I did it and
it was amazingly fun and I'm standing
here now in front of you I think because
of that experience that random encounter
with someone at a conference who I'd
never met before I'm pretty sure that
that this amazing job at mpm that I have
is the culmination of this experience of
conference going it's I'm now working on
the thing that got me involved in
community in the first place that first
package that I published that was me
putting my toe in the water I'm now all
the way in it and it is fantastic
so okay I'm talking about me and all
this stuff that happens to me am i
special no I'm just a human being I took
the first step though I went and I made
contact with other human beings I went
to that conference and I shook Bryce's
hand and I talked to rod bag and I said
yes to Rick Waldron when he wanted to
give me a leap motion controller this is
I think should be no surprise to anybody
we are social animals we thrive on
connecting with other people and we
especially thrive on meet each other
face to face we the human contact is how
we we get to know each other and we meet
each other Rick thought I could give a
talk because he'd actually met me and
see me talk and see me code so the way
the world works is not a secret I love
to say this humans are social animals we
we do a better job connecting with
people we've met at least once and
that's what's happening right now here
in this room social connections or how
our industry works it's how our lives
work admit it live with it it's another
amazing thing that happens serendipity I
did not know what I woke up this morning
when I got on bart that I would be
excited about debt I had no flipping
clue if I max didn't know he was going
to be talking about that this is this is
this is the awesome thing that happens
at these conferences that can't happen
anywhere else I am going to have our
chance encounter with someone of you
after this talk is over and you're going
to tell me about something exciting that
I didn't know existed then I couldn't
have predicted existed surprising things
come from new experiences we learn
better when we're having new experiences
we're more creative when we're having
new experiences you're stuck in a rut Go
Travel somewhere you haven't been before
go travel to a conference meet someone
you haven't met before
add newness to your life in some way
being here at this conference makes that
happen almost automatically if you
introduce yourself to someone you
haven't met before you are bringing new
things into your mind that you hadn't
thought about our experience before and
that is going to teach you something
completely new okay cats and love cats I
was not noticed that there's just sort
of a thread through all this I haven't
actually been a passive consumer of this
community experience I took risks every
single one of the opportunities I've had
or the experiences I had at no cough
2013 paid off for me because I met him I
met them halfway I had to be a stranger
I had to have a conversation with rod
I'd had to take that risk and publish
that first module I had to make myself
vulnerable and put myself out in a way
that you know maybe for some of you it's
easy your extra verts but I'm kind of
not I like to sit in a corner and write
code all of this experience has been me
pushing myself into some place where I'd
never bed before here I stand in front
of you telling you about this story
about me I don't know whether you're
going to judge me for it or whether
you're interested before whether you're
falling asleep or not but this this also
is a moment of vulnerability that I hope
is going to pay off because I hope to to
get you guys excited about participating
in this community there's is one more
thing I want to talk about about
community participation I want to talk
about responsibility
every one of the opportunities that I
took advantage of comes with the flip
side and that flip side is a
responsibility that I took on what I
decided to take advantage of do
something exciting here's an easy
example working at mpm right I'm at the
heart of the community that is actually
an enormous responsibility I hold the
heart of the node community in my hands
I can bring you all down I can make it
not work and which is not something I
ever want to do but that it's like my
daily job is is important and it's it's
a burden and it's it's something I take
on and to give back to all of you all
right that's like big and like
mechanical but it's actually at a
smaller level 2 when I stand up here and
i gave a talk to you I have a
responsibility to do it well to tell you
something that you didn't already know
before to inspire you to give you
something you didn't have I don't want
to just stand up here like a look at me
and I awesome no this is a
responsibility that I feel towards you
because I'm participating in the
community and there's let's let's make
it even smaller than that being kind and
welcoming to other people your behavior
here affects other people you can make
the difference between a newcomer like
me havin a miserable experience and
continuing to eat meals by myself and
not meeting people having an amazing
experience a life-changing experience a
friend building experience I had an
amazing node cough because the people
around me take that responsibility
seriously they were kind and welcoming
to me and that was fantastic
all of you are part of the node
community just by being here your
president at a tiny conference right
you're already like risk-taking in a
really big way that responsibility is
already yours okay how many of you in
this room know me like like get a hug
for me what do you mean okay that's
that's not enough the rest of you can
know me too and if you don't know me if
you--if like I don't look interesting
there's somebody else in this room you
could be who's pretty interesting you
could this is a tiny conference we could
end up knowing each other every single
one of these people every single one of
you guys could know me and know each
other at the end of this conference I
bet we could do it if you felt like it
but the very least I want you to
encourage somebody be somebody's
inspiration be kind in your github
conversations answer questions in a
friendly way share your code on github
or in 9 p.m. if you can mentor a node
school you want it that's actually not
very hard to do you don't have to run a
note school just be mentor at a note
school it's easy and it's awesome
watching newbies get going with node is
really fun it reminds you of what your
new node experience was the first time
if you want to like move to advanced
levels run a node school talk at a
conference let yourself be encouraged if
you saw a talk today they got you really
stoked roll with it be stoked write code
do something with that monkey patch
something ridiculous I want every one of
us to go home and watch you pack Bucky
patch something horrible that would be
awesome take the risks when somebody
offers you an opportunity here take it
maybe not every opportunity but I want
you to be a little bit daring do it this
is how our community is built this is
like where it comes from this is like
all of it right there encouraging other
people at being encouraged yourself it's
why we're here it's why I'm here I'm
here because of that moment when Max was
talking about that and I said oh my god
that's
fantastic it's going to be okay this
community is awesome I think there's a
reason i picked this community rather
than any other two to do my little
daring stepping out from my cubicle farm
i have had nothing but fantastic
experiences the fact that i'm standing
in front of you at all right now is an
existence proof there's nothing special
about me all of this can happen to you
to take the shot take the chance i want
to see you up here next year thanks CJ