my name is John han this is brian
cavalier everybody I you I architect at
a small startup called life image and
I'm a web architect at a consulting firm
in Pittsburgh hovercraft studios and
we're kind of partners in crime trying
to cause trouble in the JavaScript
community and in general so this this
talk is to further that cause actually
so slick get a quick survey how many
people are using javascript modules
today awesome how many of those people
are using them client-side or is that
excellent all right how many people are
familiar with common jas how many people
are familiar with common just come and
jas AMD you are you using it today no
all right okay so we might have a little
bit of time to talk about AMD and a
little bit more detail because that's
kind of integral to this talk so anyways
so anyways this is um this talk is going
to be about modules and why it's my
personal mission and my belief and I
can't speak for Brian because I'm going
to be injecting a lot of my opinion here
I kind of drag Brian along with me
because we work together about why
modules to me are much cooler than
frameworks so so at least Michael appear
to refute everything John says yeah
exactly so okay so first of all was a
module we just saw some modules with Yui
there's actually some other talks about
modules by a strict definition from
Wikipedia modules are you know single
purposed there this compact unit of code
and there you know pretty much self
contained you can take that and move it
around from one project to another and
very importantly and this seems to get
lost a lot they're interchangeable
like we saw in the previous talk the the
most one of the most exciting things
with modules today is the the way that
they can help speed up your application
and we just saw a perfect example of
that with the ue loader but but I'm
going to be talking about the exact
opposite that's that's a huge benefit
with modules but we're not going to
totally ignore that right now and talk
about the coding benefits so just a
comparison what's a web framework and I
tried to grab this off of Wikipedia as
well but it's kind of fragmented all
over the place conversely to a module
which is this compact unit a web
framework is is more multi-purpose and
it tries to commoditize services so that
you know coding is easy and in one of
the ways it does that with is with an
API abstraction and I caught in a set of
built-in best practices say here here's
how you you you build a application with
our framework so so like if anybody uses
dojo dojos a great example of a
framework or Yui yeah where you they
have you know most everything you would
need built-in right so yep one of the
biggest peeves with it is though is
everything's Global's with frameworks
today so so this is wed libraries jquery
is an example what is what is the web
library it's kind of a you know small
and a framework still it's it's as
globally available set of tools for you
to use helps you get done you know
it's bigger than a module but not quite
as big as a framework then we have these
micro libraries these micro frameworks
and and you know it all gets kind of
kind of confusing you know when do I
pick one one do i pick another and it
all comes down to the same thing to me
is just how much of you know how much
functionality do you get and how much
are you you know you know kind of forced
into this this framework so which which
which is my biggest pet peeve here is
that you know going with a framework or
a library kind of locks you in because
you're coding to that library or
framework now and if you've wanted to
switch the
witching cost is is extremely high
because you've coded basically around
this framework and the code infiltration
is is extremely high so not just not
just how the modules work but just even
the names if you're using something like
dojo you do have dojo dot throughout all
of your code so if you wanted to change
any of that you know you have that name
litter through your code so you would
have to you have to refactor all of that
code to same same with you or any other
large framework their name spaces are
throughout your code right so to me this
is kind of like coding dysentery you
know it's just you know I I just want to
say get your out of my code you
know but but you know I saying that I
really do like the frameworks it's just
it's just when a client or or my company
says okay so why did you pick that
framework you know it sucks at this you
know and you know I'd like to be able to
say oh don't worry we're going to switch
that out for you it's harder than it
should be so and and then on top of that
you know you get the problem with the
fact that you know you want a code to
standards you know but you can't because
you're stuck supporting these sucky old
browsers so so here's an example of you
know some coding dysentery and i'm going
to pick on dojo because dojo is actually
my my number one library that I pick so
so of examples here you know I got dojo
sprinkled all throughout my code all
right and then and then to make it worse
I've got these non-standard calls to you
know basically this is this is a wrapper
around prevent default and stop
propagation right so if I were to if I
were to do some awesome new event based
library out there that that does event
handling way better than though Joe then
I know what you thinking so but if they
way maybe there is but I can't just swap
it in for dojo and expect
to work because my code is infiltrated
with all these calls to proprietary
differently on proprietary frameworks
and again I'm not picking on dojo here
because this is the same with every
library or framework that I've worked
with so far um and if anybody has any
questions or I've been going too fast I
like to be interrupted actually because
sometimes you remind me of something
that I'm forgetting about so if you have
an intelligent question to ask please
please ask it at any time all right yes
I said intelligent yes so what is what
is the Utopia you know what is at least
to me what is what is the coding utopia
I'll have in my my toolkit of dozens of
stand-alone single purpose modules all
right something I can take it I can grab
this the best of breed here grab this
best of breed here and and and and
assemble an application together again
as we saw with modules they give you the
opportunity to have small fast code they
load you know really quick I like to I
like to be in charge of my code you know
so my code is is my code and and and
then again no Global's at all you know I
don't need to tell you guys about why
Global's shouldn't be in your code but I
and share their name spaced and there's
all these no conflict type mechanisms so
that the frameworks don't don't fight
with each other anymore but you know
just it's time we get rid of Global's
altogether and in my coding utopia I'll
ignore it ignore IE six through eight so
so here's here's an example of you know
this coding utopia I'm using standard
methods here using preventdefault i'm
using query selector all using array
iterators that have been available at
least in some browsers since 1990 i
don't know so
and here's here's here's his a second
try you know here's here's maybe this is
good enough instead of going coding to
standards why don't we just agree on
that there is a standard but maybe we've
had to wrap it to help support the older
browsers right because because if we
were going to work this way this means
duck punching the older browsers
basically prototype augmentation which
arguably is good or bad if you're
augmenting the prototype to a standard I
think some people think that's
acceptable but I think we've been burned
so many times in the past so maybe this
is good enough you know if we just have
some wrapper function that looks and
behaves exactly like query selector all
or if we have this object with array
iterators and array mutators on it that
works in acts exactly like the standard
but instead takes takes an array as its
parameter so this kind of wrapper around
arrays maybe that's good enough and
here's another example we've got some
event library here
so is this feasible so in order to get
this to work we would have to have
number one standard api's and again my
pet peeve no Global's
so and again you know in order to meet
this utopia we need need to be able to
take these modules because they've got
standard api's we should be able to swap
out for the best of breed and this last
point is what we were mentioning earlier
when you have when you just use a tool
kit directly and you're not using a
module framework or module loader that
allows you to take control of the name
spacing you have things like ue and dojo
and dollar sign sprinkled throughout
your code which makes switching harder
one thing that modules allows you to do
and with something like an AMD loader if
you've used one you control the incoming
namespace so in the example that John
just gave the code example where he has
event add event listener event is not a
global event is something that we
defined the name event and we said we
want this module over here maybe it was
written by someone we found it on github
it's really awesome we pull that in we
assign it the name event so if we wanted
to change that later we control that
name we can say okay now I want this
module over here this event library and
I want to call it event and because it's
been coded to some standard API you know
possibly a common j/s API it just works
we don't have to change the name here we
don't have to change the name of the
methods no refactoring it just words
right so that kind of gets in with this
slide what's wrong with this code you
know it looks like we're still using mod
Global's but we're actually not and
we'll show you in a minute why that
we're not but what else is wrong with
this code the w3c you know Dom methods
everybody's pretty sick of them is you
know besides a lot of typing and whatnot
you know it's just not it's not a nice
way to code so so we still got that
issue to get around and so there is a
way to get around that and we'll talk
about it in a minute so can we have
these modules today
not really you know people are still
creating libraries frameworks that use
these global invasive ways to write your
code and swapping out requires standard
api's and of course javascript has no
standard api's well that's not true
because it really does and a lot of them
are hidden and and I was surprised when
I started digging in to find to find
some of them so so for instance just
JavaScript itself you know eka the
forthcoming ECMO standards of some of
them actually I say forthcoming but
they're really here it's just we're
waiting for them to infiltrate browsers
you know arrays objects there's all
these standard interfaces already and we
should start well actually dojo already
does this already and some of the other
frameworks out there and libraries are
doing it as well creating wrappers that
actually mimic and look at you know have
the same parameter function signatures
as as the standards so and there are a
bunch of others out there this JSON
schema Jason referencing Jason path yeah
html5 and css3 give us some great ap is
that we can we can model our our
libraries against query selector all the
event model Dom again those are quite
ugly and unwieldy but we can we'll see
in a minute while we can address that
the rest rest is a de facto standard for
for web development so there's some
excellent API as we can mimic for that
and plus this is common Jas proposed
standards common Jas is is not it's not
the it's not a dictatorship that says
this is the way you have to do things
the way comedy is works is people
propose things and people basically vote
on it through popularity and just you
know by using these standards one of
them will come up to the top or several
of them come to the top and become de
facto standards and that's that's that's
happening right now and it's very very
active right now we're seeing lots of
things come out and pop out of standards
well potential standards
and a lot of our are being used I mean
they're they're on they're on a wiki on
the common J's wiki but a lot of them
are being put into practice today so
this is going to happen more quickly
than you might think a lot of these
standards are going to become actual
standards pretty quickly I think yeah
there's actually a lot of momentum and
and of course the proposed standard that
really helped us out on the browser side
is asynchronous module definition and
I've got a great overview of
asynchronous module definition at this
this address here don't we don't have
time to go into all of it of course but
I'm going to at least touch on it a
little bit so so that's how I felt
basically when I when I discovered AMD
well in a nutshell it's it wraps you
know our common j/s standard module
format which is quite plain and simple
again we might be able to take a look at
that a little bit if we have some time
during this presentation but i encourage
you to take a look at that it works
today I no need to wait for all the
current browsers and I we can start
using AMD actually it's already being
used in several places and it has a
migration path strategy there's been
several proposed strategies to migrate
from AMD to JavaScript modules when it's
available in ECMO script and and
definitely check out the ten o'clock
presentation tomorrow by Dave Herman
about JavaScript modules and what
they're going to look like when they
really come to JavaScript so
unfortunately the standards don't cover
everything today you know we don't have
standards for templating we don't have
standards for data binding application
control flow this just distill a
bazillion things we do on our apps that
don't have a standard so how do you deal
with that so there's plenty of ways to
run around that and I probably shouldn't
say run around because they're they're
actually very cool strategies Bryan
later is going to talk about in
inversion of control and dependency
injection interrupt any time you want so
I'm in 220 this room yes you're all
about it so so we're places where there
isn't no standard API you can actually
inject functionality or even use an
observer or adapter patterns and we're
doing a lot of that actually in our
projects where where you build code that
acts on your coat and is not instead and
not integrated into your code so and
adapter patterns these plugins can work
in conjunction with IOC or in
conjunction with module loaders in order
to deliver additional functionality so
yes we can't have modules today here
very briefly is the AMD module format
your code your actual module would go
here and basically the way it works is a
single free variable we don't call them
Global's anymore we call them free
that's how we're getting away with this
is a free free free variable as a
function called define and the first
parameter defined is it I'm lying
there's actually another parameter that
can go in there but don't use it is
there's a way to identify your modules
from within but that's a strategy that's
meant for the the optimization the
concatenation and the compilation pieces
of AMD so if the first parameters you
specify a list of of modules you want to
pull in and I'm pulling in you know
something that looks like query selector
all I'm pulling in that array wrapper
I'm pulling in an event Raptor
rapper Raptor and I'm pulling in
basically a promises library here so
here's an example of a plug-in I'm
pulling in a text module and I'm pulling
in this proprietary CSS module and and I
actually could just write that CSS here
I should have done that so these are
like standard a standard plugins so and
if if you look closely all of these map
to function parameters here corey
selector all rares where the names don't
have to be the same right the dependency
names are actual names of modules
actually it is actually they're not here
they're not here I remapped them already
so so these could map directly to files
files in your in your in your web app
but actually there's a way to map them
so they this query selector all could be
actually pointing actually is right now
in the project wanna show it's pointing
at sizzle the jQuery selector engine but
we could easily just point it at dojos
query engine or at NW match your Diego
paninis query selector engine and same
with array this is actually pointing at
a small library I wrote but it could put
it be pointing at Uber's array rapper
could be pointing at dojo array you know
are just the dojo object itself so so
sorry there's your brief introduction to
AMD I do have a whole presentation on
that and can show plenty of examples on
how to build AMD style modules and so
bug me later today if you want to get a
good intro into that here are the AMD
loaders today require j/s being the one
that's been around the most James Burke
did an excellent job getting that going
and getting that integrated proposed to
common j/s Chris I've had a big hand in
that as well curl j/s curled ojs is the
one that I wrote pinned by Christophe
Dorn thank you BTW load which is the one
that was adapted to
work with dojo that's by raúl guild
there's even one startup in Spain local
net and Dan right from Twitter is
building one called loadrunner Jas and
from quick discussions with him it
sounds like he's also leaning towards
AMD or at least common Jas format and
Kyle Cal symptom Simpson has been
working on module modular based lab Jas
as well so and add I've been arguing
with Kyle back and forth he's he's I
think he's going to go AMD so so I don't
think as a choice actually because AMD
actually has a lot of momentum right now
Firebug 18 is using it already if you're
using the Firebug alpha version it's
already using Andy formatted modules
dojo 16 and 17 1 dot 6 is in release and
it's using AMD format there's dozens
dozens and dozens of Production apps out
there if you follow the required j/s
Google Group you realize that there's
just there's just tons of people
actually building production worthy
applications with it and open
cooperative web framework has also
adapted it as their standard for modules
as well this just tons of plugins out
there oh my links didn't work
coffeescript loaders Google loaders you
know CSS loaders CSS manipulators you
know you can load text you can load
translation files you can light load
plain old JavaScript I almost called it
lame-o lame-o JavaScript there's also
lots of modules already available Chris
type adapted sizzle which is one we're
going to be using today there's a ton
Peter Higgins has and bryan forbes have
created tons of modules you can use
under the uber github repo brian's
written some modules I've written some
modules there's also lots of module
helpers IOC wire is an IOC and inversion
of control of what do you call it you
know Colin front was called framework
yeah it's a inversion of control
container I'm a server-side guy turned
front end guy so for y'all's sneer at
ioc container in the server-side world
this is sort of a fresh take on it for
javascript if you're interested come at
220 today and walk about it yep there's
has how many people use has as jas it's
a way to to feature tests and fine tune
your modules so that only the code
that's necessary gets shipped up to the
browser it's an awesome project and then
there's other there's lots of other
things in the works I just named one of
them here Cola to help deal with the
other pieces that don't have standards
so that again Cola uses an observer
pattern so that it doesn't infiltrate
your code we've almost got utopia today
as she saw you we uses modules and they
do an excellent job they've got the
performance thing down pat dojo is is
hot on their heels with one dot 71 that
six is actually pretty good one dot
seven is going to be awesome in terms of
modules talk to some of the jQuery
people bought modules they're looking at
it become so so yeah sorry there's some
examples of the dojo ones that are that
I think are the most awesome you know I
can just swap in a qsa if i want to or
deferred as promised implementation and
the work crews I did on Jason rest i
think is an excellent example that we
should be using first standard for for
server communications moving forward so
but the big issue with with dojo and yui
is is still quite a commitment because
just for instance if you load dojos
deferred it pulls down an additional 20
files well obviously be compressing them
but you know you're you're kind of kind
of still locked into the whole dojo
thing as well
so I want to write a module so here's
here's a quick recipe if you want to
write a good modules that somebody
anybody could start picking up and using
you know focus on a single purpose
minimize the number of dependencies so
that you know wider audience can adopt
your module write some kickass code of
course and and follow the standards even
if it's just proposed standard selected
just about everything's a proposed
standard if it's not in part of ECMO
script already right so innovate
obviously without breaking the standards
too badly or are you know if you have to
break the standards you know get some
real-life code out there and and get it
out in production and propose a standard
you know if you're doing something
that's awesome and and lots of other
people agree with you you know or you
think they should get out there and
propose a standard it's it's not that
hard actually the commonjs blog is is
open for anybody to participate so
actually they probably hate that I'm
saying that right this right now because
because you know they've been locked in
their server side world and when the
browser guys are starting to take over
so and you know document where your
module deviates from the standard so
someone picking up your ear module that
you've written can can know exactly what
they need to do in order to make sure
that they're there you know not locking
themselves in or and if they do you know
you know what they need to do in order
to get around that you may be doing
something that goes above and beyond the
current standard and you know someone
may choose to use that because it's
awesome and if you document that in your
module that's some that might be a
reason for someone to choose your module
especially if you're already out there
you know sort of pushing that extra
functionality as an addendum to the
standard or you know a change to the
standard and and one of the really cool
things here if you sum all of this up it
means you don't have to write a massive
framework to
get people to start using your code you
can write something really tiny you know
an array library an implementation of
the wind function thats related to
promises small things that that you
think could be really useful to people
or that you're already using in your
code you can wrap them up as an AMD
module put them up on github tweet about
them people might start using them if
they're awesome people will use exactly
share it questions so far okay so let's
let's dig into the demo
I can find it oh not good the green
button work green one zoom
did all right
alright so we gotta get a cute little
application here it doesn't do a whole
lot you basically have to pick which of
these code snippets is more priority
than the other priority being a good
thing by the way think of it as ninja
you know but with a je s conf theme so
just demonstrate this really quickly if
I think this one on top is more priority
because oh I like that I like how that
works i'm going to choose that one I
should have done that all right sir but
but no there's actually a performance
problem with doing it this way with this
inline function in the line anonymous
function the JavaScript engines can't
compile that effectively so this one
with the function hoisted is better so
that's that's not really what we need to
talk about here so really the the flow
is you choose something you're right or
wrong you click Next so you pick another
one let's see sorry which one of these
is more priority top one at the bottom
raise your hand if you think the top one
is 0
that better you see now good so I'm
gonna pick the bottom one no it was
tough one sir so IMHO right so let's
take a look at the code here this is our
project we have a just a standard HTML
file and several folders with modules in
them we've got this our library for our
array we've got this CSS x module to
load and manipulate CSS we've got our
AMD loader we're using curl and we've
also what we're using wire for our
inversion of control and we've also got
this view folder and this controller
folder here that actually have our
application code and and how this this
is laid out is just for simplicity you
can get really much more detailed with
your folder structure this is just so
it's easy to easily laid out here so our
views we've got several views in here
let me go back to the application here
and show you how this is we've got a
codes view a heading view and a score
view actually the score views hidden
because we don't have that running yet
but this section up here
this is our heading view up here this
section of the of the application up
there at the top and our codes view is
everything underneath so this is its own
view so i'm using i'm using client side
views so each of these views is actually
a component in our system and each one
of these components consists of three
different files a JavaScript controller
an HTML template this is the PureView in
an MVC world and we've also got a CSS
file this companion to it so and again
the heading has again similarly this
heading component as a JavaScript
controller a template in the CSS joke
right yeah okay so let's see I'll assume
that in for you guess
so so here's a simple template we've you
know it's just very straightforward
here alright here's an example of us
using an AMD defined module our module
itself is that this is really considered
to be a rapper this is the part that one
day when we have javascript modules
that's going to disappear or it's going
to it's going to morph into something
that looks more like import statements
this is really the meat of our module
down here so down here if you if you
take a look we're using almost entirely
standard code you know actually I take
that back we're actually using the
wrapped ones in this version i had
another version that wasn't quite
operational where we were using what
looked like standard dom w3c event codes
so this one uses these wrapped modules
to UM to add remove event listeners to
do a ray iteration and whatnot and we've
also get promises in area yes reset in
the structure of how you're building
that very pop
sort of one aration in your ear mapping
that into the arguments point why don't
you have it was just sort of a name
value set up somebody else coming along
because it I mean that you're going from
vert come from vertical vertical to
horizontal yet III agree actually this
is this is something that takes get some
getting used to and kyle has been
playing with this idea with different
types of rappers that that may or may
not make more sense to you that so he's
gotten mixed reviews about his his
versions of this as well so so but i
definitely agree that sorry indicated in
here at the fact that that this it's
kind of hard to visualize the
relationship between these dependencies
and and there the way they're basically
quote imported as parameters into our
our module so really quickly here we we
just invented our own quick and dirty
templating system here which is just
replace of some tokens if this this is
actually a piece that can be abstracted
out entirely so it doesn't even appear
in your code so your did you don't
you're not actually manipulating your
view inside your controller they just
kind of coexist happily and as well if
you're abstracting the event delegation
out for the event handling out again
this this part down here also can get
extracted out of your code and we're
actually you can actually going to show
an example of that at two o'clock right
yeah yeah yeah cool using an observer
pattern external to the the code itself
to actually hook events together right
so once you pull that out the template
out in the event handling stuff what you
end up with is just pure business logic
and that's that I think is as close to
the ideal as we're going to get so
so let's take a look then at the main
file so here's the main HTML file
standard html5 let's see the first piece
we want to look at is this is the way to
get the AMD loader kick-started we're
saying that look for all of our modules
and the root of our marginal is going to
be in the jas folder here is where I I I
insulted you by correcting you about
where our files are located we can
actually tell the loader where to look
for our files for instance wire is here
our Dom ready wherever we're referencing
this Dom ready module is actually
looking for it here anywhere where it
says CSS in our code it's actually
looking for it here and we can see how
these are mapped over here so see us
it's actually looking for anything
that's called CSS is actually finding it
here and anything that's called Dom
ready its funding it right there we tend
to think of Dom ready is one of those
things that is integral to a framework
or a library but as you can see here it
could just be a module two yeah and
actually the AMD loaders are also taking
this strategy that yet no Dom ready is
its own it's it's own module so it we're
actually pulling them out and allowing
people to pick and choose Dom ready or
use the one in your framework already I
use the one in the loader it doesn't
matter and and more importantly here
anywhere where we see a reference to
query selector all it's actually pulling
in the sizzle engine right here right
there and again I could actually have
mapped that 22
it's actually in this strange location
i'm not even sure if it's still here in
one dot seven but I could actually map
it like that and that would work and if
I can get that running later today I can
I can actually show that I've started
working on a version that actually
substitutes a lot of these things for
for dojos and because we used query
selector all in the dependency list in
our modules we can make the change in
one spot and then everywhere we viewed
you we've imported query selector all we
get the new implementation in this case
dojo query or a jquery implementation
right and the these are some great
examples because dojo and sizzle both
both follow the query select where all
they extend on it you know and you can
actually do additional things that that
weren't in query selector all i'm not i
might be talking on my ass right now but
but um but but you know they also do
more than just the the standard and so
again that's something that needs to be
documented so you know when you break
and breaking the rules so you know if
you you know what you're switching costs
are and then here's an example of us
using the wire plug in for AMD AMD
loaders to actually go and load our app
so let's take a look at app loader this
is actually this is this code that
actually bootstraps our app right here
this this is the language of of wire so
do you want to sure okay just a quick
rundown this is just a define a module
being fine using the free variable so a
wire so a wire spec is just a module
right yeah yeah so this spec is just a
module and this is basically an object
literal that just describes all the
components we want to bring into
existence to make our appt work we have
some data that we're loading from a
module we have a
codes view which you saw just a minute
ago and we specify the AMD module path
to it and some constructor arcs in this
case a dom node where we're going to
stick that view a heading view what you
saw has the picture of the two pirates
we're going to place that in the Dom
also in the heading view container the
score of you which was hidden and our
controller so we're just declaring what
components go into our app and what what
weather where the views needed placed
our controller we're injecting a
reference to the codes view so that the
controller can interact with it so this
is just a sort of a declarative way to
bootstrap all right and all the ten
ponies all right I think we're out of
time is that correct is this we out of
time now all right but anyways this is
just a teaser about how wire works in
the aversive version of control and how
we're injecting you know other modules
and and properties into our modules if
you want to see more about this two
o'clock today right 220 sorry 220 220
today here so any last questions all
right thanks for your time guys good