good morning everybody hope you're awake
and I talk really fast and mumble a lot
so if there's any questions just come
see me afterwards we're here to talk
about insecure web apps since Crockfords
not here I'm the guy to yell at you
about security and I lied in the in the
title of talk there's no three easy
steps there's there's a whole pile of
mistakes and mistakes that we can go
through all right so who am i I'm Adam
Baldwin i founded a company called
ingenuity we do a pen testing of web
applications networks things like that
we break all of the stuff that you guys
build I am in no way qualified to give a
talk on code or developing or anything
like that I build really really horrible
apps I'm better at breaking them which
is why I'm talking about that I also in
the curator of evil packet net which has
some video demonstration of abusing web
applications there's a pile of web
well-known applications out there and
stuff we've done evil things to just
some of our clients on the bottom there
I'm going to try to really really really
not like this guy I'm going to try to
not yell at you and complain but you'll
you'll hopefully respect or understand
my side of things and I'm for most of
you in the room i'm probably going to be
talking about things that you're not
going to want to hear about you really
like well we hear about this all the
time this stuff that this is this is
stuff that we're always getting brushed
with and i know how to solve this
problem but the reality is is of it is
the mistakes are still being made we're
still running into this stuff and this
what i'm going to talk about the just
kind of some basic things output
encoding hashtag navigation and piles of
other crap is these mistakes still keep
getting made not only to mention that
we're taking javascript which has been a
typically a client-side thing and we're
going to be taking it and and shoving it
into the server side so now we're going
to have developers that are experienced
the client-side dealing with server-side
problems and so we have a whole new
class of issues that are going to happen
security issues so so writing insecure
apps you guys you guys have a really
really difficult problem oh yeah I don't
always test my code but I when I do it I
do it in production that sound like any
any of you we see it a lot and I don't
know if there's a solution around it but
so you guys have a really really hard
our problem when it comes to developing
and developing securely you you you only
have to find one way to screw up and the
security guys in the security community
point laughs right like like we're just
a bunch of dicks and we just say haha
you've got cross-site scripting and and
you know fix it so you're also
resource-constrained you you you won't
we have we as an attacker have to find
one way and you have to find all of the
all you have to solve all the problems
as well as not only being resource
constraint time money your manager
breathing on your neck to just ship it
the landscape is always changing html5
is a set in stone standard right right
yeah it's always going to be changing
and so you're going to have a whole pile
of new problems to deal with with every
day not to mention you're trying to just
get your feature out or you're trying to
just innovate and that's that's the last
problem is engineering versus innovation
right like you guys I had a conversation
with one our clients and yet and I you
know I was the typical security guy and
I said hey output output and code this
particular field in his comment back was
I haven't secured it yet I haven't got
there yet and what we find a lot at
ingenuity while while we're assessing
applications is that that that yet never
comes it's a to-do line it's it's the
famous last words right to do input
validation to do output encoding you
know check this check that and I hate to
be the guy to kind of rant about it but
it never gets done for starters stop
using to do's and use an actual bug
tracker that's that's that's a good
start so I really respect what you guys
do from a code perspective and I'm
really I
really think that the security community
and the development unity you need to
need to interact more and we as security
people need to understand what you guys
what's cool things you guys are building
and and I really want to have some
discussion after this talk with people
on how their team is handling security
how how you think that that you guys do
it right that you guys you guys don't do
it and maybe that's the way you do it
and that's just because of constraints
I'd really like to have some of those
conversations come out of doing this as
for I also think that that developers
need to take a little more
responsibility when it comes to security
and think about it and the problem is is
again your resource constraints so you
get to the end of a project where
security is usually applied and you just
ship it now you're moving on to cool
project x instead of you know dealing
with the as was mentioned in some of the
earlier talks you know dealing with the
the code that you just don't want to
work on because it's it's not cool it's
old and it's old and flabby right so so
here's the first thing that I see gets
screwed up as I went over all of the
assessment reports we've done for the
last couple of years there's two things
that stood out was hash you know kind of
a hash navigation or a shebang
navigation and output encoding and
there's a unicorn so the the reality is
is I see this done wrong in two
different ways and it's really easy to
get right and a lot of places do get it
right but it's just done wrong so you
have you have a URL right like you know
twitter com / you know hash and then a
resource and you get that Reese and the
Ajax just says go get that resource
right we're all pretty much familiar
with how that works right a lot of
places just don't bother to check that
there's I don't know a slash at the
beginning and so then you just go and it
says just get whatever resource that is
and they don't they don't tack on a vein
or they don't tack on anything at the
beginning so you put in a you know a
payload like this you know to evil site
in and I've argued with a lot of people
and they say well that won't work
because it's cross domain right
it just doesn't work we'll get guess
what of course headers allow that and my
evil site just sets that nice core
course header and and it works and the
other way I see it done right is that
they don't they they're checking for or
they don't check for HTTP so you so you
end up building a big long domain like
example com evil packet net resource and
you just do something like that and it
gets built out those are the two ways I
see it I'm going to attempt to do just
the demo just just to show kind of what
it would look like a really simple
cheesy demo that will probably fail
miserably okay so it has tests that's
the standard content we can win a life
test look at that resource great that
resources you know maps whatever and of
course we put in something you look at
the people pack it down net / cores and
we can see that it's going to not work
right
boom
all right live demo fail well what I was
going to show is that oh yeah I didn't
go get it Oh aha my app sucks so now
I'll actually work it just displays an
alert box saying that it executes a code
in the context of local I was great you
know window dot location but if you'll
actually look at the headers and I'm I
apologize because I'm not smart as Paul
Irish and I can't make this font bigger
I don't think I don't know how to do
that so if you actually look at the
headers that's coming back and this is
really hard to see there is a response
header access control allow origin star
that's all I have to set for four cores
and so just the point of that it's
really easy for an attacker once we if
you do this wrong to to execute code
within the context or application the
uneven packet there's a really
complicated example of our do had had
this problem when they came in beta and
and it shows some more complicated
execution flow for that cross-site
scripting everyone everyone's plagued by
this problem right like we don't want to
hear about cross-site scripting at least
at least that's what I hear from
developers when I talk to them they're
like it's probably just want to get go
away right or my templating framework
takes care of that the guys in the
Django community say well my templating
takes care of that rail says my template
thing takes care of that Express and
Jade takes care of that right well guess
what it doesn't if you up your
templates you're going to have a problem
and the reality is is this is this is
the reason all of these things encode
those five characters quotes greater
than less than single quote & ampersand
and if you put if you write shitty HTML
like down at the bottom there it you
don't need any of those things to
actually execute code it's just not
required the other things people forget
is that you can write Java code
JavaScript without letters and numbers
alphanumeric JavaScript
so depending on what you're actually
encoding it's contextually aware context
matters of where you're actually
cramming cramming your stuff into your
templates and you guys do some really
creative stuff with templating and and
sticking stuff where I would not
normally think think about it and in
this stuff matters well there's some
really there's some really elegant
solutions to solving this problem jquery
encoders go one way again don't write
your own quarters it use the stuff
that's out there we're trying to build a
wasp is trying to build their enterprise
security API to solve this problem to
make it easy so that there's a set of
encoders that you guys can just use and
you don't have to reinvent the wheel and
potentially screw it up they say the
same thing with cryptography don't write
your own crypto because math is hard
encoders are hard as well and here's a
simple example which I'm not going to
bother to go over but it just says
encode for HTML and they've got
different context is like in code for
CSS and code for JavaScript depending on
where you're actually dumping that that
input or that output and that's the
other thing is is that this is not in
putting not input validation we always
talk about input validation input
validation I feel is for the end user
you're going to give them a pretty
little message and tell them that there
that there that they put in a malformed
email address or something output
encoding is about sending it to a
different system so you're taking this
piece of out the this this piece of data
and you're sending it to a system a
browser is a system a sequel server
system and depending on where you're
sending it what complex system xmpp
server whatever you need to encode it
properly to send it to that system
that's output encoding and and it can be
a really really complicated process the
other thing is and I really really if
anybody from chrome team can can push
this on the chrome side I would love to
see it it just it's a new feature in
Firefox force content security policy as
anybody aware of content security policy
a couple people that's good content
security policy is is is pretty badass
it basically says that you can define
where you want scripts to run it and you
can say I only want to
load and execute scripts from my domain
inline scripts can piss off stuff from
other domains can just go away it's not
going to be executed as well as there's
there's a way if you want actually
implement this and test your app to see
where things would break there's
actually a way to just record the events
instead of actually blocking them so you
can say in the console you're going to
see how these things actually fail
another more complicated example would
be if i wanted to load different types
of objects so there's different types of
classification of objects objects and
scripts and images and things like that
and so you can you can define all this
content where you want it to come from
it gives you more control over things
that you're loading up on to up onto
your your page again I this is you might
say well I'm not just targeting Firefox
where I'm not just targeting chrome or
it doesn't solve my problem completely
but it makes it harder if you actually
implement a Content security policy on
your site guess what you're you may have
cross-site scripting problems but it's
only going to affect a portion of your
users you're going to be doing one
better than then somebody else and that
might be enough to make just somebody go
make an attacker go away it's kind of
like the the story of two guys in the
woods being being chased by a bear and
the guy takes a break to put on his
running shoes and his buddies like
asking what the hell are you doing why
just have to run faster than you you
just have to do better and that's the
truth is you can't have a hundred
percent secure site it's not possible
security is not a hundred percent thing
we all know that we all get that so it's
all about just doing better
understanding where you're at understand
where your organization at where you are
as a developer whether you give a damn
or not and just do better and I blew
through that amazingly fast so we'll
chat about some other stuff here
cross-site request forgery I see a lot
of people doing setting data actually
doing just not getting resources with
get I do doing privileged actions with
get it's a horrible idea don't do it
things like example.com / delete my
account
you know ID equals with a get and not
not bothering instead we just have we
just have a pop-up window it says do you
accept okay that's that's not really
necessarily adequate there's great
implementations out there Express
Express has a CSRF plugin I would look
if I were developing and I would look at
some of the models that are out there in
Django and in rails and and take their
model and implement that clickjacking
clickjacking totally gets a you know
most people think thats related to flash
and that type of things it circumvents
first of all if you have cross-site
scripting if you have if you have an
injection point near applications your
CSRF cross-site request forgery
protection is crap it's not going to
work it'sit's overwritten if you can
frame your application and you've got
click to basically allow for
clickjacking if you don't have frame
breakout code which frame breakout code
is not not perfect researchers have
proven time and again that that can be
that can be broken so there's a neat
little header the x frame options header
that you can set and you can say what
sites can frame your app if you're a
site that you never want your crap
framed set the header you click jacking
is just going to fail miserably it's not
going to be possible cookies I see a lot
of whoring cookies around in JavaScript
and don't do it it's that HTTP only set
secure flag use HTTPS and I guess any
questions anybody want to argue with me
or heckle me I'm yeah I'm this time the
security guy so just so you can you can
heckle I'm okay
okay so so clickjacking is clickjacking
is where you take a page and put in a
frame and make it invisible and then
make it follow the mouse cursor so
wherever you click you're going to click
on the button that I want you to click
on so one nice nun one nice thing about
forms that get filled out by like the
URL where you where you put you know
your form information the URL and it
gets populated I can just frame that URL
up and then make you hover over the
button that I want and it's invisible
and so when you click you actually click
through to that to that that frame so so
what happens is you're on you're on my
you know evil packet net and I'm I'm
really you know have facebook underneath
there so that you like me or whatever
and so when you click Facebook of course
has some protections against that but
that's one that's one example I I'm not
ready to do a demo of it but you see me
after I can show you a demo or something
if not that is it and see me after four