this is about node knockout and in
particular how to win no knockout so no
knockout is a 48-hour coding contest
using node is very similar to Rails
rumble this year it is at the end of
august again this is the second year and
oh so this is a massively multiplayer
website but since the Wi-Fi is out I
have I had a back-up plan which was a
you can use if you connect to Chi which
is my machine it should be sharing its
Wi-Fi and you should be able to achieve
that local and you should be able to
come and mess with my slides while I'm
on them and I encourage you to do it but
I encourage you also not to be an
asshole and say bad things because
that's not cool um but you should also
come and mock me if you want so there's
a random guy down here which is please
okay sweet um so let's go over here and
go to the slides um down down okay no
one still see that yeah kind of okay um
so again no not get for anyone who
hasn't done it before I kind of wet show
off the last ones with so one of the
winners with swarm nation which is not
as cool without anybody playing it so
I'm going to get that one even though
it's really cool um this was scraggly
now it's called wort square this is a
massively multiplayer scrabble game
which also like grows so these are all
little little tiles and this map got
huge but you also can't see it because
there's no Wi-Fi you're getting Wi-Fi
now maybe I should switch Oh shy call an
audible and switch networks I'm scared
I'm gonna do it no oh give me an IP
address just connect from my phone oh
crap dude led me astray wait wait wait
wait oh thank you so okay now we can
actually do some awesome things um so
yeah so this was one of the winners it's
a huge map of Scrabble tiles and that
one was pretty awesome this was one that
not in for node knockout but one that I
wrote which is massively multiplayer web
asteroids so screw that one do that and
actually I'm switching out to node
knockout calm and do this there it's the
same setup if I can get there go go go
go go faster over here hurry up little
dude so so I'm a consultant and one of
the things I specialize in is uh is
early stage startups and we helped
define product so also a way to call
this presentation is actually how to
build a minimally Viable Product in 48
hours so one of the things that I get
paid a lot of dollars to to do so what
do you care about no Tanaka first this
prizes of course last year we gave about
forty thousand dollars in prizes out
this year we hope to do better if you
haven't tried out note before you want
to try it out this is a great time to
try it out it's limited time you can
just do whatever you want and it's a
really easy commitment to just try out
note if there's an idea that you've had
that you haven't had time to do an
outside projects this is a great time to
do that also and submit it so the first
thing you need to know about any product
is you need to know your audience in
particular you need to know so you
should go and read the judging rules and
how judges work the the votes split
about 5050 judges are take up a large
portion of that
so you should actually go and check out
the judges the judges from last year was
a great set of judges we had like
brendan eich we had Ryan doll and John
Rezac people from VCS from sequoia
capital I think benchmark looking at
stuff so what you want to do is like you
go to this list you pick out like five
judges five random judges and you you
roughly google stock them and you try to
and you think to yourself would they get
my idea would they understand what I'm
trying to do and you want to try to get
in their minds and you validate your
idea against what they see and so
because because it's going to be a
normal person you might think that maybe
they nice advertisement you need need
need to think through that this year
we're gonna have a technology category
though so last year we had some entries
that were like a proxy server or some of
the technical things that most people
just don't get this year we're hoping to
to judge those better with the
technology category more details on that
forthcoming one other thing is that
these judges are looking at like 10 20
entries sometimes so if you can do it
without a login do it without a login
because no one likes to come up with
another username and password if you do
need a sign up then use Twitter use
Facebook all those general rules our
browser breakdown is really sweet so IE
accounted for one point eight percent of
all traffic so give a hand to that if
not then there's always socket i/o which
everybody uses anyway and falls back to
like I five I think so the other part of
the vote is the popular vote and you
want to I mean if you want to win the
popular vote you got to be popular the
easiest way to be popular is to be
newsworthy and the easiest way to be
newsworthy is to be controversial so I
mean controversy is not the hard to do
you can just throw up some porta-potties
on your website and your controversial a
little bit
people like tweet about how note
knockout has some porta-potties on its
website go check them out and other
people will come and check them out
there's also like scraggly last year was
the name scraggly is a little bit
controversial and and they tried to ride
that way for a little bit the other way
of course to be popular is what i like
to call brain hacking which is really
tapping into that um so people when they
when they make decisions are very
irrational and and and how they think
and choose to do things is just yeah
totally irrational and what you want to
do is from action to reward you want to
short circuit that that gap so things
like on your iPhone when you like get to
the edge and there's that little
bouncing that like animation it's just
pleasurable to like have your list
bounced back at you and so if you you'll
see people like just mindlessly like
bouncing their their endless because
it's it's just pleasurable this this
website right here rewards you for kind
of exploring and clicking around and
like this this monster just walking
around because it's it's fun to watch
this guy walk around so if you can work
that in as much as possible into your
entry then the more chances going to be
popular ah so you have about four months
between now and no knockout so that
gives you four months to figure out what
you want to do you can sketch everything
out and by the time coding rolls around
the coding phase rolls around that's 48
hours then you can just execute straight
up execute if you're going to be using a
library that you've never used before
you should probably try that out
beforehand if you can use a new
technology like Mongo or react or Redis
try it out a little bit and get get a
little feel for kind of what you're
going to be using it for of course not
your main tools get and gam core API you
want a nice tutorial of NPM I believe
Isaac's doing a walkthrough later when
you plan out your your future set you
want to be able easily divisible amongst
your team
so if you can have up to four people on
your team you want to be able to to farm
that work out amongst each other not not
step on each other's toes the other
thing you want to do is make sure that
your idea you're not going to finish
half your idea easily and you want to be
sure that half of your idea is still
viable you wanna you want to plan your
your idea out so that's kind of like an
onion and that you can just say you know
what that's not going to work I'm going
to cut scope and it's still gonna it is
kind of buggy because and I'm gonna
blame the network on that one that wants
to why it's buggy and you want to be
able to you want to be able to cut hack
your product down and have it still make
sense the best team probably is actually
two designers and to developers again
people really like pretty things even
even if it's a non-working pudding thing
they they'll give you more brownie
points than if it's a working ugly thing
so so if you can get to designers get
them so I like tests a lot but for this
competition they don't really make that
much sense tests generally will they
help make sure that things that you
don't use very often still work and they
make sure that it they kind of
communicate how you should be calling
code with this if you're not using
everything of your of your entry while
you're developing it then you're
probably doing something wrong and
you've probably actually cut that
feature and you're probably sitting in
the exact same room as as the guy that's
going to be using the code that you're
writing so you can just tell him what to
do let's move on so polishing so I don't
know if you know what dorodango is but
it's like a Japanese hobby where you uh
you get some mud and you form into a
ball you pull it all the the the water
and it becomes like a hard ball and then
you start polishing it a polish and
polish Polish polish it you get this
really shiny marble II looking thing it
looks really awesome but really it's
just a pile of mud and I
young Mythbusters they use some ostrich
feces and I think some lion feces they
did exact same thing it was very shiny
ball of that looked really awesome
and so you can take and just polish
the hell out of it it'll look awesome so
again allocate a good chunk of time to
to just polishing which is actually like
just cold dead links make sure that like
sign up to using it to the end makes
sense that people will find that way
through and just at least assign one
person to just be doing that for like
the last day the other thing actually a
little on the opposite of that is
smoking near so like if you kind of
cobble together a mobile version of the
thing that you're doing along with the
web thing say that you did that even
even most most people might not probably
won't even try it out but you say that
there's a mobile version this app to and
put a picture there they'll be like wow
they did a mobile app that's pretty
badass and you'll get brownie points for
it I don't know where pack minutes um so
I'm too old actually to probably be
doing these competitions anymore I can't
hang like the youngins and so I
definitely need to sleep and eat a lot
when I do this ah I I need a good amount
of sleep and I encourage you to also do
it some there was one guy I think that
stayed up for like thirty eight hours
but don't do that because you're just
going to be making stupid decisions by
the end take take breaks and also when
you're running into that problem that
just doesn't make sense anymore sketch
it out or stop and talk to your team
very very likely you're going to realize
that either like you're doing something
stupid or or that you just don't need
what you're working on so don't don't
lose time doing that stuff ah that's
actually about it um
I have like one minute for questions if
anything yeah all right oh yeah Braille
Marco all right so yeah no not gonna
come follow us on Twitter I'm this new i
am also hiring I don't know what else is
hiring but I myself and planning if you
have a vis new button you should get one