[Music]
hey good morning everybody as mentioned
my name is Angelina Favreau I live in
Vancouver British Columbia Canada
sunny Vancouver it's actually not very
sunny oh and I work for a company called
steam clock software and for the last
couple years I've been building mobile
applications for native for PhoneGap
I've used objective-c
a lot of JavaScript we've also done a
couple web apps and I work with some
pretty talented and awesome people there
but if you talked to me yesterday you
got a bit of a spoiler and that's that
I'm joining Mozilla in early June to be
working on Firefox OS so that is what I
do the web is actually my first love
I've been making websites since I was
really small my first one was on Angel
Fire I wish I mentioned sometimes and it
was about dolphins and all it was was
basically animated gifs of dolphins so I
like to think I've come a little a
little bit farther since then so a
little bit about me I am NOT a beginner
at programming but I don't I'm not an
expert like I don't consider myself to
be an expert at all and so this talk is
actually about trying to become an
expert as someone who considers
themselves an intermediate developer we
have a lot of resources and a lot of
initiatives to get people started
programming and Decatur to beginner
programmers and until the last year or
two it was actually really hard to find
articles and tutorial bits for people
who are intermediate developers who
think oh you know I don't know I'm
writing code but how do I make it better
you know and so that's a little bit
about what this talk is about so the
first things first let's get a few
cognitive biases out of the way because
I run into these sorts of ideas whenever
I'm teaching or presenting or when
people come to me and they like sort of
secretly disclose that their feel a bit
insecure about their programming you are
not special none of you know neither is
anybody else so that's ok we're all on
the same page I know your mom told you
this when you were a kid but this is
actually a motivational anti-pattern and
it works one of two ways either your mom
tells you they're totally special you've
got all this natural talent with the
violin and then maybe like you don't
practice and then
all the other people who do sort of
catch up and you don't feel so special
anymore or you know you think that maybe
if someone else was told they're special
maybe you're not special and so there's
some like disparity between you and the
special people often the people we think
who are experts we think there's
something very different about them from
from where we are and so what I wanted
to say is that nobody is born with
natural talent there are no natural born
programmers and whenever I say this
people get really really emotional about
this and I mean really emotional
probably because their mom told them
that they were special or probably
because if they are a good programmer
they like to pretend that they're
special and that there's some natural
talent and there's a whole body of
research out there you are all smart
individuals so I will leave it up to you
to to do your own research and take a
look there is an interesting book called
outliers by I think Malcolm Gladwell I
really hope I got that right that
discusses this topic at length now you
are the results of many complicated
interactions some of those things that
can make you seem like a natural usually
have to do with your early childhood
education the one thing that people like
to glom onto really quickly is genetics
and say like oh well you know maybe
there's like a gene for programming or a
gene for logical thinking and I'm pretty
sure that there are probably genes that
we can identify I mean I know there's at
least a few snps identified for
nonverbal intelligence for example but
it's not that simple our understanding
of genetics has come a long way in the
last 10 20 years and really the focus
now is on epigenetics the environmental
pressures that affect a gene expression
because even if you have like the
predisposition to you know unfortunately
have cancer you may not necessarily have
cancer if you know if you take care of
yourself if the environmental pressures
aren't there and so that's a little bit
nebulous to say that genetics are
deterministic because they just they
just really aren't also your early
childhood exposure to logical thinking
whether or not you had that early
childhood practice of these logical
skills and the early framing of your
relationship to logical thinking a lot
of people like myself who grew up in a
fairly all semi rural area and didn't
have a lot of positive programmer role
models like you know we were sort of
pulled that you
if you like math and you like
programming well that's never gonna go
anywhere why do you bother with those
computers and some people you know get
framed really early that like you know
math is gonna be too hard for them or
programming is going to be too hard for
them well I'm here to tell you today
that nobody is a natural and sorry
that's just another Jeff about people
not liking the logic of it they feel
like they're special so your feelings
don't matter here in spite of popular
beliefs there's no one thing that you're
destined to do purpose doesn't happen to
you any more than love does these things
evolve when you commit yourself fully to
something or someone and make the
decision to work through the muck so I
wanted to say that yes I mean
programming and math and logical
thinking can be a hard thing but that
every single person in this audience and
their kids and their friends and anybody
you meet is capable of programming and
there's so much bloody problematic
framing of this topic that it drives me
up the wall in 2006 Jeff Atwood posted a
post I guess he posted he made a post
about a academic study and I put that in
quotes because while it was put out by a
academic institution anybody who's had
any training in you know anybody's gone
and done a little bit of grad school
anybody who's been involved with
cognitive science and the behavioral
sciences and done research design will
read that paper and laugh because the
research design was very poor the sample
size was very small and what this study
was trying to say was for students that
come into our programming courses at our
university we can give them a test and
we can tell you or sorry we can predict
how well they're going to do it the
course and we can then separate
programmers from non programmers but
that's really problematic because the
way people interpreted this is the way
the media offered often interprets
things and that's very sensational and
they started to say like oh we've got a
test now to tell you no natural
programmers from from program you know
from non programmers and I was like well
no all this says that someone can tell
how well someone's gonna do based on how
they teach a course about programming
and also only considering the knowledge
and experience they have with logical
thinking up until that point which you
just don't know anything about maybe
somebody you know didn't have a good
relationship with math in school maybe
someone else who grew up with parents
who were scientists and they just loved
the stuff and so I really
I think you should take all that stuff
with a grain of salt because it's it's
often framed and like I say a very
problematic way so yeah so nobody's
special and experts are not born with
any natural talent so that you know
that's out of the way and that's
actually really awesome it's actually
really empowering because that means
that any of you have the capacity to
take from where you are as a programmer
and move towards expertise and move
towards mastery and feel a lot more
confident about the things that you do
in your job or in your side projects so
if you perhaps if you practice logical
thinking and if you practice programming
a lot and you manage to absorb enough of
the you know vast amount of domain
knowledge is out there you too will
become an expert so that's pretty fun
pretty awesome so then how do you know
that you're not a beginner so clue
number one I think is that you can use
the fundamentals in any language
so by fundamentals I mean your basic
control structures like loops if-else
statements know how to do like variable
assignments I know how to do some really
basic operations and what the what the
main operators are in a language if you
if you can kind of sit down with a new
language and get out a hello world or
make a very small app without having to
know the nuances of a language or
framework I think that you are a little
bit beyond being a beginner clue number
two you are comfortable writing code
from scratch when people are beginners
there's a definitely a pattern of they
grab like a third party library like
maybe jQuery has an example and they're
like oh wow I could do so much cool
stuff with jQuery but a lot of the time
they'll like put jQuery in and then
they'll just put in a plug-in and then
not touch it
I mean that's not really the same as
programming right so I would say that
you know someone who's a beginner or
just beyond being a beginner is a
comfortable writing code from scratch
and not just editing or gluing together
the pieces that they find and and just
to be perfectly clear that is an
important step like just being able to
like get into the code and try reading
it and edit it and play with it and copy
and paste a little bit that's actually
an excellent transitional skill than
becoming a better programmer despite the
fact that a lot of people are really
against that I think that that's
perfectly fine for beginners so if
you're not a beginner you're probably
comfortable at least writing some code
from scratch whether it's a couple fun
Asians are a whole you know like writing
all your code to make your single page
application work clue number three that
you're not a beginner when you do use
something like jQuery you peek inside
because you want to know how it works
you may not necessarily understand all
the things that are in there but you are
getting curious and you want to know
like you know what's what's going on
like how does how does this iterator
work how does you know how does this
selector stuff work and you start
getting in there and even if you don't
necessarily understand all that you're
at least trying to and number four you
may feel like their code is mediocre and
you don't really know what to do about
it and this is a really interesting one
because people will not talk about this
topic openly at events that I teach and
talk at but they'll come to me
personally later on and they'll tell me
and it's very interesting because
there's no real like trend about like
gender or ethnic background or anything
like that
it's literally like all sorts of people
be like hey so I mean I I think you're
good at JavaScript they'll say so I feel
really mediocre I feel like there's all
this pressure for me to be really good
really fast because it's a community of
really smart people and I'm like I feel
that I feel you I know them feels and so
if you have that feeling you're not
alone and you know so okay so those are
some ways that you know that you are not
a beginner well how do you know that
you're not an expert right I mean if
you're not a beginner I mean maybe maybe
you're an expert clue number one
you don't quite rock all the code you
read including comments so maybe you do
get into the jQuery source and maybe
there are some comments but you still
don't really understand what they're
doing with bind and you know that
there's these things called call and
apply and you don't understand why
there's like two versions of what seems
to be doing the same thing and and you
start like exposing yourself to some
more higher level concepts this way and
so if you don't quite understand all
those things you read probably probably
you're not quite an expert clue number
two is that you can't explain what you
know some people like to argue with me
that there are plenty of competent
developers that are awesome but you know
can't for the life of them explain their
methodology or their practice or what
their coding to someone else I think
that this is a big problem and even if
you are you know you know further on
other
avenues of expertise like maybe you do
understand bind and call and apply for
example but you can't explain what you
know to someone in a patient and clear
way that's a shortcoming and you need to
get better at that because programmers
need to be able to communicate and
disseminate knowledge between one
another and with their teams that they
work with and so clue number three you
aren't confident debugging this one for
me like took a long time like for me to
actually really get into the debugger in
like Chrome and then when I'm working
with Objective C and in Xcode and stuff
like that and to develop like sort of a
mental model of how I could solve
various problems with different
debugging strategies rather than just
doing this you know I throw in some
console logs all over the place
especially you know when I started using
node I was a bit of a late adopter to
node and I started realizing I was like
oh oh this is why I need callbacks okay
I like he just kind of stopped right
there and then clue number four is do
you rely on references too much so it's
really interesting that most of us who
are employed as software engineers or
web developers or whatever your title is
if you're writing code all day probably
you do have a tab open in your browser
that is a language reference or a API
reference of some sort because to
memorize all of the stuff is kind of
crazy and these things are changing
constantly too but I think that you
should be writing a large amount of your
code for example particularly vanilla
JavaScript in this case without
necessarily needing to refer to a
reference I mean if you need to once in
a while then that's fine but I mean you
should probably aim to write as much
with as little reference as possible and
the reason for this is just that you
will probably accomplish more honestly
you won't be stopping and getting
derailed and you can write code with
confidence when you know and you've
internalized those little bits so if
this describes you if you are not a
beginner and you are not an expert
welcome to the ambiguous zone of
intermediate Ness you are not alone I am
there with you and so from going from
there what does a curriculum for mastery
actually look like and also what makes a
great programmer and let's start with
that second one so it really depends
who's asking and these this is a little
bit of a quote written by a gentleman
named
Wiesmann who's writing I really really
love he is well I know he's definitely
older than I am but he's got something
like 30 or 40 years of experience maybe
more than that in programming and he's
written actually really interesting
ebook that's great for programmers of
all levels but particularly if you're
starting out if you're just google ed
Weissman you'll be able to find it and I
read this book and it just it really it
really got to me in a good way because
he answered a lot of sort of ideological
questions about the field of programming
that I'd been asking myself and
questioning like do I want to I don't
want to keep doing this short answer yes
so who is a good programmer it depends
who was asking - a project manager the
programmer who hits every deadline
regardless of quality is a good
programmer to the customer the
programmer who solves the problem the
fastest is a good programmer to the
business owner the programmer who makes
them the most money that's a good
programmer and to the junior programmer
the best mentor is a good programmer and
to another programmer the programmer
that they're most likely to want in to
go to battle with is a good programmer
so what do I need to learn to be an
expert and like how do you how do you
even do that you know what do you do you
want to feel unstuck so I'm going to
give you some suggestions here and a
little bit of ideas for materials so
that you too can transform yourself from
being intermediate into being an expert
so suggestion number one please ask why
obsessively short of existential angst
like all the time I mean I'm talking
specifically about code right now but I
mean like just in general with with your
life I mean you can ask yourself like
why did I choose eggs benedict this
morning or why did why did I choose more
better example why did I choose to use
jQuery like why why did I want to do my
why did I why did I choose like Twitter
Twitter bootstrap is because I am
uncomfortable in the front end why did I
choose nodejs to do all my server stuff
I mean aside from it's really cool
everybody in this room probably really
likes it but like why did you make that
decision why did you use express as your
as your framework for your routes and
all that so ask why obsessively to the
point where you annoy yourself it will
give you a tremendous amount of
self-awareness about the choices that
you're making when you're doing
development so number two I really think
that you should teach or speak at an
event there's this illusion
you're standing up here that you're an
expert I like to think like I say I'm on
my way to being an expert but I'm
definitely not an expert the only thing
you need to come up here and speak is an
idea about something that you've made
and like the previous presentation where
Remy was showing his experiment that's a
perfect example if you've done something
like that you need to tell people about
it and share the knowledge that you have
with others and what happens when you're
you know teaching or speaking at an
event is that you get to sort of
formalize and sort of make the ideas
that you have about what you've worked
on a little bit more concrete if you can
communicate those effectively you
probably know the area pretty well and
when it comes to teaching I teach at
ladies zoning code and I also do some
stuff for Simon Fraser University and
that is super enlightening because it's
a really good reflection on the kinds of
assumptions you make about your own
ability for example it ladies learning
code I get people asking me questions
like well okay I've sort of worked ahead
in the slides and now I have this piece
of code that I want to reuse should I
copy and paste it and I'm like no you
shouldn't do that you need functions and
people will often add or ask really
really compelling questions that cause
you to realize oh I actually know a lot
more than I thought about programming so
I also suggest working through a
suggested curriculum of books this is
from John Resig website that he's had up
for a little while called
learning advanced JavaScript and if you
can go through this this was sort of
like a proposed curriculum for advanced
JavaScript which eventually evolved
itself into this book the secrets of the
JavaScript ninja which I think has a
samurai on the front and this book is
really fantastic for me to read because
I keep going through it oh pardon me I
keep going through it and realize that
there's a lot in that book that is
totally rehash for me and I already know
but there's a lot of stuff in there I
don't know so reading a book like this
that has a comprehensive sort of outline
of topics of mastery for JavaScript will
help you reaffirm what you know and what
you don't know and that's a really good
feeling I like to read through a book
and be like yeah I got that or to
discover that like you had no idea about
function memorization that totally blew
my mind for example experiment
recklessly the code doesn't care this is
suggesting number four the code does not
care how old you are who you are where
you came from
anything like that nobody needs to see
your code till you push it up to the
branch that you need to push it to or
until you need to show it to someone
else for code review so experiment be be
reckless like do silly things just to
see what happens the code
it's just code it's a nerd until you
give it purpose so number five you
should have opinions if you're
progressing towards I guess an expert
level of understanding and knowledge you
will probably naturally start to have
opinions although it's really important
to remember that when you're having
opinions that and you're trying to sort
of cooperate with people that you're
gonna run into people that you disagree
with and there's a little song that I
like on the internet about that and it
goes something like this it's okay to
not like things but don't be a jerk
about the things you don't like
so just internalize that please and I
really like this one by Emily everybody
we're having opinions on things again
don't forget to state yours this fact or
s you don't get to play so just you know
be be reasonable and also accept that
you could be wrong and that being wrong
is actually fantastic because there's an
opportunity for learning there so number
six seek mentorship if you're here
you're probably already in the right
place but also in your workplace one of
the most fantastic things about working
at steam clock software is being able to
turn around to Allen pike who is one of
the co-founders you'd be like hey so I
have this ridiculous sounding JavaScript
idea and or question and then we just go
to the whiteboard and talk about it with
like no you know weirdness about it like
I know that it's not always easy for
some people in their jobs to do that but
if you can't do that in your job try and
find another job where you can do that
you will become a better programmer so
Justin 7 program a lot suggestion 8 stop
programming sometimes you need
breaks ok you like to think you can code
24/7 your brain doesn't work that way it
needs it needs breaks that's why when
you like are trying to fall asleep or
you're in the shower BAM you'll know how
to fix that bug you need time away from
the computer suggestion 9 write
JavaScript a lot suggestion 10 write in
another language for a while actually I
mean you should probably be writing
mostly in JavaScript but if you get
outside your comfort zone a little bit
and start comparing JavaScript with
other languages you'll find that there
are a lot of little nuances to
JavaScript that maybe you didn't know
and programming in another language
exercises the brain much in the way that
learning I know
spoken language would in a sense number
11 think like a programmer when afk
people think I'm really weird for
optimizing my route when I go to Ikea
and figuring it look the optimal way to
get through it as fast as possible and
that might be silly to some of you but
that'sthat's great like you should be
doing those sorts of thought exercises
as much as you possibly can because that
exercises the logical part of your brain
which is largely well that's what you
need for programming and suggestion 12
know what good feedback is and reject
all else it turns out that some people
aren't very happy with themselves and
they will take it out on you
so sometimes on the internet someone
will reply to your question or your post
and honestly like if they're not being
constructive and they throw in at the
fit so they say something mean tone is a
bit of a variable one then you know
honestly if you're not getting anything
constructive out of it probably it's a
waste of your time there will be someone
else who can give you constructive
criticism so just know how to
differentiate between good feedback and
troll feedback the last one really
that's a suggestion is to break free of
imposter syndrome it just has so happens
that if you write code you are a
programmer the end relative of your
ability people that come out of the
beginner JavaScript courses that I teach
tell me that they want to be quote a
real programmer one day and I ask them
like okay well are you writing code yeah
I know I'm writing code every day okay
great you're a programmer no no Angelina
I want to be a real programmer and what
they're actually trying to say is that
they want to be good and so hopefully if
you are someone at home that gets to see
this video and maybe you are in this
nebulous intermediate zone you will
understand that yes you are a programmer
and your desire to want to be good is
good and you will get there I promise if
you do some of these things and I want
you to fall in love with your process I
want you to fall in love with the
balance between writing code and taking
breaks I want you to fall in love with
the process of like you know arguing
your point and then taking the opposite
position because this sort of variety is
what's going to help you grow as a
person it's going to expand your self
awareness and hopefully make you a
better critical thinker about your
programming and so this is the end of my
presentation thank you wonderful humans
for inviting me to share this has been
JavaScript masterclass and I'm Angelina
Fabro you can follow me on twitter at
angelina magnum questions by the pool so