hi i'll be talking about the CSS modules
work that we've been doing in google+
modules is a problem that's not just
applicable to google or google+ it's a
problem that's faced by all very large
applications that have lots of features
so this is just a sampling of some of
the top level pages on google+ and
within each of these pages we have tons
of features and lots of features add up
to a lot of javascript in a lot of CSS
and as you can see from these numbers
here we have a ton of CSS and so we have
a problem to solve again and this is not
the only problem we do have the problem
of big CSS and us and we want our
initial page load to be super fast but
in addition a problem we've been facing
a lot over the last year has been that
kind of broken you is a lot of our CSS
is manually curated inbuilt files and
this is brittle and it's prone to
reordering so this is the second problem
that you're trying to fix so module
systems is primarily solving the problem
of size but building a module system is
much simpler if you absolutely had no
shared code in your site so let's say
every page of your site is completely
independent and doesn't share any code
at all then it's fairly straightforward
to build a module system every page
becomes its own module and you load it
as you go but in reality though we do
have a ton of shared code and if you
don't have any shared code then you're
definitely doing something wrong because
stylez should be shared across your site
so building this dependency system
turned out to be a big win on its own
its vastly improved the CSS development
experience because now we can rely on
the framework to ensure the correct
cascade ordering and developers don't
have to keep fighting specificity
anymore so this project is a work in
progress we haven't completely launched
to all of Google+ yet we have launched
more deals to several pages on our site
and we've seen significant improvements
in CSS size
and the preprocessor we use internally
in Google is called closure style sheets
and internally we call this GSS so if I
accidentally say gess in this talk I
really mean CSS so the step one to build
an effective module system is to know
what the shared code is and this is not
always trivial to identify you might
sometimes you might notice you know the
button and a menu look similar but it's
not easy to see exactly what is similar
so we can at least start with the very
obvious let's start with the exact same
UI elements that keep repeating over and
over again and these are things like
buttons and icons and what's famously
called the media object and we have a
ton of these repeating patterns in
Google+ so Google+ is a social network
and the primary thing on the main page
are these posts which are contained in
what are called cards and every post has
the same characteristics every post has
an icon with the name of the person
posting it has buttons for uploading and
re sharing and it has common activity in
addition on the top left is what we call
the share box if you wanted to share
something with your network this is
where you would start typing this is a
completely different page it's my
profile page and you can see that the
top right card is different but again
the common theme here is there are posts
and the posts have the same
characteristics and again we see the
share box and you can see the common
elements outlined in red yet another
page on Google+ this is called the
community page it's a forum for people
of similar interest here it's
photography and again it has unique
elements like the left panel and the
right card but again posts and share box
photos page at first glance it looks
completely different but if you look on
the right band panel you see the same
repeating components again so you get
the point we have a ton of shared
components all over our site but this is
not all in addition to this we have lots
of shared Styles across Google Plus and
these are things like forms and colors
and layouts and then in addition to that
we have
lots of common styles across all of
Google and these are things like buttons
checkboxes dialogs menus this is so that
as you navigate different Google
products like map or search you get a
somewhat consistent look and feel and by
the way everything I showed you so far
is developed by completely different
teams so we have these somewhat
competing goals of all these teams
wanting to split their code by project
boundary but we want them to share all
of these common styles so this is all
the more reason why we need a dependency
system because we want a systematic
framework and not rely on developer
discipline so we saw how the homepage in
the community page share some code like
in this case they share the code for
posts and share box in addition they
have their own unique elements we
definitely want to write all of the
shared code only once we want to
download it only once to the browser and
we want to download the minimum possible
CSS so let's consider the larger problem
of code that's downloaded on the browser
and this is not just CSS but includes
everything the browser needs to render
the page including templates and
JavaScript so for the homepage we've
already seen we need code to render
posts render the share box and other
homepage specific elements so I'm one of
our main goals here is when we first
visit the homepage we want the page to
be super fast just load the minimum code
needed to render just that page and
nothing more and then later when we go
and visit the community page or some
other page that incrementally load cold
just for the features needed for that
now it turns out there is already a
solution for this in JavaScript and it's
called JavaScript modules and it solves
exactly this problem of incremental
download and any JavaScript developers
in group might be familiar with AMD or
commonjs and last year my co-workers
from google malta and john unveiled the
open source google module server however
there is absolutely no solution for this
and CSS yet and the question is can be
potentially use the same solution there
is a catch though
in CSS we have the problem of safety so
in this example when I go visit the
community page after the home page if
I'm not careful about how I write my
code the styles that I lowered later can
override the styles i've loaded earlier
so it's possible that I break the UI for
the home page so now we have this
additional goal that as we incrementally
load CSS we want absolutely no
regressions on previously shown on pages
so we're coming to the conclusion that
CSS is not as simple we have the safety
challenge that I already mentioned in
addition we know that we have a ton of
shared code we want a dependency system
but CSS doesn't have a notion of
dependencies and almost every other
language seems to have this and this is
require and comment yes or import in
Java and Python so how do we depend on
what we need and how do we depend only
on what we need recap of our goal here
is just deliver the minimum amount of
CSS do it incrementally and safely and
the challenges here are bundling the CSS
with its dependencies downloading it as
needed and safely composing it so we are
essentially saying we need a module
system because bundling CSS or depth is
really what a dependency system does and
downloading and composing is what an
assembly and serving system does so
let's look at each of these challenges
starting with the first one so we define
mcss module as a bundle of CSS that
supports the page of our site and is
downloaded together and we've already
identified CSS shared code and
dependencies and these are things like
CSS from the shared components fonts and
colors that are expressed typically as
constants and in addition we have a lot
of common CSS libraries and these are in
our case these are Google wyd styles so
let's stipulate upfront that the naive
solutions don't work for our case we
cannot just use a CSS at import on every
page we visit because this would just
duplicate download all of that shared
good and we've seen we have a ton of
shared code in addition we want to
include only what we need for example
different page
use different variants of the share box
I showed you now if the profile page
wants a bit one wants one out of seven
variants it should only include that one
and nothing more in another non solution
for us is we cannot take every single
style that's shared across our entire
site and bundle this together into a
giant shared EPS module this module is
going to get very large and maintainable
very quickly so let's start out with
figuring out how to express dependencies
in each of these cases with shared
components because we write styles in a
completely separate stylesheet how do we
even know which CSS belongs to each of
these while we don't know exactly which
CSS belongs to this we do know what
templates are needed to render those
components and we know what javascript
is needed to make them interactive and
those things are templates and the
JavaScript can in turn point us to the
CSS that they pull in so essentially
what we are saying is let's bundle
template JavaScript and CSS into
components and the starts to sound a
little bit like web components so this
idea is similar to Nicole CSS Legos
which is identify shared veges create
reusable groups of CSS the additional
concept we're bringing here is we want
to bundle templates and JavaScript
together and create self-contained
components and essentially we want the
framework to do all of the heavy lifting
and not rely on developer discipline
because the top priority for developers
is to launch their features so to create
these self components Express
dependencies from the template to the
CSS and from JavaScript to the CSS and
we've created syntax for both of these
so for the templates case we use closure
templates in google plus and we've come
up with this require CSS annotation that
you can just add your template pointing
to the GSS namespace and similarly we
have an annotation that we use in our
JavaScript for the same purpose
this can just as well be expressed with
AMD syntax so at the end of this after
we have identified these components
bundle them together and we are
expressing dependencies of them at the
end of this we have a component
dependency graph for this page and once
we do this across our entire site we
have a complete component dependency
graph the second type of dependencies we
identified a things like fonts and
colors and these are typically expressed
as constants for us there's established
syntax for this in most preprocessors
this is at import in SAS and we use
closure style sheets and our sin taxes
for wide and require and this fits in
really well with our CSS dependency
graph so let's say the profile page
wants a separate set of constants from
the home page it can depend on just
those costs constants so this is an
example of the provide required syntax
for constants in this case we have a
profile base GSS named a CSS namespace
that is exporting a constant for profile
update background color and if something
else wants to use that constant all it
has to do is say at require and use the
concert so now we are expanding our CSS
dependency graph to include these common
forms and colors and essentially all of
our constants and mix-ins become part of
this dependency graph we haven't covered
what we're doing with common CSS
libraries yet but we'll come back to
that soon so moving on to the next
challenge here how do we safely compose
the CSS in the browser but it's not the
background for this I have to reiterate
kind of the basic points of CSS which is
order and specificity see CSS is
inherently order dependent if you have
base tiles and you have overrides for
these styles the base tiles must be
ordered before the overrides and
specificity can trump order so in this
example if
I have a div rapping hello world text
and I have two classes on it blue and
red with the colors blue and red the
hello world is going to show up in blue
and the reason for this is that the
Cascade order dictates that Styles
applied not the classes in HTML however
if I added yet another class to this and
add additional class in my CSS file that
changes the color to red this is because
i have just bumped up the specificity
off the off the right class and in
general this is not a great way of
overriding because every time you want
to override something if you're going to
bump up the specificity and you're
essentially fighting in the neck on the
next override and this is famously
called the specificity Wars so we
generally want to use the Cascade or
dictate styles and not specificity so
thanks to the work that nicole has done
an object-oriented CSS there is a body
of guidelines then we've fine found
these to be really accurate it from our
own GSS development experience we want
to minimize the selectors we have want
to reuse as much as possible we want to
keep specificity low and we want to have
rules of the streams same strength and
we want the Cascade order to override
styles not specificity but ideally we
want our framework to do all of this for
us but the framework should enable us to
create simple selectors and rules of
equal strength and and cover and
basically correctly order the Cascade so
the developers are not fighting
specificity so let's take the concrete
example of a button we have a button
which has some common styles and
different pages want to override in a
slightly different way and let's say for
this example they want to change the
color in for all these different cases
there's many ways to override styles and
each one has its pros and cons and we're
going to quickly look at some of the
common ways to override styles the
typical way to do this is you should
ideally be extending
standard button class with your own
context-specific button class and often
programmers might start out with a
compound selector for this you would
write profile button dots to android
button and we've already said that this
is not the ideal way to do this as it's
prone to clashes if you further if you
want further overrides of that same
style let's say you want different
styles in profile by the way if that
button appears in the header words of
the sidebar descendant selectors is
another way to do this here and this is
definitely better than compound
selectors but to some extent you may be
tying your CSS to a predefined HTML
structure you might use tools to do this
mix-ins are a pretty standard thing in
most preprocessors and if you use a
mixin it would automatically expand the
styles in line so you're essentially
getting rid of the standard button class
and the problem with this is now you are
duplicating all of these styles in each
context if you already said we don't
want any duplication yet another way to
do this is use the site's as an extent
with a placeholder and this compiles to
something like this and this is a vast
improvement over mix-ins however this is
not our ideal solution with a dependency
graph because now we have this one rule
which has all of these features specific
selectors tied together and now this
rule is going to show up in some shared
module in our dependency graph and
ideally we just want to keep feature
specific code in separate modules and
finally a way to do this is to simply
write the overriding styles keep
standard button as it is and it's
already provided in our shared library
anyway and let every context just add
its own style but here now we need to
rely on the correct cascade order this
is in fact our preferred way to override
styles in Google+ and we have a syntax
for this such as provide and require
so if profile button needs to be ordered
f after the standard button all it has
to do is at require the standard button
so we essentially expanding the
semantics of at require to include
ordering now and we've considered some
alternatives here's like expressing this
ordering in JavaScript and templates and
this wasn't as pretty because first of
all they ever do it in both places and
now there is CSS ordering semantics in
templates and in JavaScript and we also
like the solution because it meets our
requirements we minimize selectors we
have rules of equal strength we still
haven't covered how to handle style
overrides for components yet so first of
all I want to demonstrate that using
components with a dependency graph
actually guarantees correct cascade
order as well so let's say I have many
widgets on my side and they both they
all want to use a common component like
an icon so this will basically map to
some dependency graph if we are using
component and the Styles would show up
in the graph and eventually we are going
to flatten this dependency graph into
the Cascade but we do we still preserve
the order so all the ordering the arrows
ever there in the previous graph are
preserved in this cascade and the
framework will now create the correct
cascade from this graph we still haven't
said exactly how we are overriding
styles though and well the two ways we
do this most often in our case are
either using additional classes or
descendant selectors if the component is
going to be mostly overridden in almost
every context it's used then it's better
well we think it's better to simply add
an additional class and this means that
the overriding context has to plumb the
additional class into the components
template and this is fine because it's
essentially exposing an API for the
override the other way we
do this is with descendant selectors and
with it and this is still fine because
we're not really tying this to some
predefined HTML structure per se we are
tying into a context so so far we've
covered the types of CSS dependencies in
our system and we've shown you the
syntax we use to express these
dependencies and we've shown you the oh
how to override it each category and
we've shown you what the keys are the
Cascade order so now we've covered all
our categories of depths and we
essentially have a complete CSS
dependency graph that includes all of
our shared styles and components forms
and colors and the Google common CSS
libraries etc so this covered our
dependency system we have namespaces we
have a way of expressing dependencies so
now we move on to our assembly and
serving system so I've already touched
on how modules get flat well how a
dependency graph gets flattened to a
cascade and here the only additional
thing is that we also identify modules
so you're identifying granular units of
modules in this graph and then you
compile the CSS to these modules and
then the modules get translated into a
cascade so a module is a CSS grouping
downloaded together and we always
download the dependencies for every
module the feed load on the browser and
this is analogous to our notion of jas
modules and so we are really trying to
sort of piggyback on the download system
that we already have for joyous modules
now for serving it pretty much works in
the way you would expect you have the
community page depends on the modules
for the share box and the posts and
when you where it wants to render those
those modules in turn will pull in all
the other modules that they depend on
and so this will include your buttons
and your comments widgets and your fonts
and common styles etc and then later on
when we visit the homepage we only
additionally download just the modules
needed for the homepage because we
already have everything else so the
important point with this download
system is that it also ensures safety so
we mentioned earlier how you know late
late the later page has the potential to
override the styles of a previous page
and but here we don't you already solve
this problem by doing all of this hard
work of creating this dependency graph
so now there is no question of home page
Styles overriding the community page
Styles because all of their common
dependencies have already been
downloaded so in summary the system is
solving both of our original problems
now we're solving the problem that we
are initial bundle is really big and
it's really slow and we have manually
curated CSS that can get reordered and
break our UI and these are some open
source resources we use close your style
sheets and this has our syntax for EDD
provide a net require and we use closure
templates which doesn't have our sin tax
would require CSS yet which will in the
future and that is all
you