I'm here to talk to you about cats and
the internet mostly that's it this is me
with 12 cats on me I think it's it's the
happiest moment of my life it's at a cat
cafe in Japan I thought that was a good
way to start it out but the way that I
came up with the topic for my talk is
everybody that I met in New York that
knows me knows that I've tried to build
this for a really long time it is a node
powered automated cat feeder that is on
that table filled with mms it's not the
same container that I used for the cat
food so there's no cross-contamination
there and so I was like I really want to
build this I really want to build this
because last time I had an idea for a
project I just kept on putting it off
and putting it off and putting it off
and then what happened was a Marco did
it and did it way better than I could
have so I just figured you know you just
have to do something and my friends
talked me into applying to this and to
note interactive and I was like I'll
build it if I get pics and they both
picked me so I kind of had to do it so
trying new things are scary especially
when you have no choice and have to do
it and if it doesn't work then you're
pretty screwed if it's embarking on a
new project or you know using new
technologies for the first time which I
did with this product I'm front ends I
mostly just well I do everything because
I'm the only front-end developer for my
team but I've never really done no tap
stuff besides here at jas comp and
Cassandra perches workshop and I never
use socket i/o I had never done hardware
stuff except for blinking an LED that
took me way longer than I'd like to
admit so it was all totally new and I
also never had contributed open source
so I decided to do all these things that
I'd never done all at one and then
release it publicly to be scrutinized by
people
pretty hard to put yourself out there
mostly because a lot of people that i
know that contribute to open source have
had pretty bad experiences whether it be
just trolling like random people with
the like the equivalent of the egg on
twitter like there's a bunch of new
github accounts with no contributions
that love to pop up in every code of
conduct conversation there's also like
when you finally get that project out
there people won't like it and it's
something that it might not be that good
but you can't see it from that point of
view when you've been working on it for
so long and you're just really tied to
it there's also not thinking you're good
enough so like all right I built this
code and it works but are people going
to look at it and be like why did you
use this why didn't you do this this is
better like you did horribly I don't
know there's also a lot of communities
fortunately I don't think Judd the
JavaScript like open source community
has this as much as I've seen it happen
with other languages but there's people
that are like if I don't know who you
are why are you even bothering to
contribute to this and they won't even
take you seriously or just the bad
behavior which is mostly the trolling
the kodokan duck arguments are kind of
the worst though some of the other bad
behavior that I've seen and experienced
is the feigned ignorance of oh you've
never used this method everybody knows
that what are you even doing I also
heard about people ignoring
contributions so this is this is a
tricky one though because I mean
maintainer czar super busy so you can't
pay attention to every pull request that
comes in but if you take the time and
like submit something and nobody pays
attention to it it can feel pretty bad
which the other side is the demanding
user base also people that use pull
requests for the sake of a green
timeline because it's their measure of
self-worth which is wrong and people
shouldn't think that way like you don't
have to constantly be pushing code to
prove yourself as a developer and also
just like insulting the contributors
which is ridiculous and disagreeing over
trivial things so I posted on Twitter to
like try and get people to give me
information about their experiences and
things that they've had happen
surprisingly everyone that responded
with that experiences were women I don't
know if there's a correlation or who
knows but here's some of the things that
people said Jen Schiffer said vulgar and
brutal harassment expectation and
entitlement of your time without any
compensation offered another gin they're
all not they're all not named Jen don't
worry Jen said unfortunately the
harassment was enough for me to stop
trying before I had other problems so
that's where I'm at she never even got
to get to the point where she was ready
to make contributions because all the
bad things that she had seen happening
which is horrible the next person didn't
even want me to name them because they
were I don't know scared about people
lashing out at her for saying this or
him entitlement of time the assumption
you immediately want feedback when
you're just starting nerd pedantic and
obstructing learning Caroline who works
with Tracy and I at IBM said
mansplaining mainly and a general fear
that any commit I make will be opened as
an issue and debated about caroline has
a legitimate reason to be like afraid of
this because she writes a lot about
feminism and the game industry and has
been a target of gamergate and her
mother got swatted so there's like
legitimate fear that this can come back
to you in your real life sent the pull
requests of bug fixes that got ignored
for almost a year after which the
maintainer wrote the same fixes and said
oops and Tessa means planning my own
code to me
and trolling Tesla made this really
awesome library called echo chamber jas
which is basically a fake comment form
that utilizes local storage so whenever
somebody who leaves a comment on a
webpage they see it but they're the only
ones that see it and so people got
really mad really mad she had an issue
open that said you're fat and insecure
and then there was a really really long
issue about this person who I don't
think has any commits to anything except
maybe like gamergate block list or
something like that that was seriously
worried about the psychological effects
that this was going to have on the
people that couldn't get their voice
heard and the like what was it it's like
as a web developer or a site maintainer
you owe something to the people to be
able to like not mess with them sec like
no you know anybody it's the
internet like get over it so all of this
was before I even started trying to
build the project and then I was like oh
ok so now I have to do this so I guess
instead of trying to like commit to
anything else in open source I'll just
do it myself that way so my proposal to
anybody else that hasn't contributed to
open source is find something you're
passionate about for me it's cats and
then or something new that you want to
try which could coincide with the first
make something cool and open source it
yourself like I did and then that way
the first point of contact that you have
is with your peers so you're not gonna
just post it out there and people find
it and are like this is dumb lol it's
going to be people that you care about
and trust and you know are there to give
you good feedback because construction
constructive criticism from your peers
is a billion times better than randos
being jerks on the internets so once I
was finally ready I was like
all right now here's for some cat
pictures again these are my two cats
this is reset Smith and Rick Deckard
they're both named after Androids I like
cats like I said I'd been talking about
building this feeder forever um I had
the idea in my head and I was like it
would be so easy like you just hook up
the motor to it and write some code and
it'll work it'll be great my only
experience is with the node wats
community had been at JS conf last year
in 2014 and here over the summer and it
was great everybody's super nice it was
super welcoming and really helpful so I
was like at least if I mess up somebody
will be there to help me and it'll be
cool I told you that already and so yeah
I built Robo kidding it's a DIY
automated cat feeder there's reset again
he's the handsome cat and Rick is the
dumb one
but everybody loves rick because he you
can literally like do anything you want
to him you pick him up and put him on
your lap and he stays and then he just
like flops over and he's the weirdest
cat I'd ever seen in my life so yeah for
the feeder I ended up using a few things
that were new to me I use node I used
Johnny 5 which is a node box or node
BOTS robotics framework maintained by
Rick Waldron and there's a ton of
contributors that are here too and it's
great it's really easy like the main
reason I say really easy but I got so
mad at this stuff like the reason it's
great is it has the best documentation
for anything that I've ever worked with
ever and I am that horrible developer
that doesn't want to read the
documentation and just wants to like
jump into it and figure it out but this
is actually helpful because you can go
in and you're like I want to work with
this type of module with Hardware I want
to use a potentiometer or a servo or an
accelerometer and you go to it and
there's code snippets it tells you
exactly how to use it there's even like
wiring diagrams for various
microcontrollers and it's it's really
easy especially for somebody to New like
me socket i/o so when I decided to use
socket i/o I was just like I know I have
these things that need to talk to each
other that's like something that people
use right it sounds good so I just
picked it and it works um I bought an
arduino uno and then i was like oh wait
there's no internet on it you know i
would have to like buy a Wi-Fi shield
and i'm not exactly sure what that is or
a breakout board and i have no idea what
that is so I was like okay I'm going to
try something else so I bought an
Arduino you and then Rick was like oh
the Johnny Five support for that's not
good and I was like okay so i bought a
particle photon so the project itself is
cheap but that's when you buy the right
parts first and not all the wrong ones
don't worry i bought all the wrong ones
for you um the parts that you actually
need for the project are a dry-goods
dispenser which is the thing that has
the mms and it's basically if you've
ever been to a continental breakfast
you've dispensed goods it's like 12 or
16 dollars on Amazon you need a particle
photon kit with a breadboard if you
already have a breadboard and you just
need the particle photon it's like
nineteen dollars for the photon and then
the kit is 29 I think if you bought it
on Black Friday there was a sale you
need a continuous servo which is a
server that's continuous which means it
can keep on turning over and over again
a four double a battery pack with an on
and off switch the photon itself doesn't
have enough power to run the motor on
the servo so you need to power it
externally and as I'm finding out that
that's actually probably not the best
solution because the batteries don't
last long at all so if you think this is
cool wait a minute and let me fix it and
then it will be even better but for now
for double-a battery pack it's two
dollars it's fine that it's cheap and
then miscellaneous hardware accessories
which are male to male jumper wires a
soldering iron and heat shrink if you
already have those laying around great
that saves you more money so yeah when I
first got started the way that it felt
trying to put this together was like
this just trying to fit things but uh
things things were okay they went pretty
smooth when I started wiring it together
it went really easy of the coat I
started it all off with them I wrote my
code so that I had a element on the web
and then I had the controller on my
server code and I just started off with
LED blinking because I was like okay if
I can push a button and get the led to
blink then I can just swap out the motor
and it'll be super easy and it'll be
done it'll work it'll be good um but I
didn't think about the fact that I had
to like do math with electricity stuff
and I was afraid that I was going to
like electrocute myself the whole time
also didn't realize that I needed to
power the servo I thought it would like
magically work by plugging things in
because I don't know you connect it and
it should go in my head that was like
how it works I also didn't know how to
solder but I luckily typed into youtube
how to solder and this really awesome
doomsday prepper had a video and he was
like all you do he was talking about a
lot of other stuff too but it was it was
really easy and I was surprised at how
easy it was um yeah so then I had
everything set up with the servo and I'm
ready to test the codes working great
it's looking good I don't think there's
anything wrong with it the cron job that
I have in the code which is for the
scheduler part you can set it so that it
feeds the cats every like 124 I don't
know something divisible by 24 then you
can feed the cats on that schedule it
was working good because I tested it
with seconds before I set it to ours the
servo was strong enough to power the
feeder which I was and I was like if it
works with a little bit of food is it
going to work with a lot of it a lot a
bit of food and it did so that was good
except it wouldn't stop so it would just
keep on going and all of the food that
was in it would just come out and I was
like oh that's kind of important I need
this to work and so I freaked out I have
this really bad tendency whenever
something goes slightly wrong to try
everything I can to fix it which is
especially bad when I mess up get
branches so I I freaked out on Twitter I
censored it in case you're offended this
was actually because I had reset the
access token to communicate with the
photon and I forgot to update my code it
took me like three hours to realize that
because I wasn't reading the whole error
message and I just knew it wasn't
working so I was mad so I decided to ask
other people to help me there's a really
great get er chat for Johnny Five where
there's people there that will help you
and people helped me but it didn't
really help there's also a Brooklyn jazz
node box room which Francis who helps
run
Queens no only Sarah does Queens jesse
is working at beaucoup now he does a lot
of no bot stuff he made a room when I
was having problems probably so I would
stop asking them on Twitter all the time
um people ravine my code and said
nothing was wrong Sue's reviewed my code
and she's like it looks good I don't
know what's happening and I was like so
what is happening why is it wrong and
then something awesome happens um after
Rick told me to stop buying shitty
servos he went this is Rick Waldron the
guy that made Johnny 5 he went to the
store that i bought my shitty servo from
bought the same one and realizes it was
a bug in his library so I tweeted this
the code for my automated feeder is done
if I didn't already have a cat named
Rick I'd named the next one after Rick
Waldron and he gave me the credit for
finding the bug when I didn't I guess I
did I I guess I found it even though I
didn't realize it cuz i don't know i
still don't know anything about hardware
i just try and plug things in and it
works so that was really great because
what ended up happening is servos have
this thing called a dead bands and
sometimes you need to adjust them with a
trim pot which is like a hole in the
side that has a screw if it has a trim
pot mine didn't I had to take the whole
thing apart and there's one inside so
you turn it until it stops when it's
going and the code in Johnny Five that
you can set a dead band in wasn't
implemented into the Sox top coat for
the servo so even if I had everything
right it was never stopped it would have
kept on going but it's fixed now so
that's good I'll show you the code
really quick I made sure I took out my
access tokens so this code to is not how
it's like on the actual repo anymore
it's just typical I'll scroll I'm not
going to go through every line you set
up your server you out all your things
this is the code for Johnny Five to set
up a board you've got the function that
is making your Kron strings
for however you want it to feed it and
then the boards ready there's a servo if
you've got the listener for the board
connection and the web connection and
then you've got the feeding event so it
feeds the cat and that's great and then
there's also an event for the cron job
it's really simple code and then the
client code before I added routing was
just a button and a drop-down and now
this is what it looks like so basically
what happens is you hit feed me
immediately and it dispenses the food
which I'll show you really quick can you
switch the on button on me so I have it
here watch it not work I will cry you
push the button and it doesn't work okay
well it would it's not important i'll
show you later and then the casket food
it's great so you're almost ready to
open source I put a call on Twitter for
people to review my code and the
response was so good so many people
helped a lot um they refactored it so
that had happy um Jacob where are you
here somewhere oh there he helped fix my
code to it was really cool i was so
happy so they did all that Ashley made
Ashley Williams made it into a mpm
module um reviewed the readme for
language and they liked it it was great
my cats liked it too it worked they ate
it I got a really good jiff don't get
mad at me for saying jiff um I mean
brick likes food so he would have no
matter what but it made for a really
good thing so when I was ready to launch
I changed the repo to public I tweeted
about it I submitted a link to hacker
news and then I went to sleep and then
when I woke up I don't I wasn't quite
ready for what happened i was on the
front page hacker news people retweeted
it and saved
it so much there's like over 500 stars
now and github which is really cool and
I'm huge in Japan it was really me um so
basically the whole entire project
helped me realize a lot of things don't
be afraid of the unfamiliar because it
doesn't matter if you don't know it cuz
you will when you're done and definitely
don't be afraid to ask for help I
struggled with this for a really long
time I because I didn't want people to
assume that i didn't know what i was
doing so i would spend a really long
time trying to bug fix or figure out any
problems cuz i just wanted to do it
myself no matter how long it took and
now I'm lazy and I don't want to spend a
really long time doing stuff so I'll
just ask people to help me out and it
goes a lot quicker um also people really
like cat stuff more than me maybe um
also don't downplay your abilities uh
when I was almost done with the project
whenever I would tell people about it I
would be like it's not that impressive
but and I dusted who's right there would
they stop telling people that it's not
that impressive like just tell them
about it because it's cool also I like
note blocks a lot it's really fun it's
relatively easy even though it's kind of
stressful like when things don't work
when you're supposed to demo them yeah
it was it was really fun I'm going to
try and get it to work really quick okay
good you can't see my terminal oh wait
that's okay it disconnected i think that
makes sense okay we're up it's on are
you sure that the switch is on on is it
breathing okay great maybe it'll work
now okay oh you know what I wonder
I spent like twenty dollars on eight
bags of M&MS so I'm just going to keep
on pushing this please go eat some candy
if you want it because one more time
okay the last thing that I wanted to
talk about is trying to get this full
screen okay is my history with jazz comp
my first j/s comp was last summer so may
2014 I didn't know anybody here's a
picture of Tom Dale throwing a ball at a
dunk tank and there's me standing in the
background by myself watching because I
didn't know anyone this was the dunk
tank if you weren't there it was great I
actually dunked everyone besides Tom and
I think that's the only reason that like
Chris remembered who I was the next time
he saw me because I seriously I'm really
good at dunk tanks so I didn't really
know anybody besides the few co-workers
that I had and so I just would drink and
go in the pool every night by myself and
that's where I met this guy um he was
like you live in Brooklyn that's cool I
live in Brooklyn there's this really
great thing called Brooklyn jas you
should totally come and I did and um the
first Brooklyn jf said I went to I met a
lot of people I became friends with
Jennifer who now you can thank that for
horrible moments like this um and
she invited me to da HTML comp which is
a part of jazz fest in oakland where i
got my first speaking opportunity that
was a satirical talk about me being kind
of a big deal on the internet which was
basically history of all the bad things
that I've done on the internet since I
started building websites when I was
like 14 and then my first borough meetup
talk Jed close your eyes I Manhattan
jeaious is this really cool thing where
it's three technical talks and then a
passion talk which is I'm sorry I'll
just I'll go back um and I do special
effects makeup as a hobby it's really
fun and I like fake blood a lot and so I
made will Duffy look like he had a half
of a cut on a space so I met all these
great people and they really encouraged
me to be more comfortable with myself as
a developer and not be afraid to do
things so when it came to Jas comp this
summer it was vastly different I wasn't
staying to myself I was in a much better
mood I wasn't afraid to try stuff I
actually got to do things like I went to
the node BOTS thing and I built a robot
it was me it was really fun um I also
had to put this up there because I don't
think I'll ever forget anything about
lithium polymer batteries um but the
coolest thing that happened over the
summer was because of Jess calm I got a
job and I had my first interview in the
hot tub and I know that sounds horrible
but there was like 20 people in the hot
tub that
it was it was cool it was fine no code
of conduct was violated I just had an
interview in the flesh though Evan here
you know talking to all of you and then
on Monday I have to go to Portland and
talk about it again and it's
overwhelming but I don't think that I
would have done any of the things that I
have done in the past year or Matt like
half the people that I've met and became
friends with if it wasn't for Jas comp