okay so introductions I'm Marcus
Phillips I'm from hack reactor we're
almost goal teaching people to be
professional developers in 12 weeks so
every seven weeks a new group of people
shows up and we go through a lot of this
fundamental material and I've seen a lot
of people experience the same stuff over
and over again so I'm going to be kind
of guessing and anticipating what it is
that you are confused by as it happens
you've just come to the easiest session
of the entire week the secession is
incredibly easy it's know how do you
know node is just stunningly alarmingly
straightforward it is so simple for a
long time I thought known was like uh I
don't even know what I imagined it to be
it was budu for sure it was really
intimidating and I thought in colleges
complex I don't even know people said no
lots of passion denim I'm not sure
what's happening anymore one day I got
to sit down and learn note when I sat
down to learn note I you know I actively
researched it and try to figure it out
understand it and it got really got more
and more complex and sprawling until
finally I struck on what it really was
it's about one sense long what know it
is and that's all you need enough so
here's the sentence you're welcome to
walk up at Liam what I'm done node is
JavaScript it's not running in your
browser that's it let me just show you
some JavaScript running in a browser
let's go to the jsf website open up the
chrome console and say I don't know
three plus three good to know so
JavaScript running in my console and my
browser we're all very familiar with
this seems reasonable someone at one
point said okay maybe I want to get
access to
move some more stuff browse and puts you
in this little box maybe I want access
to some of that stuff sure maybe I want
baby I want to run JavaScript from the
hand line as a cron job raise your hand
if you've ever used to prom okay so
there you go you're working in the
command line you want to run JavaScript
type node boom tellin everybody go so
for whatever reason known has
accumulated this this steep as being a
really rich complicated thing and in
fact the ecosystem around node is pretty
nuanced and interesting but as a
fundamental concept if you're in the
room thinking I don't know what no it is
I don't know how it works on what I'm
doing believe it or not you're basically
done what I'm going to do next and this
is mainly going to be a mainly going to
be a quick demo followed by you guys
trying to do whatever brings you to this
room you go you start working on that
stuff again and our TAS will circulate
and try to help solve any problems
you're actually having on the basis of
having this orientation to them so the
slight differences that you're going to
encounter our a how you define files
right so in in the browser you make a
script file in imported using HTML tag
in node I hope it's all right that I use
Emacs no no you can't tell what's going
on there I'll Swiss something that has a
mouse and embarrass myself if I Emacs a
file like hello world James I can type
you know three plus three council blog
and console that log for poor just write
some random code and close it out and I
know just like I did before but I typed
it into the file hello world it does the
work that that code specifies a couple
of existing things where does the
console go while it goes into your
terminal what happened to the work that
I couldn't that didn't count becomes a
walk it got done the answer was computed
and in this case grown away but if you
can write JavaScript in any environment
you can write JavaScript it up so there
are some aspects of node that were
fundamentally differently the first is
how do you include other five how to
include files in the browser how do you
get one file of JavaScript to run there
had to be available to another five it's
a reference it with this script tag
right close you're correct but I'll
expand on your language to fully
specified you use script tags and in the
browser you have to specify you have to
include one script and then trust that
all of that code will have been executed
and hopefully it mutates the global
scope and then immediately after that in
the HTML file you write another script
and this new script will run in the same
global scope the fact that both files
run in one global scope is the only
point of interaction those two files get
this is kind of problematic you can't
for example happy where you can't write
a javascript file for the browser that
says and by the way i want this other
javascript file to run first you can't
use strip dependency management in
vanilla JavaScript you can't specify the
pendency in one screw in one file upon
another body you can't get that indicate
you can't get code to run and receive
the results as an input to a file as
something that only that file will have
access to it will have a local name for
that for that dependency that doesn't
work either it is all the mobile scope
every file that runs in the global scope
in the browser has access to the same
global area so they all just sort of
willy nilly right to the global
namespace and hope they don't trample on
each other and hope they run in the
right order this is the challenge that
we face in the browser people have
written some pretty good tools for
getting around that when hope started
writing known and saying we would like
to be we'd like this to be easier we
would like to be an easier story buried
porting hope they invented a syntax that
we use with required than exports so
let's take a look at that let's emacs
hello world again let's say I wanted
underscore let's say I have a copy of
underscore in fact I can download that
briefly no that's right that's right
r
ok
students
export study exports
go so in this file this is the
underscore file I've got the source code
for underscore approximately and because
i want i want the each function to be
available as part of the package that
i'm exporting I make the each function a
property of the exports object if courts
object one of the things that note gives
us to facilitate code being shared
between files exports is the objects
that will be made available to other
files when they require that thought
let's go to another file and say far
underscore let's give them more than
equals require dot slash underscore I'm
using dot slash because I mean it is in
the same folder so let's give it a shot
did it work we can't quite tell yet it
didn't fail didn't throw an error let's
log in log the underscore object that I
got back it seems to be an object that
has a each function on it right so this
is how you're going to write two files
of your own code that depend on want to
know are there any questions about how
you to do this goal but I don't want to
write out this for myself I want someone
else to write it and then I just want to
download so instead what I'm going to do
is take off this dot slash and that says
to note please give me the copy of
underscore that is in my packages in my
package management system summer let's
see if it works this will only work if
waiting
exactly so I've taken off dot slash to
clarify it suddenly naval undersea about
uh no that means facing express what
express I probably have a quick
statement heck they don't what is no no
Dale patty spelling one word unveiling
cool so I can require known mailer and
we know that I don't have closely so I
can't say dot slash I'd like to do taste
that i use a package from a hacked
management when I run hello world it's
like I don't know that so I have to
install a package I have two out I can
either install a locally to this project
Arkansas it going let's just too low
Clippers NPM note package manager helps
you load packages npm install novela
when I run my hello world again that has
required this thing there it is I am now
logging instead of underscore i'm
logging the note baylor module this is
what the note mailer module made
available to us ok one moment if we look
in my current project folder will see in
this list of files the node modules
folder when I am being installed that's
where I put it let's take a look inside
node modules there's no mail if I RM
node modules completely and I try to run
have a world again it's going to fail
again all i have to do is installed no
nailer again and it's going to bring it
back and put it in that's going to
invent that folder remember noted
modules is gone but as soon as i install
the male organ is going to come back so
that was the local install you now have
the ability to define a dependency on a
file on a package to you didn't right if
I want this to be available globally on
my system so that I never have to
install it for a new project ever again
I would just say that's G this means
that my whole system will have access to
it and it's a little more riddle because
I might accidentally start reading
software that depends on node veiler
without realizing that it's not going to
work anywhere that doesn't have it as a
global dependency instead I should
probably just install it locally and do
some work to make sure that that project
pulls in is dependency
and that is about it about all you need
to know the next thing I'd like to do is
turn it over to you guys to do the this
is a half hour session toxically happy
which is supposed to be hands-on you do
what you're working on and we can help
you solve whatever problem you have
we've got a couple of minutes over but I
think it's ok the next things I'd like
to do our answer questions you guys have
about this this basic stuff and then get
to having you guys write some scripts
that depend on one another and load
scripts that are next to each other from
files that are the same folder and then
maybe download and install some NPM
packages and fri playing with that once
you've done that you can write code that
interfaces with any of your hardware the
big punch line probably the main reason
to use node apart from the fact that the
browser is a bit complicated and not the
best target environment for all
applications is that no one has access
to hardware you can interface with
low-level libraries that talk to your
network card but don't need to go
through a dollar a jacket or something
like that they talk to your mouse
directly they talked to the primitives
of the system you can do file system
access info if you get done loading
scripts between between two different
files and you want to try to access a
file that seems like a good next step
extra credit there any questions before
we turn over to the independent exercise
yeah when you send that you have access
to it our work is well the code is being
compliant in the server right no one
actually is compiling
lying ah sorry you step the question was
you get access to the to the hardware
when the code is on the server not when
it's on the time and this is actually a
distinction that this is a spurious
distinction known code fundamentally
does not run on the client it doesn't
run in a browser it will never it will
never be shipped down to any one node
code is just JavaScript the interpreter
the environment being run without a
browser around so if the user if the
user has known on their computer and
they type node and the thing they will
have access to their own heart if you on
your server type node or whatever you'll
have your that process will have access
to your heart it takes a lot of work to
get any code to be shipped down to the
client even in know even in JavaScript
there are home old tutorials on how you
can use the node execution environment
to serve web requests and in so doing
you are fundamentally homely capable of
sending down files and perhaps their
browser is going to be rendering and
then then your client on the other end
will be subject to whatever constraints
that long time and fire attacks but on
your server you're going to be running
no through the command block furthermore
you can be running known from some
machine that is not its officer it's
just a machine into a search engine any
other questions okay sweet if you have
not already dabbled with it I encourage
you to find the documentation or node
these are all of the these are all the
packages available in tone
these are available that by default some
of them you might have to require they
all come as part of the note environment
when you need access to the
functionality that one of them offers
like for example console if you want a
lot of things out you might need to
include the console obviously we didn't
have to do that in my environment but
HTTP will probably have to bring it
yourself you need to make network calls
you don't have dollar Ajax anymore
you're going to have to require HTTP so
just remind you how you do that in here
is if our HTTP equals require
all that you've got
alright so please start a file using
terminal or your Windows user using uh
whatever they have and if you can get
two files one file to make an export and
the other files are loaded you're doing
good if you want to take further than
that RT is should be able to help you
with whatever puzzles your basic you got
about seven minutes before we start the
next session which is keyword this will
probably keep hanging out through the
break though it's a half-hour break in