hi I'm Juan I'm from Buenos Aires Xena
this here my whole life and I'm a
JavaScript developer I've been working
with well for the last 10 years probably
and I've recently joined yahoo a year
ago I've been part of the why I
community for a long time and I was
grateful to join the team there I'm kind
of sad to see it go in the last couple
of months but we're working on some new
siding projects justices from a DSS I
presented today under stuff around es6
and no tears applications ok so I'm am
pure JavaScript developer I actually
started doing some other stuff like PHP
and working with games but I eventually
specialized a lot in JavaScript I do
mostly big web big front end
applications and no Jas and I've slowly
become some sort of you know lawyer on
specifications and I'm hoping to get
involved with 279 and all the standards
process Jasper well i think i think we
stuck up a couple of you know hints at
where we're going with the web already
with such as in mr. dibbs presentation i
think we're going to see even more and
more intuition with childhood anywhere I
mean there was is talk like a stock
called the birth and death of java
script was written in which a guy told
the history of javascript and the future
of it in some sort of a fictional way
but eventually in this fiction just keep
ended up everywhere even in processors
and i think it's kind of a joke but
we're seeing that javascript is kind of
permeating everywhere from hardware to
robots to
built our reality so I think the web
will keep being this thing that connects
us all and at the core of it will be the
web platform things that we working on
today my talk was about
internationalization and you know it's
one of the core things in the web that
you don't think about you all the time
you're used to dealing with one or two
languages in our case like Spanish in
English but the web actually reach these
people in Africa in the east in our
countries that I speak Arabic countries
speak Chinese or Japanese and dealing
with language it could be kind of
complicated so we're working on things
that try to simplify I really happened
to be here being a you know one of the
things that you think oh maybe I could
give a talk or not but I'm really
impressed and I'm really happy to see a
really great audience that come here to
learn with a an open mind and I think
that's something you don't see every day