ah
I'm Mike this is Evan and as our wives
like to say we are technology life
partners so if we do everything together
but we're here to talk about spackle
we're members of the spot for 14 and
it's we're here obviously representing
the community there's a lot of work
that's gone into what about to show you
most of it is not ours which is cool we
get to present and them a lot of stuff
that that we haven't done only just just
a 12 or one demo stuff that we build so
yeah so so this is pretty cool so we're
just going to jump right into sprout
core um so what a sprout course Brock or
is the way to make blazing fast native
style web apps so sort of a buzzword
right now and um how does parkour do
that we sort of take what the power of
the browser eat and also its constraints
to try to do the right thing which is
going to be the most fast thing for the
web and um like new technology to come
out like html5 and you know we don't
really take a position on the spec when
we use html5 we sort of mean sort of the
technologies around like the cool
features like the cool video tag video
tag audio tags so awesome humbly and
respectfully I'm gonna have to disagree
with Pope crockford the first that html5
isn't really from the devil it's not
going to make you go blind it's not
going to put hair on your palms I've
tried it many times so you know we think
that using html5 you know can be
difficult can be a kind of the Wild West
but for for sprach room make it a very
simple and very easy to use there's some
really cool some really cool stuff okay
so we just went 1 point 0 earlier this
year and we have all these really cool
features but the thing about sprout core
applications is that people don't it's
hard to to know what sprout quarry is
you kind of have to see it for yourself
right so so to show you what a sprout
crap looks like we're going to kind of
give you a quick look at our day job and
we're gonna bring up our boss this is
sewage it gupta he's the
is the vice president development where
we work he's our boss and he's going to
demo this proper up that we've built on
our day job morning's you all right once
your whole damn life all right so while
they're bringing this up just to give
you a little context so eloquent okle
company we're a market leader and demand
generation we have over 700 customers
something like over 30,000 users we've
been around for 10 years so when my
Kevin and I joined two years ago we were
given the awesome job of turning that
company and to bring them into the new
you know technology set and we had to
write a user interface that i'm going to
show you on top of three million lines
of vb code on the back end we do two
billion transactions a day so this is
truly a large-scale application and in
fact it there's a talk I'll you know see
how built that's all so what we want to
do is we wanted to set out and build
something that's gonna be an awesome
experience desktop like you know people
forget that they're running a web app so
let me show you that so when you come
into our app you first come and see this
beautiful dashboard for those of you OS
10 fans and I don't see Tony max here
today but you know you'll see that it's
all too familiar paradigms right you can
add widgets you can remove widgets you
come into what we call our campaign
canvas this is basically where you go in
and create our marketing campaigns and
what a marketing campaign is is that
give you a story that you some of you
will participate in a week and a half
from now we're actually having a
Northern Virginia javascript meetup at
our office so there'll be beer and pizza
and some more cool demos so we're going
to use our own software to send out the
invitation for that so first we did a
segment in marketing terms where we're
going to take people that attended GS
hunt and then those people that live in
you know Virginia Maryland and DC we're
going to send you guys an email and then
we're going to if you click on that
email you get to a landing page and you
submit the fact that you want to show up
and what kind of pizza you want so once
you've done that then we automatically
send you a reminder and one other thing
we're going to do is let's say that you
don't plan to come so we might add
another step that if you do not click on
the email you'll see how interactive
this is you can just come in and connect
this program step to it and now if you
do not
the email maybe we'll send you a
newsletter and I'll use some other way
right so let's take a look at some of
the real interactivity here so you can
see that as you move this around now if
this is all open source this framework
Evan wrote and one of our colleague
Jonathan has been using this this is
available so if you want to build
something like this you can go get the
open source framework now let me show
you another part here so let's take a
look at the email so this is like
spotlight type search so we're going to
do a GS let's type end up so you get
your familiar search results so I had to
steal some pirate themes nurse so I you
know branded our email with the GS comp
logo and I even got a skull and
crossbones in there but you look at this
app this is kind of like a typical
desktop iWeb style app so as you move
things around you know it will resize
you'll see and if the snappy blue lines
are visible here but as you move it
around it shows the centering lines and
so on again open source everything that
we've built that has nothing to do with
Tahlequah I've really pushed the team to
open source that so that it's available
to the community we've taken a lot from
the community and so we want to give
back so let me show you just a couple
more things so you know we have a lot of
aspects of the system you can go in and
do set up and you'll see all these
transitions you know they're all desktop
like so we really wanted to essentially
have you forget that you're in a web app
I mean our marketing users they're very
creative people we wanted them to you
know I say to people that there's three
categories of apps there the suck to use
apps there are the easy to use apps what
we're building is what I want to call a
joy to use that where you come back for
more you actually enjoy your experience
so anyway that's my spiel alright thanks
sewage it so that's that's what we do in
our day job we're pretty proud of what
we were of what we built and it's all
due to sprout core so it's pretty cool
stuff but anyway okay so back to spark
or back to sprout poor right so where
are we so you know open source
communities how do you measure success
in open source community so there's a
lot of ways you got logos right how much
money is being invested you also have
libraries how many libraries bed bill
apps are being built on your project how
many Forks do you have on github maybe
and how much money or your company is
offending on oh yeah so one thing that
we think is important in sproul core is
developer engagement you know it's no
secret that a lot of the core team for
Spock word is is that Apple but it's
actually the team the sprout park
community was actually lot bigger than
that so and just to give you a sense of
that so this is the set of features that
we start off with 2010 right right so
this is the core team kind of got
together in the beginning of the year
tried to figure out the 8 things that we
really wanted to complete this time so
now we're here we are in April about a
third of the way through so let's eat
let's see how far away so we go wow yeah
because like that's Paul Shaffer right
there oh wow yeah hi we've gotten those
five things done but you know that's
exciting but that's not the most
exciting thing we also have these 16
other features that were completely
introduced and put into the sprout core
framework by external members of the
community yeah people that weren't an
apple people like people like us just
much guys so there's so all over the
place so we find that very exciting and
you know honestly we could talk about
every one of these features but we
really want to focus only on three right
so we have to boil it down because you
know we have 45 minutes so here we go so
the first thing we want to talk about is
common j/s so last year I went about
comedy is at this conference and I
thought well this is really cool and
actually a lot of guys in the core team
thought the same thing and so what
school is with sprout core 15 which is
the next version that we're working on
so now we've gone in 10 we're actually
going to be fully common jazz compliant
all our stuff is going to be built with
common J's packages and I'm just modules
excuse me and and the bill tools which
are now Ruby are going to be completely
in JavaScript witches which is pretty
cool but you know as we were doing this
we kind of had a problem because we
wrote all our code before Common j/s
existed and probably a lot of you did as
well and we thought well can we build a
tool that will help us do this with with
the with with with the code that we have
that's not written for common J's and
that helps us solve the problem of
sharing because come and jess is great
for module
but we still can't share our code right
so so there you know the most
communities like Ruby and Python have to
solve this with the gems and eggs and
stuff like I could manage right so
package managers so we looked at all the
package managers and found that they
didn't really help us in the way that we
had with mikes big problem I mean with
the big problem that Mike pointed out
yeah being able to take large amounts of
existing code and make it easy
convertible into common GS so we'd like
to offer the community we've been
working on this thing called CJ s why i
personally has you know as the community
has I've been working on CBS and this is
we're trying to solve that that problem
of making it very easy to take existing
code and put it in there and share it
with everybody right so um this is how
you would install a package of and to be
used in your software so it's one line
command easy this is actually using the
package so it's just you know you just
do some requires and then use the motion
sensor code looks pretty simple pretty
simple um it's built into extend so it
uses get under the covers so when you
fork that you fork a package and it
makes a local version so you can edit it
okay whether you're telling me I don't
have to go dig into some library
directory and copy oh okay it does it
specifically open house built in okay I
like that so I mean you guys may not
like it but i like it i mean so in
packing is when you want to save it onto
a web server this is for like
client-side stuff and it sort of minify
zit and makes the easy to use it's like
build tools built in are so if you want
to push a package that you've done it's
just a single command it goes up there
so all this stuff is pretty simple
pretty easy so I'm going to hopefully do
a short little demo of this um yeah we
go to the command line all right you
know what let's blow the font up let's
pull the phone up in here hang on let me
go to you and get you okay so tech oh
can you blow the spawn top yeah I can't
man plus there you go bigger more bigger
I want more you want it yes all right
more okay
I technology life partners remember ok
so I get more what it's not even going
shift shift command shift hey yeah yes
not now you're in the sorry yeah I'm
good okay so um very simple this is
actually beautify ASI don't know if
everybody seen this it's just a library
jayus library that i found on the i
cloned it brought it down i just made
this one directory where i put index.js
which is actually the same code as
beautified ijs this is doing some smart
defaults and the only other file i need
to add in here said I mean um down at
the bottom I just I need to add this one
line exports beautify j/s beautifly okay
one line of code one line of code to use
this okay and then in the package Jason
this is like telling it I need just
these two things the name of the package
and then the version that we said is
that semantic versioning it's a semantic
right I can't do anything but semantic
versioning yes semantic versioning so I
already did have five so we can see that
you can update like this is a case where
you cloned it make a new version
excellent save it um and now let's go
you guys can you guys read this when you
make this bigger okay how's that that's
good that a little bit better that looks
good alright and now we just do seed
push
and it's pushing it up and now it's up
on the CJ s server so that's all I had
to do to actually import this thing and
that server is all written in JavaScript
right it's all written in JavaScript
it's using nodejs on v8 right now but it
can be easily ported to any JavaScript
meant background platform right okay so
let's actually use um this so I also
leave you that I'd you know you're just
tricking me so my music pushed it up
there now let's install it seed install
jeaious so one line command installs it
now that's not version that I just put
up there let's go so to use it i just
added a bunch of stuff here so make that
bigger all right sure so we can read
that code because I there we go don't
trust you okay so I just require JSP you
to Phi which the package and there's
another native package called assist to
do some print out things because we're
going to do run it from the command line
because this is going to be server code
just passing some regular JavaScript
that's enough formatted and then we're
going to beautify it and spit it out so
this is all we should be able to should
have to do four finger swipe down I know
oh no stinky no sticky fingers hairy
palm hairy palms too much html5 Pope
croc all right so all right here we go
okay so wow so please purchase it pretty
printed it out server side you can do it
with client side code and it makes it
easier we've already poured it over a
bunch of libraries yep that are up there
so you can even look at that so okay so
now is the part where I get to tell you
that okay we're all in the JavaScript
community here and it would be really
really good if we had a package manager
guys okay we are all still on islands of
code I mean c'mon Janice is part of the
solution but we really do need to sort
of unite around a package manager it
doesn't have to be this one doesn't have
to be this one we're just offering this
up as as a potential solution but we do
need to unite around something so please
go and download it play with it and tell
us if this works for you because you
know it
actually make a huge difference for us
as a community of JavaScript errs if we
can just have a JavaScript package
management if you just look at the stats
one like egg and Jim came out like you
see the explosion of the community and
different packages that people use and
different projects to come out so you
know and imp and impassioned play ok so
that was CJ s so it's quick simple and
it uses really it's very easy to use
existing code for it looks really easy
and look pretty good never use elected
I'm gonna try it ok next thing we want
to talk to you about is interface
builder um as for sprout core we sort of
been a little bit late in the game here
um you know you've seen like eh tjs
there's a couple of ones out there and
you know we felt like we didn't want to
start doing it before we were pre 10
because the API was changing and now
with the API static and you know we can
support this API we don't want people
building stuff with the UI to the UI
machine and with the interface builder
and not having a change underneath them
so we also wanted to decide that oh
we're calling it greenhouse yes now it
is greenhouse and this is particularly
the thing that might decide what we've
been working on for the last two months
or so about two months we really like
the logo so let's just look at that logo
enough with the logo okay next slide so
we want to innovate in some small way
you know interface builders haven't
changed a lot in the last 20 years old
in some small way we wanted to try and
push it forward a little bit so the
first thing we wanted to do was sort of
clean up the UI a lot of these you'll
see and like they have all these panels
and it's like well there's your UI in
that little box okay the too small so we
we've blown it out so it's all this is
your whole UI and we've just cleaned it
up and it's just the top bar and the
bottom and that's all you've got and
then the rest of it's just your UI so
and we also have these Pickers that come
up when you need them and you tear them
off and if you want to hover them and
you can dock them to the side if you
want to as well and you can close them
get rid of them when you're done okay so
this is a big one so the other thing we
wanted to do is we want to solve the
blue box problem so for four years this
is what real
face builders look like I don't know if
you guys have a reviews interface
builder but you have blue boxes because
these are all custom views and the guys
that wrote the interface builder didn't
know about these custom views so you
know they don't have pretty pictures for
them and you don't want to write extra
code for them because you've gotten out
of time so so you just got blue boxes
and we think that sucks and so well so
that's what it would look like and so
here's what looks like in greenhouse so
here's a similar you actually about the
same and so you can see we've got all
the custom views in and the way we're
able to do this is the magic of iframes
we actually load your entire application
in a suspended mode we like suppress
main and we keep it from running and the
whole thing lows and so we can access
your custom views and render them and
draw them and you don't have to write
any code it's really great all right so
it's going to transition next ok so
finally yeah well what we wanna site we
kind of feel like building you eyes with
an interface builder is an inalienable
right of doing a web application
framework so we are offering this to the
community for free right right now free
it's completely some people want to
charge you money for this but we think
that this should be free so this is free
it's on sprout PortMaster right now you
can play with it today so and now we're
going to i believe show you a demo so
i'm going to attempt to do this all
right so so on the third tab so let's
get rid of this and
oh we do want chrome but we also want
okay so this is what green house looks
like so I've got a simple little app
then fired up loads loads the app up
give it a second here to to load up and
so now here it is loading your app in
suspended mode okay so BAM now we're up
so now we can just open up our page
files and for all of you that have built
sprout perhaps this is backwards
compatible with all existing sprout
four-page files it's the exact same file
so it just works so we can bring up our
main page and so as you can see we've
blown out the design area it's really
clean and empty and this is what I've
just generated a really this is like if
you type SC git or svn it's Brock or app
this is what you get so this is like
what you would see maybe there still is
a blue box problem here I can't tell um
we'll see okay so um here's our so we
can move our label element around we've
got a little inspector that's like we
can pop up right there we can also get
to it from up here and sort of tear it
off and put it over there we can open up
our library pain let's add a button we
already have the propagator open so i'm
going to do that let's change the title
will say hello jayus comp I'm very
limited so I have to speak what I type
all right so let's talk about our layout
control so we can anchor obviously you
know this is a an application framework
so you use absolute positioning and you
can just anchor this to the top center
it so let's say we Center this one here
let's just make this 0
and 0 and this one let's anchor tap top
okay ideas okay perfect let's save that
and then we'll run it let's tear this up
whoops will tear this off so we can
resize it so you can see that whoops it
did in fact set the layout so the button
is centered and the label is anchored to
the top as you can see so yes in fact we
can affect the labels and so this is the
code that it outputs and there's this
big warning that says you can't really
edit this in you can if you think you
know what you're doing but do it at your
own risk so now we're going to do
something a little bit more interesting
have we solved the blue box problem
where is the terminal there okay so
we're going to i'm just going to write a
custom view real quick and then we're
going to load it into a greenhouse and
we're going to use it so let's just try
this we're going to generate this view
and now you get to see what it looks
like to write a custom Spronk overview
so the generator ran and now we're going
to find a property called color when it
started with READ&WRITE our render
method will read this function
and die install this I think it's got a
call he does not the coloring okay so
now we're gonna say context add style
something right ok background color and
we're going to say this get
color property right and lastly we want
this to redraw whenever that color
property changes so we're going to say
display a display properties array okay
so there we go simple custom views so
now because we load this thing in an
iframe we actually have to reload the
app so I'm going to tell reload so so
while we wait for this to reload wait
for it to reload okay so we have a small
bug here and I will fix there we go okay
so here's our page that we were on
before and let's add our custom view to
our library so it was called colors duck
color i'm going to set a layout we give
a dull fault lay out so that it's just
not really big and huge winged dragon on
nice okay so now some are just drag this
puppy and then so there's our custom
view rendering no extra code BAM okay so
let's do something a little a little bit
more interesting with this let's do some
findings shall we text field it's at a
controller down here we're going to call
it color controller
and as you would expect to just drag
these lines I'm option dragging so it
draws the line for the binding so we're
going to bind from that color property
and we're just going to add it to a
property called color on this controller
because this is JavaScript you don't
really have to predefine anything we
just say you know color and that's the
property that will bind that too and
then this text feel really the same
thing except for the text field is
called value to that same color property
okay BAM so let's save that and run it
with any luck you now have the blue box
problem again okay so there you go
that's greenhouse simple and free yes
it's free so that's greenhouse so this
like I said we've been working on this
so it's out today you can check it out
and play with it and it's sort of a
Developer Preview they're still bugs
like you saw and but I'm we're actually
working on yes so been working on for
about two months and we've done our day
job that mean that like so after hours
trying to figure it out ah but will we
will actually be building apps on this
oh and there's one more thing I wanted
to show you just so you can see that it
works with with bigger apps so here's
there's a big there's an open source
project that sujit wrote first proper
called tasks and this is a big hairy
existing sprout corps app and you load
it up and it loads and these are all
custom views and yes in fact you can
manipulate all the custom views and do
whatever you want with them so there you
go that's greenhouse
ok so that was greenhouse and last thing
we want to do is talk about touch this
may give your hairy palms um warning
warning so common knowledge is you know
that touch is actually very difficult to
do and very difficult to do in the web
um one of the you know we thought so too
and then we decided hey why don't we
just try this why don't we try to try to
do this gun bunch of guys an apple and
bunch of guys outside in the community
started working on it and we worked
really hard over the last I think these
last six months or so to get touch
support natively in time inside of
sprout core um you know and we it worked
and we actually got it so we actually
have it in it's an edge right now you
know download and start to use it and
it's a very simple API it's almost like
you doing the normal sprach or touch
event I mean a mouse events and
everything like that so um and with very
little extra code so we're going to show
you right now is a really boring demo so
these are the sample demo controls in
the desktop just so you have for a frame
of reference so so these are the mouse
events this is what it looks like not
really exciting just you know not
anything crazy going on and then
hopefully without too much awkwardness
we will switch ok so about a couple of
months ago a device came out that nobody
really paid attention to and we think
this represents one of the greatest
revolutions and web applications it may
not have half eaten fruit on the back
it's probably going to be some other
device but the idea of a touch large
device that everybody uses is going to
be something that's very very prevalent
so let's look at the samples out see
we're gonna have to do some rigging here
to get this to work hi guys all right
all right all right it looks pretty good
it's not tear won't some terrible is not
terrible ok so with touch events two
buttons exactly just like it before we
have click events on each one of these
things
let's go to check boxes click on the
checkbox got progress bars so all these
things are the stuff that we've sort of
ported over and we've got lists you know
they got cool bouncing cruel scrolling
oh sorry there we go see if we get it
okay yeah there you go okay okay so
enough now rotate it oh wait i know it's
fine i got to find we got on okay so you
can see we got the automatic list as a
picker so you get all this for free
because we handle all the extra code for
you here so this is pretty cool touch
it's not up for you know one of the
other difficult things we serve a scroll
lists and a scroll lists see they said
it couldn't be done so you see there
squirt less in there I'm sorry I had a
fireball on my throat okay so this is
really cool it's really exciting uh but
let's see what people who do so after we
got the touchdown were working and not
made or the community community got
touched demo we made a call out to see
what people could build with this touch
interface it's like two weeks ago this
is sassy Oh basically hey guys we have a
presentation of james Kalm can you build
us some Touch apps and so in two weeks
we're going to show you three apps that
the guys have thrown together what's up
orange shirt so you guys have seen the
NPR app right sorry so
really smooth scrolling we got
multi-touch action going on with this
app let's see I think you can drill into
a story like this and it loads we can we
can play the you can listen to her own
direction so there's a yeah go back keep
going with all this stuff at the same
time so um and so but Mike I wanted to
show them the native app which ones that
oh right this is this is sprout core
guys being used on days so this is the
application that people didn't think was
going to be able to be made right so I'd
like to show you guys the actual NPR app
this is the one that's out on the iPad
normal one on the ipad right this is the
sprout core one no don't cry have more
demos oh yeah it crashes nice so the
sprout for one comes up native one
crashes okay all right see you've gotta
wait why guys what Oh what does the deal
okay so it doesn't even work okay hang
on so sprout course a big improvement
over Objective C because it actually
works all right guys no I'm they worked
really hard on this I know they did okay
there we go there we go okay so let's
see if we can do I know if you can see
we can square soon so so you can see
actually the sprout core is hardware
accelerated wear this actually has to
run through a bunch of stuff it's not as
hardware accelerated so it's actually
smoother on the sprout corps app than it
is on the native objective-c and also I
think you yeah so there you go so there
you go so the app that couldn't be built
we didn't think I'm to be honest we
weren't sure it could be built either
and you know we're just blown away with
what some community member was able to
build right and to do it so that's not
the only app that we'd like to show
fired up dude alright we saw you this is
all about the twee
the Twitter okay so I'm not going to
bore you guys with writing in my
password there you go so we think this
is cool we are building web applications
that are as good as the native apps and
with a lot less code I mean these guys
through these things together in a week
and I guarantee you that if you compared
the objective-c code to the JavaScript
code the stock or code you would you
would take the JavaScript code every
single time I were trying to log into
this twitter app sorry sorry got the
wrong password I know it's calling it
struggle oh it's your mom's password
okay really okay so see bouncing just
like it is and the other cool thing
about this just bouncing scrolls
bouncing scroll so all these things are
like the normal picker panel we can
tweet
typing on the video this is exciting I
know sorry just anything will work yeah
cool all right so the other exciting
part is all this works offline so you
can actually save this to your home page
and that's actually what this is save to
your home page so it almost acts exactly
like a native app so this is sort of
like a huge revolution that we can see
so we got one more apt to show you guys
this will be a little excitement I got
are you going so this is a little
documentation app yeah I'll hold it for
you well oops yes that's the CEOs iPad
to the Barbies so here's our these are
god's little docs appt so these are the
sprout court docs so really smooth
scrolling you show you how to do the
touch bends so this is explaining how to
do the touch events we can fire up the
example and then we get the little
sample code and we get the multi-touch
so how does this happen it's single
threaded Oh like I don't know where's
the work it's it's the magic of sprout
core and it's little red gnome green
known hey let's play up Rock'em Sock'em
robots robots all right oh all right all
right okay so if you really want to get
worked on their source code that tells
you how to how to write these this is
our little document of yours all these
all these apps will be will post these
on the sprout for website so you guys to
be able to go and play with these so go
check out the blog post and they should
be out should be up soon by the end of
the day if you rotate this that's lot so
we get a rotation event it does do the
little guy thing like we saw before when
we can flip documents really just a
gorgeous app great way to and this was
done in less than a week guess was so
here's another demo that won't stick
fingers take over the screen with red or
not okay pretty cool alright alright so
that's that's what we have and switch
this around so we think that's really
exciting and
school is this your like this is your
chat channel it is yeah it is haha chats
was Evan it's nice on my IRC channel
okay alright so this is how you get in
touch with us go to our website and
check out those auto demos so the three
things common Jas it's great thing we
need to get behind a package manager
please go check out CLC James and you
know any comments that you make please
we have a RSC channel just post some
comments and stuff like that and what we
want to do to change it join the project
I'm not the google group mailing list as
well if you have all the mailing list
and go check out spray wore those dumb
is that you just saw are going to be up
there you can get in touch with Mike me
and Charles who you know started sprout
boerum and everything brains behind the
operation so those are the last thing so