oh man it's been so amazing I this is my
J's conf 2010 was my first ever tech
talk ever and I only got in because
Felix caisson Dover couldn't make it
because in icelandic volcano so that was
my intro to this whole thing and it's
been an amazing ride just to see the
conference grow and the community grow
on the conference super amazing which is
why i am super-psyched Chris and I have
been working on this for a while and I
want to let you guys know that Chris and
I are taking can Henderson open source
it's not ready yet but next month on
github the entire genome as a JSON file
if you want llamo he's got an issue a
full request so thank you can sorry
about that we can truncate if you want
or at school darn it but no seriously I
was actually gonna give a talk about the
this tech like I di had that was like a
thing but like I was like well this
seems like really really good timing to
give a talk about building community
this is last call which do you rember
the Semisonic song closing time you
don't have to go home but you can't stay
here so the idea is well if it is
closing time let's what do you do in a
bar closes you go home and you drink at
home hopefully with other people but
definitely not in the bar that's closed
so I want to talk I want to talk to you
about building barodius and so first of
all tell you what board Jace is if you
don't know borgeous is four months sorry
monthly events ok so there's Brooklyn
jeaious there's a matin je s there's
Queens Jas and there's Jersey script ok
so these are things that didn't exist
you know even two years ago the last jus
that i was at was 2013 none of the stuff
existed and now two years later we have
this all amazing community Brooklyn jsu
know Brooklyn that is where I live you
know who'd you know I guess Bernie
Sanders was born there Hillary Clinton
headquarters there Manhattan Jas this is
Manhattan obviously it's the city who
lives there Donald Trump you might know
him
david koch of the koch brothers he might
know them Tom Dale lives in hatton gives
you a kind of a flavor of that Queens if
you don't know Queens it's very
interesting because it's kind of a
holding pen when your price out of
Brooklyn but before you retire to
Florida that's you live in queens and
then Jersey script is obviously I don't
tell you a lot of interesting j/s
products humor come out of that from jen
schiffer to Jon Stewart so that's our
family this is beau geste I don't tell
you it's like literally you cannot swing
a dead cat in New York without hitting a
javascript meetup now it is amazing
every week of the year there is a
javascript meetup it is so amazing and
it's like just it's an amazing so I want
to tell you the story of these ten
people this is that 10 did I kept that
right off by one no okay I know how what
we'd like how we took you know the
JavaScript community from like kind of
lame to like pretty cool so I'm gonna
take it all the way back to 2013 i was
living in tokyo i was there was my first
tech job and I you know I decided to
actually move to Brooklyn and so I was
super super psyched you know in Japan
Brooklyn is like a huge brand like
there's like bars named Brooklyn and you
can go and have a cocktail name type of
Brooklyn and then when you're hungover
the next day you can have Brooklyn
pancakes and then like you'd only have
pancakes you know mister donuts and they
give you as like swag like Brooklyn jar
which is just literally a mason jar
called they call it a Brooklyn jar cuz
it's more of a Brandon Mason who I
actually looked up he has nothing to do
with Brooklyn except he died there
that's it this is probably my favorite
they have Brooklyn roasting company is
an actual Brooklyn legit Brooklyn
roaster in brooklyn on j street an at
brooklyn roasting company in tokyo they
sell brooklyn brewery beer which they
didn't do it in america so it's like
clearly just a brand i scrub stuff i was
interesting that i was interested in
moving in brooklyn because John Resig
the guy who basically taught me
JavaScript lives there he lives in Park
Slope this guy Jeremy ashkenaz who like
built all the stuff that I was using at
the time like backbone and coffee script
and underscore he bought that he lives
in
brooklyn heights this guy Ryan doll you
know 2009 where note came out that was
Ryan doll to give you some perspective
here this is after he was John Lennon
but before he was sleepy Douglas
Crockford kind of in the middle so I get
to Brooklyn and there's a thing because
yes I'm like awesome I'm gonna go meet
all these folks at meetups and like it
had been defunct a year leader because
their final meetup can actually do this
Yazoo min herre their final meetup was a
beer Jess Brian LaRue and that's when
the meat offended no don't invite deer
meat up so that was kind of faded by the
wayside I was like okay let's cast the
net a little wider there's got to be
like and my CC no I CJ s actually really
good meetup actually went long time ago
I met Aaron Quint there that was super
awesome and I checked their website and
you look at their last year meetups and
they're all sencha touch meetups which
is like that that's what kind of ass
code smell for a for a meetup if it's
like literally one technology so that
was kind of not cool basically it was a
total wasteland there was no one okay
maybe Will Smith in his dog but always
no one and so I was like well that's
kind of sad that we don't have seen here
oh well I guess they moved you for
nothing but then I decided to let go to
some other parts of the world and see
how they did commute me and conferences
and stuff i went to austin by the way
this is tilt shift from Apple maps it's
amazing that sort of like not an actual
photo I went to Austin that was super
cool i went to TX JSI met brian j
Brennan who is I will talk about later
txt is a super awesome a regional
conference I highly highly highly
recommend it I guess it's now again
maybe the one of the largest in the US
now coming in 2016 went here to amelia
island that was super cool because like
there's all you awesome folks and i had
a really good time here and then i went
to Berlin and then I went to reject jas
which is inspired by a conference that's
inspired by this one which is kind of
amazing then I went to see us coffee you
and that was another conference it was
inspired but kind of inspired by me
jaise conf EU inspired cska vu they kind
of run as a pair that was really cool
they let me do some cool stuff I gave an
entire presentation in CSS about the
Berlin Wall and I use the border
collapse that was a
it was it's funny in German okay hey I
went to JS conf they let me crowd surf
they let me sing songs this one is I
sang nice that's nice this is me singing
under the sea with many Lauderdale to
say an objective-c I'm not going to do
it now so don't ask that was super super
fun and then I got back to Brooklyn like
wait a minute this is still kind of a
wasteland that kind of sucks we should
totally change this all of this inspired
stuff that I had done for you know over
the course of a few months it was super
super awesome and totally wanted to
bring that home so I was want to take
jeaious comp and like shrink it down to
8.3 3 333333 percentage size and then
like spread it over a year that was kind
of like the idea take that vibe and that
was that was my idea behind Brooklyn J
yes and so I ran into this garbage
monster Brian J Brennan future at that
point future speaker at JS coffee gave
he closed Jeff last year in 2014 with
the talk called being human which is
weird cuz he's not a human he's a
garbage monster he's in a shoegaze band
he's super cool shoegaze they call
shoegaze because they look at their
shoes while they're playing guitar he
didn't even see the shoes because he has
so much hair sorry he appreciates craft
beer he he appreciates his pictures of
him appreciating craft beer that's
really cool he also owns one shirt
little secret her yeah so we're like
Ryan let's do this let's let's take this
Jess calm flavor which are both familiar
with and let's like shrink it down and
like turn it into like a like a monthly
thing so what do we do of course copy
everything Chris Williams does so
weekend so yes basically let's take this
model and you know it's it i mean he's
basically i mean he would you know the
two of us did it together was he was
basically the laura williams to my chris
williams except for the fact that i did
all the work so he was basically chris
way as to my laura wings that's cool
we're not give you know the details
there but we went to chris's repo and we
and we copied his logo and we made our
own and like a kind of a subway motif
after the j train in the s train neither
which i recommend taking we made a
website that's kind of like a like a
metro like a subway map
we made posters we copy the code of
conduct which is like that's like such a
no-brainer slam dunk now that like you
know if you have JavaScript community
they're probably probably been here and
they probably are familiar with it so
that makes everything so much easier
it's one less thing to shave a yak on
which is really nice or bike shed no no
or the same thing I leavin now anyway
j/s code of conduct is such a slam dunk
it's basically it's like it's a no
smoking sign for your meetup like it's
like just it's like it's so easy so I
really am so glad that I Chris did that
because it makes it easier for the
organizers to not just the attendees
because you can you don't have all sort
of fuzzy think and while you're doing
the event you got a fine line which is
super super nice so we got the code of
conduct we got the logo get the posters
we found a really nice venue we totally
lucked out on this it is a super super
cool bar they have all sorts of awesome
craft beer like set bud light lime
that's like local this is actually a map
of like a distorted map where Brooklyn
zoo JH of basically the mid-atlantic and
New England stage super cool it's like a
really awesome vibe you know it's cool
because it's like in Japanese magazines
that are like all about Brooklyn that
was really cool oh cool so we found a
venue that was awesome oh yeah rap
battle had a rap out with Oakland
Oakland is basically the Brooklyn of San
Francisco I guess and so I was talking
smack to sub stack that was cool yeah
and that was it and then we were like so
we deal of planning and we said you know
we look put tickets on and like it was
free awful idea and then lit literally
sold out in like an hour and like you
know I had to send an email everyone
like hey guys remember the thing was the
tickets for free well guess what they're
not for you got to pay five dollars and
then tickets allowed again I was like ah
so anyway it was fine there were five
dollars which is such a bargain
especially New York City so the idea is
this we would do five talks it would
just be 5 10 mint lightning talks of
course gonna start with John Resig
because he likes started it all for me
at least don't start of meet up without
having him speak at your first meetups
my place we had a lot of awesome other
folks help out there's Jen shipper she's
taking a selfie but I think she gave a
talk after that she's super awesome
person to have in the committee I can't
imagine the New York scene without her
you have a lot of journalism in New York
so rich Harris from the Guardian you get
visions asset from the New York Times
and Michael Donahoe from The New Yorker
you have here some familiar
there's our jhemini giving a talk about
anchor points number ember component
sorry and so she gave a talk there's
Tracy giving a talk if you like familiar
faces here some more there is a me and
there's Pam and there's no sucky and
there's Earl and there's Lynn and
there's Jane and they have all spoken
Brooklyn Jace there's Charlie a confined
picture of no no why and then there I
don't have a picture yet but this is
Rachel who is it was right there she's
speaking actually this month at Brooklyn
jas and he or she is singing karaoke in
Brooklyn with Michael Rogers about it
was a such a meta moment it was amazing
really early for all cool folks New York
we have really awesome folks in the area
as his amigos cook doing stuff a code
Lauren we had tiny subversions come down
from Boston this is he makes these
amazing apps this is where we're kind of
leaving JavaScript doing like more like
webby stuff kind of broadening a little
bit he does this thing where it like
literally takes definitions from a
dictionary and like girl you must be a
blank because definition of thing it's
an amazing go to that website it it's so
good other things we have Bloomberg
sponsor of this conference Bloomberg had
this amazing article called what is code
who read this did anyone read this
you're lying you did not read the whole
thing it's like 38 thousand words no way
and actually so he came in he gave a
talk about like how the color background
color actually changes the more you
scroll down the more you read so if you
take a screenshot he knows that you
didn't read it it's amazing anyway so he
gave a talk about that that was really
really cool that was by the way the
best-selling issue of Bloomberg of 2015
so awesome awesome work we had marine
have Rebecca come talk about all the
stuff he's doing with whiskey whiskey
whims that was really cool we had oh
this guy oh yeah oh yeah Brendan Eich in
my meetup that was really cool who he
had this these are all hot takes this is
amazing this is so true Microsoft is
Mozilla right am i right oh it's amazing
so you heard it a Bricklin Jays first
and then so he spent about two and a
song about that and he literally spent
about like ten minutes playing video
games so I'm just saying you're warned
if you would invited her to your meetup
he's going to play video games we had
really cleared these two guys we
actually so we started doing let's do
stuff with other languages
go for those of you not familiar with Go
Go is basically the language to which
javascript is retire to when they get
old it's the Florida of programming
languages basically as I'm saying that's
cool we had this guy can't see him
because it's so dark that's not neo
that's Martin klebba this is the thing
it's a quine it's like running itself to
create the whole thing that blew my mind
this is van Newman doing stuff is like
we did like we started doing a hardware
themed event so here this thing where
like he had a camera that filmed all
these random lights in the wall and then
like calibrated it and would like move
his hand like light would change in like
Aaron goes yeah the guy who runs the bar
that we hold a meetup in actually made a
custom popsicle sticks tamper like an
automated one so like he we had like
custom popsicles with booze in them that
was super awesome but the best part and
probably the best thing we've ever had
was this one this is super mario
brothers world 22 if you're familiar
with that that's the underwater one you
can tell from all the water and so Kris
Williams came up from the DC area and
what he did is he actually had a instead
of a controller he had a bunch of wires
rigged two glasses of beer there was a
beer for left there was a beer for right
and there was a perfect jump and we had
Rachel and Jen sheffer and Mike and what
they would have to do is actually drink
to get Mario like through this thing
right but that's not even the best part
the best part is while we were doing it
this one was actually playing the Korean
which I was playing the actually
from the board it was it was the most it
was like the biggest moment of synergy
and like a meetup history was amazing
and then yeah all sorts of cool stuff
started to happen here's Jenna's eigen
giving her very very first tech talk and
then that talk actually got picked up by
Jace conf use and now she's speaking to
like all these people and then she gets
hired by a digital ocean the she sprang
droplets here so you know she's now our
sponsor and she comes and talks every
week it's like just to see in two years
like all the stuff changed from from
just creating this nutrient agar of
community here's marie cocco Sokka is
this your first tech talk or no this is
one of your first tech talks first one
uh again she blows up she I was speaking
in Europe speaking in Singapore shout
out over there about knitting she made
us a thing she made us a thing that was
really really cool we started doing
different kinds of formats because like
CSS cough came into town and scheduled
for the same night his Brooklyn Jas and
I was like what but like let's do
something together so we did we had a
panel gencha fermanagh Amador there's
Chris coiour and cloudiness awry and we
just did like a chat about you know
various issues it was a it was just a
panel thing it was a new for us but it
was amazing and actually what I just
found out the other day this guy mando
Amador speaking at Queen's jas last week
told us that he because of that gig got
a job the CTO of the company that he
works at was at that meet up and so that
was actually really easy for him to just
slide into that job so it was like super
awesome so yeah we try to get
interesting speakers in in one of the
ways we do it is by the same way very
similar to what Jays conf does it's like
a huge basically a pull request it's
basically you just propose it instead of
us curating the talks with the talks
come to us so you just go to gab you
edit two lines and that's it and you're
in so then we have you know talks but
you know it cuz not enough so you know
after the talks because you know people
can always get tickets so we need to
have like a beer j/s thing afterwards
people can't get tickets but we decided
to innovate here and instead of bjs we
now call it beverages
wow that's that's great Willman Duffy
women Duffy I don't don't follow on
Twitter just look at his thing but don't
click the follow button he's an amazing
amazing guy if you like this by the way
you will love his twitter feed it's all
puns music so yeah that was really cool
and it's funny because it's like better
just because well people who don't drink
beer you know one of the organizers are
broken jest doesn't drink beer also like
half of Brooklyn is gluten-free so beers
literally literally literally so yeah we
did that so we added the beverages and
then what else is going on here up there
were just you know it kind of extends
like we closed the tab at 1am it's it's
fun and there's people just get tickets
doesn't matter they'll show up anyway we
have a table for him we have some snacks
they can chill out and talk to folks and
then when everyone floods out after the
events over it's a super cool thing um
what's going on so now it's you know
it's me and Brian and it's basically
like the me and Brian show and like you
know we try to work a little bit of
comedy and here we're explaining how far
away Queens is like for people who give
Jersey about being not a borough
like Queens is like super far away so we
try to make it a little bit entertaining
so the intro actually is is it kind of
metastasized to this it's like literally
for talks worth of time but the audience
seems to enjoy it and if you're in the
audience you know it's hard to see
sometimes but that's cool that's cool
this is the sea as the hazard of come to
Brooklyn jayus sometimes it reports out
pretty weird but people like it here's a
marine have Rebecca saying he just came
like last month any he said this like
super super nice thing because I met him
at berlin's is like way long ago and I
was like that's super sweet until I saw
the follow-up tweet
let's go in whoa thanks for coming to my
meetup yeah so we can add I got
beverages what else yeah the interest a
lil bit longer fine sign no good school
but but yes hey shut your mouth you see
all those black lines between the talks
that was kind of an issue I don't know
if you've seen this crate recently but
we have the same projector literally
same projector and so between the talks
we have these sponsors in like we pay us
money to like have their logo on the
screen and yet viewsonic who pays us
nothing is literally on the screen for
like 15 minutes a night so that was like
kind of not cool so we wanted to let me
kind of like smooth it over and so we
decided to basically take our format and
basically fill in the gaps with music
okay so these are 10 minute talks really
fast people talk as fast as I do you
need because everyone's trying to
squeeze all their ideas in 10 minutes
you need something to like decompress
between talks and fill that awkward
silence of people setting up so what we
started we look to the community to find
people who could do music so this guy
Vince Allen who presented here I believe
recently and he was an EU recently he
talking about like a tornado simulation
here he plays a base I'm sorry no uh
what he called slack key guitar that's
really cool here's sandy she came and
she actually played piano with her
husband who plays clarinet that is
actual speed believe it or not so she
played piano clarinet for us I was a
cool do we had this guy over there with
the what he called hair that's Adam
sonntag I'm sonntag helped us organized
the CSS comp thing that we did and now
he came and he played Broadway like
1930s show tunes that was super awesome
Jen Schiffer came teamed up with Adam
karaoke night that was really cool we
have you know a corny an artist this guy
with the guitar in the white shirt he
actually works at about me about that me
he has a whole band of like 11 people
that was super awesome this guy plays a
Japanese weird kind of Japanese flute
that was cool also plays saxophone we
had this band come and play is like a
old timey what would you call it the
trio thing that was really cool we
actually got a guy in the community John
Kay Paul to come in just saying I've
been working on a rails app that was fun
and then well the thing is we have a
house band actually and it's
like barbershop quartet because if I
didn't if I didn't bring them to
Brooklyn joyous we wouldnt have any gigs
so so I was like guys throw move on and
so we are called the four fives but you
wouldn't know that because every time we
sing it's the viewsonic logo everywhere
so now everyone in New York is
conditioned to know that when they see
the view sonic logo that I'm going to
sing for them which is not true but yeah
we're the viewsonic quartet and one of
the really cool things about running a
meetup in 2015 is you actually get to
engage with brands that or saw that
feeling that was super awesome we pay
this venue 61 local awesome bar fifty
bucks a day the entire day and we use
like literally like two hours upstairs
so what we're like well if we have the
thing all day let's actually make an
event and so what we did is we actually
decided to instead of just having the
evening event we have the evening that
we literally pregame the entire thing
from 10 am-10 a.m. on with programming
do you guys programm programm programm
yeah so we are all programming all day
in the borough of Brooklyn we're trying
to reclaim programming it's like a right
take off the edge this is bro gramming
and so yeah it's cool so here's the
actual bar downstairs you come in
through this door you know the sign that
tells you where it is you come up this
venues empty anyway let's fill it with
tables let's fill the tables of people
and let's just hang out you know they
have fios internet which is super cool
cuz that for America is really fast for
those of you out of town the best thing
about the speed test thing is that it
literally literally looks like this news
pissing on New Jersey
I don't blame him but we have food they
said like this this venue 61 local has
this amazing kitchen and so they started
just doing catering for us and so they
have a triple kale salad because you
can't have enough kale in Brooklyn with
roasted veggies and like awesome fruits
and like meats and stuff and you know we
hang out we work and we chat and we and
we danced and you know at 5pm go down to
the bar for beverages and then you know
we start actually developing a
relationship with this venue where they
actually start catering to us they
actually started making a menu for us
because we have so many people there in
such a short time that they need
actually food that turns around fast so
they make our own menu for us they
reserve a table for us they are super
super awesome so my recommendation
you're doing me to find a home getting
that out of your brain and not having to
worry about you know having a meetup in
a start-up we're like they're not
recruiting this month so like get out of
here or like you know they go to
business or get out of here like not
dealing with that 60mm local is happy to
have us because we bring people with
money who are not bankers right because
in New York the people with money or the
bankers there so in San Francisco the
tech people are the douchebags in New
York right finance or the douchebags so
like we're like Thoratec it's awesome so
thank you Tom Dale for teaching me that
I didn't realize that I was amazing yeah
and so what we'd so would like ok cool
so now I have this meetup for charging
money where's his money going to go we
decided we there's an organization
called scripted and what they do is they
go into schools and they bring
volunteers to teach web skills and they
actually help place those kids into
internships in New York and companies
super super super awesome so we're like
well how can we actually we're charging
money we're giving it to them but how
can I actually take you to the next
level what we started doing is instead
of getting people tickets so that you
buy a ticket and you get a beer so like
check your ticket and give a beer that's
it we're like well what if we actually
spent more money to actually make custom
3d printed tokens custom for each event
and then give those out like it's going
to cost us two hundred dollar more these
things I got like a dollar piece it
costs us more money but it actually
makes the bar tab go down which is
really really cool and it's also it's a
keepsake that you actually get to keep
so we actually it's almost like Google
Analytics here but you can actually see
how many tokens each month are being
redeemed and you actually see like how
successful you are and actually getting
people to to hold on to them we want
them to hold on to the token instead of
paying for a beer a beer in Brooklyn at
this place is like eight bucks so if
they can hold on token that's like money
that we say which is super awesome but
what happens is we end up with all these
tokens I don't need so this is actually
a cruel thing I actually decided to up
source up upcycled these things into an
actual thing what we did is I got
together with my fellow organizers and
we made plaques at some brooklyn brewery
beer as one does and we took all the
tokens after our token run ended and we
made a plaque theme and we went we sold
the plaque so take all the unwanted
tokens put them in plex sell the plaques
back to people to make more money for
scripted right so the idea is now that
you have a place where the money goes
and they're doing awesome stuff you want
to give them as much money as possible
you start looking for opportunities to
actually like tweak the algorithm to
actually send them more money so you
know and we change things as another
learning opportunity we don't do tokens
anymore we do wouldn't Metro cards which
is just the most precious thing ever and
that was actually a really good
opportunity to learn how to use laser
etcher laser cutter which is super nice
it doesn't always work this is I'm sure
you work with I work with bits and bytes
and work with but like it don't always
work out yep oh hey whoa oh well there
it is so yeah that was no learning
experience but through all this stuff
through all the stuff that we did uh to
send money by you know getting basically
our event is a black box that takes
developer intention and turns it into
money for new developers cynically but
that's basically what we do and over the
course of our existence we've been able
to raise this much money for scripted
yeah they're an amazing organization
they're super cool and because we're
tweaking this algorithm are actually
trying to find ways to send them more
money by actually getting people to not
drink beer it's really cool so basically
our bar tab as you know you'll see it go
up as even gets more popular but then
actually in the past few months the bar
tab has gone way down and for the first
time last week went down to ninety
dollars that's literally like of the
swag that we make like everyone is
keeping it no one is redeeming it for a
beer so that's like a total success so
that's a really cool thing we did if you
want to see our finances it's all in one
gigantic javascript Express
as one does our entire budget is one
giant JavaScript expansion that exits I
hopefully an integer probably not it'll
coerce don't worry about its JavaScript
but if you end up with any money like
basically travesty I yells at you
because you exited with a code that's
not zero does that make sense and so
that's how we do our budget it's like so
just like you know if I'm embezzling
money like Travis is going to snitch on
me so that's how that's how we figure
that out and we're starting to if you
guys want to support the cause we
actually have a few of these left over I
believe we made sucks check it out socks
and you can buy them if you go to
Brooklyn jest are you wearing your socks
is wearing the socks oh yes Oh excellent
thank you they look great on Bo as they
look great on Tom Dale if you're one of
those people awesome but no we have
talked in so they come with a free
ticket so that's a really cool because
tickets go really fast tickets for our
last event with Brendan Eich went in two
rounds the first one was 28 seconds in
the second round was seven seconds and
that's 100 tickets so tickets sometimes
based on the speakers are super super
hard to get so by a tying it to the well
you can get a ticket now be get to spend
more money in that money goes to
scripted total win-win so find the wind
winds that has been awesome so that's
basically what we did and then Brian and
I we grew the family so we should and so
now we have a marie cocco soccer right
there helping us out do an awesome job
woman duffy who brought you beverages
this is actually yes woman Duffy thank
you this is actually my last month as an
organizer and smc uh so it's my last
call I have to go home right but with
the the meetup is an amazing capable
hands and I'm sure you won't have seen
the last of me but but yeah not only did
we grow the Brooklyn Jas family but we
grew the other family the bore ojs
family we basically now have siblings
and this is basically what i want to say
this is like the best part of this whole
thing is we created this community you
know we tweaked some knobs to get things
to work and then it just created this
environment where people can like
interact and meet and like get jobs and
like hang out and like there has been
such demand for this I don't know why it
wasn't the thing even when I showed up
but we made the thing and so now it's a
thing until like now there are you know
every week there is a meet-up so tell
you a little about a few
they have different like we're all doing
a difference if llings like siblings
have different personalities Manhattan
jayus started by these lovely ladies
here it's brenda zara and rachet machine
is here became are you where are you
there she is they started had and jace
super super awesome there they are
prayers on the mic they do different
thing instead of doing music between cuz
like the filling is a good idea but you
know music is maybe not their thing they
do battle decks which is like power
karaoke PowerPoint so like they'll just
do like have Zara will choose random
slides and like some people have just
riff as if they're giving a presentation
that's like super super fun crowd loves
it and instead of doing ten minute talks
five of them they do 20 minute talks
three of them so you can actually have
like a real talk Brooklyn say has a 10
minutes a lot of time so they have
awesome passion talks here's Charlie
Robbins speaking tomorrow talking about
making chili what is this this is a hot
sauce sorry out of chili peppers they
make the hot sauce out of all so here's
another one hey remember this one that's
Tracy she gave a pass and passion
talking about baking there was a tire
love gave this awesome it's like a rave
at this point this is like so cool I was
like a musical thing was like a smoke
machine and just so you know they
started their first prezzo John Resig so
I'm telling you get John Resig to speak
at your first event sure fire meanwhile
Queens you know Sarah gorecki was a you
know she had just come out of a flatiron
school she's super super awesome gave a
talk about spider solitaire Brooklyn Jas
and then peeled off and made her own
thing in Queens and it's amazing thing
it's in an awesome venue with its own
bar and its own bartender and it's super
chill they have sweater ugly sweater
contests I don't think there's any
winners there but that's cool and we you
know it's like siblings so like we have
fun together so like we did a takeover
with Queens or like Brooklyn goes to
Queens and instead of doing tokens we do
coasters and like do fun stuff like that
or Jersey you know like we turned the
Brooklyn to Jersey script and like Brian
and I went over and do thing and you
know then we go to a bar cade afterwards
and play video games like super super
chill so that's been super awesome but
it's not just borja since then this guy
right here the smiling guy right there
he came to our June event which was the
CSS conf one and he was like all right
you convinced me i'm going to start a
more fun based j/s meet up in SF similar
Brooklyn jeaious awesome he wrote this
ruling
post on medium and then he started this
thing called waffle JSC view her as you
bend at waffle dress people here yeah I
haven't been yet I really want to go I
heard it's super super awesome and so
he's trying he's trying to basically
take that culture back to San Francisco
and then you know jason rhoads doing the
same thing Charm City jas in Baltimore
he came in dis abroad ramming with a
super chill guy and now he's he's
running his thing in in Baltimore and
then it gets picked up by like Max Ogden
who's trying to take the waffle one into
portland so if you're in portland please
help amount i would love to go to Waffle
Jason Portland and that's basically
about it so like if you are thinking
about building a community like this
where you live to kind of carry the
torch for JS conf i recommend you just
do it