hello my name is my name is luke and I
had JavaScript wait which conference is
this oh right yeah so actually I'm not
entirely kidding I really I really don't
like JavaScript and I've been doing
cross-browser compatible web development
for about about 10 years most of that
time I've had to deal with CSS issues
between the browsers which if you've
been around long enough in this industry
you know that that basically translates
into I've had to deal with CSS since
internet explorer has supported CSS and
I'm saying this so that you'll fully
appreciate the significance when I say
CSS support across the browser's over
the past 10 years has been a bit of a
mess understatement of the century and
so what does that have to do with
JavaScript well me hating javascript in
particular and it's a it's the same
thing where it's all the JavaScript
incompatibilities between the browsers
that I really don't like and that's not
so much app script as it is the Dom
perhaps but not less in general I just
don't like to ask it don't like writing
it and so
oops so I've been doing this CSS thing
mostly for 10 years and you know it's
pretty bad when the guy doing CSS is
complaining about JavaScript you know
your situation is pretty bad when I mean
I feel sorry for you guys having to deal
with all the JavaScript stuff on a daily
basis but wow so this kind of a brief
like two little questions I mean if I
hate JavaScript Who am I and why am I
talking at it at a conference so let's
let's start by the with the first
question Who am I but before I go on to
that just a quick I want to briefly
point out that at this conference I'm
only the third speaker so far I have to
hate on JavaScript so I'm not even first
which says something I think anyway so
Who am I well aside from evidently being
a route 66 traveler I'm I do things like
design web standards evangelism
accessibility photography and you'll
notice that programming isn't really on
that list now I've done a lot of
programming in my life actually but the
vast majority of that has been PHP post
grass python in other words mostly
back-end and database programming so
funny thing is the very little
JavaScript that I've actually done in my
career has somehow given me this this
reputation of also being a JavaScript
guy small reputation but still and I
don't really I have no qualms being
lobbed together with without JavaScript
guys and girls it's you know they're all
good people but i think it's it's not
entirely fitting and i don't think it's
entirely fair to all the very talented
javascript people and here in the
audience who do i can pretty much
guarantee no more about JavaScript than
I do and
which brings us to question number two
why am I here what path have I traveled
that leads me to meet mr. I hate
JavaScript to speak here at a JavaScript
conference in Berlin well the first the
first stint that got me this disk urea
sleep laced reputation as being a
JavaScript guy came with face an acronym
that stands for farooq's animated CSS
enhancements clearly a very inspired
name and face was face was a little tool
kits that I released in in 2005 which it
allows you to do stop-motion animation
using nothing but CSS it is a little
JavaScript toolkit but in using it all
you have to do is write CSS classes and
they would be steps like frames in an
animation the JavaScript would then
figure out what you were trying to do
and it would animate through those
classes and you have your animation all
you have to do is write it in CSS and
somehow because it's JavaScript toolkit
this land me that's this started that
little reputation of being Josh would
bag but I find it kind of ironic because
if you really look at face I mean the
whole toolkit is about not writing
JavaScript about writing CSS so clearly
people could have figured out that i
don't like javascript back then face
eventually led me to a job at a certain
fruit company in california where i
worked for a couple of years for company
which will remain nameless and after
after a couple of years of working there
i left this summer and very shortly
after leaving i released the second
piece of JavaScript that got me as this
recognition and that is moderniser
moderniser is a JavaScript toolkit that
makes it easier to use html5 and css3 in
your websites today and I will go into
that more in a moment first I want to
talk about what face and modernizer have
in common
besides being the combined reason that
I'm standing here talking about
javascript javascript conference I mean
why am I telling you all this is this
just to further inflate my oversized ego
no I actually have a point here there
are three main reasons why face and
modernizer got the recognition that they
did now face has basically been made
completely completely obsolete with the
arrival of proper JavaScript driven
animation engines one of which you and I
already know and probably use as it's
part of jQuery I mean who here does not
use jQuery what's wrong with you people
I mean John rezac is he in a room is
like Europeans el sol face has been made
obsolete by proper josh cribbs animation
engines but modernizer first of all
monetize is only a couple months old but
it's actually it it's good becoming
increasingly more useful the more people
learn about it and the more people start
using it while building websites and it
started becoming increasingly more
valuable so what do face and modernizer
have in common now first of all they are
both unobtrusive tool kits which means
if you use them properly and as intended
they will not break the website they use
them in they will not break for people
who are be might be using all our
browsers or who might have javascript
disabled or filtered through proxy or
something so there are unobtrusive which
is a good thing second they very
strongly encourage the use of
progressive enhancements and that
basically means that your website will
look better and behave more
interestingly the better the browser is
that you're using it really is just a
way of saying the better your browser
Richard experience of this website will
be for you and that's a powerful thing
we'll get to that in a moment and lastly
they are both accessible they are very
accessible they'll talk wit meaning that
the use of them does not impede on the
web accessibility of your site and that
means so yeah it's still possible to use
these toolkits and make a very
inaccessible website but if you use them
as intended as as designed then they
won't have any negative effect on the
web accessibility of your site unlike
certain other JavaScript toolkits and
libraries out there so another thing
they have in common is that they serve
to enhance your website in one way or
another nowadays website enhancements
come in a large number of you know many
shapes and forms but they're also
becoming increasingly native now what do
I mean with native this kind of refers
back to the whole you know I hate
javascript thing for a past couple of
years or past many years actually
javascript has played is this really
important role in augmenting older
browsers with features and technologies
that the newer browsers were
implementing natively they had it an
older browsers you now didn't have it
people using javascript to kind of like
shoe horn all these new technologies and
techniques into the older browsers and
it's it mostly about html5 and CSS
features were seized as three features
in particular newer browsers have been
adding these for the past couple of
years other browsers in particular
mostly just internet explorer they've
been around for years without really
adding any of these features so people
have had to rely on JavaScript to add
them and that able so that web
developers could actually use these
technologies take advantage of them but
it wasn't it wasn't the greatest
situation I mean can anyone here guess
how many
javascript libraries exist to do rounded
corners in internet explorer anyone
you're all so shy oh sorry well the
funny thing is no matter what number you
say the answer is wrong because the
right answer should is there shouldn't
be any I mean you can ask Dion he was
complaining yesterday about how many
posts here to write to a Jackson about
this there shouldn't be any at all zero
that's what it should be so I'm going to
tell you something that I'm you probably
either already agree with or you're on
the fence of this issue or you haven't
really decided yet or you're actually
again set and it is this a website
should not look and work the exact same
in every browser it's it's it's
basically the principle of similar
versus the same it's very simple matter
actually first one is good the second
will make your head hurt especially in
that in today's browser landscape now if
anyone disagrees with that notion that a
website should not look the same and
that in fact it should give it time
you'll come around eventually
your first realization will be websites
cannot look the exact same in every
browser I mean you can make a one page
single image website if you can still
call that a website and even then the
different color profiles between
browsers means it won't actually be the
exact same it may behave the same
because it's an image but this is an
extreme example it's not very realistic
at all and that's the closest you'll
ever be able to get to a website that is
the exact same in every browser if you
have a much more realistic website with
you not text and well not you'll note
he'll discover very soon that text
rendering and tax time in between mac OS
10 windows and linux very different
dramatically different can't even
possibly get a deep Zac same on top of
that process will never implement the
exact same set of features as one
another and even if they were I mean
even between up round windows and up
around the mac for instance they will
never have the exact same set of bugs so
the various combinations and
permutations of browsers implementations
bugs and features means a website just
simply cannot be the exact same in every
browser and now I mean yesterday
Francisco Tomas key spoke about image
sprites and how cappuccino the Arab does
horizontal sprites and vertical sprites
and dynamic sprites now sprites are a
great way to optimize your website but
you can overdo it for instance jcrew.com
I mean I'm pretty sure everyone here is
at least familiar with jquery calm and
knows the website and recognizes the
who's using jquery section where they
have a bunch of logos of all these
really big name companies that are using
it and that's great and they're using a
CSS image sprite to do the little hover
when you go with your mouse over logo
it'll you know it becomes fully opaque
instead of semi-transparent and shifts
down a pixel they're using a lot of CSS
rules to accomplish that effect and
they're using a sprite that has both
states of of each logo in there and
that's you know clearly that's not the
most efficient way but well yeah it does
work in internet explorer but uh I every
wrote this well you know just that
little part and oh actually I can show
it briefly and I move this over so I
this is a local file basically just
jQuery calm but with with my changes and
you know it behaves the exact same
there's a subtle fade in and out on each
logo if you hover over them it's it's
very subtle but you can you can tell the
difference it's not just an on/off
switch it's now it's it's a little
gradual impression slightly richer
experience but the funny thing is doing
this it allowed me to use about
thirty-five percent less CSS to
accomplish the same effect the same
effect which then gave me more control
and more freedom over it because now I
mean I can do whatever I want with these
logos I can you know skilled and move
them around 3d space have them animate
or whatever and I couldn't do that with
just the background position in the
surprise and not just it's not just that
there's you know less CSS more freedom
more controlled experience it's also
much less maintenance work if you ever
have to update the sprite with logos add
one or you delete one or you know you
change one just to rebrand it you don't
have to make two copies of the logo all
the time you only have the one copy the
only difference is between my version
and the one on jcrew.com is that by
default it doesn't work in
explore it you mean you just don't get
the automatic Faden hover state and even
that hovers that you could implement
with a one-line CSS filter for internet
explorer that's probably worth it
something more extensive I would say not
really worth it but yeah this is this is
a lot it's more efficient cleaner code
it's more powerful and half as much
maintenance especially going forward
it'll be a lot easier where's my cursor
so why do well why do clients and
companies still expect that their
website will be the exact same in every
browser and what do i do they they think
that makes sense well because design
agencies and developers don't tell them
that it can't really be done and more
importantly it shouldn't even be
attempted it's much better to focus on
providing good rich experiences and
proper web accessibility then spending a
lot of time using you know little
augmentation tools and trying to get
things to work the exact same or be
pixel perfect a lot of time spent on
that for very little actual gain in the
experience and I mean there are a
thousand and one permutations of every
single website on the entire world wide
web out there and your life will just be
so much easier if you can convince your
employers or your clients or your
designers that you know the website will
have a million-in-one permutations just
the same no matter what you do it's just
this just so many in the browser
landscape that you can't control so it's
better not to spend a lot of time on it
oh yeah so uh html5 css3 getting back to
a JavaScript there's some there's been
this trend that's been emerging with
that an increased availability of actual
native implementations of html5 and css3
in browsers and and thereby reducing the
need for and the interest in JavaScript
driven augmentation libraries and
toolkits and this is a very good thing
this dis Trant actually is is one of the
main reasons that came up with the idea
from modernizer in the first place
because you know browsers can do a lot
of really cool stuff nowadays and they
can do it without having to rely on
JavaScript which means you know you can
spend time on other things and being
more innovative with JavaScript and
being more creative with it and and take
advantage of these really cool features
I mean let's look at them rounded
corners yes excitement is palpable fun
facebones this is actually that actually
is quite exciting browsers are now
starting to have very good solid support
for font face ones in them natively so
you don't have to rely on siffering and
or q fun as much anymore canvas very
powerful drawing RGB a color something
actually really like because I like
transparency in nice solo uses thereof
border image very powerful to do to make
use of that box shadow you no html5
audio and video since as animation CSS
transitions to the transformations you
know CSS gradients SVG geolocation
ceases columns local storage web workers
offline web apps and so on and so on
that one now many of these were actually
mentioned by a by Remy yesterday so it's
very clear that a lot of really cool
stuff is happening in
in this space but of course not if your
browser supports it yet that's where
previously you know JavaScript came in
as I already mentioned and it was used
to augment these older browsers with
really just approximations of the same
thing somewhere quite good somewhere
really good many of them were just okay
and most of them were pretty messy and
convoluted more importantly none of them
stacked up against the actual native
implementations and the browsers that do
have them so this situation this
situation can force browse what
developers to to make a choice do I
start using native implementations and
ignore browsers that don't have them or
continue playing it safe with
augmentation methods now that's a bridge
that every web developer web developer
will have to cross at one point in his
or her career for some the the chasm
below is much deeper than for others so
there's no clear indication on when
exactly you should cross this bridge or
how for that matter but in order to aid
people making this choice that's kind of
where I came up with with moderniser so
let's look at that moderniser is as one
of this kind of like example situations
where if I don't like the options that I
have available to me in doing something
I just create another one kind of go out
of the way and figure out what can I do
and said and I mean I really wanted to
use these native implementations of cool
html5 and css3 stuff but I also wanted
to have a really easy way to accommodate
the older browsers and in other words I
wanted it to be super easy for me to use
the cool stuff and have multiple levels
of supports in each website that I built
one for each degree of sophistication
that a browser had and so that's how I
ended up with moderniser
which what it does is it allows you to
use or start using html5 and css3 today
it allows you to have full control over
what your HTML your CSS and your
JavaScript do in browsers that may not
have the more advanced features yet and
that level support staff area like
random and vary chaotically in the lands
across the landscape so and that
actually brings me to kind of the most
important part of this presentation Dada
feature detection I did not pay for that
slogan no royalty fee feature detection
is cannibal is an incredibly important
technique going forward in particular in
the world of html5 and css3 where this
technique is far less widely used I mean
you're all jobs for people you probably
know this as object detection and have
used this for years we're now in your
scripts you first detect the presence of
a function or method or our property
before you start using it so and thus
preventing errors and warnings from
being thrown well the same technique can
be used to feature detects the
availability of native implementations
in browsers for html5 and css3 and it's
it's a really powerful and very
important technique moderniser just does
pretty much that and nothing else it
does a whole bunch of feature detection
and then it's test no not everything but
almost everything that's currently
implemented in at least one browser from
html5 and css3 and then what it does it
tests the weather the features
implemented correctly and then tells you
as a web developer in the current
browser you have this feature you do not
of this feature you have this feature
you do not let this feature and it also
creates a JavaScript object that allows
you to just you know use that in your
scripts and for cure code based on
whether or not the browser has certain
features implemented so it's it allows
you to do very clean for king of all of
your code your HTML CSS and JavaScript
depending on what the pressure can
actually do and what account so it's
kind of a simple example of you know if
you have a native implementation
available there will be class at it
called fun face and you can do use some
cool custom font or if the browser
doesn't have it added you can you have
the no font face rule and use some
fallback if you want or not even that I
mean that's up to you but the important
thing is you have full control over what
you do and don't do for browsers that
don't have these features and this very
fine control mix makes it a lot easier
to actually start taking advantage of
all these really cool stuff so let's
look at a small demonstration of how how
this works or how how can be implemented
yeah so have a virgin my website here
come on all right so this is this in
Safari which I can see so this is in
Safari you'll just have to take my word
on it but you'll see pretty quickly that
it is and you can see here on these tabs
that's all just CSS there's no
JavaScript at all involved besides
moderniser running at the start of the
page and this is just a bunch of CSS
rule saying like hey I on hover State I
want it to be 15 pics wider and I want
to have this move out a little I want to
have the color become fully opaque you
know change the text color of course
that doesn't work quite the exact same
way in in other browsers but
so this is Firefox coming in now in
Firefox you know Firefox doesn't do
everything that Safari does and vice
versa but it does support a lot of stuff
it supports rounded-corners sports
box-shadow sports rgba so you can see
that better than this one it just
doesn't animate well if I wanted to like
you just say like well I don't have
native implementations for CSS
transitions but hey I can use this
JavaScript library to do it anyway so i
can just animate it as i go with
javascript i chose not to do that I'm
fine with offering dis experience to
Firefox kind of making a point but it's
very easy to add a little bit of
richness with JavaScript depending on
what the browser can't do here and then
let's look at opera now we have right
here opera me another thing you can see
is that this is not only one column
whereas in Firefox and in Safari it's
two columns that's just done in CSS and
opera just doesn't have support CSS
columns so mama I didn't bother doing
some JavaScript implementation for that
I mean really it's not that important
it's just part of blog post content
opera doesn't do a rounded corners as
you can see doesn't quite look the same
but you know what it's not that bad and
I I was ok with this I kind of like that
implementation certainly much easier to
do this then creating images with
rounded corners for all of these tabs in
different colors and you know they also
wouldn't allow me to transition them in
Safari so that would have given me much
less freedom much more stuff to download
as a you on the user side you know I
have to download all those images and
just for a bunch of rounded corners yeah
not worth it so to me this was very much
an acceptable solution to opera and for
upper users I also kind of pointed out
that you know opera really needs to
get their together and start
implementing some of these css3 things
and not just make promises that yes it's
in the next build that we know you know
not show to people sorry I kind of you
know I'm annoyed with opera sometimes no
offense to all my friends at opera but
yeah it's disappointing and internet
explorer I'm not going to show it to you
is now p.m. and all that stuff but in an
explorer what I'm doing in in exports is
I'm not even moving it out I'm just
letting it be a hover state in the
middle because in and explore doesn't do
rgba so it doesn't show you that nice
little subtle transparency and the
see-through on the edge so it just won't
look quite as nice anymore that way
opera at least does and within the next
four it just changes color and that's it
pretty pretty simple but good enough
experience for IE users don't not used
to great stuff anyway I mean after all
they use ie so it's you know it's great
having all these cool html5 and css3
features available to you but kind of
becomes this question you know what do
you have available and what don't you
have available and in which browsers do
you have it available and which browsers
don't you have it available well who
here does not know this website when can
I use oh yeah she shouldn't have put up
your hand because now I'm gonna rant at
you for not the way this website it is
really really useful website it's
something you really need to know you
need to like bookmark this make it your
startup page for your browser go there
for a week explore it you know it's a
really good website it has this
incredibly detailed list is a massive
overview every single feature out of
html5 and css3 cross-reference to every
browser that has some semblance of
support for it and any browser that is
currently publicly available that makes
sense to include and it allows you to
see exactly you know what's currently
implemented
where is the next browser for this
particular browser coming and is it
going to have an implementation for this
feature or is it not it's a really
fantastic website and you all should go
there like as soon as this presentation
is over so let's say let's talk about
some things not to do well you don't
want to dress up as a storm trooper in
30 degree weather stand out in the Sun
all day and certainly not as a second
you know not an original trilogy storm
trooper I mean that's just disgraceful
also very important how you don't want
to do user agent sniffing and you really
don't want to use it you really don't
want to use a chat you ah you really
don't want to do user agent sniffing but
I really don't want you to be doing any
user agent sniffing because use you a
sniffing is a really bad practice and
it's I mean it's very unreliable it
breaks usability for a lot of people who
have done nothing wrong except just you
know try and use your website and is the
main reason we have this really
ridiculous Internet Explorer mess right
now and I mean Douglas Crockford
mentioned yesterday that Microsoft you
know they couldn't really fix a lot of
the issues in IE for ie8 not entirely
true there was a way for them to do that
but you know of course they wouldn't
because they wouldn't have control
anymore but yeah user agent sniffing is
the main reason that we currently have
this absolutely dreadful intolerable
mess with internet explorer in the world
and i really want everyone to stop doing
that so if you if you do that if you're
still using that technique please stop
get get it out of all the scripts that
you have filter it out replace it do
objective tection do feature detection
instead and get rid of those things it's
very unreliable kind of breaks the web
it's really bad and I was originally
going to show so don't do it just don't
do that so I was already going to show a
big table here that would kind
like highlight and explain this mess of
Internet Explorer with ie8 the rendering
engines in I ate how the price will
identify itself depending on what kind
of markup you were using what kind of
HTTP header see we're sending out what
kind of domain you were on you know
whether your domain was blacklisted by
Microsoft or not and that table became
so big that I couldn't fit it in a slide
anymore at any kind of reasonable font
size so instead yeah it was really
really messy really big instead I sum it
up in a quote you can have the ie8
rendering engine in a browser
identifying as ie7 and vice versa yeah
think about that if that doesn't sound
frustrating to you imagine that adding
to that complexity ie9 doing the same
thing and thus offering ie8 i9n ie7 as
rendering engines in browsers
identifying possibly as I 708 or ie9 and
all other possible combinations thereof
don't do browser sniffing please it's
it's so bad built your code based off of
feature detection and object detection
and sell the ID to your employers or
your clients that websites just should
not look and act the exact same across
every browser because that's kind of the
source of it all so don't just do this
because I say so I mean it's great if
you listen to me but now do this because
of these real-world benefits you'll have
a shorter development time you'll have
much cleaner and clearer code you'll
have much lower maintenance overhead as
you go you know if as time passes and
you have the website and other people
may need to get on board and start
working with it your maintenance will go
way below or way down and all that
translates to lower costs and for
because time is money and so these are
very important real world benefits that
you get from not doing you a sniffing
and doing object and feature detection
in your code and just kind of like doing
things the right way it's not just the
right way though it's it's also just a
smart and cost-effective way and I
should make a small mode here that
shorter development time you you may not
see that like right away when you start
doing this but once you get more
familiar with these principles and these
techniques and how everything works you
become a lot more accustomed to the
approach and you'll become much more
efficient over time and very pretty soon
on you'll be much more efficient than
you were before you started doing this
so let's say let's take a step back and
look at the bigger picture the bigger
picture of you know the JavaScript
landscape or the Grand Canyon escape in
this case we have you know we have all
these things like moderniser all the
cool stuff in html5 css3 and these are
all very big influences in what's
transforming the JavaScript landscape
but they're also not the only things
going on I mean we have other examples
are these great frameworks that have
been popping up in recent times and by
recent times I mean like the past couple
of years two of them i want to give some
particular mention here the first is
proud court which has already been
mentioned a couple times at this
conference it's probably most well known
for being the javascript framework that
powers to mobileme web applications at
me calm sprout curve basically allows
you to use javascript to do or to build
desktop like applications in the browser
and it's gone through an enormous amount
of development in the past year and by
now it's become very refined very
powerful similar to that is cappuccino
the makers of which are here this
weekend's I take it you all saw their
talk yesterday here today is conf if you
missed it that's a shame
cappuccino is very similar to sprout
birds basically the objective-c runtime
and objective-c is like the mac
applications framework or not entirely
but it's like objective-c runtime
implemented in JavaScript I like I do a
poor job of explaining it so i really
hope you caught their session yesterday
because it's some seriously cool stuff
that's going on in the JavaScript
landscape there's a there's even more
going on but we're kind of starting to
get way past the scope of this
presentation so all these cool new
developments in the world josh cribbs
you know the changing kind of my my my
opinion on Josh of itself and I'm
starting to hate it less and less and
you know maybe someday I'll not even
hated at all since you guys already
don't hate it and probably quite like it
I mean you're here at the JavaScript
conference I hope you use these tools
use them well use them responsibly and
that you'll just make really exciting
things and spend less time trying to
polish things for internet explorer
because it's not really worth it and
that's kind of all I have for today and
I I reckon we go get some lunch well oh
really huh what time is it um but it's
not shine well anyhow nonetheless lunch
or not