I work at boku where I do JavaScript
development and stuff and we've been
stickering everywhere with lots of Bob's
if you want some bob thicker come talk
to me it's a little bit about me because
you might not have heard of me before
I'm a programmer I've been programming
since I've been nine and all is great
and my kind of my focus has been data
visualization and I've been working a
little bit on my own and this year with
the guardian newspaper interactive team
where we've been working on some open
source libraries and some interactive
pieces for the Guardian and what we
realized when we started working on data
visualization open libraries is that
most of our work kind of all the snags
were hitting had to do with data and so
the first library we actually released
had to do with data management on the
client side and this talk was kind of
born I realized that what I really want
to talk about is that you can indeed do
data crunching in your browser and so on
and so really want to talk a little bit
about what is we currently do a data I
would say most of what we do has to do
with this crud space you know we create
records and we update them and we modify
them and and delete them and whatever I
did see no me toque really exciting and
that's great but there's all these other
things that we could be doing right we
could be with all this data that we're
gathering we could actually be computing
various metrics not just for our own
analytics but even for our users and
even more we can give our users filtered
views that have to do with the things
that they care about right and so the
reason I'm here is because I think
that's kind of the awesome zone where we
can combine all these practices that
we've had for many years I have to do
with crud apps but join them with some
more data heavy processing to create
this awesome square right there and so
why client-side a because their browsers
can handle it right if any of you are
done writing apps for IE which I'm sure
all of you are deep down inside then you
know how powerful or modern browsers are
and you can do so much with them so
that's pretty cool and I would say if
you're doing a lot of computations that
have to do with the specific users that
are visiting your systems it's much
easier if we do it on the client you
have to cash less you have to process
less and you're not taking up all those
valuable computing resources so
maybe you can serve more connections or
maybe you can just have more CPU cycles
to do whatever with so yeah browsers
right so before I talk about the various
libraries you can use because that's
what we're going to do today I'm going
to talk a little bit about three
different libraries that have to do a
data crunching including one that had
co-authored with the Guardian folks but
two other ones that are very good at
what they do but before we get to that I
want to talk about how we actually treat
data it's very meta right so so
traditionally we think about data as
rows of Records if anybody's use sequel
or even no sequel whatever call it a
document and the end of the day what you
have is this collection of properties or
dimensions that all combined into us
into this collection of rows right so
something like that right that's what we
expect to have in a client we have this
array of objects with names and
properties and whatever and that's
really great when you are iterating over
things right when you're iterating over
all those objects and you're displaying
them and a list so you're rendering
something all is great but it's really
bad if you're trying to figure out
something about a specific property
right so for example i have this age
property maybe i want to get an average
of it well the first thing i have to do
is iterate over all my records and grab
that age property right that's pretty
wasteful so an alternative way for us to
do this is to actually look at column
wise databases right so in a column wise
representation of your data what you
actually have is you have every single
data type every dimension every column
whatever in its own structure right and
the only thing binding these together as
a row is the actual index position of
those values right so here's the same
data that we just represented an
object's but in this column wise store
right so the first array is the name
property and it's just the names of
whatever we're looking at and the second
array is a specific type at these all
happen to be heroes and then the bottom
one is just those aged numbers right and
now the great part is that I just have
an array right so I can do a lot of
things to it just from the native array
implementation or if I really want I can
go ahead and use underscore or whatever
textually process that but at the very
least I have all these data types all
these data fragments in in single arrays
so this talks can have a lot of code
which is
cool if you have Wi-Fi access which
comes and goes feel free to check it out
I Ross slit / client-side data is the
repo there's a lot of different
libraries covered there because client
data is awesome and I'd like to talk
about all of it if I could but and the
examples I'll show today will be there
too but you know feel free to ask me at
any point about anything else there or
call me out if I make a mistake I'm all
for that so you may have noticed various
names I'm throwing around I thought that
would be really nice to have a theme for
today's talk and because we're a bunch
of nerds I thought superheroes and
villains would be kind of cool so I went
ahead to this website called superhero
DB where people have a lot of time on
their hands go and spend inordinate
amount of time classifying superheroes
and villains right I don't even know
where they get stuff but I scraped it so
I'm very happy so I just wanna I know
it's pretty small but I just want to go
over a couple of properties because
we're going to use them later down the
road so this is the profile for Batman
it's actually the piece of profile for
Batman and he's got various capabilities
like his intelligence or strength or
speed so his intelligence is it maxed
out at one point oh very exciting so
we're going to look at some of those
capabilities and he's got some
attributes about his height and weight
which you know is pretty basic turns out
he's 188 centimeters tall never knew
that and last but not least he has some
superpowers so actually every single one
of these records has about over 170
superpowers and their binary attributes
so they're either set to 1 or 0 1 if
they have it 0 if they don't and we're
going to look at these superpowers later
down the road because it's kind of
exciting so if you want to look at more
the data there's a data folder in that
repo where you can look for it just
heroes JSON or just villains or all of
them combined and there's a type
property so feel free to build cool
stuff on top of that and let me know so
we're going to start off and look at
rows of data I'm going to look at one
library that does rows of data and two
libraries to do that very good at
handling columns of data and the first
one I wanted to call out was called
taffy DB so taffy DB is very database
like and that records are JSON objects
so again that
polite showed you early on it has very
very rich selection language so I'll
show some examples and that I would say
is the strength of this library and that
you can make almost sequel like queries
you can and you can or you can check for
existence or undefined our Nan's and
kind of change those together as you
wish so there's also a library called
JSON select I'm not going to go over but
it has kind of various CSS style syntax
for selecting properties out of your
JSON structures so feel free to look at
that but i'll talk about taffy taffy
supports saving some local storage which
is pretty exciting and it does have sort
of a built-in extension mechanism if you
will it doesn't have any updates no
events rather so if you are updating
your data and you want to have a binding
to that data because maybe your view
needs to update or so on if you're used
to MVC frameworks that kind of do all
that wiring for you that won't be there
you'll be on it'll be on you to kind of
wire that stuff together and it has some
templating support which doesn't mean
much because you can just throw an
object into any templating engine these
days so but here's an example of me
wanting to find all the male heroes the
female heroes and unknown gender heroes
that have height right so the first
thing I do is I create this database by
calling taffie the function with my
array of objects and then I go ahead and
find the male heroes by saying find me
all the heroes that have the gender male
the type hero and then the height cm
property is not undefined because for
some heroes that value is undefined and
then I do the same thing for my female
heroes and then here's an example of an
and that's kind of cool i say that type
of be here on the height is not
undefined and then the gender is not
male and is not female so you can sort
of pass this array of objects so it's
pretty cool and you can do a lot of
things in terms of querying or data and
so it's that we'll look at an example
right so I was very curious as to
whether certain capabilities appear
together or not so if I'm faster and I
also better combat or not so if you want
look at the code the example is under
taffy the under staffy dashdb space
competencies that HTML and there's a
chance bin that's slightly out of date
but so what we want to do first really
are
pretty much the only taffy part of this
of this example is to find all the
heroes that have all the competencies
defined right because the last thing we
want is to be comparing ones that have
some don't have some so this is me
really pretty much to sue my query I go
ahead and I say give me the six that I'd
shown you and make sure that they are
not undefined right so and then the rest
of this is actually a bunch of d3 code
which I'm not going to go over even
though pulsed I don't want to talk about
visualizing big data not going to do
that to you guys but here's an example
of what that built right so what that
did is it selected all the superheroes I
have all those abilities and then I
built this very slowly scatter plot
where I can say oh how does my power
compared my power well that's a stupid
question but how does intelligence
comparator our right so it looks like
just about all the heroes are clustered
and kind of the mid-range intelligence
and so on and so forth I don't know how
they have to do with combat also not not
that different but it looks like most
superheroes are kind of on the slow end
so that's kind of interesting right so
that's a quick example of taffy and you
know let me know later if you have any
questions about that and the next
library I want to talk about is cross
filter so I used III a bunch in my work
and it was written by a really great guy
and Mike Michael Bostock who writes a
lot of amazing dataviz and he's also
written this library crawl called cross
filter which has to do with dealing with
high dimensional data so it is
incredibly fast because it uses type
arrays very heavily the thing it doesn't
do very well is actually deal with
incomplete or messy data before I get
into that I want to show just an example
of how you would use cross filter so
again you would sort of call the cross
filter function and pass it your array
of objects in case case heroes and then
what you do is you build these
dimensions a dimension is really just
the cash right we've all created cash
objects was just an object with a key
and then either an array of our objects
or just single objects the same thing is
done by cross filter except he calls it
a dimension and so and they can be a
little more flexible and that you can
actually you know combine them in
whatever way you want by using this
callback function so in this case I'm
really just creating a dimension on the
intelligence property right because we
really what I want to do is be very
quickly able to get all the heroes of
intelligence Oh point 75 or something
right so once i have my dimension builds
the next thing i can do is actually call
a filter so i'm going to say okay give
me all give me a filter that only gets
me the here is between 0 and 0.25 right
so that creates a filtering and then
actually go and get the top records so
dot top infinity really clear API not
and you know what I'm done I have to
clear my filtering again so that's an
example of using cross filter and
there's all sorts of additional things
you can do on top of that you can group
things so for example here what I've
really done is I made a group right I
said I'll give me the group of things in
between these brackets but there's
actual kind of a contract for that call
the group so I mentioned typed arrays a
little bit now i'll talk about them
because territories are really really
cool they allow you to very quickly
manipulate rob binary data because what
you start off with is just an array
buffer and then you kind of say oh I'm
going to look at it at 8-bit chunks or
at 16-bit chunks or whatever and it's
nice because they initialize by default
20 instead of undefined which is what
traditional JavaScript arrays
initialized to which is really fun if
you've ever done data things and it's
nice because you can share buffers you
can have multiple views applied to the
same array buffer and if you know the
dimensions of your data if you know
you're only going to look at values from
0 to 255 that's great because you can
have a really small memory footprint but
the problem with typed arrays is that
just about anything that doesn't conform
within the dimensions you specified is
going to turn into a zero so an an an
undefined string or even the value that
is outside the range right so here I'm
defining an unsigned 8-bit integer array
and what that means is I can fit value
from 0 until 255 into it and what
happens when I put a value outside that
range for example 258 what I actually
get is the number two because it's kind
of just roll over it just does not have
enough bits to fit that data so you have
to be very careful because you're not
actually going to know that this is not
going to throw an error right and the
same happens in cross filter if you put
through data and you don't filter it
appropriately
don't clean it up appropriately or it
has kind of little pitfalls it's not
going to air out what you are going to
get is slightly wrong answers so you
might get a filtration of 100 records
and two of those records don't actually
belong and as someone who spent like two
days debugging stuff like that it's
really not fun so so typed arrays kind
of yay kind of nay and so but
nonetheless crossroads is very cool so I
actually thought okay now we looked a
little bit at these competencies now I'm
very curious to see how they're actually
distributed right so I want to look at
the histograms hopefully focused on what
those are so if you want to look at the
code it's under cross filter / visual
data HTML and we're going to look at the
all that does not very complicated what
I do is I for every single competency I
take all the values for all my heroes
and then I bend them in this case in 27
bins randomly selected number and I just
try to kind of aggregate to see how many
i have in each in each grouping so for
example you can see my intelligence very
Gaussian distributed that's good to know
combat almost so not so much and
durability for some reason just a lot in
the extremes and then kind of strength
is all over the place for most part and
definitely a lot more slower heroes and
villains then pass one so kind of
interesting but we can look very quickly
at the code that put that together so
I'm gonna zoom out a little bit
hopefully you guys can see these screens
are so tiny so the first thing we're
going to do and this again is not really
cross filter this is me using underscore
because again I'm trying to first reduce
my data to make sure i only have records
that aren't going to break cross filter
so here i just iterate over all of them
and make sure they're not undefined or
nan and then only get those those
records um but then what I really do is
for every competency I build this
dimension and then I go and I fetch my
records and I get my mins in the max the
other nice thing across filter does when
you build a dimensions is it sorts it
for you so if you have numbers the max
is always going to be the first record
and the men is always going to be the
bottom record so that's exciting and
then I go and I kind of built my my bins
that I talked about kind of that first
example and then here I do the actual
grouping
and I fetch my records and I do the
little sparkline chart so not very
complicated but again very handy and if
you look at some of the examples across
filter there's a lot of cross
coordination stuff that that he does you
know it's not inherent cross filter it's
just a cool demo so but that that's
cross filter and if you have any
questions do talk to me about that and
then the last library I want to talk
about is the one that I'd written with
the Guardian folks with Alex crawl if
any of you know him and it's a part of a
bigger project called the miso project
where we're trying to build libraries
for enabling interactive visualization
and interactive media JavaScript
development stuff so I'm i really love
dataviz and i want to help people write
it and especially in journalism where
they don't have time and not have
developed personally don't have budget
and they don't have anything really um
so they're running on a dime so we build
data set to kind of try and cover the
entire workflow of data management so
this is kind of a transient FSA but not
really in that what you start with is
you fetch your data and fetching a data
most of the time is really simple right
because all you have to do is make an
AJAX request for a JSON file well
sometimes it's more complicated
sometimes you're going over WebSockets
sometimes you actually want to do
polling and sometimes you want to reset
your data every time and sometimes you
want it to be unique against the data
you already have because maybe you're
polling Twitter every second and you get
an overlap and records right so all
those sorts of things are really stupid
mundane data things that nobody actually
wants to deal with so we try to build
into data set this idea of importers
that really have to do with just
fetching of your data right they don't
do any data processing they don't do any
data management their only job is to go
ahead and fetch things and by default
you know they just go make a JSON
request an AJAX request for whatever
type of file but practically speaking
you can kind of write your own we've
written our own so we have one for
example for google spreadsheets because
that's a commonly used data store in
journalism and also a really easy way to
pull up your data in and a really hard
place to get your data out of so if
you've ever tried
then the next step is really parsing it
right so again if I just have my data
pre-formatted into arrays of objects
that's awesome but most of the time
that's not going to happen and so what
we do is we have things like comma
delimited parsers and and Google
spreadsheet parsers which is absolutely
the most horrible format and whatever
other parser is you really want so if
somebody wants to write an XML parser
please do we don't so we're not going to
and then once you do what the parsers
really do is they combine all the data
into this unified format that data set
actually uses and from there on you can
do a bunch of different things you can
compute various values you can filter
the data and whatever way you want and
you can derive new data sets out of that
data and the nice thing that you can
kind of once you do one of those
operations you can do the rest so for
example a selection from the data set is
actually another data set to be more
specific it's something called a date of
you and that it's immutable because it's
not supposed to be mutable it's tied to
your original data but the nice thing by
doing it that way is that we can offer
things like event coordination so doona
sets available both in nodejs and on the
client side and we've piped hundreds of
thousands of tweets through it in node
and it didn't break which was the
happiest day of my life ever not really
and as I mentioned it comes a lot of
importers and parsers importers and
parsers for common data sources and
structures and we're definitely taking
contributions for that and it has this
idea of a vented views so once you have
a selection from your data set or maybe
a selection from a selection from a
selection doesn't really matter you can
enable synchronization between them with
just a little flag and what it does is
whenever you add or remove or update
records it's going to pipe that those
events to those to those views so
because really nice if you have various
visualizations or other views built on
top of selections you're not responsible
for propagating those changes yourself
you can just kind of enable that in the
data set and it'll you know trigger the
events you're expecting and then it has
some common math functions mins Max's
means whatever we're always writing more
as people asked for them and some
derived functions and by derive that
mean things like group eyes or count
buys or
some of those slightly more complex
sequel type things that come at the end
of the query after the where so we try
to have as many of those as as people
ask for again so here's an example for
if I want to dry just go ahead and fetch
my heroes from a URL I go and just say
new me so dataset from a URL or if I
have it locally can just use the data
property instead and then I go ahead and
I call heroes that fetch then so on the
background I uses deferred if you really
want to pass it a success or an error
call back you can but by default we
really want people to use the firts
because you can chain them and do all
sorts of great things and so all that's
going to do is it's going to output the
length of my data set which is I have
570 in my data set or a slightly more
complicated example so I go ahead and
get my heroes that I want to count them
by the hair color because i'm very
curious how you know what distribution
of hair colors are in my heroes and then
i go ahead and actually sort them so we
take for those of you who like use
underscore and are and do not like the
the sort by only taking one value
neither do we so we we have a sort by
function that takes both rows and then
you can kind of define however you want
to compare the two as long as your turn
1 negative 1 or 0 and now we'll just go
ahead and sort your data and then you
know let's say we have some print
function so we're going to get a list of
all top hair colors turns out none is
the most popular value and then black
and brown turns out bald as a hair color
I was not aware that's good to know for
fall fashion anyway so there's a bunch
of other examples there of data set
things but I wanted to go over one
before we're done called super powers so
again I mentioned those many many super
power properties and I thought it'd be
fun to kind of take a look and see if
they're related in any way so I tried to
see if there's any clusters of
superpowers they're used together there
aren't so but that example is still
there if you want to look it's called
co-occurrence HTML but we're going to
look at super powers HTML and it just
has a few metrics about superpowers so
there's a hundred and so
24 of them total and there's about five
pursue / hero and that's kind of the
distribution right there there's one
person it was 45 and I keep meaning to
go back and see what that is and then
there's a top ten right and these kind
of represent how many heroes versus how
many villains have them so it looks like
there's a lot more super-strong villains
and there are heroes which is kind of
interesting my favorite is actually the
bottom 10 because for example I didn't
know that wishing was a superpower that
makes me a superhero and quite a few
other ones like or Bing I don't even
know what orbing is so anyways just an
example of cool things you can query out
of your data so let's look very quickly
at the code that put that together so um
whoops so as I mentioned I go ahead and
I fetch my data I just call it the fetch
on it and then the first thing I do is I
just need a list of all the superpowers
so i'm using underscore for this right
super the standard lived for javascript
and then what i want to do is actually
want to add them up right i want to get
that count of how many superpowers each
here has so in this isn't actually live
yet but we're going to be releasing oh
point three soon it's going to have
computed columns which everybody has
been asking for but it's just a way to
make a column that you don't actually
have the data for to begin with it's
actually a calculation of a bunch of
properties whatever and the nice thing
is that stays in sync for you so if
you're updating anything about your rows
all your computer columns are going to
go and recalculate for those specific
rows so that's pretty fun so really all
I do here is I say Oh create this column
called SP count and it's going to be a
number and then please just go ahead and
add them up right I'm just doing a
little inject here starting with 0
basically add the zeros and ones which
is pretty simple and then I go and
update those little charts and so that's
an example you know in terms of
iterating over all my data I can just
call dot each again very common pattern
and this is sort of our selection
mechanism and that you can just call dot
where and pass in a function as long as
it returns true that function will be
included in your selection versus not
right so again very basic and the rest
is all just kind of you know HTML
updating and stuff so that's useful data
set in a in a really quick whirl
and that's the one I can answer the most
questions on if you ever need anything
please ping me about it and I just want
to kind of sum up a couple things that I
learned from data crunching in the
browsers is the first thing of course I
think about whether you're going to most
of your operations involve rows or
columns because you may need both or you
may want to optimize for one or the
other you may have seen that I mix and
match my libraries all the time right
i've used underscore and just about all
my examples because sometimes it's
really fast but beware of iterating too
much right if I call that filter and
rejects and each that's three times that
I've iterated all over all my data so
there may be a more wise way for you to
do that and there's a couple examples
for underscore as well and that in that
repository beware of premature
optimization right so I like performance
testing like the next guy but unless I
know that I'm going to have two hundred
thousand records on my client I really
don't care because practically speaking
when you're dealing with maybe a few
hundred or even a few thousand records
those performance metrics might not
really be very accurate because they're
going to be impacted by the load on your
machine or other tabs are doing all the
other JavaScript running on your page so
they're just less consistent so as much
as I say everybody performance test your
code practically speaking if you know
you're not going to deal with a lot of
data pick the library that works the
best for you instead of the one that
might just like be two percent faster in
that guy's benchmarks if you're going to
be searching a lot through your data
then precash it right just create those
objects some of the libraries I showed
allow you to do that or they allow you
to filter things or so on but beware of
over caching because keys also take
space right anybody who uses I didn't
know sequel databases like I do
sometimes or whatever we all know that
Keys take space and its really nice to
structure with these really smart keys
that you can very easily select but at
the same time that is costly and if
you're going to be only using a subset
of your data be sure to filter that out
and then act on it there's no reason to
to have your data there if you're not
going to be using it and don't forget to
clean up your events right if you have
you eyes or tied through data that have
events and so on and so forth triggering
then the best thing you can do is make
sure those are outbound when you're done
and last but not least not everything
can be client-side right so I still do a
lot of my data
I in our or in the server or wherever it
is I need to have it happen because the
reality is most sometime idea doesn't
start with 500 records thankfully
there's not that many superheroes or
villains to keep track of but the nice
thing I can do is what I do have
multiple you is or visualizations or
whatnot that all require the same subset
of data the best thing you can do is
come up with that smaller subset and
pipe that to the client and so that's a
question I always get is how when do I
know what to keep on a server would to
keep on the client well find the
smallest upset and pipe that back but
when you do pipe it back it doesn't mean
that you're then left to your own
devices and and JavaScript basic API
there's lots of libraries that help you
work with your data so if you have any
questions please do reach out to me I
absolutely love answering things about
client-side data and data visualization
and a couple of like small buku things
that are not related but if you are into
gaming in JavaScript we're curating this
website called build new games and if
you want to write with us we get to pair
speakers which is really excite us which
is really exciting so contact me or
email admin opoku and we've all been
talking about functional programming and
no programming and I'm tired of that
argument so if you're interested in
application control flow management
which is really what we need just come
chat with me for a library that we're
alpha testing now and I'd love to give
you access and get your opinion so
that's that