alright so tonight or today I'm going to
talk about how we're going to code like
it's 1999 if you guys want I know you
don't have interwebs but for later on
you can follow along I've got a longer
version of the slideshow here so really
briefly Who am I once upon a time I used
to be a civil engineer but I quickly
became bored with a slow pace of the
projects I was doing so then I decided
what industry do I want to be in I think
I want to be in tech because it's super
innovative it's super fast paced and so
I started working in this industry as a
quote community specialist in other
words i was doing customer support so i
totally hated it and i taught myself to
code i would spend nights and weekends
working on my side projects going to
hackathons hack nights things like that
and eventually that led to success and i
landed a job as a web developer at hot
pads and i've been working there ever
since so here we go as a web developer
my first assignment at hot pads was to
redesign all of our emails and to make
the mobile friendly and i was like a
piece of cake no big deal right wrong I
quickly realized that I had no idea what
I was doing but fortunately i'm here to
share all of my strategies and my
mistakes with all view so here's my
story about how emails are evil i'm
going to talk a little bit about design
a bunch of things i learned before
during and after my emails were released
and a bunch of resources that i found so
first up a little bit about design so
the first thing i wanted to do was to
redesign our welcome email since that
was kind of the punch in the face of our
users it's like hey come to our website
welcome so what I did was I started
researching other people's welcome
emails so I look I scoured my own email
accounts i started signing up for all
these different services just so i could
look at their emails a lot of the stuff
is pretty instinctual
but I made a quick list oops so my
favorite email actually comes from indy
gogo it's not a welcome email but it's
just really pretty so let's take a look
at IndieGoGo well it's huge okay so the
first thing that I notice about this
email was like the huge top anchor logo
ok this emails from indy gogo FYI I
noticed that they also have a lot of
really great content so you see lots of
images less text in general another
great thing they do is all their calls
to action are this bright magenta so you
see URLs here in that color and then all
of these read more buttons and that's
consistent through the email a couple of
other things I noticed is they've got
these social media icons as well as the
text down here which is really great for
accessibility and then at the very very
bottom of course the unsubscribe and way
to update your subscription preferences
I am trying to switch tabs now
whoops
sorry about that
all right let's go back to my slides or
not
all right everybody take a nap i know we
just had the lunch so yep thank you all
right so from that email and the bunch
of bunches of emails i was looking at I
had a found a bunch of takeaways and
those are that you want to keep your
emails texts light you want to keep them
image-heavy just to keep the interest of
your users have that huge top anchored
logo so people know where your email is
coming from and then also you want to
set a max width on your email you don't
want people reading across the screen
just to see what you want to say alright
so the next thing I wanted to take a
look at was the emails that I'd be
working with so I did and here's the
welcome email from hot pads I was like
oh my god so a couple of things first
off why is the logo right in the middle
of email I don't know another thing
you'll notice is the spacing is really
inconsistent throughout the email it
doesn't really make any sense why things
are have the margins that they do the
last thing I noticed was wait where do
you unsubscribe if your user the type of
user who gets really annoyed at all of
these emails pummeling your inbox then
you definitely want to be able to at
least find that unsubscribe no matter
how hard it is to find so basically I
was like dog I was like wow okay so
that's what I'm working with so the next
thing I wanted to do in designing our
emails was to plan on what I was making
and I had a couple of goals in mind so
the first was to bring a bunch of
consistency to our emails I took a look
at all of our emails across hot pads and
they were all different like the logos
in different places there are different
margins different icons so I was like
all right let's bring some consistency
to them and in general having that
consistency will bring brand awareness
again seeing that top anchor blue logo
over and over again will make sure that
your brand is recognizable so another
thing I took a look at in my planning
was a bunch of pre-made templates I'm
sure a bunch of you guys have seen all
those and there are just lots of options
which I'm going to talk about a little
bit later and I actually didn't use any
of them
the reason why was because I was redoing
all of our emails we have a pretty like
specific user base that uses outlook a
lot still so I wanted to make sure I had
something that was customizable also
being that this was the first project I
did as a web developer it was a learning
experience for me and I had a lot of
time on my hands so if you're a company
that doesn't have the time you could go
with a template but if you've got a lot
of time and you need a customizable
solution then I'd recommend just
building your own the next thing I did
was a bunch of sketches so if I've
learned anything from UX it's that
sketching is awesome so you see here
I've actually sketched the same email
four different times and in general when
you do sketch you will find that your
later sketches are much better than the
previous ones so it's good to just do it
over and over again another thing you
can do in planning your design is if
you've got the skills for photoshop i'd
recommend it it's great you can have a
quick mock-up so you see here one of the
earlier mock-ups of our wealth of our
welcome email that i did another thing
to keep in mind is what i call the rule
of thumbs so minimum touchable area i
think a lot of people heard the number
44 x 44 pixels this is actually based on
the original iphones human interface
guidelines which actually no longer
exists so wipe that number from your
mind take a look at these links you'll
find a bunch of different minimum
touchable areas for different devices
they vary quite a bit so you probably
want to take a look at the devices that
your users have and then base it on the
largest size all right so here's my
template this is the email i created
from the original one again you'll see
the top anchor logo you'll see the links
are underlined for accessibility as well
as color colored differently i changed a
bunch of things for mobile and for
social media so that you have images
instead and again with the text below
for accessibility it's a little bit hard
to see but below that in the footer I'm
mimicking what hot pads
website used to look like it's the same
footer so people kind of see that
consistency from the web on to the
emails so I like to say that it's an
aesthetic that Prince would approve of
and just for reference here's the
original email and then the email that I
designed so they see the content is a
little bit longer in my version but I
think it looks a whole lot better and a
lot of trap or traffic shot up shot
through the roof after the redesign of
this email all right on to code a bunch
of tips and tricks so you can find my
template on github it's just the general
template that I created for the hot pads
emails so why template a great thing
about having a template is that you can
keep your code dry so you're not
repeating yourself so see in my email
what we're calling our little micro
listing it's like the same little block
of code just repeated over and over
again again you'll see the consistency
in the hot pads logo so that people know
where emails coming from as well as the
frame and the footer so a little bit of
abstraction goes a really long way all
right some things that I learned before
I started coding my emails tables are
coming Mozilla developer network says
note prior to the creation of CSS HTML
table elements were often used as a
method for page layout this usage has
since been discouraged or excuse me been
discouraged since HTML 4 and the table
element should not be used for layout
purposes emails sale ol to that so one
thing I found out was that tables do not
display as inline or block the default
CSS for a table is to display as table
probably makes sense but one thing I
found it is you actually want to specify
your tables to display its block other
chrome otherwise chrome is going to
totally ignore your max width
another thing I learned about we're in
line styles you've got to use them
because most email clients do not
support a head section in your HTML page
there's a CSS excuse me a page on
campaign monitor letting you know what
CSS is supported over different email
clients and also there are actually
really great websites that will actually
put your styles in line for you so
unfortunately you're going to be doing a
lot of this you'll see all of my Styles
in line it's it's a mess but like I said
you've got those tools that can help you
another thing is the max width so you
see here I've got a really wide email
that I received so you're just going to
be just reading across the page so just
take a note from print design you don't
want people reading across the page you
want them to be able to scan with their
eyes so good max with number to keep in
mind is 550 to 600 pixels and that's
based on most email clients preview
pains so quick note about comments
you're going to have tables all the way
down your page tables within tables
within tables for your email so you take
a quick look at the code up here I've
got a couple of comments letting me know
when one table starts and one table ends
and it's a good thing to keep in mind so
use a lot of comments alright another
thing to keep in mind our image alt
alternatives so it's really good to
always have an alt attribute on your
image tags or a background color set on
them it's really good for accessibility
in case the email client isn't going to
display your image oops so you'll see
here gmail is not displaying the hot
pads logo so by having that alt
attribute it's really helpful for users
to see what they are missing out on and
you know if they want to click just to
see the hot pads logo that would be
great another thing again accessibility
so below you'll also see that I've set a
background color on the footer of my
email just in case that image at the
bottom doesn't show you'll see
see this nice blue border surrounding
the email all right some things I
learned while I was coding so media
queries we all love media queries right
maybe well they're really great for
things like readability and targeting
specific devices again this talk is
about responsive emails so here you'll
want to keep you'll see here that i set
a max width on the background table of
my email for any device or browser
that's much wider another thing you can
do with media queries is use them in
conjunction with fluid layouts and
percentage based widths so you'll see
here I'm targeting devices that have a
max width of 480 pixels and for any
email clients that actually don't
recognize media devices I also have the
table with set to one hundred percent so
it's really good to use those in
conjunctions you can hit all those
different email clients and a quick note
about media queries so when I was
designing these emails I actually focus
on the browser first and then had them
degrade over mobile and that's just
because our users mostly were accessing
the emails on route on browser versus
mobile devices so it's a little bit hard
to see here it's cut off but you guys
can check out those slides later alright
the next thing to keep in mind is again
device pixel ratio for your media
queries so here I'm targeting all the
retina or high res devices and I'll get
into that a little bit later okay
important when should we use it most
people say never and for me and emails I
say sometimes so important here what
you'll see is sometimes your inline
styles will be will overwrite your media
queries and you don't always want that
to happen so for my mobile devices I've
set the header bar to be a height of 5
pixels and for browser-based or like
wider devices I
have the header bar set to 10 pixels so
you'll see the inline style will
overwrite the media query so in this
case having important there in the media
query will make sure that the header bar
stays small for mobile devices all right
this one's a little bit weird so the
very bottom of this image you'll see a
thin blue line at the bottom of that
footer and I was like what is that where
did that come from why can't I make it
go away well it turns out it was a line
height issue so there are a couple of
solutions that will resolve that for me
and one is to set a line height on the
surrounding column element the other is
to set the image to display as block so
it doesn't interact with those line
heights all right lastly things that I
learned after the release of my emails
whoops so this one is super weird and
only occurs occasionally so occasionally
that I don't even have an example of it
but once in a while your image will
appear with a thin gray border around it
I was like why is that happening and it
mostly only happened in gmail and I
couldn't figure it out until I just
tried something randomly so it turns out
the reason was because I had the image
on a different line than my anchor
element so actually putting them in line
got rid of that border don't ask me why
if you guys see a gray border around
your images and emails now you'll know
that this is the solution another thing
I notice was my high-res images for
retina were not being sized down so
people were getting this email which
obviously is not going to make them want
to go to our site so it's like okay what
do I do well the problem is that outlook
2007 1013 and outlook for internet
explorer don't allow for HTML or CSS
resizing of images so there's like oh
great what do I do now well the solution
is to replace your image with a
background image style on the
surrounding column element and then set
the image to display as none and i found
that solution from campaign monitor
so see the code here so up at the top
you'll see for my high res devices that
I've set a background image on that
surrounding column element and then I
set the image to display as none and
you'll see the HTML down here alright
another thing I learned was at outlook
2007 2010 and 2013 ignore max width so
what you want to do here is have a max
width bypass so you'll set a fluid
layout for your baseline elements so
you'll see here i set a width fluid
width of a hundred percent and then a
media query for any screens that are
larger than that to set a fixed width
instead of a max width of 600 pixels so
you may be wondering outlook 2007 10 and
13 WTF well it turns out that the
rendering engines for CH outlook 2002
2003 our intern is internet explorer for
2007-2010 in 2013 it's microsoft word
yeah and i don't ask me why I would look
2011 they made the right move and they
used WebKit they call it outlook for mac
so the rendering engine is awesome but
then I don't know why they just switched
back in 2013 alright the last thing that
I learned after the release of my email
who is that gmail ignores any color
styles on your anchor tags in the head
of your HTML page so you actually have
to go and sell every single anchor tag
in line in your email all right now some
quick resources so I found all these
really great blogs style campaign is a
company run by Anna Yemen you'll see in
the background it's kind of faint but
you'll see her device library so she
spends a ton of time on email and
marketing it's a really great blog lots
of solutions there litmus is a testing
suite for emails they also have a really
great blog and they take note of
weirdnesses in the
for an outlooks and I think everyone's
pretty familiar with campaign monitor
and MailChimp again they have a really
great blog and they are both online
marketing email solutions all right so
off to the templates that I had
mentioned earlier so there's herb Inc
the same company that puts out
foundation again campaign monitor and
MailChimp have their own templates which
are really great and then there's the
HTML email boilerplate by shawn powell
and i don't know if you can see it but
it's in the background of this email so
or of this slide and you can see it gets
a little bit complicated so it
definitely takes care of everything you
need but something to keep in mind it's
a lot of code another thing to keep in
mind is i just found out that sir pink
actually doesn't support outlook 2007 10
or 13 so they made these great templates
but they took the easy way and then
lastly testing so email on acid and
litmus are really great testing suites
email on acid is free witness is not
unfortunately the company i work for it
has a subscription with knit litmus and
so you may be see that in the background
as well but basically you can send them
an email and they'll display what your
email will look like across different
email clients and that's it you guys
have any questions you can speak to me
later