how's it going everybody
I don't know if this is working okay
cool
so my name is Aman this is I see my
first time in LA I'm originally from
Cincinnati I came down here for this
talk sorry
oh thank you this is also I did not know
was gonna be this many of you guys I
thought was gonna be like 20 people the
usual case but this is awesome so like I
said my name is Aman I studied physics
at University of Cincinnati I now work
for this company data czar and before I
get into d3 and the awesomeness of d3 I
want to talk to you guys about what we
do a little bit so we can be a little
context so days are is a research
collaboration or data collaboration
platform we allow people to upload data
analyze that make visualization and
stuff like that and then share it back
to whoever uploaded the data so you can
kind of see context and I guess that is
not working okay
can you guys hear anything now yeah how
about now I'm trying to hold it you got
it now good good good
Oh awesome okay all right which part
should I say again I'm just kidding so
these are a research collaboration
platform where we allow people to upload
data or share here back make
visualizations and v3 and stuff like
that so you can kind of see how a data
evolved from the beginning so goes from
raw data set to being prepared to being
analyzed to being visualized and then
share back what you found and the whole
idea was are people gonna get the same
results if they use one of the same
analysis platforms they use the same
methods and what's gonna be the
difference at the end right and so the
whole reason we kind of started was the
whole research process now was
completely messed up
all right especially because it's very
old-school I'd say for us a little bit
so you you do your analysis young you do
you view your data collection you
analyze it whatever from a network
analyzer or whatever it is and I'm gonna
be really physics specific here just cuz
that's what I know
you do that and then you analyze li
visualize them and you send it to your
advising professor or whoever it is your
team their an email and you upload it to
Dropbox and then at the end you finally
share it then in the middle you've
completely lost a lot of things all the
context you know how you went from point
A to point B what methods you use unless
you specifically specify that and
whatever you're sending right and so we
said okay let's make this very simple
you upload your data through either API
or interface and then you you
collaborate the site where you're gonna
add a lighter and why not and then you
analyze it using whatever it is showing
all the steps that you're taking and
then finally share it and if somebody
else sees that if somebody comes in the
middle of the research project they can
see exactly where you left off where
you've done to get to that step right so
you wanted everything to be in line all
right enough about that and then at the
end for us was if somebody used the
statement let's say for example somebody
use temperature data from NASA to you
know work on global warming especially
wanted the projects were working on
somebody else uses it for economics and
somebody else use it for healthcare
somebody else use it for whatever we
wanted to see how these different topics
related to each other it's really
interesting you can see some topics are
closer than you think even if you did
not see look at the data right economics
might be really close to physics or do
whatever if you guys go to here you can
guys can see all the data you don't have
to sign up you just get that okay so d3
the reason we started with d3 was people
who when people were uploading data they
were leaving the platform a lot of the
times just to analyze this data and then
they would come back and it was lose a
lot of stuff in between so he said ok
what would it take to let people analyze
data on our platform obviously the
obvious answer first was Jupiter right
you could have notebooks Python in art
but we said ok how about we use Java
scripts that can kind of give us a kick
and everybody knows JavaScript that's
really you know out there and d3 is
really awesome so we said ok let's do
that let's work on JavaScript but the
problem right
the problem was a lot of these d3 and
announces that were being made were kind
of one-off right people would make them
right hundred lines of code if you
wanted to use that same thing for your
own analysis it would not work right
it's very very project specific so we
said how about we obstruct it a little
bit and let people use each other's code
right and there was this wonderful thing
right we create our own programming
language and we say okay we're gonna let
people abstract
d3 modules and then we're gonna let
other people call those modules and
match it with whatever data they're
doing right so he said people will be
able to write you know point plot
function and then you will get somebody
else's data on the platform and then you
can plot that in real time while you're
on the platform so our whole thing was
people should not be leaving our
platform to do whatever they were doing
so this is kind of what looked like he
would this is a kind of a mix we have
structured it a little bit in the
beginning as well it's kind of a mix of
raw JavaScript and d3 so people would
make this this module they would write
it on the on our platform using d3 which
is already included as a library and
then you can even test it as a test file
here and then somebody would call that
function from our from our platform
right you know zoom in here a little bit
for the code so our code is very very
very simple I would even call a
programming language is more kind of
like these commands you would send to
get back these outputs so you would say
okay I want I want to visualize this
data set and here is this and I want to
use this d3 code specific code if you
see there the line plot the that you
mean the the line plot function I would
say okay my user name and then the line
plot function and then that would plot
me whatever this is right this is just a
random numbers being visualized so we
got a little bit more complex people
were building these modules and then you
would call them and then the biggest
problem came people had to learn how to
write a new language and people had had
to know how to make d3 modules and so
this was a complete failure right people
were not making this need to not want to
learn a new language there was they said
okay why not use our why not use
mathematic
why not using that lab we just wanted
people to stay but they would and so
what what we did now was we said okay
that did not work so how can we still
let people use JavaScript and still be
able to plot data on our platform all
right and so we went more into into
templates instead of using our own
language so let's say for example you
take this raw data set this is like this
is a temperature data we got from NASA
here's the expanded view and then we
said okay even if it's horrible let's
just let people write lines of code to
analyze this data set so here's that
just to plot this function this this
data all right that's just one month you
would have to write all of that just to
do one thing if we did it in our own
programming language all of that would
be extracted for you only thing you to
do is just give it that pointer that a
file and then you just plot it
automatically right but that didn't work
still people did not want to learn in
language here's another one here's a
he's another templated function here
this is plotting each month of the same
data set and this is kind of where we
want to go at the end of the day is
people are not leaving the platform that
you're just doing it in real time on the
platform right there right without
having to leave anything and then you're
still at the same time showing people
how you did it
people can see you see your source code
they can see what data point you use you
can see how you analyze that because a
lot of the times when you're doing
especially computational stuff you want
to see under the hood of that
mathematical function all right what is
that actually doing does that differ
from platform to platform right
especially when you get to higher
numbers if you want to get more accurate
to what extent is that approximating and
stuff like that to it so our our whole
vision is can people because people can
see more and more of the code they can
see under the hood they can see under
the hood of the functions would it be
better for the whole community right it
will be better if you can see for how I
got from point A to point B and there's
a lot there's a huge culture of just
showing the end results and not showing
what you've done before so we kind of
wanted to get rid of that it's a huge
huge problem and we're not gonna be able
to fix anytime soon but we think this is
a good start
here's another one and so when you save
these files you can see you can see
exactly how somebody did it and they're
saved just like any other file you can
download this file just like any other
file you would in a platform and so
here's another one so a few weeks ago
somebody was a few weeks a few months
ago actually somebody uploaded where
every meteorite has hit in the world
since like the 1700s we got that data we
plotted it using d3 and this is kind of
what we want happening on a bigger scale
right I upload some things everybody
else goes on the platform to analyze
something and then we would get back
results can we match this with something
else and can we predict stuff can we can
we see that how this has affected
something else right this is kind of the
bigger picture of our of our whole thing
but again I kept saying like we want to
go back to JavaScript that's just cuz
everybody knows it and it's more
comfortable to write in I think at least
we will be supporting Jupiter just
because it's a really high demand right
now for us and our as well and be
writing SDKs for all these other
languages but there's another example of
using d3 and all this is open source
open and open source you guys can go
check it out so next we'll be
integrating mass J is probably one of
the craters here mats JSON d3 so we want
to not only just visualize because
visualizations are just literally the
end of what you do in a research process
you have to do all the computation all
the analysis all the cleaning so we kind
of want to integrate that expand it a
little bit and see if we can do a lot of
the computational stuff also before we
get to the visualizations
that's it and here's my contact
information if you guys want I'll open
up for questions in a little bit and
talk a little bit more but so far is
there any questions no animation yeah I
mean do you know if we support it yeah I
mean anything you write so actually
didn't show up as PDF what anything
you're right here will be displayed if
it's animation or whatever it is
yeah we'll display everything at some
point we're gonna have to start checking
what kind of code it is just cuz it's a
little disruptive sometimes what yeah
anything is supported as long as your
browser handles it yeah oh
the signup URL
there's any question yeah interesting
so whenever we release a data set the
most common thing we see is just people
analyzing a data differently using
different platforms so we usually see
somebody do it in our somebody do it in
Python usually they look like the same
results
so just people using different platforms
there's also animations and stuff like
that we've just kicked this off about
three two months ago so we haven't seen
that much but it's pretty good we all
like we haven't pushed out a lot of data
a lot of the data we have is so we have
Olympics data all the data from NASA
city of Cincinnati Ohio and stuff like
that we haven't we haven't come here yet
we will most all of the ten secrets to
writing perfect code that I'm gonna tell
you tonight have previously been covered
@j SLA so here we go number one practice
practice practice practice just like
everything else in life that's
challenging and rewarding you need to
practice so you can practice with online
tools like node school or you can attend
to the upcoming node school or you can
do things like hacker ring you can also