well hello everyone my name is Reynoso will develop from
front-end I worked at mercadolibre a little over a year ago I think a
little my role as a front-end developer in the free market, both good me and
my colleagues have a lot of responsibility because everything
we do ends up impacting an unimaginable number of users for whom
do not know free market we are the platform the leader in commerce in
latin america and we have a lot of visits all the time so everything
what we end up doing impacts an amount as I was saying incredible
So I think we have a motto or try to live a motto a
goal you feel please and all things and most
important for us to always put the needs of the user
first even above ours as developers
and speaking of users and always for more first a little bit comes
related so I want to tell you there I think talking about users and
happy users I think well I think we all know what a user is
happy we all want to be happy users and a happy user I think that
they love to have a website or fast, that is, even if they are part of a website or
fast a happy user but we really know
which is a fast website we call a fast website
here I distinguish from two categories on the one hand that the site is literally
fast, that is, let's say fast loading, the loading times are short and for the
another side is that the user perceives that the site is fast which does not mean
the site is fast but the user something happens to him what
understand that the site itself is fast and now that keyword comes in which is
perception speaking a little bit of perception I
would like us to go back to the year 993 jakob nielsen which is a group of
toys for those who don't know him they told us one of his books a little bit
about limits in perception, that is, how the user reacts over time to
the response for example an application or a website
about these times in perception are breaking points
the first one is 100 milliseconds 0.1 seconds which is in which the user goes
to feel that the response you are receiving is instantaneous
then we have a second which is from this point where we start a little
to give the user's attention his train of thought is going to start to stray
and and then it's already the 10 second limit
that if we really still have a user who is interested in complying
with the aim that I was wanting to do grace we will have lost
completely already start to even feel frustration about what you're having
performed I think we were all there I don't know who has endured and for today 10
seconds with a blank page then us understanding what they are
our limits and how the user understands and reacts to this I think that
a little bit we can realize where where we want more or less serves
showing him some kind of visual acid I think this happens around the
second the second we have to give the user give give
a wake up call that something is happening
ok understood more or less perception and
the times we have in our pothole let's say and let's see how we can
optimize for that we have to we have to understand what is going on we have
that knowing what is happening with rendering here is a little bit that is
what is render impact we know we are talking
so well what are we really talking about in very general terms
basically that is for example we organize an action click a link
whatever we get a url and we give sit on what happens up to what the
browser performs until complete rendering on screen to our page
web for example in very general terms but
it is simply the path that the browser takes is a series of
events that meet to reach this goal and that's in very terms
generic but what is this all about let's do the steps one by one are
seven steps they perform to fulfill the rendering puff and now we are going to see
there how to give criticism to the render impact that only they have also
heard first thing basically going to do is
generate a network request out a lot of things don't happen there's a in that
place you have a cpi connection it is good then finally send
http request here between a little and a little we have
about 600 milliseconds in which we don't have too much control
about what's going on ok let's imagine everything is fine with
the request the service what it is going to do is give us an answer
depending on our role a little as you want to have a little part in what
the answer may take time but well let's imagine it helps Serbian already
replied gave us in html now a few advance what would be the critic
rendering for the critical part that the user sorry that the browser
meets to reach the goal of rendering on screen and all this
starts with the html processing I imagine we have the answer that we
gave are 8000 is super simple what the browser is going to be it is going to be processed
from top to bottom what you need to do is translate it the
browser what it will do then is generate the gift to everyone I think we know
what is it is a node map in which
going to put together all those connections what it will be then is
translate for example is in any such encounter begins
voluntary title markets etc converts them into new maps in the
Sunday there will come a point that for example find a tag of the link with
a reference an external css resource what you're going to do at this point is going to
slow down this process which is doing the html processing and once you
receives the response from the css then it will begin to process what happened here is
what the browser understands is what do you need that to render in
screen so what it does is brake absolutely what it's doing is to
what we call blogging and then start processing and it works
pretty similar with html to have all the rules all the instructions
and it is going to be turning them into other more good others like the one that is the
session in which it is good will also end with everything processed in nodes
one is that I end that one is going to go back to the previous process or is going to
continue processing the html surely the other css is in a process
it will re-process it will come back until it ends other things than what
in the render they are good there is also a script that is both an external resource and
something internal and pretty mental for example and a such for example good once you
it has finished processing the html what will happen is the following
is going to start generating around wheat that we only hear the
name already tells us a lot on the one hand that there are 3 is going to tell us that their
node map too and the randers is the part of it is actually what is going
to finish rounding what is visible on the screen so here in the render
tree what you are going to do is combine the other two trees that you generated
previously and going to combine or unify relationships
they have each other for that in the randers and they will end up locating
all the things that are going to be visible and I insist what is inside
body and well there are some parks that are included for example that will never
be render leds on screens i don't know all write all you are
etcetera and apart as its name says it is what it is to render on screen and
we are also combining the ss instructions there are things that are going to
exclude with elements of which they are in the gift by excluding from rendering the
render tree like everything you have display not for example it will not end
appearing changes one is that it already has everything processed that
This is what will end up rendering on the screen, a stage of the
layout and it is also known as read flow which basically what is going to
do is size everything in the newport is going to
interpret all according to the rules that all elements have applied
going to calculate the positions etcetera and all the sizes all this part of
processing once you have it ready and super cooked what you will do
is to paint it on screen it sounds very simple but these good times can
take more or less we know there are properties etc that are a little bit more
expensive to paint than others but well ultimately everything will end up painted
ok until we understand a bit what it is
the process ends here, finally we will have content
visual on the screen one is that we understand that this is all
we understood which also with that part is critical that is to say everything that was
after the answer forwards there is everything that does not itself
to render on screen once we already understand more or less
how these steps work and develop we can see how we can
optimize
[Music] these are a couple of tips, that is,
very basic things surely many of these things are already doing
but well they will end up helping us to save some moments in the load by
one side let's try to pack our assets we already know that if it is long dorca
Once you find something, what you are going to do is stop everything and go find it.
we give it as few opportunities as possible so that we will finish it
saving a little time, surely what is happening today is that we have the
winds on the one hand our own things on the other and the truth that no
we are benefiting, preferably having everything packaged in the minimum quantity
possible and that nobody now less request on the other hand
this is great the remains are not yet many standards but it is good
so that they investigate them so that they are taking them into account basically what
they are going to do is indicate value when using things that we are going to end up needing
in the future, so one of the processes will be anticipated
investigate pri with the dns perfetti and pri what now we are going to see a
they can give us a little hand well this is super audio
let's try whenever we can what obviously goes through this basically is
the advice let's not write on the gel and lastly
means more difficult we see where possible all our assets this we
going to save bytes by whatever or translate in time
okay
Hence, as the criticism of the impact follows, we saw a little like
optimize it but well I promised them that I would
come to talk about dss and how it is impacted in performance so if
they remember a little bit of what I told them at the beginning of the two classes
of quick websites the first part would come as meeting the
first point is to make the site really faster and I
I think the part of is essence that I am going to tell you now plays for the second
side that is to deceive the user's perception a little to make him
believe that the site really really is a little bit faster
this is where the day comes to save us criticize the css
this is a technique before starting to tell you well what
are treated I would like to make a clarification because many times we are
the first one that we are repeating criticizing all the time and it is super
confusing on the other hand we are talking about they criticize css they are criticizing peace not
there are a lot of things that end up mixing so much what
we are really talking then to critical path basically
We are talking about the path that the browser travels to meet the
objective of rendering css or just the name tells us we are within the path
of the route and on the other hand critic ss is the technique we have to improve
that journey we always try to think of it as
that one goes above the other improving and improving the path and also
we test is critical they sound like super negative it sounds like a bad thing but not
It is the truth that it is not, it is simply a synonym of what
it would be a vital necessary thing if you want you can think of it as vital
ccs instead of criticizing so as not to get so confused with the names but
well now let's see why it is called criticism etc
think for example well this is the product page on mercadolibre that
is what the user is going to give in the first stage this what I like to call it the
initial screen what the user is the first thing they will see when they enter
the page that is looking at this in the publishing world is known as the voice
folk only also know it that way basically what we want
do with this technique if this is the first thing you will see the
user is the only thing we should load for which our styles
critics or our vital or necessary styles are these only the ones that
meet this part this portion of the view port
that's why I think the translation would be like the necessary styles for our
view of the web so hello let's imagine we already defined which
these are the styles we have super cooked are these then I said
the only thing we have to send to the browser so that we can learn and be
then the only thing we should load in the head are the only styles the
critical styles now and then if we think about
a second if we see a little bit of when we talk about rendering peace and what
block if we have these styles in a separate band but no file
external we would be a little behind in the times so I think that
what we are going to have to do is the oversold many people don't
like it and they always told us not to do that is to put styles online in
the gel this must be the reaction of many
because before moving on why about the rest of our styles
before that let's see why we think the second thing basically what we don't want
is that the browser has absolutely everything necessary
if we leaving the styles in girl it will already have everything in the first html that
receive so the rendering time is going to be much less
Now what happens with the rest of our styles, that is, if the user
put to interact will see content that was without studying which is not what
What we want here is where the game comes in a little javascript magic that
basically what we want to do is help us because only
we put in the critical styles in the head what we are going to do is that when
the page finishes everything to download is to look for the rest of our styles and
put them in the browser what you're going to do is going to interpret the change and
simply what you are going to do is go find them reuse on screen
etcetera which is why by the time the user has already started to
interact there will be final content
but we don't care about us so the user for him what
he is watching the end he is not interested in the rest because he is not interacting
with that ok what are we going to gain so what is a little bit of what
we were talking about before we will gain the perception of the charge time of the
page the user as I was saying what you will see is content that is for him is
In the end, even if it is not, we are not deceiving a little, but well, he does not know
going to account there are a couple of things we have to
also take into account on the one hand we are depending on the hash creep for
which probably some user base in which we are leaving
outside now a well know what we have to do in these cases but
well let's keep in mind and on the other hand on the other hand if always in first
our styles online our critical styles online not
we are going to be putting what is super important which is the browser cache
which basically is going to allow us to speed up the subsequent visits and the
user already has downloaded in the final styles, the ideal is that
Let's always show that because it will be much faster than the browser.
go find the user's machine even though we are always printing
online styles that will never be nearly proficient
let's say so what we have to do is save that data from silverio
carbon headquarters that is if javier the critical styles is now also
let's see how we are going to do ok up to this point I think we were
seeing a little bit what the theory of the technique would be like now we are going to see a
little bit of the ways we have to put it into practice first let's see how
we are going to load these critical styles there is a productions on one hand the
javascript script now i'm going to show you a little bit of an implementation
cast although it would be the basic thing that we have to do but also the plugins like
logs and if it did it is that it is surely well known they can search it is something
very simple basically what we are doing is listening to the windows logo
and in the color what we are going to do is create a link element put a couple of
attributes so that the browser understands that they are style sheets with the step to
our final styles audio and finally learn it that to the help we give is
nothing very complicated on the other hand remember that the challenge
I was telling you a little bit about Richard people this is great pri what is neither
It is nowhere near standard but can be exploited in the later
versions of chrome also this is something to go putting as improvement
progressive without we're going to have to have a powder
he is very good man I love you if he loves us they will get to know him is a
normal link basically the only change is king
which will be instead of this situation and what will happen to our styles
finals and what the players interpreted as it is a prologue what
you are going to do is then go find synchronously and not what was the
render well we also have to indicate that it is because this also works
for for javascript if it didn't reach me and it has events so
What we are going to do is simply the moment I finish loading that that
file we just discard it being a black stage when interpreting it
it is a sheet you stretch it is going to process it was going to work quietly like how
Normally, it is great to investigate the and you can apply the
use it and well also with the space before
now we also have to do a type of check if the user already has
our final styles for this we are going to make a cookie we no longer had
much more option than doing it from the server side, check me up to
the case of the example we are using php but it is used for anything
basically if you already have the cookie and if the cookie is the same as our version
because I also don't know this way we have versioned styles we want it to always have
grab the latest version what are we going to do if you already have it because you already visited
you already saw the critical styles we put our links to our
final styles but what we have to do is basically the technique we put
our critical styles online and well we do pretty much the same
check by javascript we load our critical styles and save in the
cusp you already have has your styles seen
and well also lastly what I was saying before we depend on hacker
and therefore we have to have a forum for users who do not have
javascript enabled because if not we are going to give you a poor experience
they will give half of the things so nothing just a script from our
our final styles and ready ok now that they are no less we saw how
load them let's see the most tedious part that
I think it is the generation of these critical styles that I distinguish from two
categories by one we have the automatic magic tools
as I like to tell you they can be good reviews and that's
penthouse penthouse also has an online and critical generator basically
are its dnpm modules so implement them in our golf what
usual should be super simple what they do in theory basically that
just a series of super configurable parameters and from that they extract the
styles on our page so very magically
on the other hand if we use a pre processor
can be salt and light suns or whatever and we have a good code does if
our styles are super motorized on sundays it is all separated in parayas
It is all very componentized, what we are going to do is simply tell you
understand us what are our critical styles for the view type
add bouquets and we generate our own band that of the styles
of the components that are going to be seen in a web default
in my experience the second option is the best one is basically the best one
scale for projects at least in large projects than where we apply it
it simply requires having a good code base or being well
thought from the beginning and then it just comes out just because
quietly it will be generating I know later on the other side of the
automated tools are very good it seems to me not for a type of
Simple projects with very static pages with little maintenance
styles where because apart is very tied to the url for example in
free market we have super dynamic networks for which many do not
They serve and also the size of the view so in some cases it is super
limiting for them I already advanced a little bit now we are going to talk about how
we implement critical css in mercadolibre
we started to think a little bit of criticism at the end of last year I'm going to tell you
a little about the first experience we had in implementing it and I will tell you
it was not good but afterwards good so that everything is not so bad I tell you that
then we also implemented on several other sides with a little bit of an experience
a little happier but hey let's see where we did it this first time
surely capable then I don't know if this part looks good well obviously
free dial are search listings and it's a good mobile that was
where we had the greatest need to improve performance
At first glance it seems very simple.The critical styles that
we should have but what does the list look for that is super dynamic
we have different types of views we have filters we have
other times another type of view we have banners we have official stores
we have a lot of variables and next to supercables that can be combined so it is very
random and ccoo where can user take out
so well there at that point when we started to do the implementation the
truth is that I had we are about to start the redesign which is the version
that we had just seen was the previous version
and besides the workflow we had was not very oiled
it was very green no no that did not allow us to have the tools
automated and puts the modular styles hoisted anywhere near we had them
So it is something that we did very well in a decline which is why I think
we make the worst possible decision we generate our styles online
when a super artisan way of own code we had on our own
bookcase and then we just got into that blender
online that is one crossed and we ended up with more than 20
different compilations for all the versions that we found later we
we find that once we leave production we continue
finding steps that we had not contemplated at first but well
you will imagine that this resulted in a total mess and equally at this point yes that
is one of those traces of this point we were happy the truth that we
everything was going more or less well the problem actually started when
we started to put fixes officers in our old code so we had
we absolutely regenerate all our critical styles for all
houses because we didn't really know where to hit and we ended up well
with the worst experience from from the point of
development view that we had at least since I am in free market
[Music] and well nothing
basically became impossible to maintain for that's the end point
What does incredible results mean for us as well,
experience the lips version was quite bad and well this is a
before and after comparison basically
we started to see content in the critical version at 1.4 seconds while
that in the previous version we only started at 2.5 to see the logo and
as you will see it is going to end there are already 56 better
As I will see you finish the four points 5
while the previous finished version receive 4.9 which is a
only 8% real-time loading improvements
that means well you get ahead a 56 percent improvement in perception
load time is not the actual load of the site is we enter the second
category and from a business point of view we improved the rate of 2%
conversion that may sound super little but in mercadolibre the bar which is a
heap where it is very rare that something that we implement at this level of
front-end for example ended up creating both in conversion
so well then what we saw was a little bit about criticism the css and
like that along with other optimizations layoffs will basically end us
in a total profit it was very for the users because for them the page
loaded 56 percent faster it was a good one for us for the company in
general because we ended up selling more for us it was not so much a win as
developers because I already told you that we had a bit of a hard time but well I think
that inside everything ended up making a win so nothing crazy I would like it to
take from this talk that I told you is a little bit like what it is about
the technique as they can take their own projects but above all
things I would like you to take a little bit on the focus set to speed or
how important it is that we think about dispatch and performance and how this
ends up also impacting the experience to our users that yes
remember in the motto at the beginning should be what we always put