how is everybody i got in at 6am and
then I still came here and I'm talking
to you and that was the best you can do
how is everybody there you go so I've
seen Jed present before he's pretty
slick right so instead of actually doing
anything with keynote I draw my sights
on my iPad because that way I don't have
to compete with dead because he would
win so yeah this is I talked to a lot of
people I write a lot of node code and
one of the things that seems to be a
reoccurring problem for people is that
we're exploring this whole new paradigm
with server-side JavaScript any in
particular node I think really when we
talk about server-side JavaScript at the
moment most people think of node and the
event loop has a really specific set of
problems that people aren't used to we
program a particular way from the from
the browser but it's not exactly the
same so I thought I'd write this this is
how do we how do we really stop writing
code that just looks like ass and how do
we do something with that so there's a
warning i'm going to use a lot of
metaphors so i don't know i have some i
probably have a total of twenty lines of
code in this whole presentation but
there's going to be some extremely bad
metaphor so be warned but what i really
want to do is explain how this works
rather than dazzle you with code Tim did
an amazing job yesterday of explaining
this stuff anything his slide deck is is
great reference material go and read his
code go and sit and digest it I'm a
little bit less smarten Tim right I sit
I sit with ryan and i kind of i watch
these guys that I'm like ah so instead
of trying to do it that way for me I try
and tell myself a story I try and figure
out what's the simplest way that in my
head
I can understand how this stuff works
and the thing that we really need to
understand is this event loop thing
right and everybody has talked about it
this week everybody's been going on on
and on about the event loop but I have
this theory I believe that people really
get event-driven programming so I cook
hands up people that cook right hands up
people that can cook more than just
ramen noodles hello your geeks I have to
ask that right so if you really cook if
you actually you know have a kitchen and
you have chefs knives and all of this
stuff you know that people intuitively
get event-driven right you sit in your
cooking and your chopping something and
a pot starts boiling over you know you
know finish chopping you stop and you
deal with the pot and you turn the heat
down and and you know you're used to
that that idea that simultaneous things
happen and we can deal with that and yet
where did this fallacy come from that
our programmers can't think you know in
multiple multiple things they can only
think in the single you know you do this
then you do this then you do this then
you do this then you do this in our
everyday lives we're constantly
interrupted with things and we deal with
them and then we carry on and we do
something else this is this is just a
normal human behavior and it's something
you intuitively get so how do we get to
a place where we're trying to write code
and we don't understand what we're doing
so here's his made second increasingly
bad metaphor and the event loop postman
right this is kind of silly but this is
the event loop postman he's a happy
postman he's delivering lattice and his
letters are the event stack so he's got
his stack of letters he takes a letter
one at a time and he walks to the house
right his route the sort of red squiggly
lines or the callbacks I've got a letter
and I walked through my callback did he
do and I deliver the thing and that's
the end of the call back and I'm done
I then go and get the next letter when I
walk and deliver it you know obviously
he's not a very good post when he can
only carry one thing at a time but you
know Arian I did explain they were a bad
metaphors right so this is this is you
know this really interesting thing that
we're using but the problem is for a
poor postman I'm a real bastard and I
have a gate so the postman walks up and
he's like great i'm going to dealer the
letter oh there's a gate and he walks
around and it's like oh there's gate and
he walked around ki guess oh there's a
gate so our postman is stuck in this
situation where the only thing that he
knows how to do is deliver his event and
he's trying to do that but the gates not
open and you say well okay to vent
driven what if we have something that's
going to open that gate and it's waiting
on the stack it's it's another event and
we're okay because it's gonna fix it for
the postman well the problem is is the
postman's never going to deliver the
letter that opens the gate because he's
stuck trying to deliver the data that
requires the gate to be over ow so this
is this is what's really weird and
interesting about the event loop and I
think this is one of the things that I
really wanted to communicate is that
things only happen one at a time you
have to finish a call back before you
can actually continue and start getting
events i'm going to show some code in a
minute but the this is a really
interesting problem about how do we how
do we this do these things notice
incredibly fast it's incredibly scalable
you can have thousands of connections at
once but all of that relies on having an
event loop that's working all of that
relies on the fact that that each of the
events happen very fast and then they go
away so we can take away things we can
use not go to the file system there's a
separate process it's non blocking you
get the call back
so you don't have to deal with that
great you know if you want to read from
a database if you want to do something
over the network all of these things are
non blocking you you don't have to deal
with that but you can still block your
own event stack and until you really
understand the fact that you have to
finish execution then you're going to be
in trouble so this is a piece of code
that will tie up the node event loop
forever and it's and it's really simply
obvious how it works but what we're
going to do is we're going to include
the event emitter so we've included
nodes event system we've created a new
event emitter I've created a simple
variable die and then we have a function
so we want to omit on the die event
we're just going to set data true right
and we're going to set a time out and
the timeout emits that event so after
100 milliseconds not very long really
we're going to omit the event die and
then we have a while loop so while not
equals die loop and then finally console
dot log done if you run this code node
will just run until the stack crashes
because it sits there and set timeout in
order to fire that event will never
happen because it's stuck in a loop it's
it's and more than that so this is this
is fits on a side really well but if you
start having other things the that our
event driven and you're expecting those
events the fire that would you know make
this loop quit they will never fire
because the loops busy doing stuff the
postman's walking down his path and he's
walking down his path and he's walking
down his path and your event is never
going to fire until he's finished
walking down this path and that's a
really significant piece of information
because if you write code that box
yourself nobody else is going to help
you now
this is kind of facetious right nobody's
really going to you know having like big
while loops encode that rely on events
to fix them is kind of it's a strange
use case but it's completely possible
for you to write extremely long running
code that maybe won't block your event
loop forever but it will block your
event loop for long enough that it will
cause you some pain and one thing I
would mention is that things like so
things like TCP connections when you get
a new TCP connection to node that's a
separate process is handled by the
colonel the colonel will stack up the
TCP requests so no it's not going to
randomly drop them because you've been
busy you know for 100 milliseconds or a
thousand or whatever it's going to stack
up in the kernel and you can still
accept them but if you tie yourself up
that's a problem unicorn break yeah
unicorns crack rainbows it's on my
t-shirt must be true I just wanted to
inject we haven't had any intercont in
the conference or hardly any so it's not
jazz comp velasquez unicorns no waiver
fais pas yeah so how what we doing with
this stuff what we actually building
with node and what the patterns that we
can sort of use by really knowing how
the event loop works what are the things
that we can do to make this useful and
to not write things that hurt us so the
the kind of cases the common cases that
people have web servers come command
line stuff and then maybe peer-to-peer
so like these are the kind of cases it's
actually web servers I personally have
written a DNS server it's not great it's
going to get better hopefully in the
future but we have a dns server written
a note it's kind of scary and wrong
really too bright dns and javascript but
scary and wrong things are kind of hot
aren't they no so you know it's any sort
of server that has you know some kind of
client response model and these for me I
like the three more or less than three
kind
of actual writing so the the CLI pipes
this is this is really simple this is a
use case that we can more or less throw
away because if you're writing stuff for
the command line it's pipe n pipe out
right you have something that's standard
ieee standard in and then stand it out
it doesn't have to be asynchronous
because the command line is never going
to treat it asynchronously anyway so who
cares this is not a case that I really
care about it's not it's not interesting
you won't get tied up writing node code
you won't get confused writing code for
the command line stuff because it's just
in and then straight at the cases where
it's more interesting at these ones so
if you look at this stuff essentially we
have two cases we have things with
streams such as TCP you know and there's
lots of things but things like PTP
anything were it's not discreet
connections and then we have this
discreet stuff so I receive an HTTP
request and they send it responds I
receive a UDP request I send a response
right and the fact that these things go
over HTTP over TCP as a protocol doesn't
really matter what the server is doing
is the street requests and this is
actually our biggest use case so I have
a request and they give a response its
request driven you know our server
receive something and it's expected to
give something back so how do we
architect that in a way that that work
so his some code hands up people that
have used this code or run it yeah this
is the code from the front of the
node.js page so what I can't it like six
hands six people have run node really
come on hands up people that have really
done this thank you right so you've all
run this code so this is this is sort of
the one on one example and what we
actually doing with it well we're
getting a request and we fire a callback
and that callback is an anonymous
function right it were just you know
doing a really simple example but the
problem is that people start to do this
and you know judge right i call this
pyramid
but it basically it looks like that and
I think actually Tim probably coined
that yeah you know but you end up you
have like all of these anonymous
callbacks that nest together and you end
up with this giant pyramid of code that
just sticks out at a weird angle and
it's really ugly it really there
and it and it's hard to maintain you
can't read it and you know you create
all kinds of race conditions in your
like why does my brain hurt so my
suggestion to you is that if you have
this model this is a pattern this is a
really simple pattern have a server the
server has a prototype this is a pattern
that Ryan users for HTTP it's a pattern
that Tim users for connect lots of
people use it but inside that have a
request object have an object that just
has a new requests and just make these
all into factory methods so we have a
server so this could be HTTP I've used
capital uppercase server because it's a
class crate server its factory method
gives us a new server and then we pass
to that a callback server crate request
and then we give it the request
restaurant so we create a new request
whenever there's a connection and we
encapsulate everything in that request
object but here's what's different it's
not an anonymous call back it's a
specific named object that lives within
our server but it lives within the
instance of that specific server but
more than that is because we've nested
it this way is we can decorate all of
the functions into one beautiful
encapsulated object and then you can
start to map them in you and all of that
everything belongs in its right place
all of the requests associated with a
specific server belong to that server
but it means that you can create six of
those servers and everything sharing its
methods really nicely and it's easy to
understand so then you can draw a
diagram like this so for the DNS server
this is more or less what it does take
to request it passes the request it
iterates through resolve and then it
responds and this is the point is once
you can start naming what you're doing
instead of having all of these crazy
anonymous call backs you can actually
start
a really simple diagram does anybody can
anybody not does anybody look at that
and not have a good guess of what the
DNS server does know so this is really
simple and easy to understand but if you
don't name your functions if you just
have all this anonymous stuff that's
layering on top of each other it gets
really hard to do and all of these are
just call backs all of these are we emit
an event and I just attach them back to
back it's really easy to understand um
so the second case is streams and helmet
down for time where I think I'm going
really fast whoops so the second case is
streams and this is a slightly different
case so you have a socket of some kind
so probably TCP and you know you have
events that come off the socket so its
socket driven it's doing stuff you know
here's some data or you get external
events which you then push up through
the socket what's easy about this this
is this is a similar but but different
problem there's nothing to encapsulate
the socket owns itself and everything
that are event-driven outside the socket
maybe it's a filehandle you know it can
call the socket but you don't actually
need to encapsulate anything there's no
state it's not like it's it's not like
where's my side it's not like this
you're not having to run on that one
you're not having to encapsulate these
requests and save them you're simply
responding to events as they come so it
turns out that there's only one real
case where people are getting horribly
tied up and that's the case of dealing
with these and it's actually the most
popular case right I mean hands up
people that are planning to write paid
to piss drinking servers with mode right
now that guy yawn and Tim three people
so it's you know the most common use
case that people have is some kind of
request response and that's the one that
we need to focus on so I think that this
is actually an easy problem so
apparently I went incredibly first and
did it in 20 minutes but my summer is
this so don't talked about iteration
which I look that up on
kapiti i think you made that up wait
wait don't where do you find that from
he made out he did make it up something
if somebody else you'd gone create a
Wikipedia article for a now but don't
block the event loop this is this is
really critical if you block the event
loop everything will fail and until you
you know understand the fact that all of
all of the event loop has to finish
executing what it's executing that's
that's really critical and the next
thing is encapsulate so stay save the
the data that you want in a closure so
encapsulate all of that stuff down and
use name functions so start creating
request objects within your server
objects and decorate them decorate all
of them with with the kinds of state
that you want and why this is really
interesting for me is if you start to
think about not blocking the the event
loop if you start to think about the
fact that we have shared memory if you
can trace and draw the the outline of
your call backs then you can start to
remove pieces of memory that you no
longer need you can say I don't actually
need this part of the state at this part
of the request process I can throw it
away and now I can handle more
connections because my server has more
memory available and I can start
clearing that stuff off and having it
garbage collected and I don't have to
wait for the entire for the entire
closure to be closed so use name
functions and use factories factories
are great and then document your flow
callbacks this is something I've not
seen anybody do right we sort of we're
building all of these servers where's
the documentation where do people draw
this cause this and then this calls this
and then this cause this this is
something as a community we're not doing
and it's it's really hard to follow Ryan
was talking about how do we debunk the
stack you know and one of the problems
of you have is that we lose context
right well it's easy to know context if
you've explicitly written it down but if
you if you're calling everything through
anonymous functions it's really hard to
write down what's calling what which
comes back to using name functions so
that was really quick i guess i'm going
to take
lessons hopefully it was useful to
people questions Brian where was i five
this morning swing dancing so to some
weird music edgy that place played yeah
any questions about JavaScript all my
social life i guess that's fine too they