you
so again my name is Christopher I work
for ThoughtWorks I do a lot of stuff
also fronted stuff besides from from
hacking and I like hacking I like
building stuff I like languages but
today I like to talk about something
that has been interesting me for the
last year I call it a panoramic tour
through html5 rendering itself today and
it seems that engineering carefully
engineering the title kind of helped
because a lot of guys here today that's
good
but what is this about today what do I
want to talk about so in the next three
minutes I'd like to misuse a few browser
features some of those new I and that so
to make it fit in J's Kampf we use a lot
of JavaScript to play around with SVG
HTML CSS DOM and not sure if you heard
from that before the CSS object model
I do claim that we go boldly go where no
man or woman has gone before
let's see if I can hold up to this and I
hope that we have some fun on the way
because it's not as much about the young
product it's more about the way to how
to get there because I think I had some
fun on the way and I hope you guys have
some fun going through with that there's
special welcome to the chrome devs
today I have a few treats for you guys
there are three bugs I'd like to fix in
the next few weeks maybe they're not
bugs so I have to be careful but I
already talked to my quest yesterday and
it seems like we can tackle a few of
those things today I mean you think
Firefox because Firefox is most helpful
in the stuff that we'd be doing today
come chrome does a good job too so
specifically what we're going to do
today is we'll be trying to trigger the
HTML rendering capabilities that the
browser exposes well it doesn't expose
it actually the browser is a huge
external renderer but normally I'm not
allowed to call it from JavaScript
I'm trying to work around the the ways
and try to
make the browser give me a screenshot of
random webpages or random HTML um we're
going to render HTML to a canvas it
sounds a bit boring but let's see in
other words and that's what I learned
yesterday from Dominic's talk
we're building a prolly fill if you guys
didn't join this awesome talk polyfill
and I'm trying to explain that my words
it might be wrong Dom making correct me
but if you guys know a polyfill the
polyfill tries to make a browser follow
a standard the browser hasn't
implemented that yet you're going to
write a polyfill to make it work a
polyfill is not filling a gap without a
standard created there is no standard
for this it probably will get a standard
if you guys think it's useful so if that
makes sense
um so we're going to add new
capabilities to the canvas which is
basically just Troy's email that just
that Tony method method is what we will
be talking today it sounds easy
and it actually is maybe here's a quick
solution that is code that only works in
Firefox
I certainly only works in the chrome
mode of Firefox I'm posing a bit right
now because I actually don't know what
that exactly means I know that Firefox
is underneath written in a lot of
JavaScript I just don't know how to
trigger that code um because I'm not
really into that space but I know that
that works yeah so what we do what it
does is it gets a canvas and in the end
it draws a tab the content of a tab to
that canvas not sure where the chrome
has something like that I know that if
that Safari for example and chrome do
show you screenshots I guess that must
be implemented somehow possibly in
JavaScript but that's how Firefox does
that so that sounds pretty easy um but
as I kind of indicated it does not work
in a normal web page but that's what my
goal is I like to call this from any
random web page why is it not why is not
available in the web page all there's
security concerns and there are have
been awesome talks today yesterday also
from my quest about why you want to
limit what your websites or your
javascript is allowed to do
if your JavaScript would be allowed to
render random web content from random
sources to a canvas it would allow you
to inspect this and do something with
that so sadly um it does there's no easy
way to make it work so I like to ignore
any concerns that any content security
policy or same-origin policy has unlike
to work around it let's see if we can do
that so you guys I guess are all huge
fans of SVG and SVG unknown to me maybe
unknown to you has a foreign object a
tag the foreign object lets you allow to
embed any kind of HTML it actually
allows you to embed without HTML code
but you have to convert it to XHTML this
is a valid SVG and that is basically an
image that just shows HTML so maybe you
see where I'm getting here I'm I'm
allowed to draw images to to the canvas
now I have an image basically which
includes HTML so let's see if we can
build on that
so one short step as I said XHTML I
can't form and them HTML added I must
converted I need to provide XHTML and
Firefox but looking at the chrome
developers makes it very easy here there
is an XML serialize
you just ignore the basic code just the
XML civilizer that helps you to convert
any random document into XHTML now in
Chrome and Safari that does not work and
the guys have a point they say the
standard does not require XML serialize
transform an HTML document into HTML so
they have a different behavior there
it's actually Firefox that's doing
something that that's understand it
doesn't ask for so let's assume we have
a way of converting that if we if we're
going to implement that from today in
chrome in Safari
we need to have our own substitution for
that and I'm I'm really looking into a
lot of HTML parsers right lately I've
been looking for
for a year I might have found something
this afternoon but there's no good if
there's no good HTML to HTML converter
out there in pure JavaScript that works
in the browser so if you guys know of
something like that just come up to me
please so considering that we have that
what can we do with that right now
so in the future with pelops
we can basically just throw our SVG into
a blob and created object URL from that
this object URL is something we can just
pipe into an image and that image could
go into the canvas and we're done it's
not that easy because Safari isn't that
far at least it hasn't been that far a
month ago or something so we need to
fall back to data URIs your eyes I guess
you know that these I think were kind of
designed for adding small image content
to make your life easy to maybe improve
the bandwidth problems
improve upon of problems and what we can
do is basically if you have an SVG
that's what we started we can create an
image with Apps basic scheme here just
add a data image with the type SVG XML
trial said we'd have ade and then so the
SVG inside so what does that mean we can
now bring this together and remember
what our task was our task was render
HTML into the canvas so what we can do
is create a new image throw in the SVG
content and then get the canvas into all
the image and that is pretty easy pretty
simple code and I like to say
congratulations it looks like we're done
what we did is Emma did HTML beforehand
converting that to XHTML using for an
object into an SVG then we converted
that into a data URI got an image and
use the canvas dot get context draw
image and that's good so yeah not right
we have a few minutes left right so
there's more things to cover SVG is not
allowed to include any external
resources so I didn't know that
beforehand but if you
going to include refugee in your web
pages your SVG's are not allowed to link
to external resources that again is as
far as I understand for security reasons
so that is bad though because our
problem is HTML we want to render HTML
HTML allows for a lot of external
resources and I'm not sure I think I
covered all of them you have images you
have much of you knew about input
elements of type image you have style
sheets you have inside style sheets
background images you have staunchly CSS
may import other CSS style sheets you
have fonts and all of those things
linked to external resources and
although it's I'd like to render to the
canvas too so here's a kind of nifty
idea we could try to embed those
resources into the SVG SVG could take
data your eyes inside to write so how do
you find those external elements my girl
still is find a generic way of piping
HTML into the canvas so let's find out
how to make it solution to get that done
so that looks like pre a simple code I
think you create an empty document you
pipe your HTML into that document and
then you just get elements by tag name I
don't even need to carry all I can do is
just get all the images out and I can
just iterate over those images and do
something with that all right now I know
I know have all my images that might
email references what do I need to do
that's how my image looks like it's an
external image and I like to embed that
well we talked about data URIs before so
what I can do is just basically get that
image image to get the content and stuff
it into as a data URI into the source
and I'm done and how can we do that we
just use our plain simple Ajax I load
the content by our Ajax and that's how I
construct it I add that data URI
I'll encode that to base64 via B to a
function and I might be done well first
things first
Ajax you know needs to follow same
origin policy so this will not allow
me to load random webpages it only
allows to me to load stuff that I'm
allowed to see
so just need to mention that secondly
loading binary images through Ajax is
crazy that's not what Ajax was designed
to be Ajax was designed well the name
says XML all right it's used to XML and
and Jason you allow it to load text not
binary data so xhr to XML HTTP because -
now has capabilities for loading binary
data which gives you back a blob again
Safari is not playing along well here so
what we're doing we need to find a
workaround and that's what I've been
doing the whole time are just being
throwing things into Google and quite
often land on Stack Overflow and find a
solution for my problem I had so that's
something you can find on Stack Overflow
with a big sign saying don't do that
that's ugly it's bad but it seems to
work in all those browsers so the is you
know screw screw a XHTML HTTP request -
and screw blobs I can do that with all
browsers and I'm happy it's pretty slow
though if you load like megabytes of
data and you iterate through all the the
code points so what it actually does the
code I mean you can you you can read but
it basically just converts it from a to
cope point and throws away all the other
bits and just converts it back ugly but
it works so we good I'm setting the
second point now we I kind of describe
how to inline images what about
background images it seems a bit similar
they are images too but the problem here
is background images are referenced in
CSS how do I find my background images I
need to dig into CSS now that basically
requires me pausing CSS to find which we
source resources on you to inline so we
need to build something like this
function pass CSS and if I throw in a
span that has a background image I need
to find this external image PNG so let's
write CSS puzzle
you see we're getting a it's getting a
bit complicated to be fed though we're
done pretty quickly that is slide that
describes a CSS parser well we can just
use the CSS parser or from the browser I
didn't know that I've been using a pure
JavaScript solution for a long time
until I realized that the CSS only
existed
it's the CSS object model the browser
allows you to basically access its Pazza
so that's a nifty code that just does it
what it does is you create a style
element you pub your CSS content to that
style element and then you need to do
one very important step the browser only
starts to evaluate that that CSS if it
actually needs to do so so you need to
create a fake document at that style
element to that document and then the
browser starts to pass that CSS and then
you're done the style element sheet dot
CSS rules lists you gives you a list or
kind kind of lists lists like element to
access all your CSS rules that is and
when I found this piece of code I
thought that's so awesome I didn't know
that existed this is basically the
browser doing CSS pausing to be fair
it's really an air ugly API to be fair
if I just if I envisioned how I would do
that in in nodejs or any other
programming language I would require the
CSS parser and tell the CSS positive
I'll write my code it turns out that
Angele in in the browser Dom you always
tend to kind of access some weird API to
get some stuff done to be fair I think
nobody actually designed actually
designed that for that use case I don't
think anybody wanted the user or the
JavaScript rip our CSS well I need that
so here I am I want to get that stuff
done so can we put this together we now
can pass our rules we get a list we get
a list of rules and I mean we can
iterate over those rules just like we
did with the images before we go through
all the rules check if it has a
background image and if it does call our
virtual method do inline image URL
this method is something we already did
for the image we can do the same stuff
with the background images and we're
done so I showed you how to do inline
images now we're doing the same stuff
with background images only we need to
policy if that's before when we good
so next step number three
what about link elements to inline to
the reference style sheets my hTML is
allowed to reference other style sheets
if I want to run in my HTML or when I
might want to make sure that my style
sheets are rendered alongside so I need
to embed them to remember we are
rendering SVG to a canvas and the SVG is
embedding HTML but it's not allowed to
reference any external stuff time in
learning everything so it looks simple
at first we just kind of go with similar
paths as with the image we're using Ajax
to load the content
it's simple here because we're actually
using a reloading text what we do is we
throw out the link and in the same place
we put a style element that includes the
content of that CSS make sure that you
put the starlet and the same position as
a link as CSS um as we learn today again
follows the order of the declarations so
be careful here we're not done yet
it looks simple to just embed that
content but the resources inside the CSS
I'm just in lining all those relative
links are relative to the source through
the URL of the stylesheet
so I can icon just pull in the CSS and
just dump it into the HTML all those
links will be broken all the relative
links will be broken what I need to do
is carefully inspect my my CSS unloading
so I need to pass this stuff again I
need to find all those references
background images fonts import rules and
need to adapt all those URLs to a
relative to the UL of the style of the
mother starship basically so for example
if I have if I have an image dot slash
images thoughts PI PNG it's an asset
style default CSS I need to replace the
dot dot with the assets from the starchy
so I'm using a pure Jas ULP
euro is which allows me to base my URL
absolutely I think it's a wrong name it
should be relatively to the sheet URL so
if I inline my CSS content I need to fix
all those paths and when I fix all those
part and I'm done then I need to go
through and replace all the background
images we're in the like just what we
did before so there you go we rendered
HTML through the CF SVG's for an object
we inlined
not all of the external resources by now
there's a bit more as I showed before
but we load in binary content through HX
or the text content through Ajax
reinventing image images through data
URI to embedding style sheets with
parsing CSS to find resources to fix the
past
so what does that what does it look like
it's demo time I'm showing you kind of
boring demo right now let's see if that
makes sense I have a canvas up there
maybe I should assume in a bit so
whoopsie that's a bit cut off what we
can do is just switch over here and so
so what I have there isn't a text area
where I can type in arbitrary HTML and
this is drawn into the canvas up there
if you don't believe me that this is a
canvas I can show you pretty easily if I
right-click on this in Firefox it allows
me to view the image so what I have
right now here is my HTML as an image
and if you look at the not sure whether
you can see that it's pretty small but
you see the data you are a UI in the
browser resource so I basically now have
an image that I just rendered inside the
browser with an external image and I can
do way more crazy stuff with that
so back to demo so we could say we've
done here I'd like to give you a small
bonus let's see if that makes fun I
don't only want to render a static HTML
I want to render aged in an HTML page
that includes JavaScript I want to make
sure that if my JavaScript does some
stuff with my page that I render the
final outcome so is that possible and it
turns out it is well what I can
basically do is just create an iframe
throw my HTML into that iframe and just
wait for the iframe to trigger the
onload event when the onload event
triggers my page has done its rendering
stuff and the state kind of the state
possibly changed and I can just then
take the document of the iframe and then
get the HTML out again and then I'll
have like a different HTML string and
that basically allows me to execute
JavaScript at the same time I'm not
really sure about the sandboxing stuff I
did read a bit up on sandboxing the
iframe and it turns out oh yeah my
feeling from that was I don't need to
sandbox it it works but if you guys have
security concerns but do come up there
to me and tell me if I need to make that
secure somehow it's forcing my security
concerns so there are a few issues here
as I said before the same-origin policy
does not allow you to to load random
content so Ajax you know that stuff what
you can do is if you if you have control
over the origins you can expose common
object resource sharing so correct yeah
cause a problem I had with the WebKit
family I'm not sure if I feel I'm still
allowed to call it WebKit family but
chrome sadly cannot write background
images back so this is a pausing that I
showed earlier does not work in Chrome
because of this simple bug so what I do
right now is we can just fall back to
the CSS object model implementation that
a guy on github does so
he's got an awesome implementation for
nodejs which I'm just using in a browser
and that's awesome so I know chrome has
that stuff in that case I'm using a
polyfill I guess so
a kind of special problem is if you're
embedding SVG's if you have an SVG
inside your HTML remember that the HTML
goes to into another SVG so you have an
SVG inside the SVG that suit doesn't
seem to work neither in Safari nor
chrome there's a workaround but that's a
basic issue the last point is my major
pain point and that's where I needed to
ask the Google guys I had a conversation
with Mike yesterday and maybe you
listened to his talk yesterday as
neither Safari not chrome allow me to
read from the canvas after I draw this
SVG to it there seems to be a different
interpretation of what the standard
requires Firefox allows you to do that
Chrome Safari don't if you want to then
work with the content you right now you
cannot you can't which is I think a
south state because obviously I can't
think of an attack vector because if I'm
allowed to load all that content and I'm
allowed to render that content I should
be able to read from this one last sat
point is I 11
even the ie 11 preview has no support
for an object so ie 11 sadly none of the
IE versions do support that stuff that
we're doing here
good news though this ability in the
browser's have increased and especially
the Firefox guys there's one guy in
Firefox that seems to be interested in
that and every time I complained he
quickly fixed that bug the last bug I
reported was my fault so he was nice too
so what's that sorry all about I ended
up putting that into a library it's on
github it seems a few people are using
that at least they're hitting the start
button on github I just don't know what
they do move out I don't have really I
don't know what people want to use it
for I just talked to dominate and he
said he's got an interesting to case but
I still need to ask him I have it I have
a use case for that and that maybe
sounds a bit weird my originally idea
was I want to start testing my CSS my
idea was if I can just take screenshots
I'm
I just compare my screenshots old versus
new and Mike might even crazy idea was I
wanted to do that in the browser and I
can now do that I can now render web
pages in the browser and I can do my
testing on that that's also in github if
in case you're interested so thanks for
listening and do something cool with
that and I might say that because pop
works is painful for me being here we're
hiring if you interested check that out
thank