we'll chill it out who hears heard a
phonegap it's like a third or more of
the audience which is awesome we we ship
phonegap like two years ago and no one
had really heard of it until after the
first jazz comp and ya know now people
are getting familiar with it which is
wicked oh so this is an 8-bit ninjus
presentation and where are my speaker
notes according to this I haven't
started my presentation yet sweet this
is what I get for using Google Docs I
guess anything shows speaker notes oh I
know where it is hold on you guys I'm
really sorry about this it's like in the
bottom left of this thing haha there we
go okay so you probably can't read that
but my name is Brian LaRue and you can
find me on Twitter I work for a night
Toby software which is a small software
consultancy in Vancouver Canada and we
are the creators of phonegap which is a
pretty awesome project for creating
mobile applications with HTML CSS and
JavaScript this talk I'm just going to
go through the current state of the
phonegap project so you guys can get a
better understanding of what's been
going on and where we're going a lots
changed in the last couple years and
it's it's a much more mature project
when we started in fact it when we
started it was I don't want to say was a
total hack but it pretty much was a
total hack and now it's growing into
something that is being used by
thousands of people and it's actually
seeing some good adoption and a lot of
big companies behind it so when we first
ship phonegap two years ago it was
essentially an extension on the native
web view and for iOS which was only
iphones at that time now we've got
support for our eight platforms eight
different mobile platforms for creating
native mobile web apps and we're getting
tons of support from from different
companies like Sony Ericsson has adopted
phonegap as their standard SDK for
writing apps for symbian and Android and
symbian foundation recently accepted
phonegap as a part of their web
extensions package which would be
shipping in symbian3 so that's pretty
big news you can write web apps that
ship on mobile devices that target not
only symbian Android iPhone and these
big companies are supporting it so
that's pretty cool a lot of people ask
us like how many people are using
phonegap and we have no idea it's an
open source project so there's no way
for us to actually know that because we
give it away but since last January it's
been downloaded over
half a million times that's not
including any numbers on github we have
no clue at night Toby we use phonegap to
write applications for ourselves and
we've shipped over 50 apps and last year
with a team of 15 people that's pretty
impressive phone guide gives you a huge
advantage because you could leverage
your your already existing skills for
the web to create apps faster than
anyone else and and really that's what
it's all about because most apps that we
have to write or do a few weeks ago
according to our clients so what one
thing about all this stuff is phonegap
is really more of an interim solution
then then something that we're saying
that you should be using from now on
moving forward phonegap is a platform
for writing web apps but really we
should just be writing web apps but
there's times when we can't write web
apps and that's when we want to access
native device features such as the file
system or if we want to access the
contacts or the camera or any of this
other cool stuff and so phonegap really
is just an interim solution the browsers
are going to be doing this stuff
eventually anyways and geolocation is a
perfect example of this and it's
permeating back to all the other
browsers so fragmentation these are our
most the major mobile platforms we don't
have samsung bada in there i'm not
mentioning windows mobile because no one
cares OEM inching windows mobile maybe
the Europeans care whatever and there's
some interesting developments here if we
look at this there's there's all kinds
of different platforms but a whole bunch
of these platforms actually are already
starting to to support the web and they
hadn't previously and so there is a lot
of fragmentation there but the
fragmentation isn't necessarily existing
so much in how you write the apps but
rather the SDKs that you have to install
to to begin writing these apps there's
another aspect to this whole thing and
that's distribution of your applications
and about a year ago I started to get
really scared because there was
something like 50 app stores and now as
if today there's over 90 op stores and I
used to think this was a really bad
thing but I'm beginning to believe that
this is actually a really good thing
there's initiatives out there is anyone
here familiar with Bondi if you are
raise your hand okay have you heard
though the wac it's a really terrible
name what it stands for something like
web application warehouse or something
they're looking to standardize the idea
of an app store so that app stores could
be federated and this seems like the
right thing to do and I think it's sort
of a good idea on paper but it's never
going to fly all these people are never
going to work together and its
proliferation of app stores seems like a
really bad thing like oh no there's
going to be dozens of app stores but if
we think about how like physical goods
get transferred this isn't actually a
big departure I don't want to go to a
big box store or mall that it sells
everything and it's kind of crummy I'd
rather go to a bespoke store that
curates content or and or goods that I
expect and you could imagine things like
you could go to the EA app store by EA
Games and this is likely what the future
is going to hold but you know this turns
into a big distribution nightmare but
this kind of fragmentations already been
solved for years and you know it's that
whole internet thing that we've been
talking about and it turns out it's
pretty good at dealing with
fragmentation and distribution and so
once again phonegap is a way for you to
get your apps into these various app
stores but you shouldn't invest too
heavily and the idea of developing for
app stores when we have the internet to
to do this anyways so you could almost
consider phonegap as a temporary
progressive enhancement technique it's a
way to get your mobile web apps built
and in app stores while we wait for the
browsers to catch up with device api's
so that that's and another important
part about all this we've got native
device sensors and native device access
and so so what the fuck does that mean
sensors are things like your camera your
accelerometer things that that access
data and then there's device data and
thats things like photographs contacts
whatever so these are the problems that
we're looking to solve a phonegap and
we're also looking to provide a
reference implementation for install the
web apps what the hell is an installable
web app I I think like you can look at
an installable web app much like you can
look at device sensors and data it's all
it really is is an icon for the loading
screen a loading screen itself and a
permissions manifest of some kind all of
these various mobile app stores and
mobile platforms have this pattern
encapsulated somehow and interestingly
there's there's a work being done at the
w3c called the device API working group
which is tackling the idea of sensors
and data and there's the widget working
group which is tackling the idea of
installable web apps and then there's
things like the Chrome Web App Store
that are coming so so these concepts are
already out there and being worked on
phonegap is is just another one yeah I
have no idea what that slide has to do
with anything okay so current platform
support is that the next big question
people have like what are you guys
working on and what are you doing and so
before I like talk specifically to what
platforms that we're supporting it I
have to talk to about how we plan to
support it and you don't want to start
building this big monolithic system when
you're dealing with devices that have
the computational power of something
from the 90s like these things are
pretty crummy computers and so phonegap
itself has to have the smallest
footprint possible we can't touch we
have to touch as little as possible so
that we remain performant another rule
that we have to play by is that we have
to use the native SDK it would be nice
if we could write our own browser but
that would also be yet another browser
and that would probably cause more
problems and then solve them most
cardinal rule of phonegap is that we do
not fuck with the DOM and there's a lot
of reasons for that the main one being
that the DOM is a mess already no sense
in us making it worse there's plenty of
library authors that are here right now
they can
with the DOM and solve that problem
themselves phonegap should remain
accessible and the idea here is that you
can install your own stuff and keep
working so sometimes people get confused
and they think oh phonegap is for
building web apps therefore it has no
native accidents but this is an
incorrect assertion phonegap is a
starting point for writing web apps that
allows you to write native extensions
yourself so there's no reason that you
can't have native code we just think
it's a bad idea if you can avoid it you
should because it's not cross platform
and then you'll have to implement it six
times if you want to hit multiple
devices that said there is times when
you should write native code there are
certain platform specific interactions
that people look for when they're using
their mobile device and my favorite
example of this is the back button who's
got an iPhone who's got an android my
brothers who's got blackberry crickets
right okay well it iphone and android
provide a really good example of this so
in an iphone land there's 11 button and
that sort of takes you home but in the
blackberry world we've got four physical
buttons that are almost on every device
and one of those includes a back button
and nothing pisses off an Android user
more than a virtual back button in the
top left which is what you see in
Android or in iphone land in webos
things are even more interesting there's
no buttons at all and there's no virtual
buttons at all use gestures to go back
and forth which is cool but now you've
got a user experience expectation and
this isn't necessarily native UI but it
is a native feature and when you're
writing an app you you probably want to
write the best out possible and if
you're writing the best out possible
then you're going to want to live up to
the expectations of the users and so
here's a case where it makes a lot of
sense to drop in a native code anyways
there's other examples that are a lot
like that and the final thing we we say
we should not pollute the global
namespace
and we're working on that so yeah this
is this is most definitely the biggest
problem with mobile software development
right now if you want to write an app
for any given device you'll have to
install an SDK for that device so if you
want to go cross-platform with multiple
devices you're going to have to install
six or eight different SDKs in some
cases those SDKs only can be installed
on one operating system and so then
you're virtualizing windows when you
have to do windows development or or
you're buying a mac mini because you
can't really virtualize OS 10 and it's a
pain in the ass now we're not really
doing much to solve it but I just
thought I'd bring that up okay that's
right I was going to tell you guys what
platforms we support so this is what
phonegap currently supports today iOS
which does include ipad ipod touches and
iphones some reason people ask us that a
lot all android devices going back to
1.5 1.5 1.6 webos symbian windows mobile
we're going to be supporting windows
phone 7 I was talking to Dion about this
earlier and he's like what do you think
of Windows Phone 7 and Phil who's got
the giant hair and he's right over there
actually has one so if you you want to
laugh you could check that out windows
phone 7 is interesting because you know
they put the device out there to let you
know go build some apps and try it out
but we can't actually install anything
to the device we can play around with
the web browser and stuff so that's kind
of cool so we've got there's a guy out
there who ported phonegap completely to
Windows Phone 7 but we have no way to
test on a physical device because none
really currently exists so once we get
one we're going to bring it in and then
we'll say yes we support Windows Phone 7
me go work has been done this is a
similar situation in which there's not
very many devices out there so as soon
as we've got some to test on we will be
bringing that out
and so that's cool that's eight
platforms the goal of phone gapper one
of the early goals we used to talk about
was that we wanted to we created this
project so that the project would cease
to exist and it's sort of a Zen
Vancouver stoner idea and doesn't make
any sense at all but the idea is that
we're providing an implementation or a
reference implementation of the browser
should adopt themselves and it's working
and these these device a pis are coming
out now into the browser's but there's
new problems so there's new gaps that we
need to fill and we're starting to look
at what these might be and if you use
your imagination you can imagine there's
things like eBook readers there's
dashboards and cars these these screens
are getting really cheap and they're
being embedded everywhere and so
phonegap is a bit of an unfortunate name
because now we're looking at devices and
we don't know what those devices are
going to be but it's going to be really
fucking cool especially for web
developers I really only added this
slide because I wanted to change that to
either math or Malta but I didn't get
around to it and so there's there's no
real reason for this slide other than
the fact that it's kind of cool I'm
going to talk about our API support next
and the the wave phonegap works is that
we instantiate a web browser and almost
every mobile device right now is rocking
a webkit browser so that means that we
get to get all the goodness of html5
that gets bundled in with WebKit things
like SQL Lite css3 canvas web workers
eventually sockets eventually so so
that's cool and then we are further
augment with all these phonegap api's
and that's really cool because there's a
lot of power here I'm going to walk you
guys through a few of the more powerful
API is that we have given access to but
it mean if you look at this stuff
there's there's a lot of interesting
things that you can do not the least of
which is getting into things like
accessing contacts and geolocation
natively on the device things like
Magnum eter means compass people ask us
that all the time
I don't know why they call it that
sounds cool so I mentioned the device
API working group earlier if you go
check out their site you can see all the
API is that we're tracking the device
API working group i believe was founded
in august of 2009 phonegap itself was
created in 2008 so it's good that we
have aspect that we can track towards
but it's constantly moving and changing
and so this is a bit of a challenge for
our project but if you're at all
interested in looking at where the
direction of the internet is this is the
place to go look everybody's talking
about what html5 is going to do which is
sort of retarded because it's mostly
already here it's not about what it's
going to do it's what we have to do with
it and what's coming next are going to
be device api's so it's like HTML 6 yeah
so crucial concepts it's it's a
completely different world when you
start writing for for a device that has
really bad connectivity we've been
spoiled by desktop browsers and so we
don't always necessarily know the
context of which we're running or the
speed and availability of the the device
that we have so first thing that we have
to check almost all the time is what
platform I running on it would be nice
to use feature detection but this isn't
always reliable when you're you're
dealing with the same browser on every
platform so device top platform will
return something like Android you're on
an android phone device ready is the
most useful event it gets fired after
your DOM is loaded and you have access
to all your device sensors and so this
is the sort of baseline implementation
of a phonegap app is going to use these
two events are these two things the next
big thing is whether or not a network is
reachable it's a little bit unfortunate
because the spec has changed but we're
going to keep backwards compatibility
for it essentially Network reachable you
pass it a callback on success and that
will return a status that status will
tell you if you're online if you are if
you're on edge Wi-Fi or 3G super useful
for when you're writing
applications right so this is sort of an
embarrassing thing console dot log is
pretty ubiquitous and it's absolutely
everywhere except we cannot change it on
the iphone and so on the iphone it's
debug log it's a real pain in the ass
but that's how it goes and it's crucial
so testing testing is a tricky one
because you're going to have to do it
and unfortunately you're going to have
to do it on a device which means if
you're going across platform you're
going to have to have all those devices
when you install these various emulators
you'll find that they don't really
actually emulate anything and it's hard
to test things like an accelerometer
when it's just on your screen and so you
have to have the devices we have had
other tools where we found some levels
of success and one of those is qunit
it's a fantastic testing library jquery
uses it and it happens to actually run
on BlackBerry's so we use that not
telling you that you have to use that
but if you're going to start writing
mobile web app code it's it's almost
necessary right so debugging support is
something that people always ask us
about like you know you guys have a
debugger for phonegap and the quick
answer is yes it's called web inspector
most of your development can be done
right in a browser and so if you pop
open web inspector there you go you've
got a debugger right there if you need
to take it another level though and
start debugging on actual hardware or
native specific features your best bet
is to actually load up in whatever I de
that platform supports in Windows land
that would mean visual studio in Java
land that means a version of Eclipse and
they have full-on debuggers so there is
debugging support for phonegap privacy
and security is another huge question
people bring up all the time and they
ask us you know what's security like and
phonegap in a quick answer for that one
is it's the web so there is none
and not even a laugh come on man so when
we're doing web development we're in an
inherently insecure environment you have
to assume that your inputs are going to
be harmful that you're gonna have to go
through proxies you don't want to leave
keys on your device and so really that's
it there is no security right so
phonegap was originally written at night
obion worked on primarily by night Toby
employees but that story's changed a lot
in the last year and now IBM is
contributing more code to phonegap than
we are which is frightening an amazing
at the same time these guys are kicking
serious ass and we're seeing a ton of
improvements especially on android and
blackberry recently Simeon's kicked in
Microsoft has been helping us rim
recently launched their widget SDK which
is based on the w3c widget spec and
they've got a WebKit running on there
and they're totally on board for helping
us build web apps natively palm of
course is amazing and Sony Ericsson and
so yeah there's some pretty heavy
hitters getting involved it's awesome
also couch is now a mobile which is
super interesting yawn guy check it out
he's like down there and he's helping
Ryu against the evil Ryu fire guys I had
a lot of fun with that slide so couchdb
runs on Android right now apparently
it's been built also for iphone and I
can't really tell you what this means
because I'm not sure myself but I know
that it's cool because persistence is a
tough problem and synchronization is an
even tougher problem and couch solves
those really well so having a little
couch running on your phone means that
you also have a little mini web server
running on your phone which means that
you could view phonegap as a tiny window
to your couch and we've done a little
bit of experimentation with this which
means you could update your app say in
the cloud and then that replicates down
to your phone
powerful concept and so this is going to
be something to watch it's early but
it's fascinating also if you're looking
for a really ghetto alternative to couch
I wrote in library called lawn chair
which is pretty funny yeah google that
so we wouldn't be good citizens of the
open source community if we didn't talk
about where we fail because we need your
help to not fail anymore and there's
there's you know stuff to be worked on
there's lots of problems and and so what
kind of problems do we have i love how r
i turned out to be this white guy with
awesome hair so device resolutions and
pixel densities is a kind of a huge
problem we're seeing this massive
fragmentation and people are getting
worried and what about standardization
you may as well give up on that dream
there's not going to be any there's
going to be all kinds of weird shape
devices and we should really be viewing
this as an awesome opportunity to
innovate on what you eyes are we're
taking pretty pretty tiny baby steps
right now into the tablet space and in
to even the phone space and we don't
really know we're doing so far it looks
like lists and buttons I'm fairly
certain that that actually won't be the
case in a few years you see you eyes
like Flipboard and there's some really
expressive interesting stuff going on
and all these different screen
dimensions are an opportunity for new
micro libraries that will target these
different types of situations
specifically and so device resolutions
and pixel density is a huge pain in the
ass Dom inconsistencies is another big
pain in the ass we've got all these
various web kits and PPK likes to say
there's no web kit on mobile and he's
kind of right in a way but really all
these web kits are pretty similar and
there is only small differences between
them but there's a lot of heavy way
people out there that are tackling this
problem the seneschal guys have their
library jQuery Mobile has a bunch of
pngs which may turn into a library
Yahoo's working out dojos working on the
you zebu guys are working on it with
embed Jas Thomas Fuchs just released
cept ojs we wrote a ghetto library
called whoo I like septo it's cool it's
like even smaller than xui which is
library we wrote to solve the problem
what one vapor Dodgers are you joking
okay you're not joking it's an
unfortunate name for a software library
favored yes is it that small 0 bytes
yeah man it's fast it already loaded um
sweet okay and so our final biggest
problem is that we're dealing with a
movie in spec and actually that's not
our final problem we have another one
I'll get into that one soon so we've got
a moving speck and basically we're
breaking backwards compatibility right
now but we're going to stop doing that
very soon the device API working group
is starting to ratify on a few of the
core API s and so very soon we're going
to be able to say okay line in the sand
this is what phonegap looks like the
final toughest problem which I saved the
best for last is getting started getting
started in mobile is is really tough
because unfortunately while our promises
that you can do web development at the
end of the day you're still going to
have to install these native SDKs in
some cases it's not that bad you know
the iphone sdk it only takes like three
or four hours to download but once you
got it it's sweet and all you had to do
is double-click something and it's their
case of android it only takes a few
minutes to download and it only takes
three or four hours to update so I mean
whatever and like ones on Java ones
objective-c and it's a little bit hairy
because you got to learn a new IDE but
we're looking to solve that one too and
so there's two projects that are
brand-new that night Toby's just pushing
out at this very moment one of them is
built up phonegap com and I'm going to
give you a demo of it in a second but
it's a hosted build solution that
encapsulates all the phone gaps work on
to the server side you push up a in dec
HTML or a zip file or you give us a get
repo we'll turn it into a native app for
every platform and send it back down to
you sweet right the second project is it
so we might OB came out to Europe a week
early and we decided that we would you
know really lock down and focus and get
some work done but we stayed in
Amsterdam so none of that got done and
but we did we did ship some of it and if
you if you have an Android device if you
do a search for phonegap dev browser
there's an app out there and it's it's
phonegap the first two links in it are
for our documentation the second one is
to run our test suite the third one is
to add an arbitrary bookmark to anywhere
on the internet and you could load that
within phonegap and so it allows you to
start playing with phonegap right now
without having to install anything but
this app which is pretty cool so how am
i doing for time five minutes sweet okay
so
eight seven six so this is build a
phonegap com which you can always sigh
that's not it I'll show it to you guys
here and so our working name for it is
the okay API or oh cappy which is this
bizarre creature if you look it up on
Wikipedia it's pretty cool but that's
just like a whatever a working name that
this is going to be the whole user
interface for creating apps eventually
we want full get push bowl support and I
kind of put that in but it kind of broke
10 minutes before my presentation so I'm
not going to demonstrate that this is
slow because it's running on a macbook
air with like 10 mobile SDKs on it so
I'm just going to hop to this one to
show you what a final build will look
like it's really bare bones the idea is
that this will be more of an API and
less of a web app we're hoping that
developers will use this to build our
own tooling on top of it and that's it
thanks a lot everybody
there any questions or do we not do that
at JS conf yeah what's our experiences
with app stores yeah so it takes about
10 minutes to publish to the android
marketplace with a iphone a week tops
Apple's actually gotten pretty quick how
long does it take for blackberry a week
or so takes twice as long to develop for
blackberry but yeah yeah the guidelines
are fucking crazy dude I mean I don't
know like it's not build a web app if
you think it's retarded that's what we
would do right if you need to access as
the core native device features then
you're going to have to play by their
rules which means anything arbitrarily
that they decide android's market place
isn't like that any other questions
nothing oh yeah you're back okay
no windows 7 is based on ie6 yeah just
when you thought we were done with that
one it's still alive although PPK was
saying that Microsoft is promising that
ie9 is going to ship on on Windows Phone
7 my belief is that if that doesn't come
with a date that that could be you know
10 decades into the future so who knows
yes yeah it's running the simulator how
did they do it they instantiate ie6
chromeless and then they bind actually
fill can speak to that guy just look for
the guy with the epic hair you can show
you I don't have it running all right