so my name is Sebastian mark page I live
in San Francisco
for facebook on the reactor core team
here in Buenos Aires I really like the
city weather is beautiful beautiful city
looks like a combination of every other
city like Tokyo Paris London modern New
York yeah I went to the cemetery just
because I had to see that it's pretty
cool place spooky right around the
corner from here so my talk was about
how we a dog polyfills as a way to adopt
new language features before these
standards even finalized before it's
implemented in browsers so that we as a
community can unify on a single set of
tools instead of with diverging
libraries I work on the
CC 39 standards committee that specifies
what the next version of the JavaScript
will look like and as part of that work
I'm really interested in getting
adoption as soon as possible because
that helps us at Facebook but also in
our open source community in 10 years I
think that JavaScript will be going in
is stronger I think that we will
actually have shifted patterns lot we
will no longer be using as much
object-oriented styles will probably use
the less mutation we will move towards
more of a functional style paradigm and
we will start dropping
features from the language that people
will no longer use as they're adopting
new patterns this conference is really
it's really nice it's really big it's
one of the biggest J's comp events out
there and really happy to be here the
camera has really gone all out and
trying to create the best experience