my talk is called Caesar j/s and it
might not be well I was giving some
JavaScript but it's primarily going to
be about a great cocktail called the
Caesar which was it's a canadian thing
and I'm Canadian so I thought I'd talk
about it up at the front here Andrew
Lonny who is just giving a presentation
he'll actually be making Caesars for
anyone that's interested while I'm
giving the talk and so he can
demonstrate actually for you if you want
to see what it's all about hey virgin
Caesars yeah sorry how my name is dave
johnson from company called nitobe in
vancouver canada work on phonegap and
rather hungover right now so does
anybody have any good hangover cures
anyone I don't know maybe like a voodoo
doughnut with bacon on top that might be
a good hangover cure often times when
I'm hungover like this though I like to
ask myself what would Don Draper do and
I'm pretty sure he'd do this so as i
mentioned i'm from canada seized our
canadian thing it's essentially a bloody
mary as people in the rest of the world
american particular i guess we'll know
it's essentially Bloody Mary except for
it's got one special special ingredient
so there's a bloody mary or a caesar
can't really tell it's sort of red
though so you start off with tomato
juice and obviously it's just like a
Bloody Mary but you add the one secret
ingredient which is clam nectar so when
you mix tomato juice and clam nectar you
get something called Clamato juice I was
actually thinking like bringing some
real clams and making some clam nectar
but I decided not and so in Canada we
have something called mots Clamato which
is a pre pre mixed clam nectar and
tomato juice and you can get some right
up here there Steve's holding up a nice
bottle we got like six liters that we
brought down I'm surprised they didn't
at the border so the whole idea of this
came about from some dude in Canada and
he was eating I can't pronounce what
this is dishes but it's some sort of
spaghetti dish that's clammed and in
spaghetti so it's obviously tomato sauce
and clams and he was like wow tomato
sauce and clams tastes awesome
so I'm going to make a drink out of it
I'm pretty sure this guy was a drunkard
as well so he actually lived in the fine
City of Calgary where the Calgary Flames
play hockey who are not in the playoffs
at the moment and it was invented back
in nineteen sixty-nine the same year
that the gap was founded coincidence
probably so this actually mots Clamato
there's like this weird collective
consciousness going on as well
because the the motts company they
actually invented mots Clamato that same
year coincidence see that's less
collective consciousness you right there
so they actually sold I think 500 cases
of mots Clamato in 1975 across Canada so
yeah totally weird and now today there
are 350 million Caesars consumed yearly
in Canada and just to give you scale i
mean that's that's about like ten
caesars per person per year so one every
yeah twenty percent of your weekends
year you're drinking a Caesar in Canada
so the recipe like I said Andrew my man
right here who did our amazing hangover
jazz talk right then he's actually
making some drinks for us and i'm just
drinking Clamato hmmm climb nectar so
the recipe six ounces of Clamato juice
one and a half ounces or one to one half
ounces of vodka I prefer to but you know
two dashes of hot sauce four dashes of
work Chester Shire I believe that's
right pronunciation Andrew
four dashes of Worcestershire sauce
celery salt and let me tell you I could
not find that at the grocery store last
night fresh ground pepper actually I
couldn't get vodka last night either
because I didn't have my passport with
me which apparently you don't need to
get into the country but you need it to
buy alcohol not that we don't have
alcohol fresh ground pepper and a lime
wedge of course you need that so what
you do is you actually take the lime
wedge and Andres doing this right now
you you cut it and you you actually run
it run it around the rim of the glass to
get some liquid on there you have your
salt in a little basket and you put the
put the glass upside down in there get
some salt on there throw in your ice so
in your dashes of hot sauce your worst
your sauce your Clamato and your vodka
stir it up a tad add a piece of celery
or you can also add you know green beans
or any other like a lot of pickled stuff
is always good in there and then pretty
much you're in like hangover heaven yeah
there you go one crisp celery stalks
also my salary is limp the seller i
bought yesterday i mean you know it's
limp because it's at out overnight so
this it doesn't have quite the same
effect today but at any rate it will
still work for the hangover i think so
some people will insist on replacing the
vodka with either rum tequila or gin
whoa no there we go oh my god yeah so
that that's crazy it has to be
vodka so others however will use things
like Tim Hortons coffee grounds around
the top of the cup to that I say
yeah or bacon infused vodka yeah that's
got to be tasty in there or maple syrup
hey be from Canada who wouldn't love
maple syrup so that's let's full on by
winning right there
yeah I mean maybe if you had a maple
syrup bacon infused vodka and Tim
Hortons coffee grounds to a Caesar
that's got to be pretty much the best
drink ever that's a hangover Buster
right there and Andrew looks like he's
pretty much got his first Cesar oh man
look at that look at that it's the thing
of beauty oh that's terrible okay so
that's perfect timing Andrew it's as if
we like plan that or something okay I'm
still very hungover it'll take a minute
here but now I'm going to actually talk
about a little bit of JavaScript because
it's sort of interesting stuff I guess
and something that it's a little library
that we're sort of just coming up with I
guess it's sort of put in the first
commit like five minutes ago and it's
just something called high five and it
sort of stands for html5 and it's meant
to be a sane rapper to html5 api's so we
all do love web standards right man that
w3c way to go you're doing an awesome
job you know we need that stuff however
the the sad part is the most those api's
look like so I'm going to I'm going
to go over 3 of the API is in particular
that are getting better but still suck
and need to be wrapped in a library such
as high five so exhibit a navigator
geolocation got watch position win fail
options right so watch position I'm sure
a lot of you will know what this does it
calls back to your win handler whenever
there is an update to your position so
it looks a lot like an event handler
actually am i right I mean we all know
we all know how to use event handlers so
I don't know why they didn't think of
doing like this maybe do document even
whatever could be device or something
something better than navigator
geolocation watch position you can
document to add event listener location
your handler and some options so pretty
much just like Oh using add event
listener wouldn't that be something so
the idea then with high five would be
something more like this and this
ideally would be chainable and so on and
so forth and you know using all the good
javascript stuff that we who actually
write JavaScript know and love yeah so
something like this high five on
location and a handler oh it's getting
better and the handler could you know it
could handle your air state and your
success state rather than having to
passing your two separate handlers for
win and fail so this is sort of the the
proposition that high five wood or the
API the high five would create and this
sort of works right now but I think this
is the only thing that works and even
then it probably doesn't I do have one
passing test I think and then the other
thing would be doing high five done so
you can unsubscribe to your location
event so right now you would do
navigator dodgy location dot clear watch
I think and you you passing your
and it's silly then you also have things
in geolocation like get current position
so just you want to get your one
position and that's it so a simple way
of doing that would be something like
this high five dot one where rather than
doing on where it continually set sends
back your location to your handler high
five dot one would instead essentially
auto unsubscribe so to subscribe it once
it gets back the first location position
then it would auto unsubscribe itself so
this is equivalent to doing get current
position in the geolocation example okay
Exhibit B has no one come up for a
seizure yet this is terrible I can't
believe in andrew i'm selling it really
good i think
so Exhibit B device motion so someone
somewhere actually came up with a bit
better idea in device motion so device
motion is essentially your accelerometer
in phonegap itself we went and because
we were implementing these things a long
time ago we actually did it like the
geolocation case and we did navigator
accelerometer dot get current
acceleration or watch acceleration on
super ugly stuff so in the latest for
example Mobile Safari they support this
and this is in the w3c device motion is
your accelerometer so hey this is good
looks like an event right window de on
device motion much better but what's
inside of it your event object has
something called acceleration including
gravity X that's insane screw that this
is just crazy so they were going really
well but then they it up so why not
just do this I don't know a lot fewer
characters we just do high five dot on
motion so we don't even need the device
stuff either I mean I think we're
getting to a point where that sort of
implied like what else are you thinking
of when you want a document motion or a
device that motion so anyway I get rid
of that don't add on like device motion
change or device motion different from
the previous motion value don't do stuff
like that keep it as simple as possible
get your event that x y&z ok Exhibit C
good stuff
device orientation this is similar to
device motion it's a bit long as well it
could be better for just orientation and
then the awesome part here is in the
event object we have a beta gamma and y
alpha who knows what those are well
obviously it's this come on and bless
its heart Euler he's a he was a smart
dude I love what he did for that stuff I
should really know this I like do
physics or something but anyway oil is
awesome but really come on we're
JavaScript developers we don't want to
know what alpha beta and gamma are so
let's just do x y&z orientation so you
can check it out here github com high
five high five a lot of people are
showing like this sweet spot graph for
some reason in some of the presentations
so I was like oh well here's my sweet
spot so high five is toll winning in
JavaScript Crockfords mostly JavaScript
Twila she's mostly winning clam nectar
is neither and then yes of course i
bought the airline other a few guys in
need media file system system info
persistence so all of these are horribly
disgusting AP is and w3c we should wrap
those keep the underlying API is going
with w3c yeah that's fine whatever but
yeah make a higher level API on there
that's actually usable in our apps thank