today I'm gonna talk about cross from
native app development and its
architecture by the way my name is Alton
Shango I'm coming to manage it off smart
face inc is it a second sorry ok now
good right God we're based on parlor
altar in San Franciscan our R&D center
in Turkey we just write our own ID and
to make you guys all you know JavaScript
right and you all front-end developers
to write their own native mobile apps
for Android and is easily that's why
I'll show you that how we done that
first of all there are lots of questions
asking their people asking me that are
you like a phonegap or something that's
why I need to first figure out those
apps you know first section of the
mobile apps web-based steps probably
most of you know of that just writing
your HTML and JavaScript and CSS codes
there's a single code base then let's go
on mobile browsers also but it depends
on the JavaScript engine inside you know
some gecko some web kit and chromium etc
and don't give the mobile and users that
they're used to know UI and UX and also
because of the running on the web
browser it's little slow and not fluent
but
most important thing is not accessing
device api's that's why the solution is
phonegap most of probably know that
phonegap everything same with web apps
but phonegap put the plug ins inside and
you're writing those structure and
you're getting again single code base
and accessing some device API but again
sometimes not fast enough and you are
the UX may not be accepted that's why
and also we have native apps which is
objective c and java written probably
that's why here is a cross-platform
solution maybe most of you knows or not
but there are some examples for that
titanium we have we examine also we have
smart face apps to do and i'll show how
all these cross platform tools works
ninety-nine percent they work safe let's
start with it here's our architecture
but here is this architecture probably
most of them you know all the devices
which is Android and iOS devices comes
with the same not say comes with native
libraries inside their own Java and
objective-c written libraries that's why
what we've done we took WebKit you know
WebKit one and take out the drm inside
and put our core engine what our core
engine doing you're writing your
JavaScript code and we compile this
engine JavaScript engine for iOS like
Apple did it for iOS 7 also you're
writing your JavaScript code and we
wrote c++ wrappers c++ wrappers and put
into core engine and this is looking
this is looking for java and objective-c
libraries inside the devices and
matching your javascript code into that
libraries and that's why after that we
took all those calls to the C++ pool and
after that your javascript code which is
maybe you're calling an action bar or
navigation part
bar or some labels or some image
components are all components and we're
reading them and matching into native
libraries inside to all the devices like
is six are you 7 android 4.4 4.3
learning model and after that those
libraries working running on the user
interface layer and we're putting some
other extension tools like x-ray light
and others this is all architecture
that's why the differences between
phonegap and others web-based solutions
that's why it's cross platform solutions
for we are getting both native APK or
IPA for iOS and user interface layer all
natively working after that we wrote and
what you see is what you get designer
which I'll show you that and some other
stuffs I'm not going to read those parts
are just making a live demo VT and
you'll see how it works I'll explain
your architecture while I was live
coding by the way
okay here's our studio you know making a
mobile apps is such a disaster while if
you're designing your app because
designing the app is we thought that
fifty percent app app development
generally that's why we wrote our own
idea this idea is our own ID written by
C++ only reason to writing the ID is for
design editor I'll show you how it works
here is our UI component which we sorted
here UI components network components
and other components under most of the
native UI components here listed and
some of them are not distant also here
show navigation bar or action bar let's
show you if you these UI components
working with drag-and-drop tools for
example you just drag image component
into the design area and you can choose
the data for example let's put on a
picture and make it stretch and you can
check it out here it comes here actor
why I'll put text button here is button
comes change the color of the button
change the name of the button add new
phones anchoring effects etc put for
example switch button here to make a
switch button works for something and
put a map view component for example
here again we are working for
cross-platform and that's why if you're
if end-user if customer download this
app from App Store he's going to see a
Apple maps and if you download it from
Google Play Store is going to see Google
Maps and you don't need to write any
single line of code to make it available
just it's working like that for example
adding AdMob component code reader and
other things here for example also
adding some native compost navigation
bar Oh action bar is also available here
after you're designing app this easily
this what you see is what you get
editor that's why I'll show you that
here for example I'll make this like
this what I mean with what you see is
what you get design editor when I put
that component here you can see the
coordinates here weight height x and y
coordinates for example y con is two
point 92 ratio it means it will it will
exactly you can see that in the device
like 2.92 raid 2 you're under the screen
all the devices all iOS devices all
Android devices going to work with this
design language ok let's see in action
ah for example let's edit here edit box
that's a little bit customizes at the
box for example I just only want to
write numbers inside ok here is design
finish oh you know mobile apps designing
it page by page and adding new pages and
make a connection between that after
that lets go come back the script editor
this is one hundred percent cigrip
editor which means as I mention you
before we took WebKit and take out the
do em inside outside that's why you can
do everything with javascript in the
script editor without the arm I don't
say i forgot to say about architecture
why we're not using drm because we just
don't want your CSS or other some custom
plot against draw things because if you
drove things like CSS like PhoneGap or
other solutions it makes it web
application that's why we don't want to
see any web components inside we just
want to see all native user experience
that's why all native components only
available for example let's writing some
javascript code it's too easy for all of
us probably ok let's change me that this
button name for example let's make it
text button ok
page 1 i'm in page one object my object
is text button my event we sorted here
possible events on press for example i
just want to press that button and our
namespace start with pages just know
that after that because it's going with
dot pages in page one I want a code text
button to show me oh sorry not text
button edit box I want I want to show
what edit pox-ridden yeah edit box and
text for example okay let's put it in
other bugs to see native other parks in
the devices and that's all when I click
on the button it will show me the edit
box text and also we wrote some good
components to make you write your apps
easily for example data co network
component you know we can't think any
app without Jason arrest or show up
sometimes it's a little bit hard to
parse and transfer two components that
those Jason's or rests that's why we
wrote most of wizards here for example
using web collide just right here any
any standard Jason just let's have a
right standard Jason here example do you
have any Jason for standard Jason I can
test it do you remember any of them oh
okay if you're right here and it Jason I
do is it works i don't know that
facebook perks or not no this is not it
Jason I was looking ok poem that first i
will show you that example after that
i'll show the others after that point if
you when you finish your app just choose
the profile android our iOS for example
let's choose R Us and click on the
single button device simulator when you
connect your device
when you connect your device when it
sees the device for example my ipod
touch it transfer my apps file sorry
into app okay and after that my app
comes here as I mentioned what exactly
seen on the screen will be on the device
you see here is the borders to point 22i
think 92 here is edit box numbers only
available at button and it will shows
native art box here as switch button for
example he didn't write any code folder
that's all and also you can get the same
thing from Android and I'll show you one
of example also open up project
okay huh by the way we have here okay
for example here we make an example that
i'll show you our dataset sorry yes it
feels okay here in one example i just
write my url json URL clicking on next
it will start the curry and after that
it shows me the parsing the parent and
child just clicking on the which strings
of rose I want to use and after click on
that its routes on the table like this
and after that point when it rise here
to put in one of the label for example
just write it like this data start with
data dot it shows me the web client
turns and after that for example web
client ID when i click on web client ID
it will turns that web client ID here
very easily this is all i'm not going to
explain more than that but if you wanna
i'm not going to steal waste your time
bit more than that sorry if you want to
learn more about it i have a stand there
and i can make you some other good
starts with live demo this isn't very
nice and good tool and it's also free to
comment addition and most of the
cross-platform architectures works like
this like that as i explained good for