my name is Nick Elizabeth wanta and i
work at twitter for the visual insights
team so we do data visualization focused
mainly on public tasting events i leave
the interactivity telecom project and
yeah so i was born in argentina i study
in argentina until I was like about 23
24 years old and then I moved to France
I worked there for about three years for
a French search engine company and then
I moved over to the u.s. to work for
Twitter
currently I'm working I've been working
with Twitter like for more than two and
a half years
yeah April 2415 will be three years so
my talk was about from data journalism
to data illustration so it's like how to
visualize data using javascript and how
we do that at Twitter so it's like the
process of like building data
visualisations for different verticals
so we build data resulting to produce
government TV and sports and other
verticals it's like how we build those
visualizations yeah so i've been using
web standard sims i graduated basically
so for more than seven or eight years
now mostly using standards for graphics
so i am very interested in graphics
technologies in general so it's like 2d
canvas SVG and WebGL are the main three
main graphic standards and i'm using
those to create data to those agents to
give you some kind of data points like
there are a billion tweets every two
days so it is a huge challenge to try to
visualize that and also you know all the
important features of our platform that
we're global for real time we're
conversational so there are a lot of
different aspects that presenter of
challenges to visualize data
yeah around public facing events for me
so for our team right so it's like the
Oscars it's like a huge event there are
a lots of tweets you know state of the
union address there's a lot of
conversation around what the president
says and a lot of things like that so
yeah I think that it's already something
that could be in the future like if you
had a platform that's already real-time
and you know how people are using
Twitter they're using it in very
different ways and so it's it's
interesting to try to know more about
the user base and how they're using it
like we're providing them a platform and
they're building something on top of
that right so it's I can really tell how
it will be 10 years from now this
conference is amazing the caliber of the
speakers like here are great we have
Brendan Eich who's like the creator of
JavaScript we will be talking today so
that's like that doesn't get better than
that right and the community is huge
it's like I've been here in 2012 it was
about 200 people and now it's like three
times more that three times 3x that so
it's it's really big it's getting bigger
and yeah I've been talking to a lot of
different people from Buenos Aires from
La Plata and there
like there's a huge kind of movement
around like technology in general in