well then as they presented there I read to him
of today's talk is to talk a little bit that it won't be because we all came to
we learn to learn what is good we come in the afternoon we have a
lots of amazing talks of new experiments to do maybe you get
it is but better a little bit of hindsight think a little bit I want
do and that well to zero put in mind a little things to think to improve
our project twice to see in his vice president
engineering on the side we are a digital agency that we offer different
more services now targeting products it's very interesting how they get
new projects we find new solutions for those projects and the
customers are happy and more users which is the end goal is
found in at blunk on twitter is ever on
this talk is going to be after everyone jennifer serves after they can't look
there quietly and any questions like that is to buy as twitter to
for questions or whatever you like afterwards we chat
first I wanted to congratulate the guys who organized the first one with faith in
Argentina, so congratulations for all of us, we are here to talk about the ss, no
994 a propellant that the css for the future we had html that were texts
a text document but you had to put a little color, notice that in
1,094 already think about this parameter not font-size x 3 we look
but hey this was already played in 924 it will be that the blue color in the links
I had more conversion I was looking for more people and things I don't know
and there we go to these incredible places like science like Argentina which is
a marketing landing let's say sell sell the event what information
event who will come to chat who will do things
animations amazing things that made a site so we're
working fox sports is a news portal huge amount of articles
information that needs to be done and there are a lot of things that we have to keep in
account when we generate a site or not and then a
also toad marketing landing which is what speaks a little one is
bring the web to the future a novelty if you do not know the site we made a
animations system with that you see that with canvas that was very interesting
develop it later if the client let's say it was what I expected I don't know
but internally I felt it was very interesting development at least
then we go back to css the voters in the same sector as they reached a
element how to customize the properties ok color text by case all good
and then we have this our code not that they care because it can't get to
the class because he was not in charge it was possible and then
I don't know what class convention to use but then I put many classes
because to be able to step on the previous one because it did not send everything very well
and we finished everything and well nothing came out bye bye I know if it hits like we say
then let's not try that cash face back once good what
let's try to think why this happens how can we improve a little bit all of our
flow of our project so that this is not so common at least and improve
all day is a little more the first thing to improve and what not to do is improve
our communication as a team as designers as developers as the
rest of the team product nerz the customer who wants the customer who wants
designer show on the site what we as developers want
implement some technology see that we can do it then love
among the entire team project managers client producers
we are all together developing something that we have to deliver but as
team then basic things that are good to come and that not always
happen in the projects so I want to do well if I ask for a little
not to the designer who has in mind what the customer wants, who wants the
next what is your objective sometimes many times the target browser is getting very
good to have stack analytics chay who are your most common browsers
so we make sure that 70% of users have the best experience
now if we still do a we have a bug in just a browser a
intra explorer x that because we use with banking and people usually use it good
let's make sure cool so no one has let's say
the top percentile has resolution book device errors this by
example the first thing if the structure hd me the wire flips they have in mind
have layout how it works which models i'm going to use how many pages are
perhaps it is a landing and it is simpler in collar they do not need to climb as much in
terms of models and modules but suddenly we have many and we have to start
to reuse them and think what variations they will have and if we have it from the
first moment or something similar to what you are going to do one is going to start
to understand how to separate those components how to start working them a little better
this what a bit of analytics said not ok chrome 74 percent of users
good public then well let's make sure that public receives the best that
we can maybe I can use branding box to stand out a little bit more 70 percent
of users you can probably see that work that dedication of
more than we are going to give you then keep this in mind especially resolutions
it is also to be able to make a good vat on those people who are going to receive that
product then that site then
one thing that always happens is the site is dynamic all sites are
dynamic dynamic to the point of responsive I don't even want to say that I
Yes, I am going to make response sites and it is not mandatory, that is, mobile and today
occupies a minimum of 50 percent of the traffic but more in some places it reaches
up to 70 80 percent mobile then this is not an option you have to
be like this have to be well have to have half a room what is necessary
even now we are running around the base for about a year we start with
this design mobile first we design álava mobile and then
we start with progress enhancement to progressively improve the experience
user while the screen is enlarged then the component by
example button without any media query is actually the button as you would see in
mobile with the size will have for example the background image the
background color and it will have it by default and then just when
we start adding media queries we'll see how that button will behave
in the different sizes when we are enlarging before formerly we started
shrink it in the distance here the work the idea or what I propose is
let's start doing it the other way around the component alone is mobile
afterwards it is always this we talk about dynamism does not follow clients and new
guys add two buttons that lead to the form link to buy the
science entries with easy have a great day and a Sunday morning and you
They get up early but then he comes and says no but Sergio the button has
to be red well the problem I come red color and we are all
happy and I give it to you is so much on the page
yes but sergio was not the one below who wanted red not the one above
all clients always sometimes don't communicate well back the system
communication or it is a matter of perhaps one is experimenting with the site while
find things so if you think it's the beginning code and start
add classes or a bit of selectors how is the best way to work
we do that if we do something like that
they see us much better we are all happy the client knows that the button
bottom is red is well above is the other color if at first the top
We were going to put the red button on it and we are going to have problems because it should have done
after blue and the clip changes decision so if we have a code
clean it will be simpler material later but it has the same too
it comes with the content now we have to translate it and it's not there
more button is I am a button for example we want at the end
I'm a button and dot dot dot and we have to make sure that our
components are scalable not only on responsible but also on
content and this often happens that guy we are not going but I had put a
fixed height and when doing breaks because they are two lines etcetera then well that
It is one of the things that we say usually happens at another point in its structure
To generate a scalable and maintainable site in the future, it is necessary to generate with
a good structure a structure where using
processors that I think that today we should all use for the chips that
brings no matter what styles it has that no matter how important it is that
features you need from each of them sometimes for example I think it is
basic is to be able to divide our code into multiple files in order to have
a much more maintainable code and that we know I have to modify the button
ok I go to the file the button and I touch that file and that should be everything
well then for example we have these sc which is the main thing
where the rest of my components don't matter
bartz where could you bring for example ok the customer said the blue or the
designer said blue was this blue but suddenly there was
instead styles and they changed the brand and suddenly blue well this time blue blue
then we have a file of the component itself
a file structure also in terms of folders which what are
components what are layouts what are bases what are profits by
example goes like this I found a mix insights that is very good and that I use
all the good time I bring it and save it as my utilities for example
then being very tidy of these points help that later in the future
our our site is much easier to maintain
and I think this is one of the most important things about this is
set your rules set rules for a project don't let a project be
loose as the pokemons through the city of Buenos Aires that this a jungle not
decide what the rule is going to be there have to be rules in this but define the
Yours one of the great point six that is spoken is if that is not if it is because
skate which is one of the big chips of 7 I hope very careful with this
because we end up with things like these that heather main generates inside in
the one why we have to speak a submenu of the submenu and but that had to
take it out of collection and we end up with things like that then just as is the great
ssc figure is a great danger also in the future for a maintainable site
that's when we see those select ones we are a little scared that's why it's
important to generate rules for example the voters and money but as
let's call our constituents it's the same if you use is max ven or ss
it's irrelevant I chose one or some kind of rule up to a set of rules that you
serve you and your team and your project and if it is necessary to throw it away and we have what
because we are a team but as long as there is consensus and we all maintain the
same project rules we are sure that always going forward is going to
keep it the same way things like this will happen or you have to create a
new color as I put it I have gray gray stronger gray lighter good
light gray but not so light because it's a new color and you're done with this
and then guys racing his head again he says
sometimes tooling helps a lot in modern sites in our project
modern we use many
workflows with lots of your link with google with others with with web groups to
that any these and some things that we can integrate our workflow by
example which are the cute ones the cute ones basically ensure that the rules that
we define are met then if we decide that a property has two
points and then a space after the property value make sure that in
all sides the same occurs to see the example that is half naive perhaps not
it's a good guy is the space that matters if it's a space that matters but
after we have type 300 components 20 of them because our
site started to scale and the customer needs new needs once they
let's see that any developer who grabs site will read the code much more
easy is not going to start losing where was this or what was happening
with it and something very important I think that only
because the talks calls that they don't do the css and this is important to us
the importance of being the easy solution to I don't have time to find a way
correct to do it and I have to clean and I make important the house maría
so let's try to avoid using it and sometimes if we use it we even let
some documentation of why its use is important
let's try to use iris won't use and excuse lawyer let's think of some
modular way the air is something that cannot be repeated is only once in the
site imagine if this is why we have to repeat it because back there was
changes is dynamic the world the embi had only one but then we got
we said it is very good it is working very well let's put another one we have to do
a reactor is to throw everything back and that can be a problem
It wants to show a little this that we have been talking about with a module that we have here
we have a letter that has an image a title a text and that later we have
a component that has the item ticket and various options then not
we go a little to the ccs that we would have here very simple we have the letter that inside
It has an h 3 image and content, but in rated it is remove it behaves
another way because although the content is not displayed
now what problems we have here we are using an android card image that passes
is the content of an image I am not we are last night 3 tomorrow analytics arrives
we see that the ceo is not doing well that h 3 has to be h 2 h 4 when
they are related because it is less important and we start again when this factor
I know where this was happening here because we did not improve this and well in another
file we have that inside the crime works another way we have multiple
rules for this now doing a little factor we come to this that cart a
single file we don't have multiple files for this module
it behaves like this has the favors of it the shadow the edge the maximum size
maybe in related it behaves in such a way and then the different
components of drying carrie more cards of the card content this is what I'm going with
think modularly it does not matter if we are going to use is max ssv in for
differentiate why the its the modules the modules etc. the important thing is that
have a rule and manage to keep it going
So with this we know that if afterwards the h2o lh3 h4 or we change it for a
paragraph is always going to be consistent sometimes there's still to change some
property because 83 and 82 have different margins or pad only sizes
but if we feel that all correctly in tulle letter
We are sure that later when the site starts to scale and we look at other
modules elsewhere the module will react the same
way something that's always interesting is
learn from your own code and you finish writing a project
work on css and start doing a little bit of cv you will start doing
different browsers or different solutions and you start to
find how look at this I did it this way 8 and putting this property
change how it is done in firefox for example there are multiple 3ds rendering
ss and you have to be careful with everyone and the experience you gain doing this is
just queuing up in our code depending on what things
occur in each of them peer review the gdp is a very good practice for
working as a team we learn from each other's code and what solutions they came up with
in other people not always all the solutions are the same and I think it is
something very valuable to share with the rest of the team that later in the future
it even causes the code to be maintained in some way because we all
We already saw that code and we more or less know what that person is dealing with
here we are in the office doing a little care on one of the sites
that's we talk about bone dynamism it is possible it is optional you have to walk
in everything yes or yes and stop tablets how it works in touch touch is something is something
that we have before is very different how something interactively works in a
device than a computer
if those are like julia said she has her problems when they walk when they don't
but it is also very important that our source code if we have hacks or
things that we learned throughout our development
we document them well because in the future it will reach another person who
maybe it's not us who has to keep that place
and that person is not going to know why that property is there and maybe they learn something
again and it says look is talking about that in the internet explorer the images
they looked different and with this line I solved it I just
learn something new and I think this as developers we are people that all the
day is learning new things because as one showed comes there is a
development that is being promoted and that every time we implement new
technologies to make things more amazing new landings new sites
new products all here is let's say pointing to
to improve what we show the user experience and make them
beautiful obviously not then thank you all so much now if I'm not mistaken
well in coffee break we also have questions if I'm not mistaken for a little while
for that I don't know and if I'm not there to have a coffee or a beer what
like later so thank you all very much