[Music]
[Applause]
hi can you hear me
great better better okay so I'm this
nervous so I think have to read sorry
for that but I just
we'll look in everybody's eyes in
between the lines okay so did she google
that this was not the answer I expected
when I asked a senior developer for help
several times
hi my name is Castine and I was not born
as a developer 10 years ago when I
changed my profession from character
animator to development
I started at zero I did Google a lot but
I didn't understand everything I was
reading maybe this happens to you
sometimes
so being someone who believes in there
are no stupid questions and it's not a
shame to ask the answer did she Google
that felt like standing in front of a
wall with the answer to my questions
right behind it my insecurities as a
junior developer increased I doubted my
own beliefs at the beginning of my
journey in this profession I got to know
some developers I am very grateful for
they did pairing with me they did code
reviews they had patience some of them
are here today
and but unfortunately the feeling of
being a junior surrounding by the
Almighty seniors remained and sometimes
I felt sorry for bothering others and
sometimes you have to drink some water
it's my throat in the road then I heard
about CSS classes a free whole day event
for everybody skill level I joined as
attendee and some something in my mind
changed I realized I was not alone
there were many other developers having
the same questions and struggles I
realized asking questions is not just
okay it's good it might even have others
surrounding you and occurs encourages
them I realize that if the developer who
knows everything does not exist CSS
classes have been my first contact with
the community they are learned to have a
different view on my surroundings
by seeing coaches admitting that they
might not have the answer to my
questions right away and getting help
from other coaches helped me a lot and
not taking my insecurities too serious
everybody is treated with respect in
questions a welcome nowadays I am
attending CSS classes as well SJS
classes as well and I am joining CSS
classes as a coach the Chi Google that
is an answer I never heard there but
sometimes let's google together so
never forget where you coming from help
each other that's what makes this
community thank you
[Applause]