I
so the topic of this talk is going to be
a performance beyond page load I'm glad
that Jeffrey gave a real good
introduction about the networking
performance so when you say the
performance of a web page is divided
into two components that is networking
performance and the rendering
performance while networking performance
takes care of your page load time and
the start render time rendering
performance will be taking care of the
performance of your interactions on a
web page so that is what we will be
focusing upon our goal will be to build
smooth interactions and even to
understand as toward the issues are if
there are any with your web page or your
interactions on your web page and how
you should take care of them so let's
start on we start off with a small
survey I guess with the show of friends
you can actually tell whether you belong
to it or not so my first question will
be how many of you like animations in
material design with a show friend okay
some people not not all of you but i
guess it's mostly related to the fact
that animations haven't been performing
very well on HTML right or it may be
performing well on native devices but
not on nom on your mobile in the mobile
browser so we are going to tackle such
issues in the coming in the coming
slides and I will be discussing them
briefly so you won't like animations if
they are not smooth our goal will be to
make sure that we have this things in
place we follow the best practices but
some people want to tell meet like hacks
right because it's not up to you to
actually take care of them it should be
the I mean it should be for the browsers
to actually make it sure that whatever
you have put in in your code actually is
performing and varied drones on the web
browser eight runs performant Lee that
is at 60fps so there is this a
mix-and-match of different things that I
will be talking about their hacks and
there are best practices and we'll be
discussing them so starting off with
rendering performance I just told you
about the goal which will be to build
smooth interactions so let's start with
the
a steady Archy study is basically about
a girl and a boy where the boy asks the
girl to marry him he proposes her and
luckily he is responded with an answer
which is yes so what next is shopping
shopping for that particular shopping
for that wedding basically and it is a
shopping that is up the the bride the
bridal couple is is shopping on on a
mobile website okay though what happens
next is something that we didn't
anticipate for but it is something what
happened so this is the reaction of the
girl after she was I mean going through
the mobile website and trying to
purchase from over there so it doesn't
look happy right so we need to make sure
that this reaction doesn't happen for
your own customers as well so the bad
performance of shopping portal it leads
to do I need to tell you that the bad
performance is basically the rendering
performance and not the networking
performance that will be discussing over
here over here we are talking about the
interactions that are there on a web
page and how they affected the
experience of that particular bride so
this is that followed next after after
that particular reaction this is
basically a meeting between developers
project managers and the testers to
understand as to what went wrong or what
can be the solution for improving the
rendering performance of their of their
mobile web application so i am not
actually going to focus upon just the
mobile web experience but it will be the
performance it will be the rendering
performance in general ok so wait up it
is so as far as now i have just told you
about the case study in general it was
simply about tom about the experience of
the customer how it impacted what are
the different things that people are
thinking about but let's take a
technical perspective regarding this and
understand as to what exactly happen
what is the technical issue around it
what what is it because of and what are
the different solutions that
you can actually use to overcome it okay
so a small commercial break this is
about me my name is a puta Saxena I hail
from India I work as a first second
junior and you can follow me at up would
underscore Saxena if you have any sort
of questions related to performance
whether we eat a networking performance
or the rendering performance you can
simply tweet up to me and I'll make sure
that I try to answer that the companies
that I've worked with and I'm working
with ving affair before that I had
worked with LinkedIn which is now a
SlideShare which was now linkedin and
director some other conferences that I
have contributed to before the talks
mostly focused upon performance but it
was more about networking and even a bit
about gaming performance so in case you
want to check them out please do so
let's start off with basics ok so when I
talk about basics I actually come to
this I remember this picture from my
childhood which is about a Bioscope so
with a show of hands how many of you
understand what is a Bioscope ok just
one two three okay not not a lot of
people understand what is Bioscope so
basically it's a small device where
there are different stills of a
particular animation or a movie and they
are moved manually by a particular
person who is the owner of this
particular device and people will be
able to look through through these holes
that you can see the aluminum shells and
through that when a person moves those
stills it appears like an animated movie
so on the right you are able to see the
stills of the animation that is that is
played by the particular person and
that's how it is so this is a similar
concept that is followed when you even
when you even display a particular
picture on our on a screen so what
happens is that the devices refresh the
screen at 60 frames per second and that
is how they say that they are able to
display at 60fps or even more than that
like 120 fps so what is happening is
that there are 120 frames per second
that are played on a particular screen
the frame budget that
comes to us to make our particular
operation is 16 milliseconds how we did
this calculation is that in once again
you have to display 60 frames so you do
a simple calculation that is divided and
what you get is 16 milliseconds so in 16
milliseconds you have to make sure that
everything or every operation that you
are performing is under 16 milliseconds
if in case it exceeds 16 milliseconds
then you will be able to encounter
something that you won't want to though
there are also some other householding
works that a browser needs to needs to
take a while while carrying out your
operation which leaves you with just 10
milliseconds in total so you need to
actually make sure that whatever
operation you are performing is
completed in 10 milliseconds or less
than that and 10 milliseconds isn't a
lot of time when failing to meet 10
milliseconds we come across the behavior
which you don't like which is termed as
jank okay so if there's a scroll that
you're Rob doing and you see that there
is a lag in between what you will term
it with is will be jack so this is the
experience that I was talking about a
person is trying to scroll the page but
he seems but he sees that it's actually
not strolling the reason for it is that
it is so some operation is taking some a
lot of time okay which is not allowing
the pager to paint okay and because of
that he actually sees that there is a
jitter or a lag or basically he's
encountering jank so let's understand as
to how a browser renders a particular
draw a particular webpage or how a CSS
operation is applied onto a web page so
the pixel pipeline comprises of these
five stages if I may say it starts off
with JavaScript because most of the
interactions may trigger from JavaScript
it can also in the via CSS also which is
the second stage but let's think that
you have made some sort of interaction
and it goes to your JavaScript okay what
happens is that you do some sort of i
mean Dom manipulation which basically
creates us corresponding style
and it is passed on to the next stage
following the style there are three sort
of operations that can be applied
depending upon the CSS rule that is
applied from the style style stage and
these three operations are layout pane
and composite I'll be briefly described
are describing each one of them as to
what they do what are they responsible
for and what impact do they have on
performance so first comes in is layout
layout is is an operation which is
triggered when you reposition or you
change the size of a particular element
so that basically triggers a layout
operation so as you can see over here
this is a particular web page where I
have highlighted the boundaries of
element and whenever you do some sort of
change on the size or the position of a
particular element the layout operation
will be triggered in the pixel pipeline
after the layout operation paint
operation will be triggered and after
paint it will be the composite operation
that will be triggered so layout will be
the most expensive operation when it
gets triggered the CSS properties that
are responsible for triggering the
layout operation are all of these so you
can basically go to them I will def I
love I'll tell you as to what or what
site you can go to and understand as to
what CSS property corresponds to which
operation or what operation does it
trigger so over here you will be able to
see the CSS property for example width
it basically changes the size of a
particular element and thus is labeled
under the layout operation category that
is it triggers a layout operation comes
next is paint what is paint operation so
the paint operation is about when the
when the pixels of a particular element
are changed or they need to get
repainted that is that is how we define
a paint operation so when you actually
see that an element's layout has been
changed that as its size or position has
been changed so inside a web page there
might be some elements right which are
getting their pixels repainted so that
is why the paint operation is triggered
after layout but there are CSS rules
that allow you to just trigger the paint
operation
so let's understand that over here you
can see that paint comes after layout
operation but it can be triggered by a
CSS property directly also so this is a
simple screenshot or we can see
different colored pictures though this
yes CSS property that is responsible for
triggering a paint operation just a
paint operation I am NOT saying about
the layout are color background color
and and all of these CSS properties
they're all are responsible for
triggering a paint operation directly ok
the next comes in is composting
composting is an operation which allows
a browser to basically compose it
different layers together and render a
web page it comes the third in all of
these operations and the last in the
pixel pipeline ok so first comes in is a
layout operation comes next is paint and
then composition where all of the layers
are composted together so this is how
you can picture eyes a web page there
are different layers on a webpage and
upon upon the rendering of a webpage or
when there is a change the last step
that happens is this the composition of
different layers to render a web page so
this is the order of how what the
performance impact of different
operations have on in a pixel pipeline
the most impacted or the most expensive
operation to perform is layout followed
by paint and followed by composite the
reason being that layout triggers paint
and composite aerosol paint just
triggering itself but composite as well
and composite is the last operation
which is triggered by CSS properties
like transform or opacity so you might
have heard of people saying that you
should use css3 animations or you should
use css3 transform instead of using
javascript or instead of using some of
that paint operation so the reason
because so the reason is that only the
composition operation is applied in case
of transform and opacity change okay so
how do you analyze the
moments of a web page now we have
understood our theoretical knowledge
right that there are three sort of
operations but let's try to do something
practical so the thing that we need to
understand as to what how we can analyze
our web page is first as an FPS meter I
have mentioned about the chrome dev
tools because it has a feature that it
is able to display a frame rate on a
particular web page while you are doing
different sort of interactions though
they are readily available in different
other browsers and you just have to see
for it there are several other libraries
also that you can include in your web
page and you can actually see as to what
frame rate is running for a while you
are doing is some sort of interaction so
this is the screenshot a way you can see
on the top right I have my frame rate
which is running when I enable it on
chrome I even display as to how you can
enable it by yourself though it's simply
a I mean I have made a screenshot where
while doing an interaction I was able to
see that the frame rate frame rate was
dripping even below 30 FPS which was the
reason of the jank to come in next comes
in is enables paint flashing so what is
paint flashing allowing you to do it
allows you to see as to what all
elements are undergoing a repaint okay
so when you see a lot of paint
operations happening while you are doing
some sort of interaction you will be
able to see as to whether a particular
element that you wanted to repaint is
repainted or not and what other
components are affected because you
might trigger a layout operation which
can further repaint all of the elements
on a web page and which is a warning
sign for you right so this is how a web
page looks like when you have enabled
flash painting and you can see a lot of
elements getting repainted the site that
I have audited for it was material up
calm and as of now so i'll be explaining
as to what was the reason behind it
because of this this situation to
comment where you can see the entire
screen to
repainted the next is chrome devtools
timeline so the timeline allows you to
actually see as to what all operations
are performed when you do a record of a
particular timeline or when you do a
record of the interactions for your web
page so this looks something like this
and what you are able to see below is
that there are different frames that are
that you can see and with every frame
that is exceeding the 16 millisecond
window you can actually see them going
above 30 frames per second line which is
the top most in this okay below that is
60 fps so over here you can see that at
a lot of times javascript is taking a
lot of time and because of that the next
operation that happens which is paint is
is taking its own time which is because
of which the total time taken in a
single frame exceeds 10 millisecond or
16 millisecond in total this is the
reason for you to understand that a jank
is happening so what are the performance
best practices as I mentioned earlier
you might want to think of it like best
practices or even hacks but yeah if you
want to make your customers experience
sir I mean smooth then this is the way
to go forward with so first in this is
CPU versus GPU so CPU is not efficient
in handling the graphics related
operations while GPU is built for it
right so we need to understand that
JavaScript utilizes CPU which is
followed by GPU when it is manipulating
style so what you want to avoid is using
javascript to trigger style operations
or to manipulate your dome so in that in
those cases you will want to use CSS
instead of using javascript though with
the animation API coming the web
animation API coming to JavaScript it
will be hardware accelerated and we'll
be using GPU though I mean its support
is very limited as the Florence still in
the beta stage it's not very stable so
it's yet to be there so as of now you
can think of using styles for
manipulating your Dom instead of
JavaScript a rule of thumb is as simple
as that
use glasses to update element styling
instead of using javascript an example
for this will be a will be the following
code where earlier in the first part i
am using CSS and i am removing and
adding classes to basically apply some
sort of style to a particular element in
javascript what you will be doing
similarly if when not using CSS will be
something of this operation where you
define as to what all the properties you
want to change and you simply apply and
you simply change the style of the
javascript element the process that's
followed is comprised of another step in
javascript which is rasterization and
which takes a lot of time and as
continuously improved by the web
browsers though when you compare it with
the house ESS is doing it it's a lot
more performant so style calculations
are the reference will be a CSS triggers
com so let me open it up over here our
CSS triggers is a great contribution by
a developer advocate by the name Paul
Lewis and what you can do over here as
you can see as to what CSS property
triggers what all operations so if I
write or in the filter over here like
color so you can see that it triggers a
paint operation followed by a composite
operation right and it doesn't trigger a
layout operation if you change it to
width you'll be able to see that it
triggers a layout operation followed by
paint followed by composer I am NOT
asking you to mug these CSS rules and
their corresponding operations but have
a thought about it so that when you are
using it in your daily workflow you'll
be able to have that particular
understanding and gradually it can
become a habit so you are more so you
have a better understanding as to what
CSS property applies what sort of
functions what sort of operation and
what performance impact has it has on a
web page performance coming back so
these are some of the things that one
must follow
what needs to really understand as to
what impact a rendering performance has
on the webpage or how is their running
performance so what you need to do is
you need to profile you need to profile
your page you might not want to go to
the extent of using timeline as I
displayed before but you might want to
actually see as to what all elements are
getting repainted upon some sort of
interaction I guess while you you are
doing a code review you can look for
these these subtleties subtle things and
maybe help each other to uh to do it
better and that's how you can make it a
habit comes next is choosing your CSS
rules wisely once you are able to
understand as to what the issues is you
will be able to see as to what is the
CSS properties that are getting applied
when you are making some sort of
operation and you can see as to what
operations are triggered that is layout
paint or trick or composite and
depending upon that you can take
decisions whether some sort of operation
is possible in an animation or not
without a without having less than 30
FPS or 60 FPS next comes in is avoid
triggering layout / paint operation
repeatedly on when animating so as I
mentioned just before when you're
animating try to just use the composite
operation or the CSS property that only
trigger a composite operation and not a
paint because that's really expensive
comes next is a prefer using transform
and opacity as I just mentioned next
comes in reducing the complexity of CSS
selectors so this is a code by a one of
the developers at opera and what they
said is that when applying a CSS rule on
a particular element fifty percent of
the time is actually spent on on getting
that sell us on getting on finding the
particular element why the selector so
in case you are having a very complex
selector you might want to have it less
complex okay and have it that way
because otherwise it will take a lot of
time I guess in the last slide what he
mentioned was that it was like maybe a
20 or even more than that the selector
the entire length of the selector and in
those cases it took a lot of time for
the mobile to render that particular web
page and apply that particular CSS rule
on on a particular element so need to
make sure that you don't go into such
cases especially when using
preprocessors for example says or less
right so this is a small example over
here i have mentioned a class where i am
applying some sort of rules which is dot
title and on the next side I have a box
which is the parent element and on the
last child I am having inside it I have
the title div or an element which is
having a class if I can basically use
dot title instead of using this sort of
CSS selectivity I should use dot title
okay because it's a bit more performant
now the next thing that comes in is that
CSS selectors have already been
optimized I won't ask you to actually
spend your time over this but please
make sure that you have an understanding
about this the next comes in remove
unused CSS rules the CSS selectors as I
said are already performant though if
you have those CSS rules which are not
used browsers pay spends a lot more time
to see as to what element it means to
apply it on so you'll want to actually
automate this particular task of
removing the CSS that's not used at all
on your webpage so there are several I
mean tasks and plugins that are
available both for Gulf and grant that
you can use for removing the unused CSS
rules comes next is reduced the number
of elements being style so when when a
particular interaction is happening on a
web page please see to it that only the
elements that need to be updated or
repainted and not each of the element on
the web page is getting updated an
example will be google com i will be
sharing it later as to what all elements
are affected with some sort of
interaction and you will be able to
understand as to how you can implement
it on your web page also comes next is
measure your style recalculation cost so
when you're animate
there's a recalculation that is
happening with every frame you need to
make sure that the styles that you are
that you are applying on a particular
element when you are animating they are
not very expensive an example for this
is this there's a Elaine and I have
applied a hover over that I have an even
bounded on which I change the background
color now background color is a paint
operation so I need to make sure that
that no other thing or I am NOT term I
am NOT doing something in parallel which
may exceed my frame window an example
would have been on caring is calm when
we perforated them so what happened was
that there were several Li elements and
there was a whole property and on top of
it the color was changing while we were
hovering and when we were scrolling the
particular webpage over those li
elements which had the background color
change on her property it basically made
it exceed the frame window of 16
milliseconds order 10 millisecond window
so in those cases we were able to see
Jack and such is the case that you can
find when you have a style recalculation
on a particular event which is happening
repeatedly comes next is reducing paint
area or don't paint unnecessarily and
avoid union of damage reasons what I
mean by this is in this picture you are
able to see that there are different
elements getting updated from the
boundaries you are able to see as to
what elements are getting updated though
because the entire screen is getting
repainted what is kicking into place is
union of damage regions so let's say
that there are three there are three
elements on a web page which are big and
they are getting updated so the browser
says that instead of repainting just
three elements why not paint the entire
page so that it takes a lot a lot less
time for me instead of for repainting
those three elements individually one
after the other or simultaneously so you
need to make sure that something of this
sort is not happening because it might
lead to a janky experience comes next is
CSS animations as I mentioned before
you should use composite operations
while your CSS animating a lot of other
JavaScript libraries also capitalize on
this on this on this behavior of
browsers for example famous it simply
uses transformation to make animations
and run them at 60fps so you might want
to explore it further comes next is
debouncing the input handlers the input
handlers can be even the actions or the
association on a particular event an
example that I have taken is disabling
over event listener while scrolling and
this is the example that I made earlier
this is can I use com and as you can see
there are lot of allies and on the right
you are able to see that there is a
hover property in which I am changing
the color so this this was the reason
that we were able to see a janky
experience and when we disabled that
covert we were able to see the jank
being gone so how you can do this is a
simple hack that you can incorporate in
your own web pages is that when you're
scrolling you can actually disable all
of the CSS / events that are associated
on a particular element by doing a
pointer events none property on a
particular class and you can apply that
same class on top of body so when you're
scrolling you can add a class of pointer
events none to the body and it will make
sure that no such home where property
gets activated while you're scrolling
once you are done with it it will
restore it back by removing that
particular class and you'll be in a
situation and you'll be in the normal
behavior of your oval properties comes
next promoting elements that update
frequently we just saw a great talk
about SVG animations a lot of time what
happens is that the animations are
happening and and because of an
animation that element is getting
repainted now because that element is
getting repainted you might want to
actually promote it to its own layer so
that it's just composited it the time is
actually not spent in repainted it again
and again but you need to make sure that
whatever you are promoting is done after
you have profiled and
seeing that it may or that it may affect
your pace performance because otherwise
you'll just you can do a similar thing
where you can now where you can update
where you can promote every element to
its own layer right but that will
consume a lot more memory so this is an
example where you can see a particular
image which is having its own layer and
the text which is after this there might
be some sort of animation that can be
applied to the image which is displayed
over here so here is the fun fact or did
against know that position fixed
elements and scrollable elements are do
get repainted every time you do some
sort of interaction with them so
whenever so I guess a lot of us are
using headers right which are position
fixed headers or fixed elements on top
of a web page in those cases those
elements get repainted there there are
hacks are there is actually a hacked
which allows you to go over it and
basically promote it to own layer but
you need to make sure that you have
profiles it before you go ahead with it
so this is the hack that I was talking
about will change transform is a CSS
property that allows you to tell the
browser that hey this element is getting
repainted a lot a lot of times and you
need to make sure that it's promoted to
its own layer the other hack is
transformed translate Z 0 though will
change transform is is available in most
of the browsers and as a fallback you
might want to use transform translate 0
as well both of their functions is to
basically promote a particular element
to its own layer I'll basically go
through a live performance audit so that
you guys can understand as to what I'm
telling in general as of now about the
best practices but follow along with me
till we do a performance audit alive
comes next is gifs and performance so
gifs and performance don't go hand in
hand obviously because Jeff's get
repainted every time they have a new
frame so because of them material up
calm which is a great website about
showcasing the material design projects
it was getting a lot of janky experience
it was able to see that lag and
performance in the rendering performance
the reason for it was
a lot of elements were getting repainted
and a lot of time union of damage
regions was was what getting applied by
the browser so their entire page was
getting repainted when the small ships
over there so this is an example of the
screenshot that I took both of these are
images and when I enabled paint flashing
I was able to see that both of them are
getting updated every time every time
there was a change in the frame of that
particular jiff so you might want to
disable gifs once they are not in the
viewport so that so that they don't
actually contribute to the impact of
their running of the rendering
performance of your web page so now it's
time to do a live performance audit so I
have opened up this console of mine I'm
using chrome dev tools you can use any
other browser devtools lady want it's a
bit more simpler in Chrome so that is
why I'm using it so as of now you can
see the that I have enabled paint
flashing and because of that you are
able to see as to what elements are
getting repainted so let me go above and
the lookout for for its Jeff animation
ok so now i'm not into the viewport and
you can see that a jiff is getting
repainted every time it has a new frame
right it's on the top right that you can
see over here now what you can what you
need to make sure that if such a such
thing is happening on your web page as
well you might want to disable it by
removing its source by replacing it with
another static image per se or you can
use some other technique comes next is
show layer borders so it allows us to
see actually what are the different
layers on a web page it might not be
making a lot of sense but let me do
something as if now so over here I'm
interacting with this particular element
and I am just crawling a I mean up and
bottom on this particular element can
you see that entire list is getting
repainted when I am scrolling it was a
fun fact that I said before that
scrollable element skate repainted
so this is something that you that you
would want to avoid that when you are
actually scrolling our particulars a
particular element what is the need for
the entire element to get repainted so
the hack in this case would be to simply
inspect this fuel and apply a will
change transform property yep and now
when you stall you are able to see that
the entire element is not getting
repainted so this is a hack that people
say that it's a hack but if you want to
improve your page performance this is
something that you can incorporate as
well so this is it and there are several
other things that I just mentioned
before that you can apply to do a
similar thing over here also there are
the as you can see the entire element is
getting repainted which comprises of
different pics so you might want to
avoid this so a similar hack that we did
for hacker news widget you can do a
similar one for dribble as well okay and
after after we have applied this
particular will change transform
property I said that it has been
promoted to its own layer now let's
verify now when I say show layer borders
you are actually able to see a blue line
on the hacker news widget right so this
is because this element is now upgraded
to its own layer now actually let me
remove this will change transform okay
and now let's show layer Boris okay I
guess it has been already upgraded to
its own layer this is the reason for it
but otherwise it would not display that
blue border around that particular
element so coming back at H con 2012 and
I guess we are all all aware about the
rendering performance that they have a
serious impact about the customers
experience so this is a case study which
facebook mentioned that when it reduced
the frame rate from 16 millisecond
from 60 FPS to 30fps they saw a decrease
in the user engagement so this is the
reason that you should really think of
improving your rendering performance of
your webpages part 2 performance will be
to practice it and make it a continuous
habit we have put in / for dead calm
which allows you to actually see as to
when we are performance or a different
web applications we make them live so
that developers like you can see as to
how we performance or it did and do by
the same by yourself so this is what we
intend to do with / for it we have also
put in our documentation which we are
updating regularly where you can see as
to what are the different things related
to rendering performance what are the
issues what are the different articles
that you should look out for when there
is a particular impact of your web
performance so you might want to check
out perforate calm in those cases in
case you have done a performance audit
by yourself you might want to ping us at
afford it and we will be happy to add it
in our repository as well so that's it
thanks everyone I have noticed when we
were working on animation on mobile
devices different type like iphone 6 6
s5 there is difference and the lagging
of performance when it comes to
rendering so do you have any idea why it
happens so so when you say that you are
able to see a lagging lag and
performance there are different reasons
for it and the way I would want to
explain is that over in the slides over
here I simply discussed as to how CSS
can impact your page performance though
it can be triggered by a JavaScript as
well for example there is a consecutive
Dom read and write which might be
happening and impacting its performance
and there are several other issues that
can be related to it so the way that I
did up offered it for the rendering
performance you can do a similar for
your own application and understand as
to what is the thing that which is the
reason for the jank eNOS in your case it
won't be a generic answer but you need
to understand as to what are the
different issues that can impact a page
performance and that's how you can
resolve it there is a way to like
debug this on native iOS like a instead
of using chrome tools so i have because
in chrome tools it does not show any
difference even when you try to
reproduce it in the same way but on
native iOS devices it shows the
difference ok I because these issues are
like generic they happen the same way on
the desktop and the mobile devices as
well so I didn't actually had da I mean
much much difference between the while
analyzing the performance of a
particular application on desktop and
mobile but I have to see in that case as
to what what is the exact thing which is
making a difference between the two
devices so yeah not sure about the exact