thanks a lot everyone so just make it
extra clear and are confusing I'm Dave
and he's David and we built JavaScript
kids and our dream in doing all this
stuff is to run JavaScript as fast as II
so sure that is pretty much totally
crazy but it turns out that current
systems actually are getting pretty
close and there definitely will be lots
of assembly on slides today as we show
you the native code that does this so
just a little bit of background really
what sort of makes this hard right if
you use a compiler that generally helps
make your code run fast by pine native
code so the thing that makes it hard for
javascript is the fact that javascript
is on time you don't have any type
declarations anything and the reason is
that having different types in the
program means the processor needs to do
different things so in JavaScript a plus
B can actually do a lot of different
things right if you're adding strings or
finding numbers that's going to require
different native code same thing for
properties if you look at these two
things here if we try to access this
color property on a string or an object
you actually have to do different things
so you need different code and in davis
it turns out to get even more
complicated so in here i just added
something we're adding a couple of
floating-point numbers as an
optimization the engine often tries to
do things with integers but you might
need floats and so even though they're
the same jst few actually need different
get code for even those two things and
it's also the same here for these two
objects on the bottom they both have a
color property if both has the same
value but in most jits you actually need
to run a little bit different code to
make that happen so today we're going to
talk about two different kinds of jets
here so first there's the simpler
untyped jet and the idea of that one is
for every little piece of your
JavaScript program you generate some
native code that handles all possible
types so it's like you drop down this so
a multi tool that can do everything for
every statement in your program and the
good thing about that is it's
simple to do and the generated code can
run no matter what types a program
actually has but the code is pretty big
because you're generating a lot of code
maybe some of it won't even run and it's
a little bit hard to optimize so that
one actually turns out to give you a
pretty fast code if you want to get even
better what you can do is usually called
a type so in this one either by
using some type inference or just
measuring dynamically you try to guess
types for each variable and then you
generate code specialized for those
types so in this case you know for each
statement in the program you try to
figure out the types are use a little
bit of specialized code just for that so
you get sort of smaller code and it's
more optimized the disadvantage is that
you do have to recompile of types change
right so if you were sort of guessed
there would be a nail so you used a
hammer and your compiler and it turns
out there's a screw that's not really
going to work you need to do something
else so now on to the assembly and damn
it's gonna start out by telling us about
math is this here this isn't your first
sight of it hey go yeah have a thing so
to start off let's take this sample
function here takes in a left and right
variable and just adds them and let's
see how this would work in an untyped
compiler so an untyped compiler wants to
handle everything so we want to generate
code that will handle all possible types
for left and right but we want to start
somewhere simple so let's start off with
just assuming that left and right are
going to be numbers and as you know
JavaScript semantics say that JavaScript
numbers are always floating point but
machines can use both integers and
floats and integers tend to be faster so
if we call this function with say five
and ten we want to treat those as
integers instead of floats so let's
start off let's say our compiler has a
register allocator and it decides that
the left and right hand side should be
in registers eax and edx we might
generate just this one instruction
machine instruction that says add the
two integers in registers EDX and eax
both say eax is actually a pointer to a
string
and EDX is number 35 so this is bad
because we'll just be adding a number to
a string which is I'm sorry a number to
a pointer to memory which is completely
bogus and at best at some kind of
security risk so we can't do that so
what we need to do is insert type checks
before the ad and that's this code in
magenta here and now the compiler needs
to keep track with both the types and
the values of the variables so let's see
what would happen when we run this code
let's say we're adding numbers 27 and 35
the first thing we'll do is check to see
if the left hands type and register EDI
is 32 an integer and it is so that check
passes next we'll check the right hand
sides type and the ebx register and it
is an integer so that passes and now we
can just take the values in eax 27 EDX
35 add them and we get our result just
62 so does this always work but let's
see what if we call F with a huge number
so this is the maximum signed integer
that can be represented on a 32-bit
machine and this time if we add them the
machine is not going to have enough bits
to represent the actual result so it'll
just overflow and get negative 2 so
let's see what's supposed to happen in
JavaScript when we add these two numbers
we actually get four billion and as four
billion equal to negative two no so we
have to do something there and luckily
the machine sets an overflow bit on the
CPU whenever an overflow occurs so we
can just check that bit and when it
happens do floating-point math instead
so what about floats let's say we pass f
2.7 and pie and we want that to be fast
too so in this case we can extend each
of these little type checks with another
block of code
that will try to coerce the two inputs
to floating point numbers and if those
pass and it can get floats out of them
it will add them together and continue
running jit code as you can see this on
compiling this whole add expression for
numbers is about 30 instructions so
let's write a little benchmark let's say
we have a 2-d game and we said we want
to compute the distance between this
lady and the cow we might use Euclidean
distance or something so this is a small
benchmark that loops over two variables
and just computes the distance between
them and in an untyped compiler each of
those little sub expressions would be
compiled separately and in the end we
get about 230 instructions for the
entirety of the loop and that seems like
a lot but despite that jager monkey the
n-type compiler in Firefox can run 100
million iterations of that in one second
which is pretty cool for JavaScript it
means in one second you can do 100
million operations but can we do better
so let's say we had a type compiler and
the type compiler can just maybe it
wants to assume that every value in this
function is going to be an integer and
then we can start making observations
like this a minus I times a minus I will
never change inside the intervals loop
so we can actually pull it out into the
outer loop and this is called hoisting
and why couldn't we do that in an
untyped chip well let's say we had this
crazy object with a value of hook and
every time the value of function is
called it increases this goal variable
called ham if you were to pass this
object into our benchmark JavaScript
semantics say that ham has to be
increased every time the object is used
in one of those arithmetic expressions
so the hoisting is only valid if we've
proved or assumed that every variable in
the function is an integer then we can
make another observation in P minus J
times B minus J we don't have to compute
P minus J twice so we can just throw
that in a temporary variable and that's
called redundancy
elimination so in the type jit this is a
sample of assembly from Mozilla's in
development type called Iron Monkey
it's not the full assembly I've removed
some crappy register allocation
instructions so we'll get to this
eventually but as you can see there's
just a subtraction multiplication and in
addition we still have our overflow
checks and on the multiplication there's
also this test instruction and that's
testing 40 because in JavaScript if you
have say negative 1 times 0 that
actually has to yield negative 0 which
can't be represented in an integer so we
have to check for that and I'm monkey
runs this in 250 milliseconds so that's
Forks faster than the untyped yet but if
it was a little smarter it could
recognize that if you have an expression
eight times a it'll never be negative so
we could get this down to six
instructions and that runs in just 220
milliseconds or four and a half times
faster than the untyped it so our goal
is to get as fast to see how close do we
get to that so in see this is just for
instructions really three our
subtraction multiplication add and then
a register move and see one's this in 97
milliseconds so an untyped it got within
10 X of C and at type Jake gets within
two or three acts of see that's actually
really cool considering that three or
four years ago javascript was a hundred
x slower than C but how can we do better
well in this case it's actually pretty
hard there's this semantic gap where
JavaScript just does not have integers
it only has floats and C has integers so
it does not need those overflow checks
and now dave is going to talk about
property access
okay so this is the other major type of
jade code that we're going to show you
is how objects and object properties
work and in general this is one of the
most important optimizations in practice
it gets a huge speed up it's important
for real programs and so I'm going to
because it's complicated right Jas
obvious properties are complicated and
the jit code gets complicated too i
boiled this down to pretty much the
simplest thing I could possibly think of
just evaluating one level expression no
next it's just to get a property and I'm
thinking of kind of a linked list here
that I can diverse I did that so I could
sort of do some benchmarks and show the
performance so in order to show you how
you get these things first I have to
show you what's inside a GS object so
here's the constructor I have in mind
and this is from spider monkey a
simplified version of how that objects
represented it's just this little memory
object to see struct so there's some
stuff in there like the prototype and
things you'd expect but the most
important things there are first there's
the shape and that's something that
gives the object format so the main
things it has are a list of properties
and then a slot index as to where you
can actually find each one and the thing
to note about the use is they're
generally shared so if you have what the
system will try to do is every object
that looks like this it will try to make
sure it gets the same shape and has
shape 45 so you can easily tell that it
does and then the automated fingers this
laws and that's just where the values
are held it's just a little array of
JavaScript values and so to look up the
next property what you do if you're not
using a jit is first you go to this
shape table you find next you see okay
that's in slot 1 and then you go over to
you read slot 1 you say okay that
has type special and the values though
so let's start a gentes in an untyped it
like Jager monkey so we'll just start
off first thing we'll do is load up the
type tag and verify that it's an object
it's just like before we have some fast
path for object we need to make sure we
have that so we're just loading a tag
from Emory we compared to this FF 87
which tells us it's an object so if
that's good then we continue on now
oh the value note there is some little
register allocation glitch here fairly
harmless but these things do happen and
so now we have the object one operates
what do we do next well the n-type Jade
actually has a problem here right for
that one we want to generate fast code
that handles all the types but here's
the text you can get you could get an
object that has a type that looks like
this here's a different type of object
requires different jet code here's a
different type of object even more jet
code so really there's a infinite number
of possible types here so there's no way
that you could generate them all and
worse than that the JIT doesn't even
know like what they are what shapes they
would have how you'd identify them
anything at all so pretty much at this
point we get to go to the simplicity and
ease of self-modifying code and so this
is called inline caching it's a bit of
historical term it's from the self
research that really pioneered a lot of
optimization for dynamic languages and
so to show you how that works i'm going
to work backwards so first i'm going to
show you the code we want to get so this
would be code that would run fast and
get the next property for the shake 45
so we have that top that operates that I
already showed you that gets the object
so the next thing we need to do is make
sure that we have shape 45 so in this
blue code here ESI hose the object so
we're just loading that shape field we
test it keep going it's matches so then
the next thing we do is we load that
slots porn air out of the same object
and then at the bottom here we load the
type and value so this ESI plus 12
that's loading from the slot array type
and then we load the value so the only
problem here is that these values in
white you don't know that my compile
time we don't know what the shape is we
don't know its shape to expect or what
the floor mats are and the idea of
inline caching is to really say well
let's just generate a template here and
then have it modify itself to the right
code at runtime so here is the actual
code it's the same thing except as w
values in those positions and I'll just
show you how it works by running it so
first we run this top part that gets the
type it's this FFA 7 it matches we keep
going then we wrote up this value then
we do our little funky right
allocation thing so now we load the
shape which is 45 and we compare that
with this 8f does not match so we jump
to the C++ function get prob so get
prompt there's a few things first it
sort of looks up that shape and finds
the property and then it uses that to
catch this code so it says okay the
shapes 45 so I'll patch that and it also
knows what these offsets should be
patches those finally it gets the actual
value because of course you need to do
that or to keep running properly and
keeps going so next time you ride it
works pretty much you know how that code
I showed you so we were on the first
part gets this value and type then we
load up the shape this time it matches
so we can go on to our fast property
access code we get the slots or eight
kind of looks like this thing and then
we get to load out the type and then we
load up the value from that okay so that
actually work pretty well it got a
tattoo above instructions it runs really
fast but Java scripts a dynamic language
and we want to be able to take advantage
of that so you know here is the shape of
object that we generate a fast path for
but somebody might write a program where
they do this right maybe you pass things
that have a label food property as well
and we really do want to make this work
correctly and run fast and it turns out
the icy thing really does it it's almost
exactly the same thing so if you run the
code again with this new shape of object
does the first part is set value so now
we get the shape which is 70 compare
that to 45 and it's not evil so now we
jump to this get pop function again so a
gift fob again it's going to look up
that shape and find the property and now
it's supposed to patch into shape and
slot offsets but actually that wouldn't
be a very good idea here because we
could patch disseminate cody fast for
that new shape but it's slow for the old
shapes so we're kind of stuck right we
sort of either have to be fast for only
one or else we're constantly patching
and constant patching is definitely slow
so instead we're just going to generate
a new code for the new shape off the
side so it looks like this it's almost
exactly the same really the only
difference is we're comparing with shape
70 instead of 45 those offsets 12 and
eight they could be different if it was
position that object happens not to be
in this example and then we need to
detach these jumps a little bit right so
before if we didn't match we jump
straight to get prob but now I want to
jump to this new little fast function
here and then we'll jump back so at this
point we now have it fast for both
shapes and you can really extend this
process and definitely right it can
handle prototypes you know you can do
get setters really anything you want and
just generate as many of these as you
need ok so now I just want to show you
what a type compiler can do for this by
taking this untyped property access code
and just seeing how we can speed it up a
little bit so the first thing to observe
is that in these objects so I put one on
here so it has that prototype shape
slots sometimes but not always the Jets
has an optimization we'll put the value
slots right inside the object so if you
do that you don't really need to load
that slots pointer and then load the
value you could just see oh actually
they're at these offsets so we'll just
load it that way and we just eliminate
one load the untyped compiler can't
really do that because it has to really
conservative and assume the object could
look like anything the types compiler
gets to wait longer and say oh I know
exactly what these objects look like
before it generates any code so next if
you look at the bottom here you'll see
that we're loading this tight tag that's
what ESI plus 28 is into EDX and then
what you don't see on this screen is
that gets stored the memory and then it
gets reloaded again and then we test
again so we're sort of getting this
thing just to move it around about three
times then test it the types compiler
could actually see that and optimize it
better and say you know what we should
just test it at the bottom because
that's all we really need to do so
that's two more instructions out we
freed of her register so here's a little
thing you don't really need type for
this but you know it just so happens we
generate this move and compare but you
could do that with just one instruction
so we'll do that and then the last thing
is to look here at the bottom right when
we get this node next value it goes into
ESI in my example program that gets
stored in node so again it sort of gets
sort out and then at the top we're
reloading it just to put it back
SI we can say hey let's just leave it at
ESI this will work completely so we move
to our free to register so here's the
theoretical code that we get if we start
of use a type of pattern optimize it as
hard as we can that I reduced from that
jam code just has five instructions it's
really just two checks says do we have
an object doesn't have this shape load
the value so if you compare a see right
I'll let's see what need to do is the
green thing but it's quite folks so iron
monkey is not at the stage where you can
actually compile this code yet so let's
give some props to crankshaft and show a
better version of how they did it so I
just started out in my program and you
can see that it's actually very much
like what I came up with so the top here
they have a test to verify it's an
object just like we're doing those looks
different because instead of using sort
of separate type and value areas they
just put the last bit of the object they
just set it to one that's how they say a
snob drink so and then they check the
shape it's actually very similar to ours
you can see that they're just loading a
value and comparing that with some shape
in their case they have to have this
little minus one there because their
object pointer has that extra one from
the tag otherwise the same and then they
just load a field out so it looks
exactly like that all right so here's
the performance that you get when you
use all these things in a classic
interpreter spider monkey if I search
the link list with 1 million elements
like this it takes 100 milliseconds so
if we use an untied from piracy ICS we
get like a three or four x speed up down
to 29 that's jager monkey and if you use
a time compiler like crankshaft I found
that you are actually you know almost
within 1.5 x of C but definitely 2x very
very close and that's your even the
highly optimized seen so last things
that are like yes we actually can run
JavaScript within two or three ecstasy
sometimes now and in fact with floating
point things because we don't have that
semantic gap we found programs where it
runs just as fast and jazz to see and we
really would like to keep getting faster
and faster there's a bunch of stuff we
can do but to really get there we need
to bridge this semantic gap we're sort
of the processors
semantics Jas has others were two
different and sort of if we could nudge
either one a little bit close together
we might be able to get there so thank
you
awesome any questions
oh yeah Eric
for the for the untyped compiler when
you're checking the shape and it doesn't
match you're doing a jump to the stub
how does it know where it was called
from the stuff is there's a journey so
there's actually several different ways
of doing that do you remember which way
we're doing it right now the jump
actually goes to a little path that
bakes in all the information you need to
to patch the code all right now the
question over there
how do you handle the cache invalidation
like you mean you major in line cash for
the structure of the objects are the
shapes better and people change the
upper side like the prototype and oh how
does invalidation of caching works so
there's actually the flexure question is
kind of complicated but the example you
gave doesn't really require the
invalidation of the cash so if you
change the prototype of an object that
will change its shape so the next time
you have that code maybe it's now shape
46 because you change the prototype so
it doesn't run but there are cases where
you have to do that because if you do a
GC garbage collection then often that
will sort of clean up a bunch of old
shapes and it might change shape IDs and
things like that so on certain events
like that you actually do have to go
through and basically purge all the
inline caches and reset them to the
original state so and and it turns out
that doesn't really bother performance
too much because they kind of you know
get turned back on pretty quickly you
mentioned that you would like to see the
the instruction set four cpus or your
javascript a lineup so where you could
optimize things better what would you
like to have included in javascript the
language to help you achieve better
better speeds well I guess I don't
really want to make specific suggestions
because I think that should be up to
people that are sort of really language
designers it's kind of more like hinting
at what we do need but so I think typed
arrays help and the binary data API
that's coming in es6 if you're familiar
with that one so it's time to raise you
can actually create an object for you
say this is an array of doubles for
example and that means you can get a lot
better storage because you don't have to
store all these type tags and things you
really just store the numbers you know
when you read them out you know exactly
what you get things like that so
otherwise I think and so that it
basically gives you something like see
raised by an errand data API
gives you something like see struts so
you can be fast that way the main thing
is integers right that's sort of the
hard line and I could imagine different
things like if there is even just a
little dynamic type like new in 32 or
something like that in JavaScript like
that would work there's other ways of
doing it to you could imagine creating a
library that just has integer math
functions in it teach the jits how to
how to see those but it's really all
just about I guess some way to express I
want integer semantics now and then you
can compile it exactly the integer math
on the processor and be fully fast so
that's pretty much what you need another
question all right let's give these guys
another own applause for making