hi everyone and welcome to Jack Buster's
I'm Tom will seus I'm a product manager
on the chrome graphics team yeah I'm
that I hack on the rendering system
where I could stuff like that and we're
here today to talk about jank on the web
what it is and and how to fight it yeah
so what we usually do when we talk about
Jang because we sort of start with like
what smoothness is right so you got a
screen in front of your a lot of you do
and the way that things working right is
it's tricking your eye and perceiving
motion when in fact what it's doing is
it's updating the screen those lcds
really really really fast once every
sixty sixtieth of a second now sometimes
it's like 50 Hertz sometimes it's 54
it's all over the map but the idea is
you've got to do it fast enough so your
eye perceives this as movement and if
you do so then it's smooth if you don't
then you get Jack yeah Jack comes in in
in a whole variety of formats we refer
to something as a hitch when you drop a
whole bunch of frames in a row so say
everything stops for 200 milliseconds or
a low frame rate is when maybe things
are still still happening routinely but
they're not having as often as they
should be so you only get a new frame up
every 50 milliseconds instead of every
16 milliseconds that kind of thing and
the worst is when these things combined
and you get you get a really variable
frame rate you get new frames coming up
on the screen at irregular intervals
your eye is really well it tuned to that
sort of irregularity because it's how we
notice motion and if you you look at
something that's supposed to stick to
your finger right like something like
say this div that's rolling up and down
it's pretty fast because this resolution
is a little smaller than the monitor I
try this on a high res device or a low
in computer for then then you'll see
that once that physical metaphor gets
broken of your finger moving and the
screen updating sort of correspondingly
then all the sudden things start to feel
really bad right and this is the
difference between something that feels
smooth and feels really nice and
responsive is something that feels janky
and this is what we're talking about
when we talk about Jack yeah I mean
basically you know we all talk about
it's all well well established right
you've got to optimize your lip you know
loads minify do this do that make sure
that your
you know doing the right request to your
network but there's the second class
citizen right which is the rendering
system which we haven't typically had to
think about because you know frankly the
old web pages of yesterday you move up
and down right and the browser can do
lots of tricks to make that just fast
but nowadays when you have you know
complex beautiful looking websites for
those to feel native for those to stick
to your finger the thing you have to do
is you have to run calculation of layout
you have to run JavaScript you might
garbage collect somewhere in there you
might have some animation that you have
to do you might accidentally query a
style select you want to interrupt yeah
right like say something where it's
really it's really hard right like
there's a lot that needs to go into that
16 milliseconds and that is rattling off
this list of things but it's it what
we're here today to talk about is the
stuff that I guess I would summarize as
the green bars in in chrome devtools
right so yes there are a whole wide
variety of things that you can think
about when you're thinking about
performance and that includes all the
the network latency stuff and that's
talking about it includes a lot of
JavaScript events but what we're here
today to discuss is what we call
rendering and that sort of breaks down
into painting compositing we're going to
talk about both and in fact there was a
really cool post by Paul Lewis just
today where he said I bet you that if
you go to your favorite website out
there you will see a whole lot of green
and purple in in the modern web and I
would encourage you to give that a try
and I think you'll find there's a lot of
websites out there that are basically
paint and this green bound that's what
we're here to talk to you about that's
jank busting yeah so how do you Jack
bust first step is you try to paint fast
right try to get those grain bars to be
as short as possible we're gonna talk a
little bit about how to do that but
better yet you're going to try not to
paint it all we're gonna talk about
about that in probably greater detail
and lastly we're going to go into a few
cases where because the platform is not
always as obvious as it might be you end
up painting when you really don't have
to and and you might not even be
noticing this kind of thing because it's
the sort of thing that you need to use
tools to sort of proactively look for
but we'll show you how to do that and
we'll show you how to hopefully get a
better glimpse into what's going on
under the
so you've heard us use the word paint
right and I think that's really the
building block here that we need to talk
a bit more about so you go to you know
goog and you you get this right which is
a blinking cursor right whoo
earth-shattering now what's going on
behind the scenes here is that Chrome
has the cursors a lie this is not the
operating system doing it chrome has
just a bitmap in memory just of RGB
colors and the cursor is just some dark
colors in that in that bitmap and link /
WebKit has book keeping it very
exhaustive bookkeeping that says who
this part of the shadow Dom changed I'm
going to repaint this part of the bitmap
because it's different now and I need to
put a cursor where there wasn't or I
need to remove a cursor that is called a
repaint and so it has a there's a
repaint rectangle you can imagine right
when something changes visually we have
to repaint it and you can sort of
imagine that the cost of a repaint is
you know to first order proportional to
how much you have to repaint so
certainly you know blinking that cursors
going to be a whole heck of a lot
cheaper than blinking say all of google
to black and white right back and forth
it's just sort of intuitive right you
have to touch more bits of memory but
you know of course that's not the whole
story we could all go home right the
other part of this is that not all
paints are going to be the same speed so
of course if we want to just fill in a
part of the page with white there's
gonna be a lot cheaper but if we go to
this I'm feeling lucky button and you
actually like really look at it and
actually i think this audience more than
anybody understands sort of the details
in some of these elements all of those
little effects you see the the
anti-aliasing on the text the rounded
corner the line being anti aliased all
of those things are costly and they're
costly in the sense that they eat CPU in
order to perform the computer you know
the CPU just has to sit there going oh
is this line on the pixel or halfway on
the pixel in it just you know noms away
at the CPU so the i'm feeling lucky
button is three or four times slower to
paint than just a white area and this
sort of makes sense and then if you go
to a low-end device like a phone it's
even more
or that that difference is even more
amplified so this is all sort of my
long-winded way of saying don't paint
right like don't do it and and in
particular if you're thinking about
mobile really really don't do it and to
help you with this we built into the
browser and not just we chrome pretty
much all browsers now have this concept
of a layer right the best way to think
about layers is we look at you know your
dom and we got this this thing is an
over scroll that like an overflow scroll
did you're probably going to move that
up and down right so hey let's let's
instead of instead of repainting in
order to make that scroll happen let's
take that thing and make it into sort of
like a Photoshop layer right and then we
can move the layer up and down right and
fake it out and then what we'll do is
we'll store the contents of that layer
on the GPU and then when we actually
just do an action on the page that moves
the document up and down like this all
that you have to do is ask the GPU to
composite so now in modern chrome you'll
see two steps in the in the timeline you
see paints which you don't want to do
and you see composites the composites
are us taking these layers and smashing
them down and if you do that chrome can
really hit some super super high smooth
frame rate 60 Hertz whatever it is if
you don't do it and you paint then
you're in trouble right so I'm going to
walk you through sort of an example of
that scrolling working well or not and
this is a site it's pretty simple a list
of 100 images and you can see that again
demos might be slightly off modulo the
the resolution being slightly smaller
than what's normally on this laptop but
this Scrolls pretty smoothly I can like
fling up and down in this area no
problem you can see the disc release ID
is updating like really nicely and I'm I
would not call this janky right but
you'll notice that as I'm doing this
I've got the mouse cursor sitting in the
gutter of the page and if I mouse over
one of these images I've got like a
simple animation effect that happens
just based on like the hover pseudo
pseudo class right and I got a little
bit of a drop shadow
right in the image a little bit nothing
nothing all that fancy but it is it is
an effect that changes things it's a you
know two or three lines of what you'll
see is very destructive CSS exactly and
you'll see that if I try to do that same
scroll haha it's pretty fast here if I
try to do that same scroll with the the
mouse an overlay images then all the
sudden things start to kind of fall
apart and the difference is something
that i'm going to show you right now if
you open up devtools and you turn on
show paint rectangles which is like our
beloved feature in devtools you can you
can see what the difference is the
difference is whether or not you're
painting during the scroll so if I just
move up and down now what's happening is
that crumbs pre-painted a little bit
behind the scenes and it can pre-paint
about fast enough that you don't
actually get paint operations that
happen when you actually need to show
new content on the screen and so that
means I can sit here scrolling up and
down and I don't get any red rectangles
which are the areas that are being
repainted just like the blinking cursor
from so this is that layer analogy right
then in this case the layer analogy is
working well right you're not seeing any
repaints it means that you're going nice
and fast you'll hit 60 Hertz in fact the
only thing repainting you'll notice is
the scroll bar on the right hand side
there and there's no helping that if I
mouse over one of these images you can
see the throughout the throughout the
course of that that hover effect I
animate in and out the classes i'm
changing and I'm getting repaints sort
of every frame of those of those effects
animating and that's that's really
really painful right not only is it
making the animation run a little bit
slow in theory if I invite you this and
scroll up and down all the sudden I'm
having all these red rectangles flash
during the scroll operation yeah we saw
this happen on a popular photo blogging
site thing where he can sort of guess
what it was we're basically they have
this nice hover effect and if you had
your cursor in the wrong place the site
was just completely unusable yeah and
and so I mean hover is something we're
picking on here but hover is actually
relatively simple to deal with it if
scrolling performance is important to
you you can turn off the hover effect
during scroll right like I'm going to
achieve that with a non scroll
handler on a timer and indeed if I do so
you'll know that I don't get the
repaints during the scroll but then as
soon as the scroll stops I sort of get
them again 200 milliseconds after the
last scroll event and that's great right
but it does change the UX of the site a
little bit and this is the kind of thing
that you need to start sort of
reorienting yourself re orienting
yourself to think about when you think
about design right because you can do
some really nice visual effects on the
web today but it's also really easy to
shoot yourself in the foot
performance-wise and I'm going to just
sort of assert that things like good
scrolling performance they're actually
just as critical to the design and feel
of your site as really nice visuals are
I'm going to assert that as well just to
be with him right so again i'm picking
on hover like the point here is not use
hover the point here is use dev tools to
see what's going on right so there there
are a wide variety of ways to get paints
that you don't necessarily need or want
during a stroll they include some of the
things on this list and if you do get
paints during a scroll it's not
necessarily a problem right like it's
entirely conceivable that the paint's
can be so fast that you can afford the
paint and the texture upload to the GPU
and the composite and whatever else goes
into the rendering pipeline but just
don't pay like don't get into a
dangerous situation just don't paint
because there are a lot of things that
can make make the paint's take a long
time right I'm like yeah the rounded
corners and drop shadows and the other
effects that we're all sort of familiar
with can play into this but there can be
a lot of other things that are a lot
more subtle are the bane of our
existence right now in in this category
is is definitely image decodes because
it's really possible especially on
high-resolution screens to blow a lot of
the internal image decode caches inside
of blank / WebKit and then like
everything so so this slide don't don't
sit there scrolling down you know
scribbling down this slide or like
whatever you know we're constantly
changing our minds and krumitz growing
up and chrome chrome has a very tiny
brain and it gets really confused really
easily so this is the current list of
bad things but the best thing to do is
to pay attention the techniques we're
showing you to measure the source of
Jack and then sort of deal with the
latest canary of whatever
the thing is at the time exactly and the
the layer model that we're talking about
that's so great for scrolling all of
this applies to other types of animation
too there's nothing sort of special
about scrolling other than that we've
put sort of an extraordinary amount of
work into trying to make that particular
kind of scroll a lot on the web yeah
because because it's so common but like
a lot of the same primitives or what we
use to try to make things like say CSS
animation also work well so if I open up
this demo this is super ugly we're not
designers but we're trying you'll see
that this is just a drawer right thus
animates in and out it's using CSS
animation so great right like I'm using
modern techniques I'm telling the
browser what I'm trying to be doing it
should just make things good for me
right well kind of but the way CSS
animation works you can actually you can
animate all sorts of stuff right and
there are things that you can animate
that don't play very well at all with
this notion of everything needing to fit
into 16 millisecond frames for instance
what if you need to do a lot of reflow
during during the animation right that
means that every time a new position
ticks out of this animation running
stuff could be like moving around and
that's the kind of thing that blank /
WebKit gets really really bad out really
fast so if I I was cool surprise if I
open up devtools again and I have show
paint rexin then you can see that during
this animation I'm actually painting
every single frame with it again that
red flash that means repaint and that's
bad that's really bad for animation and
you can even see that it's a little it's
a little jerky right all I'm animating
here is the left property and if I had
say text in the middle you would see it
reflow and stuff and and that reflow is
is really really negative for
performance if I open up the devtools
timeline I'd take a recording of that
animation running you can guess what
you're going to see but if i zoom in
here I get like style recalculation
re-layout paint operations composite
layer operations and on that paint thing
will basically if you take this to a
low-end machine that paint can balloon
to 30 40 50 60 milliseconds you know in
a blink of an eye you put an image on
there you
so shadow on there you put a border you
sneeze back there gives you 60
milliseconds and and you might be saying
like well the wouldn't it be great if
the browser could kind of make this
better for me but again there's
something kind of fundamental to the way
the left property works that makes that
hard because elements elements flow
right so instead if I use something like
a WebKit transform this is probably a
trick you've screwed my demo this is
probably a trick you've you've read
about online right like these transforms
promote things to their own layer so the
layers we're talking about for scrolling
earlier they apply here too and if I run
this animation using a translate X for
my transform instead of the left
property then all of a sudden those red
rectangles go away during the animation
and that's great right because that
means I'm not I'm not painting anymore
and indeed I can confirm this if i go
back to time line take a recording run
the animation stop it look at what's
going on here all i'm seeing or
composite layer operations and the
reason that we can get away with this is
because the transform takes the element
out of out of flow right and and it lets
us sort of make some guarantees about
the thing inside the transform being
kind of independent from the the sort of
parent container and that's that's
really nice but you'll notice there's
not quite done yet right because i'm
still seeing these red flashes at the
beginning and end of the animation and
this is the kind of thing that if you're
thinking with 16 millisecond frames in
in sort of the forefront of your mind
should should stand out as potentially
problematic right because that means
that as soon as I click the button a
repaints going to happen and if that
repaint might be slow then all of a
sudden there's this lag when I click the
button right and that sucks that's
that's really bad that's not what you
want it all you want things to feel
really responsive you want them to
respond immediately as soon as the other
the other kind of responsive right and
so it it so happens that there's a
relatively easy way around this and that
if you use a translate 3d instead of a
translate X the thing gets promoted to a
wire all the time if I want to
illustrate this I can use a great
feature of devtools called show
composited layer borders and if I turn
that on you see this sort of cyan
grid the grid is not important what is
important is the sort of yellowish
orange border that goes around the
viewport in this case and that yellow
orange border it means everything inside
of this is in its own layer so these
layers that we keep talking about here's
a way to sort of visualize them and if
you look at what happens as I run that
animation you can kind of see again if i
zoom in that the drawer gets a yellow
orange border of its own throughout the
course of the animation but if I make
the red rec go away the repaint wreck go
away you'll notice that there isn't any
yellow orange border before or after the
animation and that's bad right and
that's the reason that you get those red
flashes the repaints right at the
beginning and right at the end because
what happens is that I start the
animation the drawer gets ripped out put
in its own layer this is a new layer so
now chrome needs to paint the thing that
didn't exist before right that takes
arbitrarily long and then weary
composite recompose 'try composite the
animation runs and then we smush the
drawer back into the base layer of the
page when we smush it back into the base
layer of the page we have to repaint
that area and that's why you get the
second red flash with the at the end if
I use the the translate 3d instead of
the translate X this is sort of
incidental but you you don't get those
root glastron you get yeah it has a tiny
brain so it gets confused right it's a
well-meaning brain you'll see that now
there's this sort of orange-ish border
even when the animation isn't running
this is what we call sometimes pre
promotion because the layer is promote
the gorge of its own layer at all times
so if you have something that you think
will move in the future you need to
start thinking about not giving it a
layer at the last second like in the on
click but having it have a layer well in
advance so that it's already primed up
and ready to go so that when you get
that on click it just starts moving and
okay means fast right and you might be
thinking this feels really happy and you
would be you'd be correct yeah this is
this is the platform right now and it
stinks so sorry but but it is summer
tomato so actively changing because for
instance the the translate example I
have in the latest canary is it actually
stopped working as a bad example because
when there's a WebKit transition or a
transition property on the
the drawer element we actually are now
teaching link to be smart enough to
actually creep on pre promote the thing
on its own but you need to think about
this because it's just you don't assume
that the platform will get it right yet
someday maybe but not yet exactly so
that is layers for animation but
sometimes you need to see more than that
and that's going to show you yeah I mean
we like giving you eye strain with the
yellow lines those thin little yellow
lines that are absolutely critical for
performance like that's really nice
right so what what we've done is we
built an internal tool this is quite a
bit more technical than say you know dev
tools but what it will do is it let you
see your layering so here I just have a
you know cats search and when you use
chrome frame viewer and you can google
it to find info on this what you get is
you get a list of frames that were drawn
by the by the compositor so for example
here and then what you can end up with
is this which if you remember my gmail
slide that showed the gmail layers well
this is this but for your site so these
are your layers in your site and just to
give you sort of a morgue you know
complex example we've got you know plus
and here's plus here and the interesting
thing here is as you scroll if the
viewport sticks there it is over there
you can see sort of there's a viewport
here up there right and then we've got
the content for everything below the
page and so in this case as you go
between your pages what you'll see is
the actual viewport moving you'll see
the layers stuff like that and this can
end up being very useful because you can
pull things out like why a layer was
created and you know how much GPU memory
it's using it's sort of advanced stuff
but if you really are going to try to
push your content to the limits of the
current platform you may want to check
this sort of thing out particularly on
mobile where you run into things like
memory memory constraints a lot more
readily yeah this is kind of what we're
gonna we're gonna be pretty brief on
that though a pretty low level tool but
grab us if you're yeah we're happy to
talk about it more
ya later on last category of stuff we
want to talk about which is which is
that there there are times when you can
get one of these these repaint flashes
even if it seems like you didn't deserve
it and this can happen in all sorts of
scenarios but I'll walk you through one
if I click this button I add a div to a
container pretty simple fantastic so 100
100 pics square nothing complicated at
all about this styling right and if I
open up devtools and I have the the
repaint wrecks on I'm going to turn off
the layer borders have the repaint
wrecks on as I as I click to add more
you can see that i'm sort of repainting
where the button is and I'm repainting
where the the new divs are and as I get
sort of off-screen adding more I can sit
here all day mashing this button and the
only thing that repaints is well the
scroll bar and the button right this is
great this kind of makes sense it's it's
intuitive to think that well if I'm
changing something in the Dom but it's
only affecting things that are
off-screen shouldn't need to repaint
right and that's great when it works but
unfortunately repaints don't only happen
when you make changes that end up with
visual impact it's entirely possible to
do something like say toggle the padding
on this container block that you can see
outlined in black and when you do that
you end up repainting the entire
container and again if you think about
it a little longer maybe this makes
sense again because from blinks
perspective what happened you added a
little bit of padding but potentially
everything inside refloat right this is
like the beauty of the web and when that
happens all bets are off about the
content inside of the container blink
needs to be very very conservative about
maintaining like what might be dirty
what might be out of date and we have to
repaint and when we repaint this is what
you get so it's really important to
think about this in terms of like you
can't blink and get confused and it gets
confused very easily so you have to
monitor this sort monitor for this sort
of thing during your development there
ways with chrome developer tools
protocol to get the paint stream out so
that you can monitor and test harnesses
for example but you need to keep an eye
on this sort of thing
because stupid and knock your stuff like
setting width to the same thing that it
used to be can sometimes cause this and
and then it'll you know ruin your day
and this is the kind of thing that again
we're trying to make better all the time
but there are always going to be
pitfalls like this so it's the kind of
thing you need to sort of watch out for
yeah but I mean ultimately there there
are just times when you do your best
you've got you know everything done as
well as you can but you do have to paint
sometimes that's you've added something
to the dominant you actually really do
need to paint it and sometimes it's just
an effect that you're just not willing
to compromise on you know there might be
the g-wiz thing that you've done you
know who knows what it is but it happens
so we we started off with with sort of
this this thing up right and it's a
little janky er when you go fullscreen
and blah blah blah so we're showing you
this is sort of an example of bad
content right chrome has a feature
called continuous repainting mode or
devtools does so if I check this button
here and go back now what chrome is
doing is it's constantly repainting so
it's a little hard to see but basically
they're the whole page has got a little
red and that's because it's got a big
repaint rectangle on all of it and
what's happening here is Chrome's
constantly re re repainting all the time
as fast as it can go and up here is the
number in the top right the the paint
speed that we're sustaining so this is
assuming that you've just do you confuse
blink and it's going horribly so when i
unplug projector here this goes at like
167 milliseconds the idea here though is
you can sit there now in devtools we're
going to play some window size
acrobatics here to get that up on the
screen okay so we have another piece of
you know feature addition to dev tools
which is at the H key on the element
panel super super you know the top
secret yeah we live in large so we've
got this H key and what it does is it
hides that element and everybody that
descends from it and if you watch that
number that's being reported we're going
from a big number to a really really
trivial number not 20 and that sort of
makes sense we've still got to set the
page to this lovely puse color right so
but it's it's cheaper so we can go well
clearly this tells us that the thing
that slow painting is inside my body no
boo so this is simple it's just a bunch
of image you know tag so I can do the
same trick with styles so I can hide the
box shadow and now we're really cranking
we're going at what like eight
milliseconds right so now we sorta have
this idea that well maybe 22 of those
milliseconds or watch me do math some
some amount of that is going to the drop
shadow right we can bring it back on and
turn off the border radius and you can
see that well hmm maybe it's that one
right now these don't always compose
sometimes you confuse chrome so like if
I remove both of them we're not really
going incrementally much faster so
what's happening here is you're hitting
a particular corner case in Chrome's
rendering system where the comp is the
composition of these two different
styles is particularly slow don't go
home and say hey this is this this is
one to avoid because we may fix this
tomorrow right we probably won't but we
might and again keep the technique in
mind we found a lot of sites where
there's one effect that's particularly
slow now not to rag on gmail but in
Gmail there's a little drop shadow
between the top bar and the message list
and the little drop shadow that's a like
a half pixel and that costs a third of
the rendering time of the entire page
this is important to factor into your
design discussions right this is a back
and forth that you need to be having
early on so that you don't get a week
away from ship and go oh my god we can't
we can't afford this oh my god we're up
a creek so continuous painting mode
definitely check it out we also have
more fanciness coming in that high-tech
tool some of you may have seen in the
blogsphere about skia debugger and some
magic you can play that will start
showing up in the frame viewer so more
coming that's right so to wrap up again
the main takeaway here is tools you want
to ask yourself a couple key questions
when you're debugging site performance
you want to ask yourself why you're
painting well first you want to notice
that you're painting using show paint
Rex you and then you want to ask
yourself why you want to see if you can
avoid it either through judicious use of
layers or by just trying to not touch
unnecessarily and if you really can't
avoid it then you want to make it as
fast as possible using tools like
continuous painting mode the necklace
and it's especially important because
Chrome's changing a lot so you know be
familiar with what currently is bad
because it'll change again and also keep
in mind that your computer that you're
probably developing on is a really good
one I see a lot of sort of good machines
out there right that is not what MA and
pas have and that is most of the web so
keep that in mind when you get something
going it you know seven or eight
milliseconds on your computer know that
that's two or three or eight times
slower out on the real world or like
also shrink it was or whatever and a
really good number to walk away from is
or walk away with is Wikipedia if you
just do like the cats page on Wikipedia
I think it takes about 150 milliseconds
to paint on a nexus 7 so that is not
Jang free right so you know keep this
stuff in mind exactly so with that I'm
not sure we have time for questions but
this talk and other sort of resources
just a bunch of bunch of links to two
similar content is all up on Jack free
org which is a site we maintain a lot of
that content actually lives on html5
rocks which is the chrome developer
relations website our contact infos up
here if you have thoughts on any of this
we're always happy to talk about it and
we like talking to develop shoulder to
cry on yeah we'll be around tonight too
if anyone has a site that's slow or
whatever we do we can take a look thank
you and thank you very much