so the boys start off can I just like
get a like a show of hands who started
programming when they were young or had
wanted to learn how to program when they
were young I guess that's cool and hands
up who had the experience of like
learning how to program by themselves
and like would break down in tears in
front of a compiler yeah that's it's a
good thing and hands up who can remember
like the most awesome moment of your
life when you're first hello world Ron
yeah so my name is James Walton I'm
Irish and the real Irish not the fake
irish like paul irish tries to pass
office okay i co-founded coderdojo by
trade I'm a web and iOS developer I
enjoy commitment and long walks on the
beach and I also won an award for
appearing in Twilight well one of those
was a lie so um coderdojo is this irish
lad global movement of coding clubs for
young people and it's such a unique and
wonderful thing it's very difficult to
encapsulate in words so starting off i'm
going to show you what coderdojo is this
is coderdojo this is coderdojo this is
coderdojo and finally this is coderdojo
young people come on a regular basis to
the coder dojos that i don't know how to
code hack create apps games or more it's
all free it's all volunteer based and
think of it like the Boy Scouts of
coding what kids who go to coderdojo
have done they've done HTML CSS
JavaScript see some node game
development um computer hardware someone
brought along a whole bunch of boxes and
kids have kids had time trials to see
who could d assemble and reassemble
computers the fastest they do blogging
getting guest speakers from various
companies to talk about the technologies
they use their careers and so on and
they also look at you know arduino who
some guy brought in a 3d printer they
did the entire process of modeling to
actually printing it out and a few other
languages as well so in this environment
in addition to learning about these
things are being introduced and exposed
they make friends they learn problem
solving skills it's an environment where
they feel that they can ask questions we
get advice and direction show off what
they've done gesh and bounce around
collaborate there is talent is exposed
and nurtured it's kind of like a
co-working space to hack around it so
it's completely different to a classroom
and there's an emphasis on open source
free software Good Conduct but most
importantly helping others in the dojo
so at the moment there's a conservative
guess there's about 60 coder dojos in
the space of nine months but this dojo
is constantly opening everything is open
source is a big mentality on it our
framework and so on is up there started
in Ireland in my hometown of cork it's
now spread to the USA to Russia to Asia
and mainland Europe it's 110 percent
free we encourage dojos to have some
spare laptops in the hands to give to
the kids that don't have them it's
probably about two and a half thousand
kids now between the ages of seven and
19 who do this on a weekly basis there's
about 200 volunteers who are really
awesome and they do you know they
volunteer and they mentor in the help
out there's major demand in Dublin alone
there's a waiting list of over 200 and
that's what that dojo taking in 90 a
week the wii user event bite for booking
system and we open up the tickets for
like spaces to be reserved on monday
think about half five and when they open
our record for being booked out is under
one minute so thankfully i can say that
we're more popular than Irish Ireland's
favorite boy band Westlife so all of
this builds up together to be one
kick-ass movement and to aid
so when you have such a movement you
know we try and build tools to you know
make it better and you know bring
everything together so I've built tools
like zen which is an online network of
dojos and people in coderdojo which is
going to build into the online backbone
infrastructure of coderdojo and it's all
open source as well it's up and get up
go for cash and there's also kata which
is the first bit of our kind of
repository of information where people
it's a wiki people submit back resources
session plans and more seeing dojos the
two new topics continually going back
and adding to it so new dojo starting up
can learn and it's a great you know
community process we're consciously
trying to work and prove these tools I
myself I'm the only person full-time
everybody else's is volunteer on it so
we also have some cool stuff we're
introducing like merit badges who
doesn't love hair patches so real merit
badge is to be to be given out I've got
a test shipment of about 500 of them
coming in next week they're also to be
available in Oakland badge format if any
of you are familiar with open Mozilla's
nua initiative for this they're earned
by completing tasks and meeting criteria
and you can get badges in coding in you
know open-source social good building an
app for charity or teaching other kids
how to code and from this spawns belt
rankings so the more badges you
accumulate the higher you go you are
from a white belt to black belt encoding
which means that you can get like a blue
belt teaching a yellow belt how to code
and so on so altogether there's only two
things to say for Jeff there's probably
there's probably gonna be kids watching
this so I can't you just like you know
foul language so what's the whole
premise for coderdojo what's the what's
the story behind it well this is me age
12 this is what I refer to as the
Ladykiller years
um I like to think I've changed since
then physically but back then you know I
was an introvert I was very shy in
myself and growing up you know I sucked
in school academically I wasn't good at
sports and it's a bit bullied like a lot
of kids I was always interested in how
things work though and I started
learning HTML was nine now my parents
were dentist so that they had no idea
what the hell was going on and they were
almost at the point of throwing water at
holy water at me like good old school
irish catholics because i was like
taking apart tvs wiring toasters to
motherboards and so on so one of the
things that really frustrated me as a
kid though was that there was no
introduction to computer science up
until you went to university and even at
that there was a seventy percent drop
out / failure age and you know the
maximum exposure you got was maybe Word
Excel but it wasn't it wasn't good
enough so I wanted somewhere to learn
when did some were to you know make
friends and who were interested in
computers to get direction and advice
you know I had no idea if I wanted to go
into like desktop development or if I
wanted to go into web dev whatever I
wanted you know to get help with
problems i was stuck on a lot of
childhood trauma was caused by c
programming for me I still have
nightmares and and I think most
importantly above all these things I
just wanted to find my thing and fit in
so out of frustration for this education
system in my final year of high school
which was I finished high school in in
June i won an award for web dev and the
school like all proud schools called it
out of the intercom and afterwards I had
a few people from my ear come up and say
oh that's kind of cool well how is
Facebook mater how r iphone apps mate so
um that monday i decided to arrange a
small technology meet up for people
interested in this stuff for my school
on the thursday so it's kind of like
fight club but with keyboards so
essentially what i thought would be
maybe like four or five people from my
year turning up to this turned out to be
you know 40 so you know for the rest of
the year twice a week i taught these
guys my school javascript and CSS and
HTML but i got to the point where people
from all the schools we're hearing about
this i got requests from you know other
schools in the inner city area from
pupils wanting to know could they come
to
our coding club after school so then it
got to you know the final few months
before the summer holidays and a lot of
like the younger members in our club
were worried you know what would they do
the during the summer was it going to be
continued then I met this guy called
bill and there's me on the right there's
spill on the left and then there's a guy
who looks like gosh might sound from the
Looney Tunes so I'll just do that and I
met bill and Bill had been an
experienced and experienced entrepreneur
and he'd you know knew the world knew
had a hustle and so on and we spoke
about a lot about this and the knock-on
effects that it might have our end for
example as a lot of problems at the
moment we've got a fourteen percent
unemployment rate yet we have thousands
of vacancies in the technology industry
and it's crazy you know we've got some
of the world's biggest technology
companies Google Facebook no Twitter and
we you know we're very very attractive
place for technology companies to set up
we we spoke a lot about this and spoke
about like a lot of knock-on effects
honest and Bill figured out you know he
knew someone who could give us a space I
knew a lot of kids who wanted to do it
so we set up what we called coderdojo
and the reason we called it coderdojo
was dojo is a japanese term for place of
learning they've been around for a
thousand plus years you've probably seen
them in karate and there's you know it's
a it's a place where it's very
community-oriented where people in this
dojo help out at each other's plus the
domain name was free which always helps
but we you know so we set up this
coderdojo on what started with like 20
and 30 kids coming on a weekly basis in
the space of about three weeks we had
kids traveling three or four hours to
come to now because of the size of
Ireland that's basically the other side
of the country so we eventually you know
with the pleas of parents we decided to
open up this second coderdojo with the
same brand and the same framework in
dublin and we had our first space was
actually in google in dublin and they're
kind of brood of thumb is that for every
five guests you need one Google employee
so we had a registered list of 25 but we
didn't actively encourage on the site
for people to sign up prior so we had
about 70 turn up to that first session
really freaked out google security so
and this was that what you know this was
purely through word of mouth some
like small treats between people so then
we just you know we saw a major demand
we got more requests from around Ireland
and we continued to set them up and then
you know knock on a few months as Chris
said I met some wonderful people at her
in a castle called funk off and yeah
who's sitting over there and vited me
too j/s con for you to Berlin after my
talk in the castle he said uh what'd he
do next week and I said oh my go to the
cinema with my friends it was like Jonah
come to Germany it's like I can't get
that far in a raft so they they brought
me over and it opened my eyes to see
that there was more people outside you
know our small island of ireland that
were interested in this that there was
more good that we could do outside of
that country and then Cameron mcafee
from github brought coderdojo to America
couple months back now so you can see
here this like a few tweets that you
know we've got dojos now in Ireland who
helped at each other a team traveled
from limerick travels for about an hour
to help another dojo set up we've got a
guy Peter Neubauer who have never met
before just solid sweet there about
coderdojo mom oh and Sweden opening up
next week coderdojo aaron that's a phone
on so i earn more is this Coast off the
is this irish-speaking island off the
coast of Donegal with a population of
400 people we got a request to set up a
coder dojo there now I didn't know this
this island had like running water let
alone electricity and now that they're
asking for mentors with experience with
the corona sdk to help out and then
finally right coderdojo Tokyo is opening
in about four weeks so there's a random
Japanese tweet there about coderdojo
which I've got no idea what that means
I've probably sparked an international
conflict between Ireland and Japan so
it's been just really one awesome
explosion of awesomeness so with this
you know what I mean what have been the
results of coderdojo well there's being
kind of like three main things we've got
this social result where you've got kids
who are in my shoes where they found
their thing they're making friends you
know kids who come in with you know a
little confidence you know they get
respected for what they do they get
praised for hacking things together yeah
I think but two months ago we had our
first coderdojo relationship where a boy
in a 15 or boy and a 15 year old girl
met each other coderdojo
are now going out so it's kind of cool
and then there's you know this economic
side were you know those kids coming
from social welfare backgrounds you're
coming they're learning you know with
the country with 14 on percent
unemployment rate and if you're not
coming from a background that you know
might not necessarily give you an
opportunity to particularly good
education you could open up a lot of
doors and really change not their life
but their family is life and then
there's also the education science
you're filling this massive void in
education and you're helping out a lot
of kids and I mean someone mentioned
earlier on about girls in coding and how
can we encourage this I mean I just saw
this tweet a couple minutes ago an i
threw it in but there's like two 14 or
girls there I one's pretty disappointed
that she's missing missing coderdojo on
the sunday and the other one is
consoling her i don't know i never got
girls so with this you know this being
coding clubs I've tried to open it past
you know one thing or another has kind
of gone downhill or you know what's what
have we done differently that's made of
work out so well well we kind of had
this thing that you know when we decided
that it should be free and it should be
open there should be like no entry
barrier this thing we came up against
was what if parents users baby singing
servers so we made up this rule that if
you're 12 are under you have to bring
your parent with you so this did a
couple of things this meant that only
the really interested kids who drag
their parents out of bed in a Saturday
morning would come but how to knock on
effect that we didn't anticipate when a
parent brings their kid not only do they
like spend time with them they pawned
over code but if a kid is doesn't get
something if they don't understanding
understand something that's done on for
the projector they can be often quite
shy and like not ask questions or not
get it and fall behind most certainly in
my case and matts is very it was a lot
easier for me to say that I didn't do my
homework rather then I couldn't do my
homework however for parents is sitting
with them and they see that their kid
doesn't get something they'll have no
problem asking a question to a volunteer
and then this kind of creates this
environment where a lot of questions are
being asked kids then get more
comfortable asking questions because
their parents are doing it so that's
something cool that we found out loose
session a very non intense very easy
kind of self fled learning
it's not we're not kind of we're not
scheduled Nazis we kind of look at
different elements of HTML look at
different tags and JavaScript look at
different functions and kids will
naturally asked questions and we'll kind
of lead the session themselves when we
started off with you know CSS kids work
and asking well you know actually how
can we like make our background colors
how can we you know set an images or
background how can we know like put this
here so the session kind of leads itself
now and even you know you find new
topics far out of it some dojos have
done like minecraft development
minecraft modding as a result of a
requests obligatory water break so with
this relaxed atmosphere you know we have
one rule and it's be cool and you know
we've done some other stuff like keep
money out of it get kids spring their
own laptop so that they have this
environment that they can hack way when
they go home you know if because of such
like demand in some places dublin for a
fact they like gave homework this week
that any kid who wanted a guaranteed
spot for next weekend had to do what
they learned in that python class and
write a program that would draw the
coder dojo logo and like randomly change
the like black bit some color and then
you know at the very end we we don't
believe that coding should be you know
the learning experience to be just in
coderdojo show resources like mozilla
stocks or site point at very end so that
they can learn when they go home and if
they encounter an issue that they can
ask the next Saturday and get kids
teaching other kids i mean we're all old
i'm 19 now and i'm all time expired it's
um so but what it is is like you know
kids now who are 13 14 16 you know the
context that they're learning and the
environment that they're growing up is
different to us and sometimes maybe we
find that kids you know if a kid gets
something they might be able to you know
converse and you know illustrate it to
another kid rather than we could I mean
we had like a 12 year old show a 14 year
old how to do a wordpress install last
week so it's pretty cool and so what
does it take to start a dojo well it's
pretty easy it's a pretty bootstrap lean
method you just need a space you know
chairs and tables Wi-Fi projector and
some volunteers and mint
and we've got a lot of documents and
resources online to help get you set up
and we've had a lot of advice and a lot
of people in the community who are
willing to help you like hold your hand
through the process so you know who are
some of the kids that have come through
it well this is hiring more on on the
left Harry moved from like rural mayo
and ireland's to my hometown of cork
back in back in September he'd always
wanted to learn how to make games but
you never had an opportunity so when he
came to cut her dojo you know we kind of
showed him how to make games and he you
know worked in a game for a solid month
called pizza boss and I got number one
paid game in the Irish App Store eating
angry birds so not sure what a 12 year
old deals with all that money I think
you bought all like the cute girls in
his class chocolate bars or something um
and then there's this kid Allen who's 9
years old and he's he's got a special
place in my heart because his family
moved from Lithuania to Ireland's 12
years ago and his dad died when he was a
toddler now his mom who had two other
kids had to go on social welfare and she
used to just put out on the computer to
keep him quiet and keep him entertained
but unfortunately a couple of months
back you know his computer broke so she
heard about coderdojo and she brought
him along and hay was free you know
there's no risk keeping entertained for
a few hours and there was free coffee
there for parents so a bunch of all the
kids help fix his computer and now you
know that he got started in JavaScript
and for a nine-year-old he's an awesome
JavaScript developer it helps tutor
other kids so you know there's a whole
bunch of things that all the kids have
done and they're happening on a regular
basis I can't keep track of everything
but you know we've had like a 15 year
old who made a physics engine with
canvas 13 year olds who learned how to
make websites and then started this
thing called crannog which plans trees
and stuff and is a whole movement about
planting trees and organizing these
meetups to do so a nine-year-old meeting
a 32 year old with a IA in this
JavaScript or Java library called Robo
code where you program robots basically
just figured out if you did something
really simple by just like hogging the
slides he'd beat all this I complex
stuff six your neural to me
and 16 year old who made like a tic tac
toe and and an AI for it in like
javascript after like seeing it for
learning JavaScript for a week and like
spending every night on it lots of
pac-man cones at variance in some 10
year old start an IndieGoGo fund to get
a mac to make his first game and you
know all this other stuff and we've had
a couple of kids who've even like open
source their stuff and github pages just
to get their page up and I mean this is
a so this is one of my favorite XKCD
comics and I mean the worst thing the
worst thing I've ever seen in coderdojo
was this kid came up running it was
crying and he ran up to me and I said
what's wrong what's wrong and he said
you know through his tears he pointed to
another kid said he dropped my database
so
so sanitize your inputs and stay in
school so I mean what it comes down to
was what what makes coderdojo well it's
the community really it's the people
involved it's the people who you know
spend time and you know volunteer and
help out or you know go talk to other
dojos and people who speak in rural
parts of Ireland to Twitter starting one
up now and there's some people who've
moved over to san fran and we're going
to attend that one to help add you know
it's people who work in the resources or
people like Chris who take a chance to
invite a crazy Irish guy over to speak
so really it's just an awesome community
led movement and there's you know
there's it like there's a couple of
people I see here who've been involved I
know Jacob who's speaking afterwards
came to her first one in san fran is now
responsible for bringing it into twitter
so what's the future for coderdojo so
it's nine months old and you know we've
got a couple of ideas so first off
improve the infrastructure and resources
there's a lot more that can be done
there and I stopped my other company
about three months ago to do this
full-time try and you know be in the
embodiment of the open web and you know
get open data from our Zen frameworks of
people kids can hack around with a API
and do stuff with the data by Tojo's and
so on build more tools which make it
easier to manage dojos and so on get the
badges sorted organized national
competitions continue to build a
kick-ass networking community grow it
out and help more kids and also the
establishment of the hello world
foundation which will be used to get
people to not only work on coderdojo but
work another coding education projects
and so on and always keep it keep the
mud John mindset iterate and make more
awesome so what kind of final remarks
would be that with coderdojo there are
ton of kids out there who could really
use this and as developers if you want
to help out to make good use of your
time I really urge you to get involved
set up a dojo volunteer and help out
finally be a hero thank you very much