you
so I'm actually giving my talk on my
surface not because I want to increase
the number of Windows users from four to
five in the room or to see if it works
on an incline which it does for now
thankfully is a lip here at the end but
because I think it really represents a
new class of machines that we need to
think about as web developers whoops
hopefully come on okay aha oh I'm going
to restart though here's my demo for
later and the reason that it really
represents a new class of machines is
that the the web and unless you've been
trapped underneath a rock you know that
the web has mobile web has been great
you know increasing really really
rapidly
sorry
okay let's try this again yay okay so as
you know thank you I knew it was a huge
risk using the surface I'm gonna push
out anyway so as you know unless you've
been trapped underneath a rock the usage
of the mobile web is increasing at a
phenomenal rate right that's that
shouldn't be a surprise it to anybody if
you were underneath the rock you know
welcome back other news the Berlin Wall
has fallen but what really compounds
this and the reason that I brought the
surface up is that it's not only it's
not only mobile devices that are getting
touched but also desktop devices and
assert their surface is emblematic of
that what that really means is that in
as we think about our websites is that
touch is really going forward going to
be the predominant way that people use
the web I'm going to pick on so some of
the research we've done is part of the
surface is there's you know obviously
patterns that don't work with the web or
with the touchable web and one of them
I'm gonna pick on is the hover obviously
hover does not work with touch a web
there's no state when you're using your
finger where you're not you know you're
not your kind of over a bit but not on
it and i'm going to pick on that but
there's number of other UI techniques
like that and our research we found that
over sixty-five percent of websites
we're using some mechanism like this
that made it very difficult views at a
very high level you I technique to use a
touchable web so I ask is that if you're
one of those 65 I have a look at your
website and make sure you're not you're
not breaking the touchable web the
second thing I want to think it wanted
you to think about is that the touchable
web means that you need to think about
the size of your touch targets and as
part of doing the surface we did a lot
of research around what's the optimal
size of touch targets and we did that we
measured people's fingers we found that
the kids when they first are able to use
a touch with where they've roughly eight
millimeter fingers up to the largest may
our adult has you know roughly a 19 in
millimeter finger
with kind of a 11 millimeter average and
we use that to do research on what the
smallest target size or kind of the
optimal target size you should use and
so we ran a bunch of experiments
changing the size of the touch target
over a range of different values and
what we found is that as you went below
five millimeters asymptotically the
error rate at which they you know the
error rate they had trying to complete
that task went up asymptotically and
it's compounded by the fact that they
spent asymptotically more time trying to
select that that particular touch target
so what our research showed was that
somewhere between seven and nine
millimeters for a touch target is kind
of the kind of the sweet spot and an on
screen that works out to something like
forty to fifty pixels eighty-five
percent of sites that we looked at had
some some page that violated into this
this rule and made it hard for touch
users to you so if you're one of you
know if you're building a navigation
that you want used on and devices with
touch I encourage you to look to make
sure that you're not one is eighty-five
percent another thing we did is we
looked at kind of a heat map of where is
easy for people to to to reach on their
on their mobile device and this is an
example we use for the surface the green
area show the areas that are very easy
to reach for the 90 percentile of users
the red areas are the people with the
biggest hands and then kind of the 10th
percentile and what's obvious from this
is that the middle right and left are
the easiest places for people to to to
hit touch targets they have the most
accuracy they're the most you know
ergonomically correct and so as you're
thinking about this and what we do at
Microsoft is as we guidance we give our
designers is essentially that that the
the band that runs kind of in a you from
the left and the right middle down
through the bottom and back up are the
best places to have your interaction
area and on the phone probably makes a
lot of intuitive sense kind of in the
middle of the screen are the best places
to have your touch targets it's kind of
the opposite for where you want
people to be able to read so in terms of
reading areas the places where the hands
are not obscuring the screen you know
work out to be the best places to have
to have touch targets that's probably
not not very surprising didn't Evo's in
this room the other thing I wanted to
mention is good okay is that people come
from native applications to them to the
you know the touchable what a lot of
expectations so they they expect to be
able to use multi multi point gestures
in order to control the web and a lot of
browsers have implemented that natively
to kind of keep up with that expectation
but obviously building an application
like this within the browser is is
something that's been beyond us and so
as Angelina said we've been working with
the w3c and it's not just us it's it's
Mozilla we jointly proposed this with
Mozilla and a lot of thanks to them to
bring a unified model for these these
pointer devices that are beyond the
mouse we've been using you know
essentially a mouse event model for the
last 15 odd years it really assumes that
there's only there's only a mouse
attached to the computer we need we need
to improve on that and it's moved from a
first public working draft or candidate
recommendation in roughly five months
which we think you know demonstrators
there's a lot of lot of momentum and
recognition that this is a real a real
problem and so I'm going to spend the
rest of the kind of presentation working
through what that means and essentially
the top level in a way to think about
this is it's an evolution of mouse
events to be more general uses the same
event model more or less you can drop in
pointer events for Mouse events and your
applications should still work the same
we have added one event a pointer cancel
event which is primarily used for when
there's an orientation change in it it
makes sense to not process the maybe
some some previous touch events that
have occurred but otherwise it's very
similar what has changed is we've added
number of attributes to provide a richer
model for handling handling pointer
events but your existing button client
ex-client why those attributes remain
the same have the same semantics are
still available to you as web developers
and so working through them one by one
width and height provides you with the
ability to have the you know or the
recognition that in the real world many
pointing devices have a real physical
size and kind of the canonical example
of that is your finger your finger can
have a small amount of contact area if
you're using your fingernail and
obviously a larger one if you're pushing
down very hard and so this is passed
through in terms in a bounding box
around the client AXA client why that
gives you some indication of how much of
the the pointing utter devices in is
intersecting with the screen and this
obviously see this later is it is a good
way of doing things like finger painting
applications where you want to have that
richness of of taking advantage of that
intersection with the screen there's
also the concept of pressure for screens
that support it and tilt accident tilt
why pressure is what you'd expect if the
digitizer surface or screen supports it
it gives you an indication of how much
pressure is being applied to the screen
tilt tilt accent tilt why are you know
probably the canonical example there is
a pen where you might want to have a
different effect on the screen depending
on the tilt you know prove it but
perhaps apply a sonography kind of
different line style or what not to
match up with the users expectation
these to provide you know the ability to
understand more to handle separates so I
point of type it gives you the ability
to handle pointer devices differently in
general you're going to want to handle
them the same but pointer type allows
you to handle you know for instance a
pen device differently from a mouse
device in you know situations where
that's important
and then pointer ID is kind of a new
concept because there can be multiple
streams of pointer events if you think
about if you have two or three fingers
on the screen at once those are actually
all separate pointer devices in terms of
in terms of this event model and so
pointer ID allows you to disambiguate
all those different events dreams so
that you can handle them in the way that
makes the most sense for your
application all right so I'm going to
switch over and do a demo all right
great and so the devil i'm going to do
is really simple finger painting
application not sure how visible that is
it's fairly visible and basically have a
canvas I've added some pointer events
here as additive as event listeners I'm
using in navigators pointer enabled
which tells you if this if player
pointer events are possible in your
browser there's two types of that in
ie10 we actually have the vendor
prefixed version and then as as browsers
adopt this there'll be a non prefixed
version called pointer enabled and then
from there every time we get an event we
start painting I'm going to maintain a
list of essentially four points and then
as we get individual pain events I am
going to just do a curve between all
those those points that we've built up
and and finally as we're doing multiple
of these will shift them off the end and
Athen do went to it so it's pretty
straightforward I'll show you what that
looks like I just thought of a problem
okay so when you know the mouse this
work this works perfectly fortunate I
didn't die didn't think about this
problem but when you touch it it also
has this problem I have is that because
I'm displaying on the screen I can't
touch this screen but imagine that was a
touch let's see okay so the problem you
have there is that we're not using so if
you look back at this code we're not
using we're not using the point
our ID to actually to actually
disambiguate the different streams so if
I had to use multi-touch there it would
it would have done back and forth across
the to the different streams of events
that we're we're being received by the
browser and so to disambiguate that and
this in this example I'm using a pointer
ID to eventually to basically build up
separate sets of content and so when we
draw the lines will be a separate lists
and it in it in it and it'll display as
you'd expect so doing two at the same
time you know essentially it uses a
separate separate streams a list to
display it the final thing you notice
there is i'm not using any concept of
the width to display or sorry the width
and the height that's passed through as
part of the pointer event to display a
different width and height to the line
and we can do that with event dot with
an event height and essentially use that
to drive the width that we're using for
the the line that's displayed and and
and if we do that that's hard to do with
my finger we get slightly bigger wets
and why it works better if it's on the
actual screen but what you'll see is
it'll it'll depend on if you're using
your you're with a higher quality
digitizer you'll see that if that
increases and decreases you by two with
your your finger so that's that's a
brief example of how you use it natively
just want to talk a little bit how you
get started so i eat n has vendor prefix
support for this this is in without
vendor prefixes in I 11-hour open tech
teams open tech inside Microsoft as a
team of folks that contribute to open
source projects and they've done a
WebKit prototype of this it's available
here I believe they've also have
announced an intent to implement for the
blink project as well
as a formal implementation but if you
really want to get started today there's
a couple of polyfills that are available
hand j s was developed by a person at
microsoft and then there's also points j
s which is developed by richard harris
so that's kind of a quick overview of
pointer events i am around the rest of
the day if you have any more questions
but thank you
I already see a question in the audience
so let's kick this off here hey um to
kind of stress what Dominic Nicola told
about told us about forcing vendors to
expose richer functionality pointer
events are great in the sense of
obstructing my mouse and touch events
uh-huh what about gestures is there
anything sure there is there's not
anything I really encourage people look
to that spac there's not anything in
this specification about gestures
themselves it's just as this event model
but it does make a ton of sense to start
building on top of that for which is I
think most gestures are becoming kind of
popular exactly so yeah I makes total
sense yeah thanks yeah other questions
okay went over there
one question about interpreted movements
of like where you have a free assumption
of what the user wants to achieve like a
scroll which is essentially a touch on
mobile devices yep is anything in this
back there that makes that easier if you
want to do like headers that like
retract or something no there's nothing
in the spec about that this is purely
for the the content region of the of the
web page yeah okay I think that's it I
don't see any more hands oh wait one
more hold on really quick okay so that
uh I'm interested the five millimeter 50
pixel thing yeah but reporting is out
that's great I've always wondered what
the sweet spot is but does that imply
anything about text size for like links
you know intertextual links with that
that research mostly did mostly looked
at the size in terms of simply clicking
it if you hit me on twitter that's my
twitter address i will i'll find out if
we did research around the text size
yeah thanks awesome thank you very much
Tim yeah thanks for having me speaker
connectors