he said although my name tag actually
just says math on it so I'll respond
equally to math or Angelina and I work
for a place called Mozilla and this is
me on Twitter for all of you time
travelers in the audience because right
now I'm going to pretend it's mostly the
year 2000 i'm trying to think right now
what Angelina was doing in the year 2000
I would have been about 15 which
probably means that at that point I've
been building websites and programming
but things look random stuff and playing
video games for maybe about five or six
years my first website was on Angel Fire
it was all about my favorite animal the
dolphin I pronounce it no I'm not I'm
not even joking i wish that i wish i
wish i had an archive of that somewhere
the ones that came after that were on
geo cities and they catalogued my really
sweet video game music midi collection
and yeah so 15 I was probably like
hacking on websites my mom's basement
and like stealing her liquor not much
has really changed i just don't live in
my mom's basement anymore and i canna
for my own liquor so that's good but
yeah that's me on twitter if you like
occasional complaining sometimes tweets
about code and a lot of cuddly animals
and like i said i work at mozilla so you
may have heard of our web browser
firefox which at the year 2000 has world
we had like something like maybe seven
to ten percent depending on what browser
share you know statistics that you
looked at and so i know that even though
I'm from Mozilla and most of you are
probably internet explorer developers in
the room given that eighty six to ninety
percent of you are using Internet
Explorer don't worry the information I'm
going to share with you today about SEO
is applicable to anybody using any kind
of browser so first of all what is SEO I
mean Jen spoiled it a little bit i'll
tell you what how i like to personally
define it as search engine optimization
okay so well what does that mean based
on this really awesome chart that i
found on the internet i can tell you
that jen is absolutely correct clearly
somebody who knows photoshop and knows
how to render things in 3d and therefore
a smarter than all of us in the room
this fabulous graph which what I saw it
is like holy I have to do my talk
on SEO for DML comp because it is more
important than idea it is more important
than code and it is more important the
design so there are three parts to sort
of three key skill areas that you want
to have to get into search engine
optimization which are you technical and
I think since I'm talking to a group of
advanced webmasters here that largely
you guys are going to be okay you need
to have technical skill so you need to
know about your HTML tags you need to
know about your D HTML tags you need to
know about like some CSS that new thing
i don't i don't know if it's going to
catch on but we'll see and you you know
then you take those technical skills and
you look at your on-page optimization
which is largely what we're going to
talk about here today and you're off
page optimization which is a lot of
handshaking and buying links so the
first thing you want to do I mean like
like what this really gets you is I mean
the first thing you do is you optimize
your site for search engines and then
after that that gets you more traffic
that's your end goal here with your
search engine optimization step 3 it
doesn't really matter and step for you
make money and I learned all this from
this really great book make money online
now the simple strategy that made me an
internet millionaire I'm actually a
dogecoin dogecoin doji lien era so that
counts as far as I'm concerned for being
an internet millionaire and then I found
this graphic which was this is just
amazing let's just take this in here so
first I like that you start if it so
where do you start right like do I start
on that side okay i'm going to pretend i
start with website won't rank because
like I just don't actually have one
right now if you go to my website
reality hacking net is just an engine X
page and it's somebody tweets me about
it every day I'm just being lazy so my
website won't rank scream rant shout
shake fist that was before I got here so
we're good by links um hey you we talk
later website still won't rank scream
shout shake fist anyway so hopefully I'm
going to teach you some things here that
will keep this cycle a lot shorter so
one of the things you might be asking
yourself is maybe you've heard that
there are companies people out there
that are SEO professionals and you might
be asking yourself if you want to hire
one of those SEO professionals after
after you know being an SEO professional
myself for basically 80 years I happen
to know everything about SEO and
tell you that if you are an advanced
webmaster and you know how to do some of
the tricks in this presentation you will
be totally totally fun in fact if you
know how most of you are probably
writing your web pages in front page
some of you might be using Dreamweaver
Dreamweavers pretty hot right now I used
to all its 2,000 so i use dreamweaver
Dreamweavers pretty great don't use it
for WYSIWYG but actually the terms of
like syntax highlighting is that as a
code editor it was ahead of its time in
my opinion so this is my advice to you
and how you can get your website to rank
well so the first thing you want to do
is of course you need to be submitting
your search engine or submitting your
site to search engines and directories
and this is 2000 so actually it takes
Google about four to six weeks to
process your submission and rank your
site on on their search engine or at
least that's what a bunch of sites will
tell you so you want to be submitting
your site often and regularly and early
you probably should have done it four to
six weeks ago now this is a quote from a
web page and I love this it says a true
search engine optimization specialist
knows the difference between a search
engine in a directory and now that so
that's right so by extension if you know
that and you're in the room right now
you are a true search engine
optimization specialist and I bet you
didn't even know it Thanks clicks calm
and that's clicks with a Z by the way
this is a blank slide and I actually
really don't know what was supposed to
be here so I'm going to then mention
that some search engines happened to be
Yahoo altavista like coast which as I
mentioned earlier if you go to lycos com
it still exists as a search engine which
kind of blew my mind ask jeeves which
when I was like 13 or 14 I just freaking
loved ask jeeves because I like to
picture this tiny little robot person
that was like they're in behind a
computer and answering it for me and
then my brother suggested me one day be
like what if there actually is a Jeeves
Angelina like what if there's just this
guy and he's sitting there all he does
is search for people and I was like holy
actually that's pretty heavy and
then msn kind of ended up being a player
in the game and as for directories I
don't think actually created a slide for
that but there was like oh there's open
directory and there was like yahoo had a
directory and that's like the only two
that ever really come up oh yeah google
i guess they're pretty important hey who
knows what's going to happen with them
okay so this is another favorite of mine
this chart this chart someone made to
represent sort of like the search engine
share at the time you've got see you
actually
Google taking up a big chunk here Yahoo
MSN and ask and my favorite thing about
this was the way the shark was described
with an asterisk underneath it
disclaimer the pie chart image is not an
exact representation of market share for
any company mentioned but simply a
visual presentation for educational
purposes translation this doesn't
mean anything this is
but I just really wanted a chart to make
my content flushed out and I just I love
that because it's honest without being
honest at all so really I mean so like
the shortcut here you know the short
answer to what you want to do for SEO is
you need to focus on key words no matter
what you do with your website you want
to make sure that you have particular
sets of words usually you know two two
for two two for fries you know two to
four words and lengths that will use
search engines will index and find them
and then you'll rank for those
particular search terms so it depends if
you have like an alpaca farm or if
you're doing like website design and
development or if you're selling some
sort of widget and you might ask how do
you know what sort of keywords to target
well the first thing you want to do is
probably copy your competitors just go
take a look at their websites go look at
their source and take a look at what it
is they're trying to sell if you're
competing with them use the same
keywords but maybe put them in your site
more often and as I mentioned two to
four words and length is about the
optimal length that these search engines
are looking for another thing you want
to do is probably have a good domain
name it should also have keywords in it
important thing is that search engines
will actually rank sites hosted on your
own domain a lot higher than if you're a
subdomain or if you're on a free site
place like Angel Fire geocities you want
to get off that and afford your own
domain so here's an example of a domain
rights okay this one's pretty good
there's a new millennium web design com
maybe your keyword is web design so
you're going to rank okay with that but
you can still do a little bit better
right like you might as well since
there's no limit on how long a domain
name can be just like stuff it in there
but I mean don't stop right like I think
enthusiasm is important so so I think
that bottom one is going to be pretty
good i've got oakland in there right
because you want to get some local
ranking as well this is about the time
that google locals started to be a thing
so then the next most important thing is
i feel like i'm kind of going like
outward into the website here we want to
start looking at the mark-up we look at
the title tag I mean the title tag is
sort of the way that the search engine
knows like semantically like what the
topic of your site is so your title tags
pretty important so you can kind of see
where I'm go
with this just you know just just just
just be creative with it and you'll
you'll be okay and then also the same
thing applies to your URL structure so
you might start with here just alpaca
farm by best alpacas you the best is
important because you don't want people
to miss you know miss miss miss guess
and think that you're selling the worst
alpacas that happens to me all the time
and you can again see where I'm going
with this now this one this one is
really important meta tags and some of
you might not know but meta tag is
actually the origin of the slang that's
so meta that came out in like the early
2000 so when someone is actually saying
you know that's so meta they're actually
referring to meta tags but what people
actually don't know about meta tags is
that meta tag is actually short for
metaphysical tags because they describe
like ghosts and stuff like that they
also describe the description and the
keywords for your website and they're
really really the most important thing
for ranking on search engines or but
maybe not this is another quote from an
SEO website circa 2000 with the wrong
meta tag you can make it to the bottom
but meta tags alone do not take you to
the top everywhere now if anybody can
tell me what that means please find me
afterwards because to me it means
nothing but that's like some real advice
out there for your for SEO so I mean
there's the description tag and you can
just you can put a you know obviously a
description of what content is there and
then you've also got the keywords tag
which you can put some keywords and it's
pretty simple and at this point I'm
going to ask Jen to passing my phone
over there for this next bit because I
need to do a dramatic reading for you
and so there's there's a bunch of
different meta tags that allow you to
specify information about ghosts and
your website and there's one in
particular called the meta refresh tag
that you can actually use to well
refresh and redirect your site which
nobody really use anymore because that's
dumb and before I'm we wanted that
actually I wanted to mention that this
is actually what you should be going for
with your keyword you can see their
imaginary restaurant website is the best
imaginary restaurant website our
restaurant is better than any restaurant
and I'm pretty sure that the search
robots will will love that you can also
stuff the the no script tag this was
some advice on a site that talked about
different colored hats they're really
into like golf hats black hats in
particular I don't really know what's up
with that but they did mention that you
can stuff keywords in the no script tag
and also in like HTML comments which i'm
pretty sure search engines ignore but i
like give them points for creativity
excuse me um so yeah so back to the meta
meta refresh tag i found this really
fantastic advice and i want to share it
with you another more creative use of
the refresh tag is a fancy intro to a
site say you wanted the page to write
welcome and then after one second get
ready and after one more second it
should say for a special experience and
finally after a few seconds the real
page would be loaded because that's
right in two thousand people still had
intro landing pages to their website
probably with flash intros and that was
a thing Wow okay so yeah this slide
actually this one's not not not not a
not a up on my part this is
actually legit slide it didn't forget to
put something here because there were
places that you can put keywords that
people don't even have to see so that's
right and you should so holy cow what's
going on here white text on a white
background ladies and gentlemen all
right also try display none by just like
you know on on some elements somewhere i
display none work in two thousand
actually didn't check that anyway
doesn't matter and text indent minus you
know a bazillion percent so that the
text can be seen by the search engine
but not by you and I don't know I feel
really bad for people with screen
readers around this time of SEO
advancement really so one thing I want
to mention is don't use frames not only
is it super 1990s but it makes it very
difficult for websites to index your
search engine or wait a minute and flash
well I mean you could probably use flash
but just keyword stuff around you now
know how to put stuff in there and have
it be totally invisible basically right
so that's pretty good java applets I
don't know why you'd still be using
those but I mean that's pretty fun games
out there but again you can you know the
drill you can just sort of keyword stuff
around it so now I mean that's a little
bit stuff to do with your markup like I
actually spent a whole lot of time going
through the Google search results
between 1999 and 2002 i padded a little
brown 2000 so I could get creative
looking at old websites on an advice and
I'm actually convinced that in order to
be an SEO marketing expert in year two
thousand you basically just had to like
you know how to write same HTML so why
didn't I cash in geez I'm
you basically now are all SEO experts
and that's all you need to know about
the topic when it comes to like on
on-page optimization someone talk to me
about like quality of content and stuff
but I don't know about that so show a
link building is the process of getting
people to link to your page so that's
when Google sees your page link to a lot
or altavista yahoo or the other you know
super relevant search engines they you
know it will know that like Oh a lot of
people are linking to this resource that
must be really reputable okay sure
that's great web rings obviously are a
way to do that although I think as of
two thousand web rings are sort of sadly
going out of vogue you also asked to
trade links with other websites you can
just email them be like hey it doesn't
matter if there were later not just
write a really convincing email me like
hey I know that your website is about
all pack of farming but I have this
great web design thing do you want to
trade links because i'm pretty sure that
an inbound link from alpaca farms to
your web development firm is going to
give you the google juice right there
again you could buy links that's super
legit and definitely whenever you post
somewhere I'd comment or review make
sure you put your website because even
though you're posting on a band review
website people definitely need to know
about your alpaca farm right like you
just never know someone could be both
like a good charlotte's enthusiast and
also like be an alpaca breeder right
like people are not just one-dimensional
you know like there's depth there so you
just got to give them the benefit of the
doubt you should just put yourself out
there so in conclusion SEO is really
hilarious nonsense I mean I think for
real talk right like in real life and
2014 I was actually looking like okay so
now that I've done this really great
blast from the past thing where I look
at all SEO from 2000 I Forbes magazine
publishes SEO articles for 2014 talking
about SEO strategy so it's still people
think it's a legit thing I would argue
its auxiliary to good content strategy
and the rest of your marketing but this
has been a lot of fun so in conclusion I
hope that this will help get you from
the left side of the graph to the right
side with a smiley face that's what I'm
looking for always smiley faces and
that's it thanks