oh right well hello everybody thank you
guys for coming out for Cascadia hope
lunch was good and it was settled in for
this talk he said my name is tre AMA
tuna and through my journey of growth of
my life I've been everything from a
waiter to a restaurant manager a
breakdancer DJ audio engineer and for
the last two and a half years I've made
this wonderful transition into software
engineering thankful from my hack
reactor crowd to really bring me into
this I'm also a partner to an amazing
woman and three boys at my house with a
little girl in the way finally and I
have this mindset that I constantly
strive to be technically creative in a
creatively technical way so I'm here to
talk to you as was said about something
that I really believe in and something
that we really do a lot of where I work
which is although right here in downtown
Seattle we are an online marketplace for
legal services and advice and through
this and my entire journey of life I've
really gotten into this factor of to
build a culture of growth is to build a
culture of engagement and truly when you
have that it's key to individual and
company success so from the moment we're
born our minds and our bodies really
strive for one thing it's to grow now
we're gonna go through why this is
important and also go into some things
that you can start at your own company
to really foster this culture of growth
and engagement but at first I want you
to remember when you were young and you
really couldn't wait to grow up right
but when we're getting a little bit
older we're like wait wait wait what the
hell were we really thinking about this
like it's fun to be a kid I look at my
three boys and I really want to look at
him it's like well it's really fun up
here
really it's a trap hold on but when
we're young we have those that we admire
and what we really want to do is we want
to grow up to be like those people I
really want to shout out real quick on
all the firefighters that are down in
California right now taking care of
those fires and hopefully a lot more
young
grow up to be like them but throughout
this entire journey we take bits and
pieces of everything that we learn and
we try to put them together in this
puzzle of who we are throughout every
single interaction that we have we take
that and blend it in with our innate
personality and they essentially become
part of our puzzle of life and it comes
to this concept of growth is an
iterative process we're always growing
and we never really stop through all of
this there's one thing that influences
us more than anything else in our lives
and it's the relationships we have with
those around us our families our friends
our teachers professors and the people
that we work with and we learned so much
from all of these interactions that we
really would never be able to learn if
we're on our own
and this is the essence of a concept
called cultural learning what cultural
learning is it describes a way that a
group of people within a culture can
pass on information and skills
much faster than one would be able to do
individually with this though it begs
the question kind of what is a culture
my personal favorite description or
definition of culture comes from the
cambers dictionary where they say
culture is the way of life especially
the general customs and beliefs of a
particular group of people at a
particular time I really love this one
because it also puts in that factor of a
particular time it kind of describes the
fact that not only are we growing
ourselves but the cultures that we are
part of are growing the entire time as
well
so what culture is really formed
whenever any group of people get
together so we're part of many cultures
at any time in our life we have family
cultures business cultures cultures
around art hobbies sports and
entertainment facilities right in fact
every single person here in this
audience right now is part of a culture
of Cascadia j/s and I want to thank you
right now for being a part of this
culture together with myself and so we
can learn and grow to get
last year indeed released their best
places to work list they do every year
and the number three company on that
list last year was JetBlue when
interviewed Rachel McCarthy's SVP of
talent described their culture as the
DNA of the company and this is really
true because in today's business
cultures it's more than ever important
to cultivate these concepts of culture
of growth and engagement because by
doing this you can pull in that factor
of engagement and of course when I'm
talking about engagement I don't mean
this kind of engagement
I mean employee engagement with their
work right well last year a Gallup
released their state of American
workplace report where they released
that 31 percent of American employees
are actually engaged in their work 52
percent are not engaged and 17 are
literally disengaged from their work
this can be really alarming in some ways
and they also talked in here about this
is costing American businesses five
hundred and fifty thousand are a billion
dollars a year now let's see what
happens in this same report when an
employee reports that they actually
actively learned something the previous
day they engaged and not engaged
categories nearly flip where you have
65% now engaged and only 30% not engaged
and even that actively disengaged comes
down a little bit of a step so maybe you
can look at this factor of constantly
learning as maybe putting a ring on
those employees because of the factor
that now they're less likely to leave in
fact they might be running around saying
I am engaged and I'm happy with where I
am and ultimately this leads to one of
my favorite quotes which is when you do
what you love you'll never work a day in
your life but how do we build this
culture around engagement and what is it
that developers really want when they're
looking for a job well there's plenty of
surveys out there for this by show how
many people have actually filled out one
of these seeing excellent thank you all
all of you because hopefully you're
gonna help me in this next few things
right here the first one we're gonna
look at is -
eighteens stackoverflow were a hundred
thousand developers reported on this and
if you look at this we have compensation
and benefits coming up as a very top and
then number three is opportunities for
professional development number six is
the culture but really when you think
about this and what we're talking about
and building a culture around learning
and development this is going to
skyrocket to the top and be the number
one thing that developers are really
looking for so let's continue looking at
this we have hacker ranks 2018 report
here professional growth in learning
took number two and then once again
company culture is down here at number
six but then when we build this this one
really probably skyrockets to the top
and I want to look at number four and
five here - that's smart people to learn
from and interesting problems to solve
we'll kind of revisit that again in a
minute but when you ask people that are
coming fresh into our industry that our
students it actually flips over and now
we have growth and learning here at the
top and all of these kind of come up so
now interesting problems comes up to
three smart problem company and
teammates comes up before and company
culture comes up to five so once again
this is very important to the people
they're looking for jobs same thing
happens with coding game learning new
things now new things now comes up to
the top by a larger margin smart
colleagues complex problem solving and
flex and then culture comes down in here
as well so people really want to learn
things to keep them engaged in this and
so the final step of this is something
that I said on the smart people team and
colleagues so the old saying and
surround people yourself with people who
are smarter than you it's one of the
classic sayings right and it makes sense
by everything that we said from the
beginning the biggest influences in our
life are the relationships with the
people around us so of course we'd want
the have the smartest people around this
in our team because then we can
hopefully become smart by proxy there
and every organization once they're the
best people on their team but which
states have the best developers they
actually did a survey on this as well
and I have to
that here in Washington we're number one
so yeah we've got the best developers in
the nation but of course every company
can't specifically have the best
developers on each team and their comes
in this thing that companies kind of are
a little bit scared of investing in
junior developers and trying to really
bring them up and they want senior
developers they want the best people on
there but I think this is one of the
craziest reasons not to in hire junior
developers and help invest in them every
developer has heard the words leave the
code better than when you found it well
what about leaving the developers better
than when you hired them right
another thing happens whenever you build
this culture of learning in engagement
that you have these systems in place so
if somebody does leave and you have to
hire somebody on you now have a system
in place to teach them and to bring them
up to speed to where you need to where
they can really contribute to your
company as one of the only little things
that you that comes out you see the talk
of a CFO saying what happens if we train
them and they leave us and the smart CEO
really comes back and says what happens
if we don't and they stay so there was
another report by a company old great
place to work
they did a generations report where they
assessed the benefits of a great
workplace across generations where they
found the employees who experienced a
great workplace are far more likely to
want to remain at the organization a
long time this of course saves companies
on recruiting and training and really
Foster's the performance of stable teams
an interesting thing that they found is
that throughout the generations really
it's really similar
Millennials Generation X and baby
boomers are in the 90 percentile when
they're happy that's when the in the red
is a happy person versus the gray is
kind of somebody's not happy in their in
their job when we really look at this
we're like okay wait a second also
Millennials are now twenty five times as
likely to stay at their job when they're
happy versus when they're not when baby
boomers really will stay whether even
they're not happy and only seven times
more likely I mean who says Millennials
are really flaky
flighty right this really proves that
that's not it's quite the case we just
need to keep these people happy and they
want to stay the next one we can see how
proud they are to tell others about
their job so that's another thing it
comes up when somebody is happy and
engaged with their workplace they want
to talk to other people about that
workplace they want to kind of display
to the world that I work in an amazing
place look at the wonderful things that
they allow me to do and learn and so
what happens with that for the company
when you are hiring somebody else now
you have a plethora of people that are
already kind of know about your culture
and they want to be there and they're
one that come work for you finally what
this will talk about productivity there
one last thing on here which is the fact
that when you have happy people they're
much more productive on the job so three
to four times as productive on the job
when they are happy versus when they are
unhappy that's money right there for any
business that has these people that
means that literally you could pretty
much take a day off of work every single
week and be just as productive by the
four-day workweek than a five day just
by having happy people so what can we do
to build this culture of growth at all
though we have a lot of wonderful things
that we do and I'm going to go through
these and give a little description and
maybe a little few tips that I have one
of these as well the first off is kind
of the easiest to do lunch and learns or
brown bag sessions so this is a simple
factor of getting together with a group
of people over lunch people bring their
lunch into a meeting room and one or
multiple people can talk about something
that they know and then it's really just
there to help disperse information or
teach something or get people kind of
enticed on on something kind of like
these talks here the next is lightning
talks once again we see this a lot in
conferences 5 to 15 minute long talks
and the really nice thing here is they
can be done really in succession so
maybe during a lunch and learn you can
have four or five different people do
smaller talks there another one that I
really enjoy working with is third-party
workshops so how many people actually
heard about the graph QL workshops or
ones are the react workshop or any other
workshops that we have
here excellent I know I saw a lot of
people at the graph QL workshop they're
here tonight as well and I thank you
guys for coming out here because that
was actually a product of my own work
using these techniques a third-party
workshop can be done in a couple ways
they can be done privately for companies
which can be quite expensive for the
companies or they can be done in a more
open way and that's how I really
presented these with it like what the
ones were like the graph QL workshop so
I contacted even Alex who put that
workshop on and said hey my company is
working with graph QL I would love for
you guys to come out and help train my
devs on this I have a room I'll pay for
lunch all I and allow you to sell
tickets outside the company as well and
bring the public into this all we ask is
for some tickets for our own devs to the
workshop and as compensation for that
and of course since they're actually
from Tahoe or Lake Tahoe in California
and not from this area I put out my own
network to get them connected with
places like Cascadia J s so that they
could sell more tickets and they could
make money for themselves so I'm really
passionate about these ones and it's a
very nice thing you can do and bring it
in and also be become part of the
community as well
another thing is learning stiffens so
every manager really should have a
learning budget for their developers and
we're not talking about really just like
tossing money at developers so it's like
hey hey hey I want to learn this I want
to learn that but they can really spend
these types of things on such like
online tutorials for you my favorite
ones being things like front-end masters
or egghead IO Kent Dodds new testing
course or the wonderful West boss
courses that are out there but this is
just a way that we can help people grow
in their own time as well now another
one is reference libraries so books I
don't know about you but I love books
I love reading them I love going the
library picking out new books and having
a nice reference library at work is
great because you can have all the
online resources possible but really it
that's physical nature of the book and
allowing you to really look
it's a different experience and you can
really find some things in there that
you won't be able to find as quickly
online another big one is mentorship
programs so this is something that
really is kind of free but it really
just takes a lot of work you have to of
course find people that want to be
mentors find people that want to be
mentees figure out how to mesh these
people together but really this is a
program that can touch people's lives
almost in a way that none of these other
types can mentor mentee relationships
can be lifelong relationships and by
working on a program like this at your
organization you can truly be touching
people's lives for the rest of their
life by this one moment and it really
also has that same impact on not just
the mentee but the mentors as well
another great one that we're all a part
of right now conferences right there a
great thing we can get together we can
learn so I mean how many people got
their conference tickets from their jobs
having a yes that's nearly half the
audience here it's a great thing in a
phenomenal way for us to keep up with
our industry network and really see
what's going on protip on this one try
to get a group of people together to go
on to conferences I mean when you have a
group of your own organization going you
can really gather yourself together you
can learn from each other it becomes not
only an experience of the conference
itself but also a team-building event
the next one is a really big one and can
kind of be a little bit harder for a
cell for a lot of companies it's called
20 percent time we have this a Tavo it
started off at Google and this is really
the concept of one day a week an
individual contributor can basically
work on whatever they want to they can
learn something new they can build a
little project that they've been
thinking about as long as it kind of
relates to the work that they do and
their job in fact when Google started
enacting this they had a few things come
out of here and you may have heard of
them adsense Google Maps and the real
big elephant in the room that was the
start of all this Gmail some of the
biggest apps in the entire world came
out of this thought of 20% time and
although we have a really sleek shipping
method and a way of getting testing
environments ec2 testing environments we
have a we go to an app that we have
simply called ship it and we make a few
clicks to the button and we have an
entire ec2 instance provisioned
terraformed and ready to go with our our
company's entire app stack on it I hit
what branches I want there's
automatically deploy and now I have my
testing environment and then if I want
to ship to production a couple more
buttons my branch is shipped to
production and it's all done as you can
guess that this came out of a 20% time
project and it saves countless hours of
our developer time on shipping so these
are really a way that companies may not
look at that factor of like what are we
really getting back to this but you can
come up some really cool things when you
just let your developers flourish have
fun and work on things that they want to
the last one I'll talk about is deep
dive days so this is a fun one that I'm
working on right now and essentially
these are full days that a group of
people will take their 20% time go into
a room together and learn something and
dig into it a lot more than they really
could on say a Lunch and Learn or a
little bit individually and as I said
this is kind of a group thing which also
allows you to interact with each other
work together ask questions and they can
be led by a person on the team or you
can do things like go through online
courses things like egghead or front-end
masters which really have these longer
courses that individuals can go through
but when you go through them as a group
you get that multiplying effect of that
cultural learning once again and so I
really also want to stress on the factor
that remember you're not just a consumer
of the information whenever you're doing
these things it's really also in your
best interest to be an instructor as
Aristotle told the world teaching is the
highest form of understanding
and it really is it helps you cement the
thoughts and the learnings that you've
had
I don't know how many people recognize
this guy kind of big in our environment
here Kent C Dodds very big in our
wonderful world of JavaScript and he has
a concept he talks to that is consumed
build teach this is the way that he
personally uses or learns new concepts
and news technology he goes out he
learns them he consumes information he
builds products with those and then he
teaches them to the world in his talk
zero the 60 in software development how
to jumpstart your career he brings in
the quote from Ashley Williams the
absolutely love teacher is nature's way
of letting you know how sloppy your
understanding is when you teach concepts
to people you're gonna get those
questions and truly you're gonna go wait
wait I'm not sure and that's something
that is that concept of a you don't know
what you don't know in many ways so when
you teach other people and you take that
time to help instruct others then you're
really also finding the holes in your
own understanding and can go afterwards
and start filling those holes in so
remember through this that the key to
success is to build a culture of growth
which in extension builds a culture of
engagement so invest in yourself and
your colleagues and leave everyone
around you better than when you found
them I want to leave you with a final
quote from actually the former CTO of
Otto kevin goldsmith where he says the
culture of the place that you work will
be much more important to your success
and Happiness than the specific
technologies you work with or the
products that you work on so find the
place that helps you grow and thrive
first and foremost thank you very much
everybody
my name's Trey Hamlett unna you can
follow me on Twitter at Trey tuna or
pretty much Google traits oOnly anywhere
and you can find me have a great
conference