alright so hi everybody my name is Kate
Hudson I'm a web engineer and I work on
web maker at the Mozilla Foundation I'm
super way more comfortable writing node
and JavaScript than I am speaking to
humans so you'll have to bear with me
today I'm going to talk to you about
diversity and I'm going to talk to you
about contributors and most of you don't
need convincing that this is a really
important topic and we need to talk
about it an open source but when it
comes to finding solutions and
practically implementing them which is
what I'd like to address by the end of
my talk I think it's worth clarifying
exactly what that means so what do we
mean by diversity and why is diversity
so important particularly to open source
so typically when we discuss diversity
we're talking about how we identify
ourselves and how other people identify
us so you know those can be qualities
like gender ethnicity our belief systems
are shape or color most of discussion
around diversity of identity and
centered around things like power
structures politics equity rights and
communication but identity really
matters but it's not the only form of
diversity it's also important to
recognize the existence of cognitive
diversity and that is the differences in
terms of how we think and the experience
and training that led us to think that
way so as a society we're really
interested in cognitive qualities that
lead to creativity innovation higher
performance that relate to individuals
but we're actually not talking so much
about how being different can
collectively lead to better outcomes so
that's why I wanted to share some
research that I read pretty recently
it's a book called the difference it was
written by a really awesome guy named
Scott page and the central premise of
his research is that diversity Trump's
ability when it comes to creating great
outcomes so the first thing he does is
defined what cognitive diversity is I'm
not going to read this whole slide you
can go and find the book if you want
more information but essentially it's a
difference in terms of our perspectives
and how we use those to construct
different models and predictions and
methods for finding solutions so that's
cognitive diversity he looked at problem
solving capabilities of high-performing
but homogeneous groups of thinkers
compared to less experienced but very
diverse thinkers and he found pretty
conclusively that for certain kinds of
problem-solving diverse groups performed
much better so this wasn't true for all
tasks routine tasks like flipping
burgers and mechanical things virtually
no benefit for tasa had to be performed
in isolation by individuals like some of
the early software development work
better for individuals with experience
but the most benefit beneficial was
disjunctive tasks so group performance
being disproportionately dependent on
the strongest member in different cases
and that's really interesting because
modern software development is to a
large extent disjunctive so for any
particular problem and set of problems
there's different cognitive abilities
that will solve particular problems
better in open source solutions rise to
the top without being blocked by other
processes and it allows for outliers to
rise when they're needed which is pretty
cool so yeah diversity of experience
matters to open source it's a perfect
problem for diversity and that's awesome
so now you guys have a pretty robust
understanding of what diversity is and
why it matters let's talk implementation
so I'm going to show you some things you
can do when you go back to your jobs
that will help attract more contributors
and more importantly maximize the value
you get
from those contributors so let's start
with code contributors it's something we
know so cognitive diversity is really
important for good engineering we
learned that already because it's
largely a distant disjunctive process
and it's really important remember that
individuals who may not have the same
domain experience will actually come up
with better solutions to certain
problems that's not true of all problems
it's not probably going to be true for
like re-architecting some of your app
but it's going to be interesting for
like new problems that nobody knows how
to solve so how do we support different
areas of expertise without slowing
contributors down and ourselves as core
contributors one of the best ways is to
make reducing dependencies on domain
knowledge and project history so one way
you can do that is by splitting your
codebase into modules so if you have
like a huge legacy code base and it's
impossible to fix all the docs at once
consider releasing part of it as modules
so one things we did on the web maker
project is we decide to take all of our
style and CSS put it on a bootstrap API
and release it as a separate module so
that contributors who are interested in
contributing to just like our UI and our
style could actually hack on that
without setting up our crazy stack with
Redis and mongodb and all that stuff so
another consequence of cognitive
diversity is that communicating and
decision-making becomes way more
difficult you already know this because
there's already a huge diversity of
opinions in your open source projects
and you have to be really really mindful
about how that affects newcomers I can't
tell you how to be an expert in dealing
with conflict if you miss Jen's talk a
couple of days ago on emotional safety I
highly recommend you check it out
another thing you can do is consider a
code of conduct so code of contacts have
been in use for a while especially with
events in the event space what they do
is they help resolve conflicts they make
people feel safe and they're coming into
their space of code contribution to you
so one example of this is Mozilla house
community
patient guidelines they're pretty broad
they cover all kinds of contribution
they're really good guidelines for
dealing with new members you can take a
look at that but another project that I
recently came across that we're trying
to incorporate into our code base is the
contributor code of conduct which is
something that is intended to be a
closer to your files on github so
something alongside contributor md and
it talks about specific behaviors and
github issues and dealing with code
contribution specifically so there's a
couple of projects that are already
using it angular is one of them if you
want to check it out for kit contribute
definitely take a look at that link okay
let's get some water all right so code
contribution is awesome and so now we
know how to equip our code for a better
place for newcomers but I think it's
also critical that we expand our
definition of contributor and this is
really what I want to talk about the
most is taking advantage of the full
range of human talent that's available
to us so like that's pretty stupid right
I mean assuming that the only part of
our what we're working on can improve
from collaborative iteration is code is
completely ludicrous even if you're
writing a library that's like really
technical I think what you're doing can
definitely benefit from contributors
that have skills other than your own so
the first thing I want to talk about on
this extremely relevant to software
develop it up development that you can
get contributors is user research how
many people know what user research is
yay sort of lots of people so I'm going
to talk about specifically a kind of
user research called user testing and
basically what that is is does my
software work the way I expect it to you
and I got to tell you based on what
we've done with user research it often
doesn't so again the idea here is to
rely on people who have more expertise
and access to communities that are
valuable to you to do the user testing
for you what you have to do first is to
write tasks that are relevant to your
project so that they can actually hold
user testing so how does that look look
kind of looks like testing but not you
kind of write down some expectations
about new features that are landing or
problems you're seeing you do the
implementation and then you run user
testing or get your contributors to do
it to see if your expectations were
right these are some examples of what
tests look like so there's user stories
scenarios where you have users pretend
they're doing something and expectations
like what will happen when you click on
something I think expectations are
particularly relevant to library
developers in the case of error states
so even if you're not doing like front
facing you I you can run user testing on
developers to see if you know when they
get an error state are they
understanding what the air is like those
are some examples of what you could use
if you were testing Bauer about you know
you could run the error have the user
complete some actions and ask them what
they think happened did they actually
understand what the error was saying and
that would be really cool for new
contributors to try doing do things fail
in the way you expect them to so some
tips help contributors choose the right
target audience it's really awesome to
take advantage of contributors different
communities that you may not have access
to but it's also really important to say
which users are not relevant like you
wouldn't want to go to a group of
kindergartners and test our error
messages like that would not be that
helpful on the other thing is you only
need around five sessions to make it
really valuable so yeah I mean you don't
have to expect your contributors to do
thousands of surveys or anything like
that we found that user testing done by
community provided different
interpretations and areas of focus even
with the same test than our core team so
I think it's really cool because it's in
the spirit of taking advantage of
cognitive diversity and finding out what
people care about okay so next I'm sorry
alright so the next thing is
localization so I actually tried to
figure out how to pronounce that word
and German to make it really you know
awesome but I know so if anybody speaks
German you should teach me how to say
that after so to demonstrate this
principle
I'm going to look at a contributor
pathway that we've actually had a lot of
successful work with my team and that's
localization how many people know what
localization is a lot of people okay how
many people actually have implemented
localization in their project and how
many people feel like they're doing it
really successfully yeah it's it's a
hard problem so that's why I want to
talk about it I feel like so
localization for those of you who don't
know what it is it's making your project
or your product available in different
languages or locales and much deeper
than that it's making your software
available that in a way that's
culturally meaningful or changing your
UI to make it more relevant for
particular cultures so I'm going to talk
about a specific process that we did
localization that made it honestly like
really easy for us to localize all of
our materials and it was an extremely
valuable process for us so the first
thing you have to do is we were looking
we started by looking at the accept
language header which is something that
all browsers send with requests to your
application and that helps you guess
like what the browser settings are it's
not perfect but it's a good start for
example in client-side applications
there's burying implementations of
navigator dot language so you may have
to rely on other things to determine
language the next thing you have to do
is have some kind of user can control
over what language for example we have
like the locale as part of our routing
i'm having some UI for users to choose
what languages honestly not that hard
just a way to detect language the next
thing you have to do is figure out a way
to include localization functions in
your templating language whatever that
is so this examples from angular
basically you just have a function that
converts a list of strings like this in
a JSON file that's keyed on some words
so hello Jas comp and a function called
get tests to get text to replace that
with the locale specific string and it's
like honestly pretty easy and finally
this is the part where you get the
contributors we up
loaded all of our we have like an
automatic system to upload all of our
Jason files to transifex which is a
continuous localization platform and it
basically allows users to look at each
string and some notes about it and
translate it into their language on the
interesting thing here is we didn't
actually have to invent this system to
get localizers to work with us we
actually use existing communities and
existing systems we went to them which
was less work for us libraries can be
localized too so just because you don't
have like a full user facing app doesn't
mean you can't localize your material
moment je s which is like a date and
time library uses a strategy to like set
language and include localized versions
of date and time so you can also do that
too so the results of this for our
project is that um webmaker in
production is translated into 18
languages in full and it there's 100
over 100 languages and also so that's
our our dashboard and if you see there
we've got a thousand 57 contributors on
a fairly new project that's a thousand
57 contributors that is a non-trivial
amount of people that care about your
project and are actively contributing to
it thank you and I have to say seeing
people in different countries with using
our tools and that where our tools are
the only one of that tool in their
language is like an amazing thing to see
so besides it being really valuable for
us to get that translation we also learn
some unique things from going through
the localization process this is our
html5 video editor a popcorn maker we
found that when we translated into
Arabic we lies that we had to actually
adjust our CSS and Rui to be on the
right hand side we learned that we had
to deal with variable string length so
we couldn't make fixed elements we went
through a whole process of learning that
we would never have done if we hadn't
have localized our apps so yeah the key
inside here is instead
thinking about always having a mentor
and make work for your contributors ask
contributors to teach you like what
they're experts at and bring them in
that way okay so these things that i
showed you localization user research
may not be relevant to you the one thing
you can do when you go back to your job
on monday and you're working on your
open source projects is take a list of
possible blind spots that you have on
your project that aren't necessarily
related to code and make specific asks
to communities about how they can help
contribute to your project you know
maybe you need accessibility experts to
help do QA maybe you need copywriters to
help work through your docs maybe you
need more animated gifs I don't know
there's experts in every field take
advantage of them so now you know a
little bit more about what cognitive
diversity is and how you can use it on
when you don't know how to take
advantage of certain things in your code
base but if there's one thing that I
want you to take away from this talk it
would be this making good software is
really hard and it's going to be
even Yeah right it's it's really hard
and it's going to be even harder for the
open source community to deliver really
great products in the future you know 10
years from now so we can't afford not to
take advantage of this awesome thing
that is cognitive diversity so let's go
make it work thank you