so yet so my talk is sweating the small
stuff recreating subtle design details
using SAS and I was going to have a
longer title but it wouldn't fit so but
my name is Tim hatler I'm an open
standards developer at r/ga in New York
City and so for the next 20 minutes I'm
going to be talking about this button
and the process that it took from going
from Photoshop comp to something that is
in production today so we were doing a
redesign for a client last year we were
kind of embraced progressive enhancement
css3 and we're like we're not going to
cut up sprites anymore we're going to do
we're going to do this with CSS and so
this is what our designers created in
Photoshop we have a normal state and an
active state and it looks like a pretty
straightforward conversion you know
there's rounded corners gradient
overlays text shadows drop shadows it
should be something easy to convert the
CSS so the designers just kind of gave
the developers the photoshop file and
they're like all right go to town and so
this is what our developers came back
with and this is not exactly what we're
looking for so that obviously the colors
are all wrong the drop shadows are weird
and they're like I don't know we just
looked at the photoshop file and we just
put everything in and so we started
talking with the designers and the
developers about like what the problem
was and so we realized in some cases the
design what the designers use to
describe something is different than
what the developers need and in other
cases the designers have vocabulary that
developers just don't have it all so you
know we have a failure to communicate
here designers and developers aren't
speaking the same language what the
designers put in the Photoshop isn't
what developers need for CSS so how do
we solve this translation issue well the
traditional approach was to create you
know a style guide like this and this is
comically complex and large you're not
supposed to be able to read what it is
but this is actually what are our
designers had to produce for us because
they they stopped trusting us basically
to produce to take our Photoshop files
and make it
in the CSS without screwing it up so
this is like we have so many different
color buttons it's an e-commerce site
that we're working for so it was like
all these different buttons and we had
to define the top grading the bottom
gradient for all the states and also in
there's a second level of complexity
because some of the buttons need white
texts and some of the buttons needed
dark text for contrast reasons so we
have this really kind of complex style
guide and there's a lot of failure
points with this traditional translation
process I mean the designers have to
translate their own designs and then the
developers have to take that file and
then translate it back into CSS and so
wouldn't it be great if we could cut out
the middleman and we could automate this
translation well of course we can
otherwise my talk would be really sure
and so we can automate this translation
with preprocessors they can act as the
Rosetta Stone between designers and
developers and we can use them to to
translate our designs from Photoshop to
CSS flawlessly and so let's go back and
try to rebuild this button using sass
and compass just to note about the
technologies all my examples are in SAS
but if you use less or stylists you can
you can definitely use the same ideas
and if you haven't use a preprocessor
yet your mind is about to explode
because they're amazing and so I'm also
using compass which is a framework
that's built on top of sass which adds a
bunch of mix-ins and functions to solve
a lot of common problems that we that we
have as developers and compass kind of
it feels like the jelly that goes with
sass peanut butter and so I don't use
them separately at all anymore it's
always a Santa compass so first before
we get into like our translation we have
to like build up our base and we have to
sort of build all the stuff that isn't
going to change about our button
regardless of the color in the context
and so we start off with like a
prototype placeholder button placeholder
selector and there's all the stuff
that's just going to undo what browsers
do by default two buttons and kind of
add all the stuff that isn't going to
change like our font and our border
radius stuff like that and so now when
we write our SAS we can
extend that button placeholder and so we
can work in sort of a object or any a
modular approach in our SAS and then
when it gets output to CSS it's done in
a performant way so you can see here
instead of copying those 16 or so
properties we actually just increase the
selector chain and so this is one of the
the more powerful things with
preprocessors because you can the way
that you write the source code isn't
necessarily how it gets compiled so you
can write in a way that is comfortable
for you and like make sense from
maintenance perspective but then when it
gets compiled it's it does what it needs
to do to have the smallest file size and
so now we have our base we and so what
we extend the button placeholder then we
just add the unique things about that
button so the only thing that's
different is is the background color
here and we actually we're already
running into a problem here because we
as I said before we want our dark
buttons they have light texts and our
latex the light buttons have dark text
so let's see how we can use sass to
automate that translation process so
that individual developers can't can't
screw it up basically so we can use a
built-in sass function to compare color
lightness there's a function called
lightness that returns a value between 0
and 100 just based on like the hsl value
of that color and so here we just do
some simple logic and we're saying if
the color is greater than 50 so if the
background color is a light color we
want to return dark text and you know
vice versa so now our text color gets
set programmatically instead of setting
that color explicitly we call a function
and give it the background color and
then so you see on the right here when
our CSS gets compiled that decision gets
made for us and we don't have to worry
about like if an individual developer is
going to read our style guide properly
or not so sass allows us to abstract
design logic and this is a really
powerful tool because we can we can
abstract this stuff so these changes
these decisions happen behind the scenes
and so also later on if like you know
our marketing department or comes in or
like you know it really should be like
444 not 333 that a be test better we can
change that in one place and then when
we
recompile all these changes get made
automatically so now that we have our
base and some simple design logic let's
talk about how to translate to commonly
used layer styles from Photoshop and how
to convert them the CSS we're going to
start with drop shadow and how to turn
that into into a CSS box shadow and so
this is a CSS conference so I assume
you've all written a box shadow before
but just to make sure we're on the same
page the CSS syntax we have x and y
offset the blur radius of spread radius
and then a color and so this is and this
is what photoshop gives us which is
pretty similar but there's some
important differences color and opacity
straightforward and spread in size are
pretty close to what we need but the big
difference here and what we're going to
talk about is angle and distance and so
Photoshop hasn't it uses angle and
distance to set the the size of our
shadow instead of just a straight up x
and y offset and so you probably you
might not know right now but at some
point you're like 15 year old self knew
how to do this and so basically what we
have an angle in a distance which is so
we have a right triangle and so to
convert this from Photoshop to CSS we
just we need to find missing sides of a
triangle so good old sohcahtoa comes to
play here when I when I was like
building these slides I was going to
make a joke about like well the only
thing I remember from trigonometry is
sohcahtoa but then that actually ended
up being exactly what I needed and so I
didn't even realize it until eyes like
wait okay yeah so anyway our our X
offset is our is our Jason side of the
triangle and our Y off says the opposite
side and so I I don't remember too much
about trigonometry but but so they're
these basic formulas come into play
where it's just cosine of the angle
times the distance for the X offset the
sine of the angle times the distance for
the y offset we can create a function
that takes all the values that were that
are in the Photoshop layer style and
does all these conversions automatically
and then returns a list of values that
turns into a valid CSS syntax and so
this has actually been
as a compass extension that you can that
you can download on github I was I was
working on it myself but then I was
doing some research for this talk and
somebody had already pretty much done
the exact same thing i had so i'm i'm
linking to their stuff and because why
reinvent the wheel so so now let's add
the box shadow art button we can take
these values and put them right into our
SAS code using these functions and then
when it gets compiled into CSS we have a
valid box-shadow so now our button has a
nice subtle drop shadow in the normal
state and then an inset drop shadow in
the active state and so we so now we
have confidence that this drop shadow is
exactly what our designer intended
because we're using the same values that
they put in the photoshop and so we'll
go over text shadow because this is kind
of a freebie won the all the math is the
same for text shadow obviously but the
only difference between text shadow and
box shadows that and CSS of the spread
radius is not used by text shadow for
some actually I don't know why but it's
just not there so so this function takes
the photoshop takes the the list that we
return for this box shadow and it just
breaks up that list sasken can
manipulate list kind of like a raise so
we're returning just the values that
we're omitting the the fourth value
which is the spread radius so that it
returns a valid text shadow value and so
again we're going to add this to our
button we're going to put in the values
directly from photoshop and then when we
get them what gets output is a valid
text shadow so now we have a text shadow
that alternates when we click on it it
just goes from top to bottom so giving
the illusion of depth so so we have our
shadows and now let's talk about how to
convert a gradient overlay to linear
gradient and so this is a little more
complex this is the the hard mode of the
talk but so again you guys have all
probably written a linear gradient
before but to make sure around the same
page we start with an angle or keyword
which is the direction of the gradient
and then a series of color stops
and so Photoshop what they give us is
color and opacity which again is you
know straightforward stuff and then our
gradient which can be a simple to color
fade or it can be something crazy like
many many stops and we have the angle
which is the direction and then the
scale which is the size of the gradient
Photoshop allows you to create grading
overlays that are larger is smaller than
the containing element and so angle you
think at first maybe is pretty
straightforward might be able to just
actually put in that value in the in the
CSS but surprise there are some browser
inconsistencies here the vendor prefixed
version of linear gradient 0 degree
points to east but in the in the unfixed
version 0 degree equals north and in
Photoshop actually the the vendor
prefixes is the same as the Photoshop
version so we have a lot of
inconsistencies of what 0 degrees
actually where that actually points and
so how I've gone around this is I
created a function that converts the
angle to to a keyword when possible so
if if the angle is is like in a cardinal
or ordinal distance like 0 45 90 degrees
it'll convert it to a keyword but
otherwise it assumes that you want the
unpriests the angle and so it subtracts
90 degrees from it so this I've never
most of the time whenever I've worked
with a designer it's a you know they're
working from like top or laugh or bottom
so this has never been a problem in real
life before but there are there is some
limitations to what this conversion can
do but then so let's move on the scale
scale is a little more complex to want
it to be we wanted to grow and shrink
and so at first you might be like well
we'll just use the the background size
property but really we want to write
this as a function and functions only
return one value we can't return to
different properties but the way around
this is to actually to the chain to
manipulate our color stops and like
where they are and so in CSS you're
actually allowed to have stops that are
less than zero percent are greater than
a hundred percent so if we won the scale
something to this gradient to one
hundred fifty percent say we still want
the middle to be in the middle of our
element so we'd actually start at
negative twenty-five percent and go to
one hundred twenty-five percent and I I
worked out this formula myself because I
couldn't I couldn't find it by googling
and this this actually ended up being
the hardest part of this talk is working
at this formula so I'm really proud of
it but so now we so so now we need to
take all of our color stops and we need
to manipulate them based on our scale
and the way we do that with SAS is we're
going to put our gradient colors and our
gradient stops in the two different
lists and then we're going to use a for
loop just you know just like any other
programming language and we're going to
go through all those colors and we're
going to manipulate that stop based on
the scale and so we're going to sort of
break those apart and then rebuild a new
list that that is and that it's what CSS
needs to create a linear gradient so
this works for simple gradients like a
simple black to white fade or if your
designer is on LSD and wants to do
something super psychedelic you can put
in many color stops you can mess with
the the direction and the scale and no
matter how complex of a greeting you
have in Photoshop it will convert to CSS
perfectly and so now so let's do the
same thing we've done with all the other
stuff we're going to add the linear
grain to our button we're going to put
in the values that are designer wanted
and then when it get converts to CSS
plot twist something went wrong and so
the the gradient looks right it goes
from you know dark to light but the
color values are incorrect and so
there's been a piece of our Photoshop
layer styles that we've been ignoring
this whole time blend modes and so let's
talk about blend modes real quick the
blend modes are there a way to combine
two different colors of background
foreground color together using
different mathematical functions and so
when I was kind of working out trying to
figure out a way to programmatically
solve these problems that didn't have to
rely on on just style guides you know
when I was reading about blend modes and
I'm like oh it's all just math functions
like the light bulb went off in my head
I was like oh well they're just math
functions than we can create you know we
can create this incest we can recreate
all these things
so these are three examples of of common
blend modes the first one is normal
which is like no blend mode actually so
it just returns to foreground color so
what you what you put in is what you get
but the second one is our x mode which
is a darkening blend mode and this
combines the two colors together decay
to create kind of a nice dark rusty sort
of more a darker color basically and so
finally but what our designers wanted us
to use is the overlay blend mode which
is a contrast blend mode so the light
colors get lighter in the dark colors
get darker it's uh it's actually a
pretty sexy blend mode i think overlay
is one of the best but so there are a
few limitations with these blend mode
functions you have to know the
foreground color in the background color
ahead of time and Photoshop all that
stuff is sort of done on the fly so for
like drop shadows and stuff like that
blend modes might not be a good choice
because they're outside of the element
so you don't necessarily know what the
background color is going to be but for
gradient overlay is we know what our
base background colors and we know the
gradient that we want to put in front of
it so blend modes work perfectly there
so let's update our gradient overlay
conversion and so this time instead of
we're going to loop through all the
colors but instead of just returning
that color what we're going to do is
we're going to blend it with our
background color first and then we're
going to return that blended color and
so this has been Turing I turned this
into a compass extension too so if you
want to use this you can go on my github
account and check it out but so let's
put that into our our project now and if
we when we use those blend modes and we
compile our CSS our button looks perfect
so now we've created a tool kit that
allows us to translate our designs from
Photoshop to CSS flawlessly with you
know a hundred percent confidence and so
we used like we used to have a problem
we're like every time a button got
created on the site we'd have to go
through and do visual cue a and there
were so many times where it was just
like well the drop shadow isn't right
but now with these with sass and with
the with these functions we we can just
have confidence that everything is going
to work perfectly and so no
project is complete without a little bit
of refactoring so let's go and see how
we can make things work a little bit
better there's a lot of redundancy here
like there's a lot of like the
background color is a repeated a bunch
of times and if we want to make a new
button we'd have to copy all this but
what we a better way to do it would be
to take all that code and put it into a
mix and that takes a background color as
a as a parameter and so now we can style
a button with one line of code and
creating new buttons stuff that like
buttons and colors that we didn't think
of originally is easy and all of our
design logic is always followed and we
can be confident that everything works
perfectly which i think is pretty badass
so so this is kind of shows the power of
sass in the way that like once you start
using preprocessors how you can start
thinking about CSS differently and how
you can think about designing your site
I think with preprocessors we can we
should start relying less on style
guides and designers and developers
should be working together to build
reusable systems that translate their
designs flawlessly it means we can work
faster and we can also be more confident
that our subtle design details are going
to translate perfectly thanks guys