Emily Gorcenski-The Ethical Things of the Internet
Emily: Thank you very much.
I'm going to talk about the ethics of this issue and I promise I won't go
Too much lecture.
This is Emily Gorcenski.
I'm on Twitter.
I sometimes say something.
I like the Internet of Things and the landscape it is creating.
So why should I talk about the Internet? Things at a JavaScript conference?
Why should I use JavaScript to talk about ethics meetings?
This is because I have given this speech many times and I joked that every time I give it, I can
Give a whole new conversation, because there are so many problems, there are many failures, and
Errors, and security issues that occur strangely if I only focus on the case
Research, this will be a whole new conversation time.
This time, I decided I didn't want to talk about this topic anymore.
I hope you guys can say that, so I want to talk more
About why ethical issues are important and why you should do this is a JavaScript developer and
How can we integrate technology into a variety of abnormal equipment and services
belong.
Doing moral talk is almost impossible without heavy things.
There are warnings about the conversation.
We will talk frankly about some incidents that resulted in injuries and deaths.
Discussion about specific examples of sex and the image of raw meat.
If this scares you, then maybe that's about ten minutes of conversation.
who am I?
I'm a bit frank.
I'm a little offended here.
I am not a JavaScript developer.
I am a data scientist and I am trained as a mathematician and engineer.
I went to aeronautical engineering school and mechanical engineering, I worked
In my aerospace, biotechnology and career I now work in the financial industry.
What these industries have in common is that they are all heavily regulated and most of them are regulated
People who work among them subscribe through professional ethics
An independent society or other organization that guides the meaning of ethical behavior.
I'm here, I'm in defense, health, and banking, and I want to talk to you
About Morality-Deduction!
What do I mean when I talk about the Internet of Things?
This is a conservative definition of warranty.
We might consider smart refrigerators or smart refrigerator cars, that kind of thing.
I like to think of it as a place where the Internet usually doesn't belong.
So it may be a smart appliance.
I think Uber is an IoT taxi.
When we look at this ethics, we have to do this to see the entire range of what we are doing
With our technology and our contact information?
The difference is that these devices and products or services are not yet computerized,
We're letting consumers have the connection exactly what's happening.
So if you are a JavaScript developer, maybe you want a bread maker so you can hack
Your code while baking bread.
This is important because IoT products are the next level of convenience and optimization.
We have been optimizing our products for the past 30 years and for convenience, nothing more
You can get the competitive advantage of the refrigerator now.
So if you don't have a competitive advantage using unconnected devices, you have to go
connected.
It is also important for those who have a livelihood to be affected by disability.
You might worry about the ability to monitor IoT devices or terrible
Uber is accused of doing things, but if you ca n’t bypass or cannot bypass
Live in a relaxing taxi service where you have other needs, something
Like Uber is a life saver and changes your life.
We can't write it as ridiculous that the internet of things is frivolous, we have internet twitter
Account, there are a lot of misses and there are a lot of good things
Also from the Internet of Things.
When I talk about morality, what do I mean when I say that word?
You may have seen this picture.
The frame is with one Nobel Prize winner tied to five sets of tracks and another tied
to another one.
Somehow you have been put in this position by the lever.
This is a very popular question on the internet now because it feels like something
If we just, we can use category theory to solve it, two, it really
For some wet memes.
The thing about the trolley problem is that the trolley problem is not the trolley problem,
So why are there problems with self-driving cars?
We like to solve things as problems-this is our nature as developers and engineers.
In the field of technology, we don't actually face moral dilemmas that often.
When there are two, moral dilemma occurs
What you take must not violate at least one of them.
I think JavaScript is attractive and the JavaScript community is in charge
Because I think the most fascinating real moral dilemma in a decade of technology.
I will tell you later.
Some people may already know what I'm talking about.
Technical issues usually mean we don't follow ethics.
I am not saying that this is an indictment that you are a bad person, immoral, immoral person.
There are companies out there that will get a side look now, but I mean in our
Industry, we have no professional code.
Some clubs can join, but if you are one of them, please raise your hand
Like ACM or I888.
There are some, but it is not the majority.
In practice, morals are about things: they are analysis of harm and mitigation
risk.
So when we talk about moral behavior, especially when it comes to research ethics, what are we
What we are doing is not to eliminate the possibility of injury,
But we are trying to understand all these ways our technology can hurt someone,
We are looking for actions we can take to reduce the chance of this happening,
Reduce its severity when it happens, and provide remedies when it inevitably
indeed.
So this is the ethical standard we need to raise when we develop technology
Especially the Internet of Things.
Therefore, injuries can occur in three ways: first, through malfeasance.
This is the most common theme in the Internet of Things.
It's safe.
This is where people talk about hacking.
This was the biggest problem when the last DS attack on the Miri botnet occurred.
Witnessing the occurrence of a DOS attack event IoT devices are insecure, you know
IoT security is in a very bad state right away.
When this happened, its timing and the way it was structured gave many people
Many people worry that this is a precursor to a US presidential election,
This will be an influential attempt and it turns out that the result of this election,
Fear is unfounded-we managed to mess up that one on our own-because I didn't
I want to talk about the security issues in this conversation.
First of all, I ca n’t cover everything; it succeeds, if we do this it may cause other harm
To solve these problems, we solved the security problem.
Failures are errors and software failures.
What happened while the equipment was running was normal business environment, but it got
Stuck in a situation we didn't predict as a developer.
Sometimes it's worth mentioning that we like to stay ... except
Semantics.
This is a good example, this is on Twitter.
The poor gentleman, Andrew, has an IoT water cooler and his TLS certificate has expired, of which
Cause some blocking code, which means hardware interlock fails, he has water
His house is everywhere.
This is a real question, right?
This is a problem.
If a TLS certificate expires in a web service, just like in cyberspace, we forget TLS
Certificate, we have a blocking code and we have someone who intends to deal with this.
We cannot treat IoT devices more like cows, we must treat them like pets
Living in people's homes, very, very angry when they are not being fed.
One day, if we are not careful, we will put JavaScript in. I do n’t know, an IoT
Kettle and lit someone's house on fire because "undefined" is not a feature.
I stole this joke, and it was such a return on investment because he didn't save me MPM socks!
This is what I have done, and I am proud of it.
A few years ago, I did this. If I can, I can do it full screen.
Where is my mouse-we are gone.
This is a Microsoft band-I am not picking here at Microsoft-this is a piece
Raw chicken.
I ’m not as scary as a chicken. There is a zombie chicken. This is a piece.
The meat I bought from the grocery store score.
Its heart rate is 120 minutes per time!
[laughter].
In the real world, sensors are messy, they are noisy, they are not perfect.
So when we design for the Internet of Things, we have to take this into account.
You can read a piece of chicken breast whose heart rate is ridiculous, but this has
It has a profound and profound impact on many things.
First, there are universities that require students to wear FitBits.
There are employers out there that have health insurance incentive plans.
If you're following what's happening in health care in the United States, now we have this question
We have monitoring equipment where we monitor our health and report existing conditions
condition.
This is not actually a hypothesis, this is what really happened.
If possible, let me get out of full screen mode.
In 2015, a lady was visiting a colleague.
She pulled police to report sexual assault.
When the police investigated them and found that she was a bit fit, and with her permission, they conducted an analysis
data.
When they analyzed the data, not only that they gave up the investigation of her claims,
But they turned around, and they accused her of making false statements to the police,
Last year, she was charged with convictions and sentenced to probation.
Prosecutors said FitBit data blocked the transaction.
I can pull 120 beats per minute raw chicken and woman's life is ruined
Because no one at FitBit stood up and said no, our device was inaccurate.
You cannot do this.
Our equipment testifies to us falsely, and they can.
The problem is that without regulation, how do we structure their guarantees or standards.
We just send the code.
We ship hardware.
We are innovative, fast, fast, fast.
We don't ask ourselves what kind of harm would happen when this goes wrong?
This is happening more and more frequently.
These devices are used in criminal and criminal civil investigations.
Just last week, CNN reported a man charged with murder of his wife
Data about FitBit says she has traveled a certain distance without
Associated with his story.
For example, anyone who wears knitwear will know that it will be recorded
You sit on the steps on the sofa.
How can we make this happen?
How can we make this information impact people's lives?
Another thing: Smart water meters were used in last year's murder investigation.
In the same survey, they also submitted a guarantee for Amazon Echo data.
The question is: who is going to jail?
When will someone try a probation device to make a false statement to the police?
And, say something, rest, someone is injured or someone is injured
Killed?
Who will be held responsible for an accident if the equipment causes it?
Is it the owner?
Is it a developer?
The company that made it?
This may seem like a problem, but it is not.
This has happened.
In this frame you will see the vehicle, the white vehicle on the right is a Google self-driving car
Car, this image is a still image-this is a screenshot taken from a video
Dashcam of a mountain municipal bus view California.
Google SUV is about to exit the bus and an accident occurs.
Thankfully, no one was injured.
No injuries, but the fenders were bent.
This is the first time a self-driving car has been found responsible for the damage
An accident.
Google expressed its dissatisfaction.
They said, "You know what?
We are not good
We will be responsible for compensation. "
They investigated what happened and they concluded that the car had predicted
Because we are ahead, the bus will affect us.
Okay, now Google is in a good position where they want to transport self-driving cars,
So of course they take responsibility because they don't want to test it
in the court.
But as we enter, we cannot rely on it for the future of the Internet of Things.
We cannot rely on benevolent companies to take responsibility once they emerge on a large scale.
By the way, even if Google is right, it will be a historic moment
Because if the bus has succumbed to the vehicle, it will be the first municipal
The bus has yielded!
A few years ago, there was a judge in San Francisco as part of a research project, not
In part of the case he investigated whether the autonomous system belongs to an existing system
Responsibility theory.
In the investigation, he found the vehicle to make our own decision, something to use
Control the system like an adaptive self-tuning neural network, intelligent system, if you want,
Designing your own means to accomplish tasks may not take any responsibility
Existing tort theory.
This is of great significance.
Because if you buy an ordinary refrigerator and it breaks, you can say, "Hey, the manufacturer,
You should be responsible for this rest. "
If you buy a coffee machine, it will burn your house because the defective unit you
Can go out safely and then you recover the loss from the company and your insurance company
Take care of it.
This is a complete ethical framework around this.
There is a legal structure there as well.
Obviously, self-driving cars will happen safer and they will save lives.
This is a very important thing.
We want to save lives.
We hope the road is better.
But the number of lives saved is not the only term in our moral calculations.
We have to see what happened to people?
How did they take care?
How can they pay for medical care or go back to work or miss work biochemistry
They are recovering, but still able to pay rent and affordable food?
So this question is what we mean as developers?
For example, will this give us a free pass?
We take no responsibility for IoT devices.
Does that mean we can ship it?
We can do anything.
Let's innovate from everything until there is a problem, and there is a precedent,
Correct?
Is this really the legacy we want? Forgotten?
Do we want to leave the legacy behind us because we can and we don't give
Damn who we hurt?
Some companies are doing this.
Some companies are actually working in spaces where they want to innovate,
They just want to build things and then ship things and they will deal with the consequences
later.
But you have to ask yourself: I want to take responsibility for this?
This is the whole point of morality.
Now, I'm talking about one of the most fascinating ethical events in the JavaScript community
In a period of technology, this is the mat event on the left.
I don't know why it's pink, but anyway.
Ashley talked about the left footpad last night and it was really fascinating because she focused
Rally in a lot.
She said that when the left foot pad went online, the Internet exploded.
People are angry about many things. The JavaScript community has developed a small module.
The system may be wrong, or it may be wrong
And friendship is lost or damaged in this matter.
What people don't realize is that all these angry and sharp reasons
Because it ’s actually the left-hander incident that reveals what a real moral dilemma is, and
We just don't see the trees in the forest at the moment because the left footpad has two competitors
Ethical decision.
The first is that the ethics of hacking culture is the most important thing.
Openness is a virtue, and that ability to control your code is tantamount to existence
A hanger to become an open source developer.
Of course, others can fork, but you have to choose to tout it.
When there are all his modules on the left and broke a bunch of things on the Internet,
MPM has a competitive framework they own who is responsible for who uses them
product.
They have the responsibility of engineers.
They also value openness.
They are an open source community.
So this is a very difficult decision and that is why there are so many heads and ass
Decision made.
Can you imagine what would happen? If this did not happen in 2016
Affect the network?
But on the contrary, I do n’t know. In 2018 and 2020, MPM is running people ’s cars, people ’s cars.
refrigerator?
Someone pulled down a module and now, all of a sudden you drive on the highway
At 70 miles per hour, your car shuts down and something goes wrong.
You think this is impossible.
No one will actually do real-time deployments running on cars running IoT devices
field.
Please do the system as we do in production now.
IoT security is a mess.
We are innovating fast.
Of course there will be problems.
And you don't want to be that person responsible for someone's refrigerator
They have lost all their food or maybe they have lost the important medication they need
Refrigeration.
You don't want to take responsibility for it-maybe you do it.
Maybe you think the virtue of openness is more important morality, that is a
Real moral dilemma.
So what do we do as a mockery?
What can we gain from talking about morality?
That's why I don't want to speak this way, instead of allowing you to
This speech, because there are things that we can do as engineers, as developers,
Make our work space better and act with more ethics.
The first is to set expectations for your boss.
If you know what pressure your boss has, if they ask you to do something you do n’t
Feel comfortable, you need to know, i can go to my boss, i feel uncomfortable
Got this?
You can go to your manager and say, "I have concerns about this?"
Do you know what will happen if you do?
This is a very important thing.
You must also be prepared to refuse.
If someone comes to you and says, "Hey, I need you to build this method of sending
Tracking someone's heart rate data to our server in real time, "Do you feel comfortable?
this way?
Maybe you are not.
But do you know how to reject an order?
Would you like to decline the order? If you do, your career will be at risk
Against what you believe?
You also need to be able to have frank discussions with your colleagues about what it means.
I work in the financial world and I'm a data scientist, so we have a lot of data about people,
And a lot of ability to work with that data, so we often talk about my
Team, about what we mean when we record customer data
Record information about its financial situation.
We keep talking about it, as if you weren't happy to do it?
What do we have a legal obligation to do?
Financially, we have a legal obligation to report fraud and view
For example, money laundering.
So we have to talk about these things with each other.
And, as an engineer, you should be able to speak frankly, like your colleagues, "I didn't
like this. "
How do we make sure we don't go there?
How do we ensure that it stays safe and not dangerous?
The most important thing is to know your limits.
Know when you are willing to speak.
Because technology is really profitable and we have a lot of privileges.
We have many privileges in technology.
Even if just looking around the space we are in, this is an extraordinary meeting
Space, and various facilities and various facilities are decadent here
This is not the case in all industries.
What restrictions are you willing to accept? Saying, "I can't have a conscience anymore
Keep doing this? "
Then do something different.
If you don't know what this limit is, then you just won't find out that you are over
Until it's too late.
That's all I have.
thank you very much.
[applause].
[cheer].
>> Thank you, Emily.
It was a wonderful speech.
I think you've touched on many very important things, the gist of our current ethical issue
Should ask.
We will work with the next speaker.