shut up or when I signed up for this
talk I had no idea what was going to
happen on black friday so thankfully
this this talk is a bit more positive
than it could have otherwise been this
very much could have been a disaster
porn segment but that's not the way it
went thankfully so this is a second year
that we've done a note BF sort of
twitter campaign and basically we just
documented what what happened in our
system as we hit the most traffic that
we see throughout the year and this year
was fairly unique for myself because it
was the first year that we were doing
some fairly intensive cpu tasks within
our note environment last year we were
basically just concatenate ingela script
or sorry concatenate HTML with a little
bit of minimal JavaScript and pushing
out to the client that lightweight super
simple easy this year to try to improve
our initial page load performance as
well as our SEO we've updated a number
of our pages to render the content on
the server and then push it down to the
client so it this provides a much faster
page load I can show you some nice side
by side videos that really drive home
the point but I don't really have time
for that today or in this presentation
the the issue that this brings up is
that it's a massively different of load
on the servers its CPU versus i/o bound
and notice awesome at a thai oh wait
sorts of tasks but cpu-bound operations
using having only one thread available
can quickly smile spiral out of control
if you don't have the proper
configuration and safety mechanisms so
this is kind of what I had thought that
black friday would be and it certainly
was in the
the couple of months prior to black
friday but we actually effectively
repeated last year this is a graph of
our I believe this is the RSS loads on
the servers and they're basically flat
there's the servers were at least on
this particular metric not doing a whole
lot this is obviously a bit contrived
because the CPU is we're doing a lot of
things as well but those graphs aren't
nearly as interesting and don't drive
the point home but to do all this it
took a lot of work to to get our system
into this state that we needed it to be
when we first started deploying this
everything seemed fine under our smaller
production loads but we quickly found
that I got our first stress test we
couldn't even deliver half of the
traffic that we did last year due to
these changes and due to implementing
them in some pathological ways which was
not good needed to say there were some
concerned people in the business group
after those results but basically we
used those stress tests as well as some
pretty aggressive monitoring both during
those tests and throughout the year to
identify issues that we may have run
into between memory leaks excess of CPU
and those sorts of things and we flicked
them fix them as quickly as we could and
push the production and moved on to the
next issue which this was very helpful
we survived so I there's three big
changes that we made that helped us out
the most and in our opinion the first of
those was the event loop effectively we
were taking a system that was designed
to generate HTML on a within a browser
on the user's device
and trying to make it work under a note
environment that has very different
goals on the user's device you may want
to show partial behavior earlier or you
may want to delay the actual you may
want to run on the event loop longer in
order to show everything at the proper
time to the user and in some cases avoid
browser bugs but this led to situations
where you'd have 40 milliseconds to
render a page and that's continuous so
rendering a single page would be 40
milliseconds sitting on the event loop
and under under small loads that's not
an issue but when you start throwing
tons of crazed shoppers at the system it
very quickly destabilize this a system
and when you're in a situation that you
have event loop contention on your node
server it you can take down the entire
thing very easily it's not just that
only those routes are destabilized it's
everything so with that ties that's
basically the behavior that we saw in
our first stress test the the entire
server went down not just the the pages
that were in question here and that's
very bad so additionally we since we had
the client side rendering path that we
had to use previous years and we knew
that that worked we were able to utilize
this to failover at the at the proper
port failover if the system determined
that it was likely to hit a case where
there would be contention or just
general stress we also designed this so
that it would be automatic the point
that you're starting to have or that the
point that human could react to having
been notified by a system that email or
pager or whatever the case may be your
systems already highly unstable at that
point
and you may even depend on exactly how
its implemented if it's a wife config
push you may not be able to even talk to
the endpoints in question and restarting
servers that are already under that sort
of load can also lead to some very bad
things so you absolutely want to make
sure that if you are doing any sort of
failover it happens automatically we
also designed the system so that it was
targeted at the public use case at the
Googlebot at the basically at the point
that we can serve only the content to
the user that or sorry that the initial
response is only the content that is
long-lived and applies to everyone so we
split out services that would either
user specific or have data that needs to
be shorter-lived due to whatever reason
and then we pushed all this into a large
number of caches throughout the system
and found that your use case will vary
but they're having offload in a system
like this is quite important so we did
all these but there was certainly a
varied amount of impact based off of
what the based off of each different
action that we took so the event loop
was very important so was the event loop
and the event loop this change added a
lot of complexity or to our code because
we needed to support rendering
synchronously on the client and
asynchronously on the server but it had
we not made these changes I don't think
that we would have survived the holiday
or we would have had to turn things off
and toned it down gone back to the older
system or other sorts of mitigation
techniques but the failover and the
caching actually didn't matter that much
for
of course that did not work on this
resolution so this is a graph of all the
server side does execution instances of
over I believe that nature there we
found that almost no failover occurred
there were some errors down at the
bottom maybe two percent at the peak I'm
not sure you can't even see the
instances on this graph of the of the
failover or the load based veil of her
cases they were there in the raw data
but in at this scale it just it didn't
really matter whether or not those
triggers were false positives or whether
or not they had they not happened the
system would have then become unstable
is unclear but at the volume that they
did occur it's it seems like that did
not help us as much dairy under our
particular load there which kind of ties
me in sorry about that this kind of ties
me into the point that everyone should
be aware on this so there's some here be
dragons to just assuming that the things
that we did for our use case will work
for your system if you're consulting
similar things but it's certainly
helpful to know that this is the case
but you absolutely have to do your own
testing to make sure that whatever your
cat your traffic patterns whatever your
Black Friday is your super bowl you can
survive those sorts of situations so
i'll post these slides later some links
to the the system that we used as well
as the write up that i did on the start
of our node BF event but thank you very
much