[Music]
thank you and you can hear me fine
everybody yes okay welcome back from
lunch I hope you're not too sleepy I'll
try to make it dramatic I certainly had
some drama in the in the break here
turns out my laptop did not connect to
the display so that was my break and I
was working what I'm still have a mild
state of panic yeah my name is Peter I'm
from Copenhagen I've been a front-end
developer for 15 years now
time flies I'm very much into tooling I
want to I want to enable people to do
complex stuff in a simple way and this
talk is about techniques how to load web
fonts fast and also tooling that I built
to help you do that so first of all
according to the HTTP archive which
scrapes like millions of pages based on
Alexa rank so like the most popular
pages on the Internet
70% of those pages are using web fonts
and that is a performance problem
because if you don't do something extra
to make a web fonts perform then they
will actually detract from your
performance and that has to do with the
wave fonts are loaded but I'm gonna
preempt myself and actually start out
with a demo and then we can look at the
difference between what default web
fonts performance profile could be and
what an optimized one could be so I'm
gonna start out with showing you the
tool and then I'll walk you through the
techniques applied which you could also
apply manually and then I'll explain
things as we go so first of all I have a
blog very rarely updated like two years
ago so this is a standard jackhole site
it's hosted on net Liffe I so I get
static file hosting which is fast I have
a CDN which which delivers things fast I
run a static build system on this so
everything is optimized there's bundling
this minification there's compression
all those things and the performer
profiles actually not that good so I can
show you first of all I'm gonna run the
demo here if Network permitting I'm
gonna run my tool here I'm gonna install
the tool called sub font which is an
open source tool I built if the network
doesn't work we'll just skip ahead
because I have a fallback it looks like
it's working
thank you for not running Dropbox right
now nice of you okay
I installed sub font so I'm gonna I'm
gonna open my package JSON and I'm gonna
autumn and my build system my build
system is currently bundled x''k Jake
you'll build so it's a Jekyll page and
after I've done that I'm gonna say soft
font bill slash index dot HTML which is
where the build artifacts from Jekyll
will be I'm gonna say - I which means
that it'll clobber the files which I'm
fine with because it's a build artifact
and then I'm gonna say inline CSS save
and I'm gonna do npm run build so what
will happen now is the Jekyll build will
will run I will have a build artifact
and index.html sup font the tool will go
in a statically analyze the page figure
out that I have google fonts and then
it'll do magic which I will show you in
in a moment Network permitting because
now it's actually going on the network
to fetch funds from from Google Fonts
and then my post optimization tool is
ran just like normally and I cheated I
already prepared a web page test or run
on my master before the optimization and
one after and it looks like this so I
don't know if you can see this the upper
timeline is my blog as I just showed it
to you on the different tab it takes
four and a half to five seconds before I
get the first paint and then it takes
slightly somewhere in between six and a
half seconds and seven seconds to get
the fonts that's a long time this is
done on a moto 4G and a slow 3G
connection that is deemed to be the
current
global average so if you have pages that
you're interested in also serving in
South America Africa Asia then you want
to perform on this profile the bottom
timeline timeline is the after after I
ran this tool and you can see that I
have a first paint at four seconds
instead of seven seconds because I
already have the fonts that's a massive
difference and obviously the difference
will be less pronounced if you have a
fast Network and a fast CPU but the
difference will still be perceivable
so let's look into why why is there this
massive difference and the upper the
upper line is running Google Fonts as as
suggested by Google Fonts it's included
with a link tag it's including the style
sheet from Google Fonts which will then
eventually point at the font files which
are needed so let's look at the timeline
is this big enough that you can see it
you think I can up it one more there we
go
alright so this is a this is my page you
can see the initial request has a slow
T&S it has a slow connection time it has
an SSL handshake then it has a roundtrip
for waiting for the data and then the
index.html drops in that's at around 2.2
seconds then a bunch of new connections
are triggered my CSS some images and the
Google Fonts CSS and then you see oh I
need to know the DNS I need another
connection I need another SSL roundtrip
and then I need another entre for the
data and then the green line indicates
that now the browser is ready to render
now it has loaded this external blocking
Google style sheet and and it says oh
there are some fonts and I need to fetch
them and then it does another DNS lookup
and another connection and another SSL
handshakes and then it and then it
downloads the fonts this is very slow
and this is like what what Google serves
you as the default it doesn't even serve
the fonts from the same domain as the
CSS so you don't already have a warmed
up connection which you can request the
fonts on if you use google fonts
out-of-the-box
this is what you'll get and we can do
better so this is the after timeline I'm
going to switch back and forth so you
can just see later so what happens here
is that my index file comes in
approximately the same time that there's
no difference and then immediately I
download the four fonts in parallel with
requesting my my stylesheet and and all
those things and then you can see later
after after the paint after the three
point two ish seconds the green line
where the browser has already rendered
with fonts it does some more things it
downloads the google fonts CSS and then
it downs upload and loads another file
that's a part I can't explain right now
I'll fix that eventually so you can kind
of perceive the difference that here you
have a very very horizontal waterfall
chart and here it becomes more vertical
so it does more things at the same time
leverage is http/2 and and downloads
things in parallel so I'll show you
which techniques I I used to achieve
this but let's first do a small video
comparison so just to have a feeling for
what the perceived difference is that's
what the user experience is right okay
let's let's dive into what what actually
happened here this should probably be
smaller and this should be prettier okay
so this is where things get interesting
my tool looked at the original link
include from from from google fonts for
the star seed and that it analyzed the
page pulled down the pages to local
which means that now I can download the
font or it pulled on the fonts to to my
local server which means that now I can
reuse my already warm HTTP to connection
from my host and I preload the fonts
which have a known file name the trick
is with google fonts and with any web
phone provider out there like Typekit or
similar
none of them provide stable URLs for the
font files so you cannot even put a
preload header and and say I want to
preload this well file because
eventually it might change the URL so we
cannot guarantee that it actually works
the worst case is you'll spend the
download time and downloading the font
file and then you download a different
font file which is essentially the same
thing so by pulling it down on your own
server you can leverage the preload by a
by having a guaranteed file name and you
can use your already warmed up already
connected HTTP to connection if you
remember one thing then then it's this
one this is like 80 to 90 percent of the
speed-up you just saw all the rest is
just geekery like preload and get your
fonts local so this one more thing I'm
doing which is cheap which you can do
yourself when you have the funds local
you can add a font display font display
has a few options on how to deal with
the limbo in between the page being
render and font being downloaded and I
recommend having fun to play swap which
will immediately draw the fallback font
as soon as it as soon as your page
renders and then whenever the web font
comes in and switches them because this
means that the time the time to
meaningful paint the time where the user
can actually read the page and see if
it's useful is the same as the time to
first paint so the larger uses to
immediately see do I want to do even
want to be here do I want to scroll or
engage with this page and then
eventually the nice experience will come
in when the web font drops in so in
order to serve it from local I'm using
the same technique as Google toss prefer
local otherwise use this URL for both -
and this URL for what you don't need to
make anymore gymnastics these days the
process are good enough that basically
all the process you want to support or
any support wofe and I'm pre loading
only there were two files because
preload support is a subset of waft of
to support so it's safe to say preload
above two files because if the browser
doesn't understand it it's a guarantee
that it probably doesn't understand what
you either
and then I'm doing something tricky so
there's a little script down here
preload is supported by around 60% of
all browsers but there exists a CSS
front loading API which you can access
through JavaScript and through this you
can actually trigger a load of the font
even for browsers that don't have P load
support yet this is what fun face
observer does if you've ever heard of
that which lets you like do a promise
based thing where I say I want to load
this font and when you're done I can
switch classes so I can like do a
loading spinner or or control the
experience in the in between in the
limbo between not having the fund and
having written at the page this is the
very short version what it's doing it
says it's iterating through the fonts on
on the on page and then I'm saying if it
has this specific name underscore
underscore subset which I'll come back
to all of these above have the have
underscore underscore subset in the name
so if it has underscore underscore
subset in the name please try and load
it and there's a try-catch around it
because this API isn't supported by all
browsers so I'll just do an empty error
handling I don't care about the result I
just want to trigger that download
immediately if it's available again if
you remember anything these are these
are the preload things you can do to get
like 90% of the speed-up I just got so
now let's talk about the hairy stuff I'm
not ok with 90% I want to enable people
to get perfect results with very little
work so I thought this sub setting thing
selecting a subset of glyphs that are
used on my page and excluding the ones
that are not using on my page that seems
like a doable thing right there are
tools to do it if you know what glyphs
you have you can apply a tool on your
font and then you can get a reduced font
that only has the glyphs you need easy
right after so after we did this we
coined a concept called hybrids driven
development and that's what this is you
think it's easy and then just keeps
going so let's dive into what's actually
happening
so you see that after I've figured out
how to how to know what cliffs I have on
my page that's hard I do this thing
where I have a new name for the font the
original name was notice Arif now the
name is notice Arif on the score on the
score subset so I'm actually including
the subset here and I've modified my CSS
so it points at the subset this is not
recommended practice in fact web font
experts will specifically tell you to
not too aggressive subsetting it is an
anti-pattern
and it just so happens that so this is
an example of a subset where only the
English character sets are downloaded
but it has this effect if you do it
wrong you might recognize this as as
Germans I have a um loud in my in my
last name
I've had many different renderings of
you or not both both this one and also
different characters especially Airlines
but what happened here was there was a
subset that and somebody forgot to
include um lab in the font so that one
glyph is rendered with a fallback font
and in this case the fallback font
doesn't really look anything like the
web font if you only serve a subset then
you might run into this especially if
dynamic stuff is happening on your page
our comment by somebody is loaded
they're Chinese and they write in
Chinese then it will definitely not be
in the web form that you anticipated so
I came up with a new technique to load a
subset and use a subset but still have a
proper fallback so at the time where a
new cliff loads or is needed it will
actually load the original font so that
is on demand and I have not seen this
technique before so I'm gonna try and
show you if if I can find where this is
used so I'm pre connecting to two more -
two more URLs one is fun stuff Google
API is calm once
funky static calm those are the the
places where the CSS and the fonts are
hosted on Google Fonts so I'm already
warming up the connection just in case I
need to look the fallbacks then all the
way at the bottom I have this ugly block
which is a script and an L script and
that's essentially loading the CSS the
original CSS from from google fonts that
I had but in an asynchronous way when
you when a script append a link tag like
this it'll load asynchronously so I've
just removed that slow connection time
and round-trip to Google Fonts from my
critical rendering path but I still get
this stuff but it's just not in my
critical path anymore so I'm warming up
these connections and in order to both
use the subset and enable me to fall
back to the original web font I will
need to look into build something that's
CSS main that's users probably know what
to say there we go so I've rewritten all
the usages so this was my original usage
as I said I want to use no Caesaria and
fall back to serife but now our
prepended this this subset so the effect
of this is that if a glyph is missing in
a web font these these declarations will
be tried in order so it'll start with my
subset figure out this glyph is missing
then I'd load the next one at least
that's the spec and Chrome and opera
does it correct Firefox has a bug which
I'm tracking right now it also has a
park where they load these things
upfront which means that you pay more
bytes but it actually doesn't infect
your your time - first meaningful paint
because the subset is already
pre-empting and and you can already
render before so even though some
browsers are loading a few more bites
there's still no downsides if your goal
is to get a first meaningful for paint
faster so I skipped over the hard part
which was figuring out which glyphs I'm
using
[Music]
it sounds easy and that's what we said
I happen to be a former colleague of one
of the web's foremost web font experts
Rammstein years ago we worked at the
same company and so we were having a
reunion birria like two years ago and I
was sitting there with another different
colleague and we were like hah I'm this
subsetting stuff how hard can that be
like you could just statically analyze
the the font or the text on the page and
then you know what cliffs you use right
and he goes no you cannot you cannot do
that there's all sorts of things and
we're drunk and we're not listening to
him we're like yeah yeah yeah we can do
this so the reason why we were that
cocky is that we spend a lot of time
building static analysis tools which
look at at a page as a whole as a one
single data model it has access to the
Dom to the CSS to JavaScript everything
at the same time which means that we
have the basis to do a static analysis
that would know which CSS applies to
which text so that's a tool set called
asset graph and it's using JSON
internally to model HTML so when we
started doing this Hybris driven
development we thought we'll just get
computed style and then we have the font
properties that we're interested in and
then we can figure out how they group to
the font files and then everything is
good handed off to a sub setting tool
and then we have a result jsm does not
have get computed style for inherited
properties so we implemented it which
turns out to teach me a lot about how
CSS font resolution is actually working
so just to do a short walk through you
you see the the the declaration you use
you see which selector applies to its
dom nodes the no declarations followed
you figure out this a specific font you
look up the front face declaration you
see which weights it has and if it's
italic and not and that classifies it to
which fonts you need to download so now
you have the weights and and the
approximate font and then if you don't
have all the funds for all the weights
that you specified it'll snap
- the ones available and then you need
to take care of things like you can set
a CSS property called font-weight:bold
er which means that after all this
snapping has happened it's gonna say oh
you want it I'm in a contact I've
already built but I want Boulder I'm
gonna do one higher of whatever is
available so all of these things are
very dynamic and very hard to track then
you have CSS generated content you have
visible attributes like placeholder
attributes then you have potentially
different states hover States active
states in CSS you have media queries
suddenly this problem is not just I have
a text node and I'm getting the computer
style its multi-dimensional multiple
states at the same time which all might
affect which glyphs and end up in which
pocket for which font file we ended up
actually implementing all of this and I
have not seen an implementation of this
before so I think this is genuinely a
new contribution there exists a
different tool called cliffhanger which
does get computed style for for text
nodes for also for attributes but
doesn't do the State thing so if you're
interested in in trying to look into
that cliffhanger is easier code to read
look at that and if you're taunting then
come speak to me and I'll walk you
through through our code and how we did
this so this tool only works for static
files for static pages so this means
that if you have a static page like
Jekyll or if they use Hugo or I don't
know there's a lot of different static
page generators these days this is a
tool for you you can keep doing the the
default recommended style of including
google fonts like this it also works
with local funds there is a there is a
Python dependency if you want to do
local subsetting it'll help you install
that when you when you hit that but if
you have a dynamic page you might be out
of luck
dynamic pages take several forms some
maybe have a static loading screen or a
static header then you could still run
this and you could get immediate
rendering of your static header but the
dynamic parts it doesn't really cover so
if you want to do fonts upsetting again
I cannot repeat this enough don't don't
do funds upsetting for that just don't
like it will not be enough to know
what's in your words in your translation
system or what's in on your pages
because there are weird States you could
get into and you cannot predict them
when you do dynamic JavaScript that said
preload preload print up preload
remember that go home and do it it's
it's like a half an hour change you can
download the web fonts from Google the
license allows you to they're available
on github I think they're even available
as NPM installs you can point a preload
link you can use an HTTP header if you
have access to to set your HTTP headers
this increases your performance
immensely so go and do that so I
encourage you to try this I want to help
you like if you have time in a break
I'll help you set this up if you have a
static page and and see it break in all
the funny ways that it can and then I'll
have Bakri posts that I can fix but I
want to close off with with this is just
one instance of a tool as I think it
should it should be built I think there
are not enough tools that allow you to
work in in a non complex way and then
abstract the complexity away from you
most of the tools that exist expose you
to tons of complexity with configuration
because you have to tell it everything
you have to tell at every entry point
everything to do you have to tell it how
to do it and you don't tell it what to
do so I I want to build tools that and I
want others to build tools that let you
achieve the goal and then just look at
your code and does the right thing and I
think this is one example of such tool I
might do a lightning talk later where
there might be another one I
what these tools to give people
abilities without having to know all the
crazy stuff that is behind it that's
upsetting stuff is so hard I don't
expect anybody to know it like I don't
even expect web font experts to do it
because it is so error-prone so I'm
really hoping that I can contribute that
people can do this and win something
from it but again subsetting that's just
the geekery I'm loading slightly less
fonts it's not where the gains come from
do pre loading so I'm really also hoping
that there might be designers in the
room or people who specialized in HTML
and CSS only and don't necessarily geek
out on web performance like I do and I
hope that they can they can use this and
that they can build faster experiences
so I think that's all the words I had I
think this room is not so good for
questions so I think we'll forego them
I'll be I'll be in front of the stage
and you can come and ask me questions if
you're interested and I'll leave you
with those words take a look at ads up
front you can install it from NPM
if you want to and give it a go and
tweet at me if it doesn't work I'll fix
it for you thank you