hi my name is Jade song Gomez I'm from
Brazil it's my second time in Buenos
Aires and I'm i feel i am home because
when as itís looks like porto alegre but
much much bigger and then i'm home
buenos aires awesome my talk was about
es6 the next version of java script we
have a lot of changes in the language we
have a basic stuff and main features and
my talk was about that i'm showing how
to use in it today because the
specification will be releasing just in
the next year but you can use it now and
my toughest about this the main features
i think is modules we can now have
separated modules in javascript and they
have arrow functions that similar to
lambda is in another language and fix a
lot of issues that we already have it
javascript i really believe in
JavaScript so I think the present and
the future will be about javascript
javascript is already running in a lot
of different environments and I think
the you can bet on on javascript
javascript is one of the pillars of the
one of the skeletons of the internet so
javascript is spread is we use it
everywhere everywhere website is using
javascript and with the new
specification we without now developers
have another way to do what we are doing