my talk for today is front end up
sterling I'm nikka you can find me on to
your ass and such gb i posted the slides
online for you to see I'm be back when
did have and i have a blog at and
panning for calm i'm also writing a book
it's called a javascript application
design all right about processes how to
write modular applications there are
testable and it comes with a lot of code
samples that are fully documented you
can look at here's the disc and God if
you're interested just go to that URL
and check out with it so for today's
talk I'm going to talk about the reasons
to build and the development flow I'm
going to talk about how to put together
a development flow that works for you
and which tools you could use and I'm
going to talk about the different kind
of tasks that you can perform with those
tools also i'm going to talk about
molarity and in particular and when they
talk about had to bring molarity into
the browser so the first question I have
is why build and more importantly why
build first rather than somewhere down
the line and the reasons for these are
process productivity and performance
process really means that you are able
to automate animation really is all
about reducing and eliminating
repetitive work and it also means it
also helps you to reduce human for
instance if you go to that link you'll
find the story about the company who
work on the stock exchange and they had
one guy doing deployments on nine
different boxes and he did it by hand on
each one of those and they also had
coding production that was ten year old
and they didn't use it and it was shot
serum behind a flag and they pushed some
new code to eight of those nine
instances because he just forgot one and
and he he forgot to reply to that one
and the issue was that the new code was
behind this old flag that they just
changed to do something else but in the
ninth box it still did the same thing
and so they started losing money because
they were they were making batter
requests and and they tried to figure
out what the issue was Anna and they
thought it was in the new in the new
code so they started rolling that back
and they started losing more and more
money and they went bankrupt in like 30
minutes they lost half a billion dollars
so like I said you're reduces human or
any eliminates repetitive work animation
is also productivity for you because if
you are automating you are able to do
continuously development for example
whenever a file changes you run your
tests again or your build again so that
you are able to develop we are going
back and forth and you can also set that
up on the cloud and do continuous
integration which is pretty much the
same same but either it on the cloud and
rather than do it whenever a file
changes in your local system is it
whenever someone pushes new car to to
your little Reaper for instance and that
also enables you to do deployments
automatically if those builds pass in
the cloud under social performance you
get almost for free compiling bundling
minifying spriting and acid hashing
which are all almost free if you are
doing built first and if you're not you
might have to move things around a
little bit too if you're and how exactly
to make those into what you are already
doing and all of this gives you faster
response times which means your goal of
making humans happier will be easier to
thing so what tools am I going to talk
about in the old days we shall see used
to have tools like make and which were
really more of general purpose kind of
tools and now we have tools there are
more oriented to front-end developers
such as NPM grunt gulp Yemen and a bunch
of father's right that you know probably
even know their names so I'll just focus
on NPM bullpen grant but really you
should choose your own tooling and I'll
just talk about this free because they
are the ones that I use but you should
find the tools that fit what you need to
do so grunt
grant is a configuration driven bill
till it's easy to configure you just
write a big JSON object actually it's
not Jason you just write the big o
checked with maybe a couple functions or
options or wherever and you can figure
the different tasks which are made into
plugins endorse a whole bunch of clients
there's like thousands of those so you
can write also your own tasks because it
just shall escape you write the function
and that's a task the issue with grant
is that the flow tends to get to burbles
if you are trying to do something rather
large in your builds because to run a
single commenting your shell with grant
maybe it takes like six lines of code
and it's not so fast as the alternatives
maybe maybe but the truth is that during
builds unless you are going for
continuous development which you should
is it's not such big of a deal if the
bill takes a little longer so to install
grunt all you need to do is have a
package.json file the the CLI and the
local grant installation and then you
have to create a grunt file and I'm
going to show you how to do that using
by creating a a grunt file that turns a
few icons into spreadsheet so here's a
grunt file that does nothing mile
exports is the camassia syntax for
exposing an API in email and in
comerciais every file is a mile I'll
talk about that a little more later so
here I am loading a plugin with grant
and I'm initializing it with some
configuration telling it where the icons
are going to be were
the sprite sheet is going to be placed
and then where I want the CSS to be
placed too and I just run grunts pride
and I get my icons so it looks kind of
like this maybe the designer gave me a
bunch of icons and threw them in a
directory and I can't just automate the
process of creating the spreadsheet
which may be in the old days you would
just make it yourself for us your
designer to that it was a really painful
process right and you can also do way
more complicated stuff we grant how many
of you have used amazon ec2 for instance
okay a few so Amazon ec2 is a hosting
environment and you can automate the
deployment to that as well using grant i
wrote a package for grant called grantee
c2 which shots with your access key or
secret access key and the fewer things
it allows you to put together a build
process that is able to spin up new
grantee instances in this case for
example i'm i'm building the whole
distribution I'm making here i'm making
a message for the release in my change
log and then the grantee see to baggage
will enable me to prohibition and
british on the amazon ec2 instance with
engine acts now the works and then it'll
allow me to push too easy to the changes
that I made since the last release with
rsync another little just install my
dependencies again restore tension
headaches on NPM and I said I'm not
going to make you watch the whole thing
um and the North gulp which is similar
to grant where it's code ribbon so it's
a little leaner you're just writing code
but it still works with this plugin
concept there's hundreds because it's
newer than rent but it's against as
JavaScript so you can really build your
own gulp tasks the issue with gulp is
that it comes with the concept of pipes
streams and asynchronous code which are
all very no the concepts and if you're
not enough developer you might have an
issue with that but it's faster than
grant so there's that to install go it's
pretty much the same as we grant you
should need the package.json god locally
and globally and that's it here I'll
show you how to build something with
gold I hope you create a gold file and
rather than require sorry rather than
expose an API you require the API gulp
exposes so here I mean to defining a
task that does nothing and I can easily
say okay I'll take this source file pipe
that through uglify in memory and then
push it to the desk a.m. and it's really
easy to add more stuff into that because
it's using streams so for instance if I
wanted to print into the council d sighs
I just other a new pipe statement and
pipe that through the the corresponding
gold plugin and I can also transform the
file using her file for example in my
license information and the version of
the package and then I run it with gold
build similarly to grant mpm is a bit
different in that it's great the ribbon
and there's barely any configuration you
can use any NPM package that you want
and it you can write in JavaScript if
you
I'm using certain Dino the environment
the issue that is that bashes and so
cross flood cross platform but if you
have to work with Windows probably use
something else and it's probably the
fastest option of these three I
mentioned so like I said there's no
installation for mpm run you just need
the baggage JSON file and then you add
the scrapes key and in that I've checked
every key is a command so here you could
do npm wrong length and you use chasing
to lend your directory the cool thing
about 10pm run is that it smart enough
to figure out if Shay a saint is
installed locally as a development
dependency for instance it will know to
look at for it in no miles chess ain't
been chase and so you need to install
chase and globally for mpm run to work
so you doing p.m. run linton that said
but the point really is that it doesn't
matter which tool you use as long as it
doesn't the shop for you and it works
for you and one last thing I wanted to
talk about was molarity for the last
year and a half or so i've been using
NPM and and i entered in el community so
to speak and i start caring so much
about modules and writing code that
that's one thing very well by one small
thing so how can we bring that to the
browser well we have comerciais right
which is the node module system but we
want that in the browser and that's
where browser fagenson which basically
will convert the commercials code into
something the browser can run
so what's commish is really my o'shea s
is a mile system which says every file
ismael miles have an implicit local
scope which means you don't have to use
weird closures and stuff you shall
declare variables and if you want to
expose something you have to use the
global that explicit call they can also
expose an API like we saw earlier same
oil exports something am i loading sir
and miles can require our meals using
require likewise earlier am i loading is
synchronous which means the module will
be pulled in as as you require it and
the arc difference with our module
systems is that in in in this system you
your modules are loaded in code rather
than having to do like using stinemans
and requiring our assemblies or stuff
like that so here's an example
comerciais file it declares a local
variable experts a couple of methods in
an API and then you can require it in
set the status and pregnant in L you run
that as need food right but that's
that's not how you how do you bring that
to the browser that's for browser
handsome browser fine lines require
calls meaning that it'll it'll figure
out what you're trying to require and
bundle everything together into a single
file so that the browser doesn't who
can't make the requests can work with it
it poured no caramel hills to the
browser so it's smart enough to work
with noodle on HTTP and all of the our
core modules in available to note
non-conscious miles can be shamed so you
don't have to go pester the guys who are
writing your favorite libraries just
because they don't support ricochets
you can use any library you want we you
just have to shame it which means you
take the global that they declare and
make that into module and it has access
to all of em p.m. right which means you
have you get access to a much broader
community of JavaScript packages it
shine light source maps which means your
development process doesn't get affected
at all and you can automate it away with
a little sub so that's pretty much it so
to run to bundle something through
verify you need to use the CLI or it has
a programmatic API as well and you can
do browserify main and and hope that to
a browser phase file and once you run
that there you go you have conscious
miles in the browser so to recap bill
first rather than later this will set up
a foundation for where where your
application looks like and enable you to
do less hacker stack down let's hack
your staff down the road make tools work
for you rather than trying to cram your
whole process into a tool that doesn't
really fit your needs and browserify all
the things really I i believe browserify
see member than yes six miles so moving
forward I definitely think this is
something we should be placing more
weight on and that's what I had thanks