so I'm a tranny i founded a company
called boxer we did this voice messaging
thing we had all know it on the back end
a lot of people may know me from doing
no dradis a lot of people using node
Vettes yay redis a ton of people have
talked to me in the last few days at
jazz camp here in no comp about node
Redis and it really reminds me like how
many contributions I got to help make
that work and like ton of people are
using an introduction and like we fixed
like a ton of bugs it wasn't just me who
made that thing like a whole lot of you
helped contribute so I just want to say
thanks for everybody who like try that
out and like you know pointed out bugs
and like gave it a shot because like I
think now we have we have a pretty good
Redis library it's like such a good fit
with node anyway just wanted to put that
out there thanks for the community and
support on on the rightest thing anyway
so I supposed to talk about a node
performance I've done some work with the
VA profile or and stuff like that and
found some interesting things but in in
the last few weeks I ran into some I
think even more interesting things as
voxer started to get more popular we
started adding more more capacity to our
system we're running all note on the
back end and it's it's raised a bunch of
kind of interesting issues that I wanted
to talk about and so before it before I
do that like just backing up a little
bit like we've always said like they've
been some things we've been saying about
node since like forever ago and I think
I think nodes been been kind of living
up to its initial promise like it works
it has very good performance on like a
single CPU core it's it it works really
well that way it's it's very inexpensive
to hold open a lot of network
connections and you get to write your
programs in JavaScript so it's like
those are like the key the key sort of
like tenets of like why note is good in
my opinion and and I think we've we've
done a pretty good job at that like it
really does deliver on all
those three things but there's always
the this sort of you know nagging
questions the the the people who are new
to note are like well geez what about
all my other cpus I mean isn't all like
modern software multi-threaded like I
have Java and like that does lots of
threads and surely in this era of
multi-core computing like you have a
good way of using more than one cpu core
I mean obviously and you know we
probably did ourselves a disservice a
lot of times in when descriptions of
node we would say oh it's more scalable
like we would throw this scalable word
out and add that was probably a mistake
it's at best misleading and at worst
totally wrong node doesn't do anything
about scalability all it does is those
three things it's very good performance
on a single CPU core it's easier to hold
open a lot of connections and you get to
write all your programs in JavaScript so
that's cool because you know event loops
are good they maximize the efficiency of
your resources and what we've always
been saying is okay listen if you run
out of one cpu like you really you got
this amazing benefit of being very
efficient on that cpu you're out just
get more node processes and they can be
on the same computer they can be on a
different computer but because we have
this amazing networking stack it's
really cheap to talk to other node
processes so like don't worry about it
like just get more node processes and
you know stop computing prime numbers in
JavaScript and so oh and you know by the
way like we've got unix sockets and
we'll do this send ft thing so you can
move file descriptors around and so fine
fine fine like on one computer like
we'll make it a little bit easier for
you to to sort of get a whole bunch of
no processes but still like event you
know get more node processes that's
that's the way to go unfortunately even
debugging a single note process is very
hard there are some tools for this there
is no to inspector which is super
awesome and if you're never using note
inspector
like write that down go check it out it
is awesome it's the the webkit you know
the dev tools you can plug it into note
it's it's super cool but even with a
great tool like note inspector like
debugging an actual server especially
like while it's running sort of
Impractical like you can't really sort
of step from asynccallback to other
asynccallback like you'd like to and
frankly if you have to stop it your
server stops working and it might not
actually be doing the same things if you
stopped it you know other people are
talking to it you're talking you making
outgoing connections those may timeout
or different states may be arrived at
and pausing a process is not always a
viable debugging node so man that's
really hard there's also a sort of a
command line e version of the same thing
in node if you like to do it that way
but still the same fundamental problem
like if you stop it then your server
stops working and that may actually not
reproduce the state that you're trying
to debug so you can do what most people
do which what I do which is you just log
a lot you're right all kinds of log
statements on on all sorts of things but
but remember remember you get all these
amazing benefits it's very efficient and
liqueur and you get to write it in
JavaScript and lots of connections and
all that so like don't give up hope like
there's a reason that we're all here
like it's cool but it's just this
debugging is kind of hard it's it's it
may be ugly but I mean you know you can
sort of you can sort of do it do
something with that so anyway like
here's what you usually start out with
like you start out and you're building
your you're building your note app and
you've got like you've got like one node
process and you know it's probably
talking to some kind of database and and
you're in this world I just talked about
a minute ago where you're like okay okay
sometimes it's complicated but like we
can figure it out we'll add a bunch of
logging and you know will will will
solve our bugs that way but then like
you you get some more you know you get
cluster or you get whatever you know
some way of getting a bunch more on
nodes on the same on the same machine
and then like okay it's getting a little
harder but maybe you get more clever law
and you figure out some way to filter it
down or whatever and and that's pretty
cool but then like man somewhere right
around here where you're like I guess we
need more computers and I got two
different kinds of places we're keeping
your data you maybe have like a Redis or
a memcache if you're someone other than
me and then like you know probably want
a real database in there too and like
jeez like everything's talking to
everything and like there are there are
multiple different states that things
can get into because you have all these
moving parts and man it's it's starting
to get really complicated now but then
like you're successful so like you're
getting a lot of traffic and you're
starting to have to separate your
components and what you know a pool of
identical node processes running out
three machines behind a single load
balancer starts to not cut it in like
holy crap now you've got like two steps
through two differently you know step
through two different load balancers and
different parts of your application or
running in different clusters all over
the place all these things are like yet
have this state that accumulates his new
traffic comes into it and wow like if
you thought debugging like a single node
process was hard like try getting like
something like this and it is a
challenge so as you might imagine so the
thing is like you may be thinking
yourself well look I'm a responsible
adult I have written a ton of tests and
I I test all my code and I've got a dev
environment you know and I got it I got
that all set up and you know and I got a
staging environment and I do i do I can
do my homework you know like I I read
all the best practices and I practice
various kinds of something driven
development behavior and and what have
you and so you your development is I
mean you're on it but the thing is like
you you can never exactly account for
all the differences like sure you may
build a dev environment but like are you
really going to have as many nodes in
your dev environment as you have in
production like are you really going to
commit that kind of hardware budget to
just so you can have the exact same
setup in dev I mean
not you're probably going to have like
one or two computers and you're going to
run a smaller version of your of your
whole set up there and yeah you meet you
may like simulate some load but like
you're never going to be able to
simulate like a real actual live
customer traffic like you'll blast some
kind of synthetic pattern of something
that seems reasonable and it's probably
the best you can do but like it's not
what happens when you go into production
there there's just no way to recreate
all of the conditions that a complicated
system like this can get into but we're
in a laboratory environment I mean I
don't know I guess I shouldn't say no
way but it's impractical from a cost
standpoint like you're just not going to
do it you're going to try it out you're
going to write your tests you can do a
simple low test and you can be like I
get good it seems like it works it works
when I try it it works from other people
try it throw it out there and see what
happens I mean I'm not saying that this
is bad i mean what else you gonna do
like you don't have time to build this
sort of perfect thing so anyway it's not
like these issues are unique to note
like this is a fundamental issue with
horizontal scaling systems in general
like you start running processes on
different computers that are all trying
to do the same thing and you add all
these moving parts like it doesn't
matter what environment it's written in
I mean it's can be Python processes or
or whatever like as soon as you start
having components on all these different
machines like it gets crazy the thing
that's I think uniquely note about this
is we have a few more moving parts
because we can only ever use one
processor so it forces you to confront
these issues when like maybe sooner than
you would need to otherwise I mean at
the end of the day it's probably a good
idea that we all confront them because
you know we all want to go big and have
gigantic traffic loads so like you just
because of that single CPU like you're
gonna have a lot of note instances so
this is going to come up and so I also I
don't want to give the idea like I'm
somehow like the world's expert on
building like scalable back-end systems
like there are people who have been
doing this for a lot longer than I have
but I just happen to have fought a
battle with this
for the past couple of months and so you
know much like Xena the warrior princess
these ideas are are forged in the heat
of battle so I mean uh like I have some
suggestions for like a couple of like
basic things that you want to do and you
know md you talked about these a little
bit like you know you want to you want
to get some good stats you want to use
that use that metrics thing like totally
do that log everything that you can
afford to log aggregate your logs like
you're going to want to do all this
stuff but um there's sort of there's
there's one aspect of you know building
these building a big cluster like this
that i don't hear people talking about
too much and it's a pretty neat tool and
it's something that we get to do we get
to do i say because we're doing this in
javascript we have a dynamic language
that can be fed new code on the fly so
like a problem a problem you have is you
run into some situation you like them it
seems to be weird this weird thing
happens like I'm not exactly sure how to
reproduce it but let's put some logging
around like you know before it happens
and after and we'll when it happens
again we'll look the logs and we'll see
we can figure out like what might have
caused that well like in order to do
that you have to push new code like you
have to add some new JavaScript you know
restart your thing you know you'll
hopefully have some clever way of doing
it so your users don't even notice but
still you have to like restart that
process and as soon as you restart the
process you initialize the state and
much of these bugs in my experience that
are really hard to track down are a
problem of sort of accumulated state in
this distributed environment that is
really like if you knew how to reproduce
it like you just do it on your laptop
but like there are problems because you
don't know how to reproduce them you
don't even know what causes them and
you're trying to track them down and so
like restarting your process to add
logging undoes the thing that caused it
in the first place so it kind of sucks
to have to just add you know restart to
add logging every time so anyway what
you can do that's pretty interesting is
you can just change your program you can
change your program on the fly as it's
running without restarting it
so I know that that sounds crazy but
when it is but I mean it's pretty cool
so what you can do is use this thing
called the repple that the read eval
print loop it's it's a way that you can
run more JavaScript on the fly in your
server so I've got a example of a server
that is modifiable and let me just get
that going here why is not that exiting
come on macbook there we go
now I'm gonna do and Hawkwind on over
here I'll cheese time to mirror
okay great
so let's just say you have a program
well that's pretty big I hope you can
see that so I wrote this little web
server it's this stupid simple example
but um it shows you how you can use a
rebel to to sort of turn on a feature in
a server that is not on all the time but
it's sort of sitting there waiting to be
turned on and then later you can turn it
off so an example of why you might want
to do this is you may want to turn on
like special tracing if something
matches a filter you know like a regular
expression of the user you know log all
the things that this user does or log
all things from this IP address or you
know something like that just some thing
that you want to do that you don't
always want to do but you don't know
that you want to do it until it's too
late and you would have to reach out the
process so so here's a really simple
little web server and let me show that
in a second but the kind of new new to
some people part is this rebel server so
this opens it listens on a unix socket
which is you know shows up as like a
special file in your file system you can
connect into it you can use a thing
called so cat you can make it a listen
on the network socket too if you want
but if you do it is a eunuch socket then
you're sure that you can only get to it
while with access from the local file
you know from the local computer so when
you you get this rebel started you
connect up to it you can just run java
script commands and the things that are
in your in the scope of this repple you
can't have to initialize it with this
context thing so I make a little object
and you can just sort of hang stuff off
it and so we made this little mjr object
and we stick it in the context and then
from the repple you can see anything
that's on smjr object so a little later
you know we have this counter and then
I've got a little a special handler here
called on rack and in the HTTP server
let's take a look at that every request
that comes in it checks to see if this
on rack is set to a function if it is
wrap it in a try-catch so you don't blow
up your web server if that thing screws
up and run it with with
a request and response object I just you
know super super simple example and so
if we run that let's just kill run that
a second oh and you probably can't see
that can you that's too bad about this
one
okay oh come on do I have to do this to
get it to override the colors okay so
we've got our server here and it's
waiting for requests and you can sort of
you can see we hit it like that we get
this little we get the Scylla Jason
thing and okay great well you know
that's that's fine it's been
incrementing the the counter every time
we hit the request so we can talk to
this there's the socket here and this
little special file here and you can
talk to it with this thing called so cat
and so now we can dump that that that
mjr object we just type it in let's like
the current value of that has has these
things on it so you can run you know any
JavaScript your leg if you haven't
played with the repple like you totally
showed its it's amazing but so here we
can we can actually change one of these
node processes and like make it do
something else without taking it down so
we can set MJ r dot on rec equals MJ r
dot log wreck and then we have to go
curl that again so server is still up
and oh I made it throw an exception just
to show you that you needed to forgot to
put that back go back here they put the
hell yeah it's down here yeah I wanted
to see I wanted to make sure that if
that thing through that it wouldn't take
down the server or get you know screwed
up in any way so it does all right I
guess I should have tested that anyway
now I am actually going to restart the
server because it has to reread that
value that with no exception in it
anymore anyway so you get the idea like
you can you can modify your running
server I mean obviously you'd want to do
this in a more sophisticated way but
this this repple tool is a it's it's an
essential way of tracking down these
these crazy things that have accumulated
stage because of course you can also
just start poking around in objects you
just have to expose them to the repple
in advance like make
sure that you expose anything you know
most of where your app stores things all
the state you're going to want to look
at make sure it's exposed to the repple
because you never know like what you're
going to need later and you can when
weird things are happening you can bring
it up and you can just poke around and
just see what's going on in there anyway
that's all I have thanks
any questions so you got a cluster
sure something Thanks and something uh
something bizarre is happening how do
you on some requests how do you narrow
it down to one of the one process on one
machine too many techniques for that
yeah I mean it sort of depends on how
you found the problem to begin with I
mean what what we do is you know we have
the logs are aggregated and they're all
kind of stamped with all that
information so that the way in which you
would notice that there was a problem
was someone you know some log line came
through that's like this is weird and it
has the ID of the node that generated
that that bad thing and you can sort of
i think it's i think it's important by
the way when you get your logs
aggregated that you can see a unified
timeline so you have like you know 100
processes that are all kind of doing
stuff they'll if they all can feed into
at least a view you can filter it down
to a view where it's like node one did
this then no two did this you know like
that because almost always there's some
kind of weird interaction that you that
the order is actually important you know
like the timestamp in the node in order
is it's pretty important I mean I don't
know did that answer your question over
here on your right so besides debugging
a large cluster can you comment a little
bit about just performance stability and
what it's like to operate a large node
cluster I am sorry I can't really hear
that there's I really wait echo in here
that's making it hard for me to come can
you comment a little bit about stability
and what it's like to operate a large
node cluster compared to other sask
ability like what what aspect of
stability um memory do you find that
note instances crashed you have to
restart them periodically that kind of
thing um yeah that's um that's been
somewhat of an exciting adventure node
it generally is really really good but
it's very new and sometimes you find
rough edges and you know they're things
that don't show up under testing that
only show up with real live production
traffic
that are weird yeah but I mean generally
speaking like I'm still very optimistic
i mean note is very very fast and the
the programming model i think is is
worth putting up with sort of these
rough edges just to get all of that
other awesome stuff but I mean you know
generally speaking like it's no more
buggy than any way of any other way you
would write some server process like
writing server processes izzy is
difficult stuff you don't get to reload
your you know like a web page can leak
some memory or whatever but chances are
you're going to leave that page anyway
and it all gets cleaned up but a server
has to run for a long time and so
managing the resources in a long-running
process it's a challenge in any language
I mean I I think note does a pretty good
job I think javascript is a pretty good
choice the garbage collection say what
you will about it but it saves you from
from a lot of messes in in a
long-running process all right so um
we've been using a repeal to debug very
complex note systems as well and one of
the very cool tricks that I I found was
that you can actually make a little bit
of code that wraps a function and just
passes it through because all the
modules are global you can very easily
target a particular export of a module
and wrap it in a sort of like event call
back so then you can hook runtime all
these functions that you have in your
note code right which is really cool for
debugging because then you don't have to
be so much upfront with your assumptions
about what you exposed to the repple
because the module space is global you
can inspect it yeah yeah yeah I mean
managing your access to the to the
repple scope is pretty crucial like like
somehow you need to get everything in
there that you're going to need that you
think you might need later just you know
simply exposing it in there is nearly no
overhead but if you don't have a handle
to it you'll you will be sorry and yeah
except mean exposing the whole module
scope like great you get even access to
even more stuff that way Matt thank you
very much you're welcome