you
I will talk to you guys about getting
rid of the keyboard so basically this
here is my view of the world all right I
don't like keyboards much keyboards have
got too many keys keyboard means i have
to like stand over here and type on my
machine i have to be like this close to
the screen when i play with a keyboard i
have to have a flat surface to rest the
keyboard i kind of balance it on my knee
which is a bit annoying and the worst
thing about keyboards is they tend to
come with a mouse don't like my see that
and when you want to play games you want
to be relaxed right you want to have fun
you don't really want to sit like
slouched over your desk and like we got
loose little mouse and play the keys
like that you know you want you want to
lean back you want to be on your couch
you want to be on a beanbag so just to
like reinforce this message this is my
view of the world keyboards are good no
wait here the other way around keyboards
are bad game pads are good but given
this is jamias confirm were all
JavaScript developers we are mostly
stuck in the browser and in the browser
we are mostly stuck with the old
keyboard mouse combination that's the
only thing the browser kind of exposures
to us and yes some of us might play with
node and like have access to everything
that the operating system can offer but
that's not too many of us some of us
might you know kind of start thinking a
little about about touch events cuz that
working on mobile devices and you know
they got no keyboards no mouse or at
least no mouse and and they kind of use
the finger like a sort of substitute
mouse but what I want to be talking
about is this like brand new and quite
exciting bit of technology that's going
to let you step away from your computer
step away from the keyboard and start
using one of these things and it's
called the gamepad API and I'm very sad
about it so the gamepad API is a tiny
little new thing a new spec that
basically will expose any game
controller that the operating system
wrecking
Isis through to your browser it came out
I think the first browser that had it
was chrome last year in August last year
chrome 21 came out and it had support
for the gamepad API since then it's
moved out of experimental it's now
implemented in chrome it's implemented
in Firefox it is a w3c working draft
which means that it still has a good way
to go before become standard but it's
far enough along that it's no longer
just experimental it's something is
going to happen we're going to see it
it's going to happen and what you get
out of the gamepad object basically
looks a bit like this excuse me so it's
got just a few properties really it's
got an ID that identify it my controller
here is saying I'm a standard gamepad
from this vendor it's this product I'm
sure there's a list of those vendor and
product code somewhere I couldn't find
it then it's got an index you can
actually hook up multiple gamepads your
browser will recognize multiple gamepad
so you know if I could clone myself and
the controller I could like play against
myself on the other side of the machine
it's got a time stamp which tells you
something about when it was last updated
and then the rest is basic telling you
what state to the gamepad is it's got
four axes which corresponds to the
sticks and it's got an array of 17
buttons which is basically everything
else and it's probably a little bit
easier to just visualize it like this so
the buttons you can push the buttons
lots of buttons you can push multiple
buttons at the same time it'll register
that you also got access to these
control buttons in the middle and with
the sticks you can sort of move things
up and down back and forth you can use
both sticks and
it's really actually quite easy to set
up if you have quick look at some code
here it's not big enough can you see it
yep cool so the first step is to get the
connection to the gamepad this is
currently not a standard so it's not
currently implemented exactly the same
in oh hang on a skip the slide in though
does that skipped forward backwards a
little bit it's a little bit of a bug
anyway let's have a little bit of a look
at browser compatibility before we move
to the actual code itself so I was
saying this is not quite standard yet
it's a little bit flaky and safari and
Internet Explorer I are both just out of
the picture on this they don't have it
implemented from what I've seen there's
no immediate plans to implement any of
it it's a matrix here because it's not
just the browser the online operating
system has to have support for the
device that you're plugging in with
keyboards it's almost ubiquitous you
can't really you don't really have
keyboards anymore that you need to
install drivers for you know back in the
day when you bought a new fancy keyboard
you actually had to install the driver
for it now the operating systems just
like yeah I know that thing it's got a
lot of buttons on it with these things
we're not quite there yet windows is
actually the system that recognizes the
most amount of gaming devices basically
because Windows is the primary gaming
platform for pc it's bit sad OSX as you
may have been able to tell from the
slightly delayed president's
presentation is a bit wobbly and kind of
flaky this controller here is using some
xbox controller driver that some guy I
hacked in his basement about two years
ago and haven't really bothered with
sins and that was the best thing I could
find to hook an xbox controller up to
the OS X so if you think of doing this
maybe windows this is the way to go
the support is about as good in Chrome
as it is in Firefox there's a lot of
different implications which will have a
look at in in a second on Linux there's
been some issues with buttons being
mapped wrong so you know you press a and
you get and y or your wiggle one
joystick and it registers and the other
one but yeah you best the best that is
windows with chrome or firefox so if you
go to step one here of getting the
connected gamepad like I said the
implementation is not locked down yet
the specs s that you need to expose to
events a connected event in a disconnect
event and this is how Firefox dusting
right it adds an event Lisa and license
to the Kinect event then you add a
handle to it and you get the gamepad
object off the event in chrome you have
to do it slightly differently in chrome
you have to ask a navigator object for
your game pads and then it'll be the
first game pad in that array hopefully
if you have more than one game pad
you'll have multiple game pats there the
second step is to start scheduling
polling for your gamepad so it doesn't
actually give you any vents when
anything's pressed right when you push a
button nothing really happens except
that the state changes the time step up
that time stamp updates but you have to
pull it and a good way of doing this is
requestanimationframe happily the same
browsers that support animation frames
are also supporting gamepad API so you
won't have any problems there and for
those who don't know what a animation
frame is it's basically their browser
running a loop for you and forcing that
loop when your tab loses focus which is
nice other ways you kind of chew through
battery like it's going out of fashion
slightly slightly different in chrome
and firefox here in chrome you just ask
the window for an animation frame and in
firefox it's a moss request guess they
want to be special so step three profit
this is where basically you check the
time stamping as a previous time step if
that time stamp has been updated that
means that the controller changed the
state has changed something has been
pushed and so yeah you can now do some
stuff whatever you want to do with those
events bit flaky so this isn't this
isn't just a gimmick though right this
isn't just something that were like muck
about and make little dots move across
the screen this is my friend Magda don't
know if anyone reads Japanese here Jed
reads Japanese is here anyway this this
is my friend magna from a hiking trip we
took last year she's holding up this
piece of paper saying you know very
politely requesting that we do not walk
on the marked paths because on the mark
paths there are beers and they will eat
us so she's Australian and she's the
kind of girl that you know she attracts
dangerous animals and being Australian
and living in Australian and being like
an animal a dangerous animal attractor
is really bad idea so about ten years
ago she got her are mostly chewed off by
a shark and that kind of kills your
gaming life kiss you're stuck with like
one left arm which is not your primary
hand and then this kind of like slightly
wobbly right down that you can't really
use for much um and suddenly you can
normally play any first-person shooters
whatsoever alright they all require you
to have like two hands on the keyboard
mouse you know clicking fast and there's
all these games that you can't
she can't play also because the
controllers aren't mapped out you can't
you can't change the controls around you
just you just stuck with whatever the
game developer gave you there's a bunch
of things that has been done to actually
improve accessibility for people with
some sort of disabled disablement or
disability and a lot of these things
actually came out after the wars in Iraq
and Afghanistan started happening people
soldiers mostly 18 to 35 year olds males
white not too much disposable income
your primary gaming demographic they
came home with bits missing and so I
suddenly became like a bit sexy to do
all these things to like help people
with disabilities you know do more
gaming and stuff but for those of us
we've been building games in the browser
just we haven't been doing this at all
right and this is something that that is
actually quite easy to change I showed
you how to set up with the gamepad
before I showed you how to start just
listening to the gamepad or you can
quite easily do it's actually to start
doing stuff like this all right you can
start playing games oh I'm really bad at
it first when I'm also talking we can
start playing game this is this is
actually just an open-source JavaScript
imitation Tetris and all I've done is
like tape get just it's exposed to the
events so it exposes the methods that
you need to call to you know move
something a turn something and so i just
added a little bit of gamepad api
goodness do this and i cannot start
playing this with one hand you couldn't
do that before this is Tetris it's got
all four controls right it's got right
left turn down and those four controls
you can find out with like a finger
missing even but they were mapped to
three keys on that side of the keyboard
and one key on that side of the keyboard
all right the other good thing about
this is they give
one hand need like Jesus if you have the
second hand and it's really quite
straightforward to to hook up to I've
done the same thing with the
presentation framework that I'm using
here using something called bespoke j/s
which spaces itself on on touch events
and key events and it's quite easy right
because again it exposes the methods
that you need to cause all you need to
do is like put some little gamepad API
script in there and call tetras right or
Tetris left you know you might notice
that I'm using thresholds instead of
discrete values and that bit of co there
that's because the values you get from
these are sometimes a little bit dirty
so with the access for example it's a
floating point number when you get it
back and even if it's like completely
neutral like now I'm not touching
anything you'll still say that it's like
zero point zero zero one zero zero
because these things are still plastic
and not that precise but it's not just
about you know it's not just about games
and so just but presentation framework
game pads are part of something that we
can we can start thinking more about how
we let users interact with the things
that we built we're talking about these
things at the moment we're doing we're
doing responsive design right we know
that some devices are sure then some are
wide and some at all sometimes we have a
lot of screen space sometimes given
little so we gave responsive design
that's cool and we go progressive
enhancement because we know that some
browsers a and some rails are great
something some browsers have really
exciting features and some browsers
don't really have features and I think
this is one of those things that should
feed into that philosophy a little bit
right we need some sort of like
progressive enhancement for input
devices because it's really not that
hard to basically set up a PlayStation
drum pad hook it up it's a gamepad hook
it up to your browser
and then start playing the newspaper all
right go left article right article you
know use the pedal to scroll get a
workout with your breakfast or you know
allow people to remap there is some
single thing that they do every way they
interact with your silly little blog so
that they can use whatever input device
they want to we're going to get more of
this and I think it's going to be really
really exciting and I think you should
start playing with it today thank you
all right all right I think we can open
up for some questions okay Oh again
you're gonna make me do this like for
every talk aren't you you first all
right Remy Thanks um do you have any
idea what the like handheld console
support is like for the gamepad API II
like the d/s has a gamepad that has a
browser yeah do can you comment on
whether any way any of them have the
gamepad API and whether they may use
that kind of thing and or if it just
defaults to the mouse I'm assuming most
than the old ones to force the mouse but
I wonder if any of them actually support
the gamepad API in the first place
things like the des are natively built
to to work with the buttons that are
there I don't think they use the gamepad
API it's not ready yet I think they use
some sort of Shem that they already have
but I'm not sure all right next question
hi there as you're based in the UK um
over here hey hi and have you had any
feelings with special effect who are
based up in the Midlands of the UK
because they deal a lot with interfacing
for disability or would you be
interested in maybe talking to them at
some point in the future I'm often gonna
be super cool to talk to them I hadn't
really thought about this until I found
myself at like three friends who's all
short one arm and they're all gamers or
maybe the exception if my grandmother
she's more of a biped what's that but
yeah that'd be really cool I'll take you
out the details and said mighty cool so
we've got time for another question
anybody else know ok well 10 my thirties
jet got it ok sort of in the middle on
it he's closer I got it okay Jed
prancing through the audience well
there's just more about the movement of
these input devices because I don't
really see keyboards are much too
fenton game pets and I see the
tendencies are that the input devices
we're using now are more the input
devices we are born with with touch and
movement with the leap motion and always
control it's still early stages but is
this something you believe that will be
like it may be interesting for gamers on
an xbox that they can navigate your blog
but for most people is it really useful
like and with the tendencies so I see
the gamepad API as it stands now it's
it's a beginning I think what we're
going to get is basically a future where
there are multiple manifold ways of
interacting with the browser and that
you'll be able to hook up you know
motion controller typical gamepads
gamepads that you'll wave around just
your hands leap motion all that sort of
stuff and I think it's now that we need
to start thinking about that kind of
progressive enhancement off of the way
we deal with input devices so no I don't
think damn pads are going to be like the
entire future of the interweb but I
think it's one of the things that's
really exciting right now and it points
in a direction that is really exciting
as well okay everybody give a round of
applause for an X thank you
you