hi seems cool yeah so I've been giving a
lot of introduction talks to note in the
last couple months and its really nice
to come to Jas Compton and be able to
make some small assumption about people
here knowing what note is and what it
does so I'm going to take the
opportunity to give you some things in
note that are less than perfect and that
need to be done and to hopefully
encourage some of you to contribute to
the project and work on these problems I
think that they're all kind of fun and
there's a lot of stuff to do so yes note
is gaining popularity it's really it's
really interesting and fun and I think
that you know it it actually has a
chance of becoming a real application
platform and we should work very hard to
try to make that the case or at least
I'm going to so yeah I hope that this
encourages somebody to work on some
stuff in note so problem one is the ssl
support in in node is is lacking and its
really unacceptable SSL is very much
an infrastructural protocol you almost
can't do internet without it and maybe
this wasn't the case a couple of years
ago but these days with more and more
websites defaulting to to SSL it really
needs to be done correctly and currently
Note has some bindings to openssl but
their buggy and they're incomplete and
they're not implemented in the best way
they're very much tied too tight into
the socket code and should be separated
a bit and all this makes for something
that is ultimately unusable and so so
this is really not acceptable and so I
think probably the most important
problem that needs to be done with note
is is that we need to have really good
support for for client and server ssl
with all these cool features you know
there there's a lot of talk about how to
speed up you know that the handshake
process and some of the new features and
that you can do with with SSL and I
think that you know we're kind of
starting from scratch with note and so
we might want to take this opportunity
to see how far we can we can go forward
with this can can we actually you know
implement a snap start sort of thing
even if openssl doesn't actually support
it yet
the second most important problem is the
fact that node is very much focused on
performance and a lot of thought goes
into how to make things as fast as
possible yet more or less we're
developing blindly so that we don't have
a continuous integration system for
performance tests there's been some work
done in this area to kind of get a
website up and have built bots that
produce graphs but there was too much
noise in the graphs and the the
benchmarks weren't weren't so effective
and build BOTS not it's kind of an
external project from note itself but
it's really important we need to know
when we make changes if it's affecting a
certain part of the system so at the
moment really the only thing that that's
being tested very often is the HGP hello
world server which is not really
important but basically anybody who
comes to note and tries it out is going
to open it up in write a HelloWorld
server in and see how fast is and you
know stupidly based their decision off
of that so we should address that point
if and I mean a hello world server does
exercise a lot of code but there's other
issues for example startup time it's
currently something like 40 milliseconds
on my laptop on the palm device it's
more than a second so this stuff needs
to be considered and we need to know
that when changes are being done that
they're not affecting performance
note introduces kind of some new ideas
about programming servers not not
necessarily new but takes them to an
extreme level and so if you've done
something with node you might realize
that you get into this situation pretty
often where an event is triggered and
you'll get an exception and you'll see
your stack trace and it's very small
because you're you're constantly killing
your it's a single step so you're
constantly trashing it all the time
every every every event you're you throw
it away and so you get very little
context into where errors are coming
from so like this example you have to
set timeouts and you don't know
beforehand which one necessarily is
going to execute the function f but one
of them is I mean this is very contrived
but you could you can imagine and you've
probably experienced situations where
two different events can lead to a
certain function and you need to know
where it originated from to solve the
problem how do you deal with this when
one solution of course is is some sort
of green thread co routine continued
continuation passing thing I don't want
to go into that at the moment but note
is not going to do that so right you
might get an error like this which you
know references the fact that there is a
neck section throne but doesn't actually
tell you from which set time outfit came
from so it's really hard to debug how
can we solve this problem it's not like
you know written into the laws of
physics that you need co routines to
solve this problem
perhaps we can think of something else
what if we limit ourselves to this to
this single stack world can we think of
some other ways of solving this problem
maybe every time you set up a new event
like startup set timeout if you make a
link to the previous event that created
that thing and you have this kind of
list of things that you could walk back
through history to find out where it
came from of course there's other things
that can be done with debugging v8 has
this really nice tcp server that that it
can start up and you can connect to it
and write a little JSON protocol between
the node process and your debugger and
kind of get information set set
breakpoints step through the execution
so you can do this currently with note
you do know dash dash debug and it will
start the server but it would be nice to
be able to turn this on dynamically so
maybe by sending the process of signal
it would start this TCP server and then
you could connect to it and and do stuff
and the v8 has has this live edit
feature which allows you to actually
change the running code and so I think
for a lot of people who are doing
frameworks on top of note that this
would be a really useful thing that you
could run your application at a normal
speed and then turn on this debugger
send the changes to the code change
change the send the diffs to to what
you've changed in the code and
disconnected and have it still running
but at a normal speed it would be nice
to
hit the process with a signal and get
some sort of heat profile or CPU profile
turns out and note one of the things
that we learned from from doing the node
knockout contest was there's often
memory leaks and in node programs it's
it's hard to debug where these leaks in
your JavaScript objects are coming from
it would be nice to be able to just kind
of hit your running server and get a
heat profile dtrace proked Joanne
recently hired brian Cantrell who's the
one of the creators of DTrace and so we
have plans to put these probes in as
much as possible so would be really nice
to get them into function calls so that
you could actually you know get stack
traces on CC where certain things
originated from with respect to to
JavaScript function calls but these
things seem hard it seems that that
inspecting the the VA keep and finding
out looking inspecting these objects is
probably going to be difficult so anyway
event emitter firing possibly some
things on the thread pool just event
everywhere so that we can we can kind of
poke at these processes and see what
they're doing and be able to inspect
note processes the fourth most important
problem is windows which almost nobody
cares about except for everybody which
is a bit unfortunate i certainly don't
care about windows i just would like to
run on windows so currently we have a
cig wind fort which is as far as i'm
concerned fine but windows people tell
me that windows people don't like that
and so it would be nice to have a native
windows port I'm it is a significant
user base and it's really you can't just
ignore it you have to have some story
there and for the moment cygwin is
reasonable but I think having a native
like an actual real native windows
program that ran well would be very
beneficial to a lot of people there's no
reason that we can't be doing windows
GUI apps with note so it's just that it
seems like it's going to be very hard
note is very much a UNIX program and not
a windows program and so in particular
the the event loop abstraction library
that note uses Libby V doesn't doesn't
support Windows very well it seems like
this can be dealt with but it's going to
really require some effort and it
requires somebody who's very familiar
with with windows system programming so
this is definitely not something that's
going to come from me but I hope that
somebody cares enough about it to sit
down and and do the work
it would be really nice to supposedly
Windows has a very fast event
notification system these IO completion
ports it would be nice to be able to use
those instead of select supposedly live
event to which is another event loop
abstraction library does this correctly
so one possibility is to actually crane
lift note off of Libby V and on to live
event to which sounds really painful and
Libby v's just so cute and like you just
really wouldn't actually want to do that
but it is nice that that live event to
is is going through great lengths to be
very compatible with windows so maybe
it's worth doing it would be a lot of
work but maybe you don't even care about
performance on windows too much maybe
maybe note could be I mean nobody's
really going to be running servers on
windows anyway so perhaps perhaps select
as okay
v8 has a has a 1 gigabyte heap
limitation on x64 just recently
discovered so this is of course a fairly
large problem I don't think we can
expect that processes are going to be
under 1 gig of memory so this needs to
be addressed one gig is a decent size 44
program so I I don't think we're
necessarily going to be bouncing against
that immediately but if people start
developing larger and larger frameworks
and you know maybe they're they're doing
a little in-memory database or something
like that you would definitely not want
this to be a restriction yeah
unfortunately v8 doesn't care so much
about this because websites don't get
that big so this this is some work that
will have to be done it's getting more
and more technical if as we go along so
I apologize copying strings out of v8
seems to be a problem so so if you do a
little benchmark where you send a larger
and larger strings as a response notes
performance degradation with respect to
other dynamic language what web servers
so clearly we're doing something very
wrong and I think the the problem is
that basically we're doing two copies we
have to copy the string out of v8 seep
into some external buffer and then copy
it into the kernel or to the device or
whatever whereas the other people are
actually actually accessing the string
in the Ruby heap itself so it some
needs to be done here at least for
certain cases for example JSON dumps if
we could just be able to push those to a
socket a lot quicker removing one of
these these copies there I think it
would be very beneficial also not
non-trivial to solve this so the current
mechanism and note for for writing two
sockets is every time you call socket
dot right or if you're in a web server
you you say response dot right it maps
to the same thing is that it actually
execute the right sis call in line in
that in that function and it seems that
this is not the appropriate design I
think what needs to happen is I mean
what ends up happening is is that you
call write a bunch of times in one
iteration of the event loop and you end
up with small packets being pushed out
which is not what you want you want them
to be bunched up because within one
iteration of the event loop it's very
very quick right that these rights need
to be buffered into at the end up until
you go to select or a pole or whatever
they need to be buffered up and then
sent out and one dumped so node has this
this watch file thing which people
probably have used and on Linux it's
really great because it actually uses
that I notify stuff and so you actually
get an event from the colonel to to tell
you when when a file has changed but on
other operating systems it's just doing
a stat over and over again with some
interval between which is expensive and
it actually is doing this stat
synchronously in the main threat of
note so of course if if you're if you're
start watching a file on say and NFS
file system then that can block for an
arbitrary amount of time in the main
event so this is really not a good thing
other operating systems have ways of
getting events from the colonel it's not
the same as I notify but there there are
ways to do this on on OS X so this is a
bit of work but not too difficult I
think I think the main problem is that
that watch file references a path and
the other event notification systems
reference file descriptors so yeah we
either have to change the interface or
massage it a little bit into into
working so node has this this little
thread pool called Libby i/o which just
has a bunch of P threads and you kind of
send it little system calls to do things
that things that would block right if
you if you have to do a get address info
you send it to that thread pool and it
blocks fine but you know it does it in a
thread and your your main thread can
keep going and then you get notified
back on certain systems you do actually
have internal asynchronous i/o and so
you don't actually need to do this this
thread pool thing in user space so it
would be nice if if Libby io actually
used these the appropriate things on on
different systems so there those are my
my nine problems there's a new mailing
list
44 note because the other ones getting a
lot of traffic that's a lot of newbies
and so if you're interested in
development you should you should join
this and if you're interested in solving
any of these problems of course email me
and we can we can discuss it but yeah
it's very much encouraged okay so this
is mostly the end of my talk I also want
to announce that joint is is having a
new release of our noge service which we
did for the node knockout and so people
at this contest can can go to n.o de and
get a smart machine to deployed no taps
to this is not our final version but
another release of it so if you go to
n.o de you can register for an account
and there's some curl commands to do
because I in the end it's some rest api
you don't have to memorize these
commands right here but um go to noge
and you can get an account and and try
to push a a note app up to it and
hopefully in the next two months or so i
think we'll have an actual release that
we will charge money for and will be
open to the public so yes so sorry for
the very technical talk I hope I didn't
or anybody but are there any questions
about anything related to note yes
so the question is should i will I be
bundling a package manager with note and
the answer is no note is more or less
how it will be now that not much more
will go into it and I think it's
important to keep it small and so of
course there's a lot of work to do I've
just laid it all out but it's not
necessarily you know building a package
manager or doing the these library or
you know building a web framework I mean
the API that we have now is more you
know we might add a couple of things
here and there but but more or less this
is what it will be not my goal but the
person behind Michael that yes the the
heat profiling is already in v8
no originally had an the question is
about blocking versus async required
note originally had an async require but
I was convinced by the common J's people
to change it in the name of common Jas
so it will be synchronous sorry I
couldn't hear you it the asynchronous
require has always been there it was
recently removed there will be no hay
synchronous require Michael
but buffers are outside of VA so just v8
objects right so if you're doing like a
some sort of database you should
probably allocate a very large buffer
and do that instead of a big JavaScript
array or some other questions okay well