usually I talk about my latest node
library and what it does and show it off
and do some live coding but today I
thought I'd do something a little
different a a question that I've seen
come up a lot with people who are
working with either lots of Io and the
browser or on server side JavaScript
wears lots of I oh is that all these
callbacks really get tangled it gets
hard to do so I talk is techniques and
tools for taming tangled twist it turns
up top and yeah so so just a quick recap
I'm sure most of you notice what makes
note fast I i work on node a lot so
that's most of the JavaScript I deal
with but this applies to other things
too so so node never blocks on Io it's
all it's all non block and it's all
callback base which means you don't eat
threads which is awesome because if
you've done systems programming threads
are not free they're expensive but this
also means that you have to handle the
scheduling explicitly through callbacks
with threading the OS does it for you
you can just say I want to read the file
system and no one s done do this and the
OS handle Zelda for you all the
concurrency not so much in JavaScript so
here's just a quick example and this
isn't even the best Ruby but the point
is we have this final new thing that
opens a file that next line will not
execute until that file has been opened
nothing happens and this line equals
file gets that will block until it
actually reads the data from the disk
which could take a lot of CPU cycles and
in the next slide happens and then you
can file close here at the bottom
because you won't get there till you're
done really simple code right because
the OS is doing all the juggling for you
with threads well here's one way to do
this a note so we got we going to open
the file give that a call back when its
open and then nodes ap eyes are a little
lower level it matches the capi is
pretty close so you got to say I want to
read some data up to this many chunks
put it in this buffer it might actually
read that many chunks and so you're
going to then check how many chunks for
it I mean
lights were red and if it's not enough
you got to keep reading you go to these
recursive loops and it's all a sink and
I don't know about you but that's kind
of hard to read it first but that that's
the trade-off so don't worry it's
actually not as bad as it looks if your
house has a fire tornado that's pretty
bad javascript you're okay so do some
tricks to this so I've got six sections
they make a cube and all the pieces make
this cool awesome train yeah all right
this is the tingle twisted train of
thought so the first piece of the train
is lambda first class functions
javascript has first class functions I
know this isn't new to most of you but
in node we have this interesting merge
of communities where you have people
coming from the server side that know
Ruby and PHP and Python and haven't
really dealt with callbacks and then we
have the people from the front end who
know all about callbacks and Ajax but
then hadn't really use JavaScript
against file systems where you have lots
and lots of i/o and so occasionally
people forget that you have all these
neat tricks with functions so just a
quick review javascript is a very simple
business understood language and the
secret is the functions a function is an
object it can be passed around it has a
closure but it's really just something
you can pass around it's not tied to an
object that's not a proper method like
in other languages where it's part of
the class it's it's just some executable
code that has some special properties so
here's just a quick example so I make
this object Lane has named laman Elena
lambda and then one function description
that returns a person named to this name
and you execute this you'll get back a
person named Lena lambda nothing
surprising right so we make another
object called Fred and Fred's
description is the same function as
lanes description but when you read it
you get a person named Fred the functor
exact same function for rain in a
different different scope so we can use
colon apply to specify what this is
and just call lanes description function
with a new object and you'll get back a
person named said the zettabyte it's
really clear right but here's where it
gets people when you start dealing with
events and callbacks if I store this
lame duck description to a variable put
that in some event system and then later
call it a person named undefined but it
was lamed that description i passed in
so i should have lain as this right no
it's not tied to the object it's just a
function and when you start doing lots
of callbacks this bites a lot of people
well this is where closures come in this
is a simple factory method that returns
a function but since name is from the
closure no matter how you call this
function it's going to have the right
name so this is a really important thing
to understand i'm sure most of you
notice quite well but that's the first
technique to doing lots of asynchronous
code is that by sound understanding of
how the language works so my next
section function composition the first
large node project i will wrote was
wheat the engine to how to note it's
it's a pretty interesting blog engine it
sits on top of a rocket repo and
basically uses get sub a subshell just
use git show and use as good as a
database there are no real files
anywhere it just uses get show give me
this file at this revision and there's
some muck down files for articles
there's some HTML and it's it's all in
get but when I wrote this I started
seeing that you got to do these complex
things wrap them in simple api's or
you'll go insane so node has a single
def s read file because it's pretty
common use case that you want to read a
file when its entirety their small files
you don't want to stream it you just say
give me the contents of that file so you
take all these other async operations
and you wrap them in one single API this
is a very useful technique so I'm just
going to quickly go through one way to
implement this so what's going to happen
zero f s open which is a non-blocking
filesystem thing all the arrows with
stars means this call
happens via the event loop you don't
ever explicitly call this when the file
system comes back and it's open it will
then call your on open function which
then will call get chunk because it
wants to start getting some chunks and
then that's going to call FS read and
then FS rate when it gets a chunk is
going to call your on read and that's
going to check if there's bites or not
it's going to loop through till you've
read the whole file so I put the black
borders around these functions that I'm
wrapping so this is just a quick little
utility i made up called wrap if any of
you have done Python this is the
decorator pattern I don't know is their
name for a javascript where you take a
function return a new function with
slightly in your behavior but so you
take your your actual on an open on
whatever callback and this adds error
handling to it because the problem with
async code is you can't use try catch
try catch is tied to a stack and you saw
the errors with the stars every time
that happens you're on a new stack and
you try catch to happen before is long
gone and it won't catch any exceptions
that happen now so if you want your code
to not throw exceptions which in a
server you don't want because then your
entire server goes down and all your
connections are now closed you need to
be careful about routing all these
exceptions to the right place you can
send the user a 500 page or something so
it takes the function note has this
convention that all I'll call backs give
you air and result and so if node gave
you an error pass it through the
callback and if actually colon your code
throws an exception catch that and pass
it to the callback super handy and then
this is just merging buffers we don't
need to go through that but so here's
here's the read frontal it takes the
fault is chunk and then here I've got my
own open on read and they're just
wrapped versions of the functions so
they handled error handling on opens
pretty easy you get the file descriptor
store it and available in the closure
and then call get junk and then I want
all errors to be ready to call back on
read pretty similar file system
I gave me this many bites and those
bites were given to the buffer I had in
my other closure and so if there were no
bites I'm done called the done function
if if it wasn't how many bytes I wanted
or if it's small and a buffer you got to
resize the buffer this is low-level node
buffer stuff but the important thing
here is that I then called get chunk
again and it loops recursively but
you're not going to you're not going to
blow it a step because remember every
time on Reed is called it's a new stack
so you'd have to worry about stack
overflow and the get chunk just
basically allocates a buffer and reads
it from the file and then done closes
the file and then merges all the buffers
and calls person here is your file nice
to do all that for you and wrap it up in
just one call read this phone give me
the data there's the data great pattern
function composition so the second
technique is called back counters since
this all this non blocking code it just
goes straight through you can do stuff
in parallel you can do weights in
parallel you can't do execution and
parallels it's single-threaded it's
JavaScript but you can be waiting for
this file to open while you're waiting
for this database query to come back
while you're waiting for something else
to happen you can do all those weights
in parallel which is great really speeds
it up but the problem is you need to do
things when it's done you need to
continue the logic of your program so
organize it into either serial actions
that maybe we'll run on another or
things going to be done in parallel so
here's a simple example suppose I want
to read two files these files are
completely unrelated and then do
something after they've been read well
how do you do that it's quite simple you
have a counter or some other variable
and each time the on Reed's come back
from those you decrement your counter
and when it reaches zero you know all of
your call backs have done and then you
call the next step so there's simple
counters here's a slightly more complex
example suppose I want to take a
directory of files and I want to read
the contents of all the files in that
directory so we have an unknown number
of things here
there might be 10 files might be a
thousand files so I'm gonna call read
directory which is going to get listing
the files when that comes back I'm going
to then loop over that and fire off a
raid file for each one of those files
and then I wanted a another all going to
call on read and then when all of them
are done it's going to pass the data to
my call back so this is slightly more
complicated but same idea so we call
some filtering out some files either a
County ghost files dot length so the
number of files i'm going to open I got
my counter again and then while I for
each over the files it's opening them
and then when those callbacks come back
document count now one thing to note
here remember this is non blocking so
this for each goes through instantly and
then the files are read from the disk
you got to remember that code never ever
blocks in this non-blocking world and
any tobacco goes straight through but
then once they've all read the count
will be the count will be zero called a
call back with the results here's a
slightly simpler version if you just
want to see count count decrement and
then equals you don't have to use the
minus minus count it's kind of tricky
but if you want really short code works
I mean it's whatever your preference is
I usually just do count minus minus 0
then if count equals 0 it's more
explicit that way but slides you got to
squish the code sometimes so that's
called back counters very handy
technique we do this all the time I
think I think every node library at
there has some implementation of
counters and a helper library that loops
not everything is a call back so call
backs are great the way the way we
talked about them originally when we
dropped promises from node is there's a
distinction you have you have things
that are basically asynchronous
functions they're going to either return
one value or they're going to throw an
error and in synchronous code that's
easy an async code you just give it a
call back and that callback you
eventually gets cold with an error or
value what about things that just happen
on several
x or never happen at all like unclick
events in the browser or on request
events an HTTP server you don't want to
really use plain callbacks for those
because it happened several times I mean
lower level it is JavaScript callback is
a function but it's a slightly higher
abstraction using events so going back
to the rube example ahead of front
suppose you really did want to read the
file line by line that's a useful thing
to do so I had this mythical line reader
thing this is doesn't exist a node and
it gives you this object that has three
events it has a line event that is
emitted every time a line is read from
the file has an end event that is
emitted when the files done and if
there's any errors there's an error
event this is one way to do it there's
lots of other abstractions but the point
is different things are happening and so
you just have various event callbacks
easy as pie libraries to see I need to
use these cool symbols so a lot of this
code as you saw it was kind of long and
hard to write and i've been writing eps
with node for a while and i don't like
writing this over all the time so i made
a i made several libraries my favorite
one is step and it's based on regular
callbacks and it's it's really simple
and it just you can do things in cereal
without nesting your code you can do
things in parallel and group and with
that writing your own counters it does
the counters for you it wraps everything
in try-catch does the routing it's just
a neat thing Chris recently released the
library promised i/o which it wraps the
node AP is in in some promise
abstraction which is a different way to
instead of doing callbacks their
promises so there's lots of ways to do
this there's other libraries too I know
step so that's what I'm going to talk
about so let's take a simple example I
want to load a user now I get that user
from the database I then we'll find some
items about that user so i need to do
some queries against the database and
then when that's done that bottom ones
labeled wrong do something else so you
notice here this there's two events from
the event loop the return from the
database and the other
on the database so to do this in step
you have three steps load user calls DB
get user and then in step this is a call
back to the next step so you don't have
to nest your code that way it stays on
saner when you have long chains of
things to do in cereal so then find
items i'm just going to do some random
query against the database and then
again this that'll pass the area to the
next one notice that i am checking the
air here and thrown it if there's a
problem normally you want to pass it to
some call back throwing and note is
generally a bad idea unless you know
something's going to catch it so just
you know a couple things in order pretty
simple right how about a couple things
in parallel you do that all the time too
suppose I'm rendering a page i need to
load my template from the file system
but what am I data from the database and
then merge the two and render HTML page
super common but I need to know I have
to have the data and the template to be
able to render it I can't do anything
till they're both done so the this
object actually has a function called
parallel which generates callbacks so
every time you need a callback for that
you just call this parallel so I can do
five things in parallel two things in
parallel it'll do them all it'll keep
checking the counters it'll even order
the results for you so no matter what
order these come back when it calls the
next thing I got my results i got my
file contents and if there was an error
in either one i have that error and what
if you want to do several things like we
did before rita directory with several
files so in that case we're going to
read the directory pass the file names
to the next step and this one I don't
know I should probably change the you've
had this really confuses people so this
step group creates a callback generator
so you got to call that once and that
will reserve a slot in the next step and
then for each of your things an FS read
file call group again this is now the
callback generator and that gives each
one of those read files a unique
callback and the contents the next step
will be an array of all the results and
those are actually ordered in the order
you called FS read file not the order
that came back from the file system
because those aren't the same thing
so so you do that we've contents now you
got the contents of all the files this
is slightly less code then doing it in
plain node plain JavaScript but when you
start getting larger programs this gets
a lot saner and this has all day or
handily built in for you so well that
was fast all right questions that I know
a lot of people have questions about
this Lamela enlist in IRC
yeah I mean note is single threaded
execution only one thing happens at a
time ever and so if I have a line that
says count minus minus and the next line
if at zero nothing's going to happen
between those that's blocking
synchronous code and so while we have
some asynchronous things going on you at
least know that random stuff that could
happen between your lines like with
threading with threading it's insane
anything can happen anywhere unless it's
an atomic CPU operation which is why we
have OS level locks and all these crazy
things but with a single threaded event
system you don't have those issues the
only time that things can happen
arbitrarily is between your weights you
don't know which events are going to
come back in what order you just know
that once you're in code you're in
control until you stop so like I said at
the beginning the difference between
this and threading is with threading the
OS handles the concurrency for you it
says you code stop you code run no no no
you run again it just interrupts them
constantly with node we're saying run
this code and then I'm done which can
actually bite you sometimes because if
you're doing CPU intensive things like
calculating the first million pi digits
that's not a good thing first Olivia
it's not very good at that particular
use case and secondly your entire server
with your hundred thousand clients is
now blocked nothing happens nothing
happens at all because it's calculating
these pi digits for this one user who
typed a really big number in their form
and so that's where things like web
workers come in where you can actually
defer this to another process that does
the CPU intensive stuff hopefully on
another machine maybe if it's really
heavy so you're not fighting for the
threads and then that will give you
something back over IPC or TCP about
it's done but if things are short and
that receive you intensive than just do
them in line as long as you're done
quickly it won't hurt the event loop
anymore questions
I
I have i I've heard different things
I've heard it being I've heard what we
do with node called continuation passing
style and I've heard other things what
what do you mean by that
the best solution
so is this is this like her routines or
sort of okay so i dunno co routines and
we we had those in node early on with
the promise wait API and while it works
and doesn't hurt the event lip too bad
it introduces thread like semantics
because now you have functions that do
non-blocking i/o but externally look
like they're blocking and so once those
get reps behind other functions and
other AP is and you just use libraries
unless you read all the code you don't
know if this function call is actually
going to stop and let the event lib do
other stuff and so then it's kind of
like threading in between these calls
random stuff may happen and it's not
quite as bad as truth reading but yeah i
mean we tried the co routines we decided
we didn't like them for node other other
frameworks use them if that's what
you're talking about but yeah it's it's
one alternative we're trying we're
trying to a nodal really trying to
follow the same style in the browser and
in the browser it's just plain callbacks
plain event single threaded single stack
and with co routines you have multiple
stacks and they that kind of interleave
dependent on when they when they waited
on the next event the question
it depends on how the DB library is
written hopefully it doesn't look any
library is a block you shouldn't use if
it's my postgres library it actually
implements that the postgres protocol
over tcp and so it's non blocking
because all of nodes networking stack as
non blocking but if you're saying just
buying into the ROM icicle library it's
going to be blocking is going to hurt
your event loop so you got to make sure
you don't use libraries that are
blocking which is another reason why
javascript was a good choice for note
people who come from Python or Ruby are
used to these blocking libraries almost
your database drivers are blocking and
so when people use twisted or event
machine or the non-blocking systems they
got to be careful which libraries they
pull in and JavaScript the spec there is
no I oh and in the browser the only i/o
is non blocking I mean there is sync xhr
but we're told not to use it so pretty
much it's non blocking and so the
JavaScript people are used to this idea
of all your libraries being non blocking
and we have a fresh clean start but yeah
you don't want to use a library that is
blocking that's that's very bad
yeah so it's a tough decision require
require especially as a special case
early on I was pushing for fully async
require it makes your code more
complicated makes it harder to read and
the same time it's you know it's
parallel what's non-blocking you can
write the same code in the browser and
because you can't really do block and
requires on a browser but then again
require is cached even if you require in
a hot loop in your server you're
probably requiring the 10 file same 10
files over and over so your first web
request will be an extra 30 milliseconds
long after that they're hitting the
in-memory cache and so it doesn't hurt
your performance yeah it's a special
case and we're still thinking about
what's a good API for a good require I
know the common jest guys are thinking
about it so yeah
yeah now you can implement your own it's
not hard no it provides a script API
where you can get access to v8's I don't
know what it's called but but yeah yeah
okay so yeah just just talk on the
mailing list give some suggestions we're
open ideas note note is still a work in
progress but it's stable enough now to
start being used for applications thank