so now we're going to the Q&A with
andreas and Brendan we have five
questions selected from your tweets so
please take a seat here
this is so exciting I'm so close to him
I have a phablet loaded with questions
so the first one came from a tweet
that's I think it's really really
interesting so Brandon at what point did
you start imagining that JavaScript
could one day run and in control robots
or games within games or zombies in
WebGL compiled from C++ when I think
around the time friends went off the air
and I lost my gig there that's Chandler
uh no III didn't foresee all that I I
thought it was going to be a glue
language or what some people call duct
tape language which is really I think
not not a meaningful phrase it was going
to be the little you know brother or the
sidekick to Java and Java will do all
the applets and components and beans and
those would be in your browser and
JavaScript would just be how you glued
them together sort of like visual basic
was to C++ in Microsoft's Windows
environment at the time but John never
really got out of the applet cage it
never loaded quickly it never learned
about the Dom so I think that that was
fatal awesome so basically jealousy was
only going to be for embedding applets
now it's for reinventing the JVM inside
JavaScript it's pretty awesome so
another thing that comes up a lot is
JavaScript to some people has good parts
and bad parts and now with old es mi
administered six and seven innovations
and additions it creates new
opportunities for now narrowing down
again do you foresee that we are going
to be creating JavaScript a good parts
again now that we get all these new
features I think this is true of the web
in general like HTML has bad parts CSS I
think we all know has bad parts the
funny thing is people think when you
have an evolving system that if a new
requirement comes into the system you
have to evolve quickly that's not how it
works in nature you are
have to have had the genetic diversity
and already have evolved to survive the
new disease or the new predator so the
same with javascript and HTML and CSS
they're going to have too much in them
they're going to have mistakes they're
going to have things that you can't
remove because they already are used by
some pages their apps on the web but
they can be deprecated and they can fade
away and so I you know I just tweeted
back earlier before coming on stage I
don't agree with Crockford he's too
prescriptive astir my taste he says you
know they're the bad parts you must
never use and there are these little
good parts that I say you should use
like the closure pattern against the
prototypal pattern it's too it's too
extreme and JavaScript needed to have
more patterns or more strength to it in
order to survive for unforeseen
circumstances and needs to keep evolving
as it has so I I think there will
continue to be messy evolution with bad
parts and we won't even know they're bad
until later that's the that's the killer
don't you wanted is it off here's no
opinion can we hello yeah all right all
right yeah I think it's especially the
part around removing things being
difficult is ray true um Brennan's
explanation reminded me of a property I
found in the Dom in missoula
implementation a couple years ago it's
called navigator enable taint and
Brennan edited like 15 years ago and it
always returns false because you never
actually implemented attained
propagation and I asked him kind of
yelling across the desk like what the
hell is this thing and what does it do
and why is it here and in my moment of
like attempted purity I submitted a
patch to remove that property because
clearly I guess this is nobody would use
this it was added 14 years ago for a
feature that never got implemented right
and this this went for the ride a train
in Firefox and I broke like half over
because it turns out that jQuery uses
that to
fact that you're running on Firefox or
not
that's really great only a GS conf do
get applause for breaking like half the
web thank you very much I feel much
better about it already so yeah this
removing this kind of stuff is it's very
hard it has to be very slow we have
removed stuff in the past successfully
right before X for example of also
removed after some pain so it is
possible it simply takes a lot of time
there's a I think there's a biologist
who wants to breed chickens to express
what are called genetic atavism the
chickens with teeth like dinosaurs
because that that'll enable taint method
is still down there in their DNA
somewhere maybe they can get teeth maybe
maybe an able taint will come back I
don't know actually I have a very hard
question for Angie as I think because he
talks so much today about JavaScript
being a great target for compilation so
when should we use rust and when should
we use JavaScript so rust was designed
for a very specific purpose to rewrite
system parts and there's actually no
necessary heart distinction between
these two languages I already talked to
the team whether rust should be able to
target JavaScript there might be some
cases where it makes sense to use rust
to implement something that runs on top
of the web stack in JavaScript and there
might be other cases where it makes
sense to implement system parts as
JavaScript so I don't think there's a
necessary order there and I will be
surprised if you don't have a rust to
javis compiler at some point yeah I
agree the rust main sweet spot is safety
with the same memory controlled C++
gives you all right and you mentioned
types today and in the community we see
a lot of different projects for tackling
types in Java Script so we have at
script and now coming out typescript
flow dart just kidding so what do we do
which one do we use what do you think
about this project do you think once
again that the better one will win and
the rest will die out I think we're
still in the early days there's just
been some interest in equity c39 the
standards body about standardizing
something to do with types may be based
on type script and flow both using the
colon annotation like the ML languages
do like Pascal's remember that does
Algol languages some of them anyway that
syntax VAR x colon t you can't just
standardized it it has meaning if you
define it it has something to say about
the types system and the type
expressions or type annotations so we're
not going to rush to standardize that
the only thing we're doing now is saying
that no engine can go claim as an
extension on its own that colon after
the name in the declaration that that's
reserved to the future standards that
might standardize it I think typescript
and then flow inspired by the much more
powerful should keep going I think the
best thing they can do is get adoption
the worst thing you could do is make
design by committee you know union of
all the systems or intersection of all
the systems or some committee
frankenstein standards that would be
terrible all right and the final
question for you Brandon someone was
wondering about what what are the
biggest lessons are takeaways from tc39
and in general the approach that has
been taken towards improving JavaScript
and where do you see that going in the
future it's been a long road I think
that my big takeaways in like 20 year
terms are you need competition to drive
the vendors to cooperate in the
standards bodies then you need good
social relations among the members of
the committee even you know croc is
welcome back any time in my book you you
need to get on this rapid release
footing we're trying to get on with es7
you don't want to do big indefinite
projects in software or in
standardization because they always
suffer scope creep and the world moves
out from under them and they become
irrelevant dinosaurs so some kind of
rapid release footing with implementers
constantly implementing w3c really
originally the what WG tried to get
browsers to do this with html5 and that
became a big living document standard
but I think now things are getting
across the web space on to a faster
cycle and that's that's one of the
biggest lessons for me