all right hello everybody my name is
Julie Bush I work at Conde Nast in New
York there we go okay so I work at Conde
Nast in New York it's right there and
we're going to put this on hold for just
a sec because before we get to business
I have been advised to be relatable and
so I'm going to tell you a little bit
about myself
so I actually don't come from a
traditional computer science background
I used to be a stage manager for theater
I'm pretty new to this game I've been
working for a little over a year and a
half in the industry to be very
reductive about what a stage manager is
just so that you understand the context
during the rehearsal process the actors
and the director are focusing on the
artistic development of a piece and the
stage manager is figuring out what needs
to be done to make all of those things
happen in real life and communicating
with the necessary departments and
people and so on so I was drawn to
coding because it has many parallels
with the organizational analytical and
problem-solving skills required in stage
management and also because both fields
are highly collaborative and I'm not a
loner so you know I enjoy working with
other people and coming together to make
cool stuff lastly I'm also a very long
game kind of person so I've always
enjoyed being in a position to watch the
evolution of a product over time it's
just as interesting to watch the process
for me as it is to have a final product
and so now perhaps you'll have some
understanding behind what my talk is
focusing on today so now that you can
relate to me I am going to go ahead and
get started with creative collaboration
building a unified design system so we
left off here conde nast new york as was
mentioned Conde Nast has a lot of
different brands many disparate types
and topics and the way that things used
to be back in the days of yore was that
every different brand had its own team
of Engineers and its own code base for
its website and of course this seemed
sensible because this is a company that
started in print publishing over a
hundred years ago and so the way that
the magazine's work is that they each
have their own separate team so as
digital started to be integrated into
the company you just add people to each
of those teams and you know carry on
but consider that despite the very
distinct tones designs and topics of
each of the brand's their digital needs
are actually overwhelmingly similar for
example some shared site needs include
the ability to show aggregated content
which is to say something like a home
page or a page showing content by author
by by subject you also need to be able
to show the actual content itself when
someone chooses an article to read or a
gallery to look at and that is pretty
much it that's what we do that's content
and you just need to be able to view it
that's a website for us for the most
part so with that being the case having
separate teams for all of the different
websites starting to make less and less
sense because with the sites being as
similar as they are in terms of what
they need it would make sense that any
feature that works well on one site
would work well on another and we would
want to pass it along so I don't need to
go too much into explaining how that's
not really efficient in order to get one
feature onto every different brand by
having it passed from brand to brand
with dev time in between and so on so
we've said that was enough of that
and we set forth a plan to create a
single application that would host all
of our sites we'd have a library of
shared components built in react and
these components would not just be the
visual aspects of the designs but they
would really be like truly plug-and-play
pieces of a website like you put in a
newsletter signup form you pop it in
there and you have a newsletter signup
form it's connected to the API
everything works people can use
immediately as once as soon as it's live
and so that's that's our lofty goal to
increase our efficiency to reduce or
done didn't see and it's really be able
to move a lot more quickly in terms of
developing products that will help us
stay innovative and ahead in the media
industry so this application which we
lovingly dubbed diverso was what we set
out to do a little bit before the end of
last year we started making the server
we moved to working on front-end stuff
near the beginning of this year and so
just for clarity's sake in case you were
wondering this is the deal if you want a
feature to be given to many different
brands all we want to be able to do is
develop it one time hence one clock
inverse oh and then it'll automatically
be available to any brand that is hosted
therein and we had a few requirements
around how we wanted to implement this
because you know without some
limitations
it could very easily be messy
so one thing was that we decided but we
would have no brand specific code
reusability was going to be the key in
terms of everything we did because if we
want to add features they need to be
able to be popped into any given brand
site and working immediately
so no brands specific code another is
that we needed to make it scalable be
cuz Conde Nast has over 20 brands right
now we need to support all of those but
also we need to support any number of
brands that they may choose to add in
the future and it should be just as easy
for our application to support 40 brands
as it is for it to support two and
lastly we really needed to get it done
as fast as possible that is because I
think that the you know the business
advantage here is clear in terms of
restructuring the team and you know how
the websites work and also because we
don't want to have to support both
legacy websites and this new app
concurrently for too long at the time
and perhaps most importantly because you
can't go to a brand and say hey we
figured out a way to make a really cool
application that's gonna be really great
for everyone in everything and we're
gonna stop working on what you've got
going on right now so we can work on
that and we'll be done in five years
okay bye so with that being the case
time was of the essence so really how
how indeed mr. walberg JSON JSON is
perhaps not the not what you would
expect for an answer to this question
and you probably also wouldn't expect it
to have exclamation points like that
because I feel like it's not typically
so exciting but here it is the the main
way that we were going to pull off this
system was by having every brand based
in a configuration in that way we would
be able to not have any unique logic
written within our components and still
have all of the brand's maintain their
you know unique visual appearance
because you know the differences need to
live somewhere otherwise you've made a
lot of people really angry and you've
just made one website so how does that
work in terms of the like what does this
configuration file look like so this is
an example
of how we started going about with here
colors one of the many many things that
need to be uniquely adjusted for every
brand so you'll see that we have these
different key value pairs and these are
referred to as design tokens the design
token just being the name of the unique
bit that is being used as the dynamic
element of a certain website that gets
changed on a brand by brand basis so
here our palette has different color
values and then we have different use
cases where we were creating tokens that
were semantically named but still
decoupled from their usage again for
reusability we didn't want to name
something you know footer link because
theoretically that everything should be
somewhat consistent and you might want
to use that link token again elsewhere
that's not a footer and you know you
don't confuse people so so how does that
actually become styles what we did was
set up our JSON to be loaded into our
Styles which we were writing in sass as
a map and then from there we can do
things like make this nifty function you
see at the bottom that just references
the map to get a color value and then
you can use that function like so in the
sass and without having written anything
brand specific within your Styles you're
getting brand specific values based on
what your domain is also how is atomic
design you may have heard of atomic
design if not is essentially just a way
of sorting things from the smallest most
indivisible pieces and combining them
into larger pieces
this was against a way that we chose to
do things for the sake of reusability we
actually hired Brad Frost who wrote the
book atomic design and who is the source
of this image as a consultant on this
project and he did say that while he has
a ton of experience making design
systems for individual brands what we
were really doing was making a design
system of design systems and he didn't
really know how it was gonna work so we
were going into uncharted territory here
and so without really a case study to go
off of
in terms of workflow and such we set out
with our initial process and the way
that we thought was best to get started
which was to reverse engineer the design
system from the existing brand designs
because we did want to give the brand's
some assurance that they would not be
losing a lot of their uniqueness in this
changeover that we wouldn't be just
producing cookie-cutter websites that
just you know changed the logo at the
top or something everyone was very
concerned about maintaining their design
integrity and so it made sense for us to
start with the original designs in order
to maintain that so we would get design
specs as usual with just an image of a
page make this thing have it look like
this have it work there you go and it
would be up to the engineers to actually
find and separate out the different
components that would be part of the
atomic model and also to decide how to
make those different dynamic elements
between brands into tokens that would
then be part of this JSON configuration
getting started we went with two of the
more minimally designed brands and chose
them for the pilot run of a templates in
this case here was the contributor page
so you'll see we started with Golf
Digest and self which are
somewhat similar few things differing
mainly the shape of the images that's
you know the most distinct thing a
couple of quirky nav decorations at the
top there and in order to get this app
running we decided to go with two to
start with and then add the rest of the
brands in in stages so we were going for
a process that we intended to be very
iterative so we started with the first
two brands very similar here and here
built an app and then would loop in
another brand that's a little more
complex and another brand and so on and
our theory was that eventually once we
had gotten all of the brands supported
in our application we would be able to
support any other design that came our
way we would have all of the knobs and
switches needed and everyone would live
happily ever after
that didn't happen right away so there
were some things that we found in this
approach that were not ideal first of
all I did mention the speed thing where
it was of the essence to get this
project done as quickly as possible and
with the setup that we had multiple
engineering teams couldn't work
concurrently because merging without
conflicts was essentially impossible
that is because with the JSON
configuration with it being up to the
developers to decide exactly how to
abstract different parts of a visual
design into a purely data based form was
well not not only difficult more
difficult than you might think in terms
of making it make sense
and having it be semantic and reusable
but people would make different
decisions that would cover different
things thinking that they were different
things but they weren't for example
people would be working on the
contributor page you might set up the
in a certain shape to cover a certain
piece of the design such as let's say
the difference between the image shapes
and another team working on say an
article page would set up a shape of a
JSON config and it would be made to
adjust the image shapes and not only
would those thing pieces of code
conflict but they're duplicates of each
other and so we can't just have 17 ways
of doing everything in this file and so
then we would have to sync up on it and
decide which approach to take that
brings us to another finding which was
that we were having constant meetings in
order to try to keep everybody on sync
with this project it was there were
almost more meetings in a day than there
was time to code really because it's
just not really feasible to keep a
multitude of teams or even just a few
teams it's very hard to keep people
synced to the moment on a line-by-line
basis in a gigantic JSON configuration
file and know that nobody is stepping on
anybody else's toes that nobody's
duplicating anybody else's work so the
constant meetings were a very valiant
effort I will say to end that but there
just aren't enough hours in the day and
lastly it was hard to create a system
with these problems because with the
ensuing chaos that that's just not a
system if you have all sorts of ways of
doing things just looped in there ad hoc
so with this information we decided to
completely turn around the approach we
were taking to building this application
and focus first and foremost on the
system itself not the end product that
we were trying to achieve but the pieces
that would become the end product so
in this case I think of it as making the
bricks before the house whereas before
the house was coming first and bricks
were being pulled from the house
magically except not because magic spot
real and neither was the way that
working on that project was going so the
designers actually needed to get a lot
more involved in the implementation
usually as I mentioned they hand off a
design a nice you know flashy finished
product and it doesn't matter how you
make it happen as long as it happens and
in this case we found that design needed
to be the first people thinking about
how to make it happen so that rather
than having all of the engineers
deciding on a day by day basis just as
they were going through tickets what to
turn into a token what not to how to
structure that JSON naming and so forth
the tokens were determined by the
designers up front so we started getting
specs like these that were much more
technical where this is also you'll
notice not a brand but just a general
brand list template and the designer set
it up so that they could decide all of
the things that they felt they needed to
achieve the unique designs of all the
brands and labeled them upfront and
decided how they wanted to structure it
in a way that made sense to them since
they're the ones ultimately assigning
these tokens to their designs when they
create them and then handing it over to
us where we would just need to make this
completely brand agnostic entirely
reusable template and fill in the blanks
when it came to what parts of the
template were dynamic this is a little
bit more of a detailed view of that spec
just in case you wanted to take a look
you can see that each of the blue
circles on the top part our numbers
labeling the different things that a
designer wants to be able to control on
a brand basis
and then they've hopefully listed out
all of the things just like a blueprint
so we also had to end the merge conflict
madness which wasn't going to stop just
because the tokens were handed over to
designers for their ideation with the
JSON going directly into component
Styles as people were working on those
new specs that I mentioned there was
still the high potential for chaos and
despair so in order to rectify that
situation we decided to actually put the
JSON configurations in the hands of a
single team who would be the gatekeepers
and set up a layer of abstraction
between the JSON and the component
styles that would allow developers to
make the component styles safely in
peace and so we called it our SAS API
because it was a layer that we created
within the SAS itself in order to
isolate the JSON from just the everyday
developer making patterns so the SAS API
starts out with the same sort of JSON as
we looked at before and rather than
going directly into a function that gets
used to set a style as we saw we first
create a variable that's using that same
function we were using before and it has
the information needed for the token
that it represents so we made a one
variable in this case per color token we
made mix-ins for the typography and took
every token that design handed to us
and made some sort of SAS mixin or
variable to cover it and in this way any
developer working on one of the
components would just have to use the
variable in order to style it and that
was then safe because should the
structure of the JSON change which it
was likely to do or if anything
went wrong or broke anything behind the
Sasse api could happen without us
needing to update every single instance
in which a token was used across
numerous components all we needed to do
was update the definition of its
representation in the SAS API and then
everything would be good again further
we worked on automating the creation of
these JSON files one of the JSON files I
would say one of the smaller ones is
about 1300 lines it just goes up from
there and you probably just don't want
to hand copy that so this is an example
of the way that the designers in this
new way of doing things started creating
their sketch files for the brand's
themselves making tables of all of the
different values that they wanted for
the different tokens that would end up
creating unique results within our
application and as I said it's just not
practical in any way for us to be adding
brands by manually coding this into a
configuration so the designers and an
engineer worked together to actually
create a sketch plugin written in cocoa
script that would scrape the files which
the designers normalized for us so that
there would be a predictable output and
this little button here produces a JSON
file
in a minute listen a minute I mean it's
a computer so this is a big game changer
in terms of moving forward just setting
up brands adding to our application so
the results as I said multiple
engineering teams were able to work
concurrently on components after these
changes that's because with the SAS API
and without tens of hands mucking around
in the JSON everyone was able to work on
separate templates an article a gallery
whatever they needed without being
without
having to interfere with anybody else's
work and that gave teams a lot more
autonomy as well because they didn't
need to have several meetings with other
teams in order to come to an agreement
on how they were going to do things the
way that things were going to be done
was being determined higher up than that
further the design system actually
became a system so instead of it being
just drawn from visual designs by
engineers the designers creating it
really took it and made it what they
needed it to be
and lastly which was the ultimate goal
of verso pages are able to be created
and used by all brands immediately
because before we were going to add
brands one at a time so that our app
would only support what we had already
woven into that sort of diagram there
now with brand agnostic components
anytime a brand is added via config to
the app it automatically has access to
everything within the app any feature it
wants or needs and that wouldn't be
possible if we hadn't switched the way
that we start working from design first
to bricks and pieces first so that's
what we did and we continue to do that
we are actually in the process of
cutting over brands from their legacy
applications to verso little by little
we have some brands at a hundred percent
of traffic going to verso depending on
the content type and we just keep on
adding and adding to them and someday
all of our pages will be coming from
verso each and every one and the
prophecy will be fulfilled
so thank you very much I'm Julie Bush
I'm a curmudgeon so I only participate
in LinkedIn you will not find me on
Twitter or elsewhere if you want to
friend me or I guess in this case it
would be colleague in me leave a little
note because otherwise I'll think your
spam so I appreciate your attention and
excellent let's have a good afternoon