my name is reached a fever of well
friends and non Russian speakers call me
Slava and I walk in denmark on v8 for
the last two years and initially I
planned to call my talk one day of life
in v8 but then it was explained to me
that nobody will give me the whole day
on the miserable 30 minutes and so I had
to chop it down to something much
shorter and more energetic like directly
proceed to questions answers for example
but yeah so oh my god so it's pretty
often that people ask me can we do
something like here's a piece of code
what we can do is that and my goal for
today is actually encourage you to look
under v8 hood and to understand what we
eat can or cannot do and maybe
contribute something back to eat if you
see that way it can do something better
and it's not scary so I will be maybe I
will try to be a fear killer by showing
you some horrible machine code or
something like that and yeah so that's
nagar i decided to use examples of code
that people sent to me in various / time
and like for example asking what we ate
can do with this multiplication of dot
product of two vectors representatives
external WebGL erase or maybe what it
can do if it just represented that if
these vectors are represented as a
normal JavaScript arrays because they
heard that they are less efficient in v8
then the typed arrays or maybe a piece
of horrible code like that that can be
found in some library like prototype I
think where you have this constructor
with an apple application of the
initialization function and people ask
oh there is a apply and there is an
arguments I heard they are very
inefficient and what we eat can do is
that compared to the old school
structure which just construct an object
and doesn't try to be clever and and
even code like that so some functional
programmers they ask I like high order
functions i like to map my reduce and
reduce my map and currently oh my god
can we ate can we ate can we eat
transform it to a native loop maybe
please please please and so the answer
to these questions are actually pretty
simple you just need to look at the code
that regenerates and of course you can
do that we does not hide it anywhere and
doesn't try to I don't know put it
somewhere on the protected data center
it runs on your computer so yes of
course you can look at the code we it
generates unfortunately you have to
build v8 yourself to do that we don't
ship it together with chrome by default
because it occupies some space like
there is a built-in disassembler who
wants a built-in disassembler in the web
browser not that useful so well I am NOT
going to explain what's these days you
just build wit with some options and
then you run rate with some options and
then you can see everything that it
produces including the internal
representations of the functions it
optimizes and now we will try to apply
this sacred knowledge to the examples
that I have shown in the beginning of my
speech so this is an example and hear
somebody who actually reads what's
written and the slide can say oh my god
what's this that it wasn't there there
is something some dirty trick what's
happening the dance is very simple you
have to force me to optimize your code
in a sense that it does not try to
optimize anything that doesn't occupy
well any measurable time in the
execution of your program why waste an
effort and
so you have to put a pressure on this
function to get it optimized and to may
create to some work and produce some
sweat yeah so and here's the questions
that you should ask yourself when you
look at the JavaScript code of this
function is that can we eat hoist a dot
length it's one of the religious
questions actually i think in JavaScript
community should I cash this in the
local variable or should I just write it
like this fight fight and the other
question is can they access here be as
efficient as an array existence see well
because you everybody knows that the
race in JavaScript just normal objects
and the properties have names and erase
they have property which is called zero
probability called one etc and another
question is that can lv 8 avoid boxing
are temporaries produced by the
computation so we ate allocates
floating-point values in the boxes and
it doesn't sound very efficient so the
question is can it avoid doing that for
the local results and the other question
which is quite similar to this one is
can we eat avoid using floating
precision numbers entirely because here
we have one variable which is obviously
an integer and it doesn't make sense to
use the whole floating-point number to
represent it and here is an answer to
all the questions
so I actually skip the ski removed all
the comments to make it fit on the slide
actually v8 produces more than just this
loop entry comment it actually annotates
everything with like why did I produce
this bunch of assembly here like there
was an addition so I produce this
instruction but here i will be your
comment with a Russian accent so let's
start so this is this is a comparison so
they'll end the conditional branch
somewhere obviously it corresponds to
the loop condition because we will head
like I less than array dot length so if
we think a little bit about it it
becomes obvious that aesi contains I
andy sixx contains rate at length and
this already answers our question there
is no load of a rated lengths in the
body and it sits in the register and
obviously we ate somehow managed to move
it out of the loop so sometimes guys who
say your girls who say diversity that
you don't have to cash lengths they are
completely right then there is a bunch
of code that we can just keep because
there is no corresponding JavaScript
code it was produced just to support
such stuff like pausing the script
execution with the pause button in the
dev tools or terminating the busy loops
when some evil guy ships you a page
which has while to do something and
chrome will pop up the windows that you
ask you where they want to break this
loop and this is this code so we can
just keep it this is a load from the
array you can see a bounced check we're
checking whether something is inside the
bounds so ESI contains I ebx apparently
contains the lengths of a
and ii IX apparently contains length of
B and then there are loads of this
double floating-point double precision
values into XML registers so it looks
very similar to what a C compiler would
spread you so you could actually ask GCC
to produce their assembly and compare it
and it's pretty similar and here is a
multiplication addition so you don't
need a like any there is so you know
there are three volume of overall your
mental reference manuals and you don't
actually need them to understand that
this is a multiplication it says mal SD
SD we can skip mal so and then there is
an addition and you can notice that d it
also sits in the register xmm too so
everything looks very nice very tight
very compact and then they do the loop
increment so here somebody might have
might ask wait wait a second wait
javascript is a dynamically typed
language and where is all the type
checks and stuff like that there is
nothing like this in the loop at all we
just increment load but you don't check
the types we don't check that the array
is an array how does it happen well
actually we it moved everything let's
invariant like we know that a stays the
same during the whole loop so all these
checks they were moved out of the loop
entirely and if you look was before the
loop so the number 146 kind of indicates
that there is something before that and
there are a lot of stuff before that
here is for example the load of length
array that links properties so and he's
this is the magical number that allows
me to check whether something has a
certain like shape this is called the
hidden class so map in the eighth
basically every object has this attached
to it and then need only one instruction
to say to determine whether something
has the particular type and then if it
does not have UD optimized so there was
a talk about multiple tiered compilation
in JavaScript code before and so it
should be already
Amelia with this term and there is a
load so everything looks pretty
understandable after a year or two so
and here's the question how we do does
that and the answer is pretty simple
tons of this text but what this boils
down to is actually that v8 observes the
execution of your program somehow and
then it adapts itself and the code to
this execution so if you have stable
types stable ranges for your variables
we it would be will be able to adapt the
code to get the most out of the
execution like here we it adapted the
loop to use like WebGL load from the
WebGL erase because it have seen that
this loads are loading doubles from the
floor 64 a and the key thing here I
inline caches so every thing that has
dynamic her like behavior dynamic lookup
built-in has a corresponding inline
caching v8 and inline cash remembers
what it have seen it's the whole goal of
caching so when they tries to optimize
this function it will just ask the
inline cash what did have seen and then
specialized the code for this
information so different colors indicate
like the yellow one so whatever this is
is like a lookup of a property and
purple I don't know what's pink pink
ones are like numeric operations or
comparisons and the other important
moment is that we it makes optimistic
assumptions about the code it compiles
basically it says okay you used float64
array and
cash tells me this I will assume that
this is always true and if this is not
true i will just sorry guys this will
run slow i will be optimized and this
enables the whole basically this enables
me to make the whole function fast path
for the stable types and stable behavior
so if you are not stable in your
JavaScript programs and your tight
computational kick kernels are not
stable it typed this is not go this is
not good I'm sorry okay so here is an
example of optimistic assumption which
v8 makes it doesn't like out of bounds
reads from the typed arrays it just
checks the bounce and then it does not
try to handle this situation it just
goes to some address which doesn't even
belong to this function it goes to some
deep cuts off fee to switch to none
optimized code and twice this is the
case why why is this the case on English
is difficult language and the reason is
very simple JavaScript has a very
peculiar semantics as you might be aware
if you do an out-of-bounds free it from
the typed array I think you should do a
prototype look up and go up rota type
chain so you can write something like
this very easily so you can have a gator
on the object prototype for the property
called too and if you make a floater 64
array of a length 1 and look up the
property to you will get getter executed
that's why you don't want to implement
this in Fast Pass it will just make the
whole loop huge if you start handling
these cases and it will also it will not
allow me to like assume that after the
load from the array there is there were
no side effects at all by then this
basically inhibits all optimizations if
we ate can't assume that so
this is the this explains why we does a
lot of local assumptions here somebody
evil or maybe not so evil moderately
evil might ask what if I write the code
like this to add a function call to the
mix and if there is a function called v8
can't do anything because it makes local
assumptions obviously can i defeat v8 I
want to defeat we 80 year and the answer
is no no not so simple my friend we does
in line of functions as well so yes it
can't do anything across cause but if it
knows the target of the call it will in
line it and the inline code will be
accessible for the analysis it will
analyze and it will see that there is no
side effects and stuff like that so
that's what happens here so the cold
almost didn't change because the
function is in line but of course if you
look before the loop then there will be
a piece of code that checks that the
target of the call is the same and you
can also notice that this check was
moved out of the loop as well like all
other checks so now I will try to scare
away in lining so there are constructs
that Lee does not like because there's
Carrie and one of the scary constructs
ease with which is all scary and yes it
it is so scary that the proper use code
is also scary because it scared away in
lining and v8 had to produce some pretty
generic code for the loop so instead of
looking at the generated code I
encourage you in this case is to look at
the high level intermediate
representation used during optimization
it's much less scary than the native
code and much more verbose so this is an
example of this or both stuff disregards
faiz they are coming from something
called single static assignment form and
what we should pay attention to is this
stuff this is an invocation of our
function called mal and it has this
scary changes
square brackets star thing it says that
we it can't su menacing a decent
vacation because it can change
everything and of course we it can't
optimize anything across the the
indication of this function because it
no knows nothing about side effects like
what will happen what if somebody will
define a property on them like float64
array which also has a gator or whatever
so the load of the length property now
in the loop so they did not manage to
hoist it out and there is untagging
which you can disregard and there is
this strange stuff so we call the
malfunction and then returns t46 which
will then convert to double so t46 is a
boxed double and we need to extract the
double which sits in the box take it and
then they all sorry and then actually do
a an addition on the doubles so you can
see that so when we inhibited these
optimizations by scaring away the
inlining we could not avoid boxing on
the boundary of the function call and it
could not host out the lengths load from
the rail loop so the know the advice
here is that if you have a tight
computational kernels you should ensure
that we it is able to inline all the
functions that you are calling these
tight computational kernels usually it
is able but you should check that out
and some people see like maybe ten
twenty percent improvement if they are
then lined by hand what we decided that
it can't in line for some reason or just
make it suitable for in line and this
all is visible under like high level
representations and stuff ok now let's
quickly go through this case so I remove
the type to race entirely because some
people ask her we heard that typed
arrays are more efficient yes they were
but now we are working on enabling v
to understand when your array contains
only numbers on the doubles and unbox it
automatically so you wouldn't table you
would not need to use verbose flow 64a
just write a normal JavaScript code and
this is the Chi removed all the codes
left only the loads from the array so it
looks pretty similar to what we have
seen in the load from type theory but
there is some strange stuff they're
still in addition to it like comparison
is some strange constant and this is
because float this is because normal
JavaScript arrays they can contain holes
and if you load something from the
nimbus which is the whole you have to go
up through prototype and we in the v8
again does not support that so for typed
arrays we know that there are no holes
but for GS erase that were unboxed they
can still contain holes like you can
delete the property with index 2 and we
don't want to convert the array if you
delete one element there we don't want
to convert it to a hash table because
this is an insanity so we use a special
non-value to indicate that this is a
hole because the non values are very
nice you can have different names even
if you can't observe that from
JavaScript so we use a special name to
detect that and this is the whole name
okay anyways yeah this is what we do and
here one can also suggest for example
and then submit as a change list which
we will accept and land maybe I'm pretty
sure we will that tracks the denseness
of the name of an array because it will
have to remove these holes checks and
make the loop even tighter and more
concise and faster obviously and
everybody who does computation in pure
JavaScript will be happy and praise you
so please do this if you want to
experience something beautiful
now this example there was this applied
arguments which I removed and so I do
test which creates this new class with a
class constructor which has this dot a
neat apply these arguments in sighs okay
who thinks that this can be as efficient
as a old-school constructor one person
you don't believe in the eighth it can
be there is no apply at all if we look
at the high level representation that
something we did recently so there is an
object allocation then we in line vector
function and then we load init function
then we do a couple of checks directly
push the arguments because we are in the
inline context so we know how many
arguments are there there is no need to
materialize have been subject at all and
the semantics of the apply function is
known and inline cash tells us that it's
always an apply so we can just in line
everything and directly invoke the
function so yes we can apply it
completely gun and this example
unfortunately not now so I had to
include something that we can't do
otherwise it would look that way it can
do everything which is obviously not
true and but actually the whole
crankshaft pipeline was developed with a
thought in mind that you can do all
kinds of strange optimizations then this
optimization is available kind of
well-known optimization the functional
programming world when you combine
several high-level function in vacations
into a one tight loop so if you do this
plumbing so the infrastructure is there
which allows you to say this is the map
function this is a reduced function and
you know there is semantics so you can
just transform it into a loop like that
with some additional plumping I can't
say what's the length length of the pipe
that you need to stack their to do that
but it's doable so we accept patches as
i said i'm looking forward to see one
and there is this site which i will skip
and proceed to the questions and answers