I'm here to talk about perspective and I
seen today's talk and I kind of feel
like my knee a little bit silly but
hopefully you'll find it interesting so
i'm going to introduce myself and a
really good drubbing grower I try very
well so I web designer like most people
here and i teach web design and in
university also community manager at
that part of university that's really
fun and well I have these ACA a visual
communication with other Photoshop this
exam and then I go google adwords 35 on
way to thing about me I'm a coffee
addict I drink a lot of coffee I'm one
of those harry potter crisis pants that
dress like harry potter from time to
time so and now let's go with
perspective so what we must wonder is
what is perspective and we're going to
look into the dictionary this we find
this the perspective come from letting
perspex Syria it means to see through
and it's an approximate representation
on a flat surface such as paper or our
computer of an image at a system by the
eye I don't know if any of you have a
study and television or something like
that there's always by white balance a
lot of things because everything with
you on TV your wee-wee seen on the
screen is never liked the icy seeds the
ice is with live in the screen there's
no left so now we can create it with CSS
so basically perspective have three
elements those are point of sight
horizontal line vanishing point those
are things of graphics to not really CSS
so the pontiff site is something like
this is the point to which and the eye
of the observer is supposed to be
directed well he looks so if we are
sitting down we have a different point
of sight and if we are standing we have
another different and there's this the
horizontal line and which is also known
at the horizon which are symbols that
horizon-- or boundary the line that
seems to part the ocean or grin from the
sky from in the shown in line so this
could be this as well and it's determine
I but the point of sight which is
determined by the real or supposed
vision of the beware so if we are
sitting down or we are standing it will
change and the vanishing point is not
this movie but it's something different
and is the point on the horizon which
receiving lines of the perspective
converge it could be one or more than
one and this is Campbell day or two but
in this one for example is only one and
it's always on the horizontal line so
they could be using photography as well
we have the vanishing point in the
middle we see that every line goes to
that point and there's kind of a golden
rule we must listen to that says the
upshot of drone a smaller as a decent
from the observing increases that means
that we can make em funny photo apps
such as this one or even funnier this
one so you can go and try this outside
and well what is perspective web design
what why am I talking about point of
view that well perspective and means
that we are going to play with the axis
of things z axis y axis and this seata
plane so we are moving the elements
through those those places so and we're
going to use the transfer property with
we know because if the scales things
xq rotate translate we can make excel ad
out of it as well mixing all of them and
what we must be remind is that the
original space of the element is still
occupied even the widow teeth so we have
something called transform origin which
has been mentioned today already it's
really easy we have here in both
elements with the same transform which
is rotate 40 degrees and scale 0.6
wasn't exactly the same but if we add to
this one a transform origin we see that
what's known as the anchor point or the
PI world changes so transformed
nourishing wicked boot and top right and
when we hover over it it goes the top
right so we changed that point which
could be also our vanishing point
besides between the things we can also
put percentages but we know we heard
today that there are a few badge back
box with it and but we can put numbers
such as 200 + 0 which is exactly the
same or we can put as well numbers that
are outside the element this element is
200 pixels wide and chocolate fails
height so we can put 400 even though is
outside the elements and we get this so
what we find here is a little problem
because when the element moves will lose
focus of it and it goes really crazy
like this so we must fix this and it's
really easy to fix and there must be
very ways the one that it found what is
in a father such as Darth Vader over
here so here you are when we hover over
the father we activate the return form
oh thank you and I was going to put the
boredom of the he has no children so so
this is our HTML we have daddy over here
we have the deal that we want to
transform so when we apply our CSS we
ask and dark that means the father and
when we hover over it we activate deep
that means this red one over here and we
change it so we can now put whatever we
want in from for origin modify this and
it goes crazy but we don't lose focus
because we are covering father or Darth
Vader so that's one good solution for
for that well how do we use perspective
with this is it could be simplifying
three steps first we create that parent
element then we apply it transformed
style / serve 3d and then we apply a
transfer perspective with a value so
here is a dolly which is red we can see
it if we do this is right we have the
zone which is this ring one and we are
going to work with a son once it is
applied from from Stanford 3d
perspective 600 and so we can transform
for example rotate the x and y axis
maybe three degrees and we get this so
it's pretty cool and it's pretty simple
and we can complicate a little more if
we go over 90 the element centers around
which is really easy we can also apply
transform auditioned over these
and it gets like this so this is an the
basis of perspective but we can
complicate it a little more because as
you see this is not a random number and
because if we change it will see a
difference if I could put a double of it
we can see that the the perspective is
less intense it's more subtle and if i
put in a smaller number such as 200 and
what happen is really strange the
element first goes behind the father and
besides the intensity of the first of
the fact is figure so what happens over
here when we cross a line is that we are
affecting the stacking context of it so
transform perspective effect and the
sucking contents such as opacity does I
don't know if you heard what a pathetic
office this problem as well so we have
these things that prefer freely grace in
your stocking context and so that's
opacity and the value of the perspective
the terminal intensity of the 3d effects
that means for example if we are a
little and looking at the dog will see a
big 3d but if we are a human being we
may not see the effects so big and
intense and we can modify the vanishing
point or the anchor point and by using
tranform origin so and we can do this
really useful stuff such as a wiper this
is a car wiper doesn't really look like
this what it is so yes it's really
useful I know everyone wants to do this
and then we have black face visibility
which has been talked already and which
is really really simple so we have this
element which is slightly the same as
before and we apply transform rotate we
can rotate wine instead of eggs
and if we were treated like 100 degrees
we get to see the other side of the
element for example we can put like this
so everything is turn around and if in
in one case we don't want to see that
back part we can just tell it then we
don't want to see the back of the
elements and that could be done with
rock face visibility simply hit them so
now we don't see the back of the element
but it is still there because if we do
this with it until we don't see it
anymore so that's basically by back
fights visibility it has largely hi the
back of the element which of course was
unable to see before this property so a
simple thing to do with perspective
which is really nice if flipping a guard
what we are going to flip now it's
actually a letter and so this is our
HTML we have a father and which holds
all the elements and then we have and
another the evil is kind of hidden that
will help us to not to look for boobs
and then we had the front which is an
image at the back which is another image
so this will be our CSS this is a
hogwarts letter we are getting to the
school and so we have transformed style
/ circularly apply and perspective a
hundred so we need is first of all to
show in these two parts and we can do
this by applying position absolute so we
showing them like this
and now we have this and so what we
should do now is in applying the
transform and to generate around so we
will apply to that when we hover over it
what will we actually applied to hidden
because we don't want to lose focus so
hidden we have a transform of rotate why
because we want to rotate you one way or
not the other of 180 degrees which
should be the middle so we have this is
not quite finish and it turns so that's
okay so what now we need and simply to
show the front in the front and the back
in the back so for that we simply hide
and the back of the element with
blackface miscibility and now we will
have this but it's not likely right
because what we are seeing here is and
the front in the back and windows the
front if I can be back in the front so
we don't want that we don't want it the
other way around so it's pretty simple
to fix it which has need to ask back to
transform and rotate why another hungry
and 80 degrees in order to get the front
into the front on the back into the back
so now we do have the elements and its
really pretty on is our Hogwarts letter
and we are getting there so that's
simply that and with a little more of
animation and that we can do this kind
of crazy thing and it just turns around
it turns around forever so that covers
another few things and such as another
transformations and animations so these
other components are really simple
we're going to see them here this is
what we saw by now it's simply that
hover and from so we turn the element
this is what we see for now but we have
been working only with roti why and what
8x this is what we get but and besides
that we can also mix them so now we get
to rotate both axes at the same time and
we get this and besides there's
something else we can turn which is the
seat a plane so you can rotate ghana
cita maybe around 200 degrees so we can
see it right so we can mix all of the
axes mix them all together this is one
way of the unit but there's actually a
shorter one that's rotate 3d which is a
really a little special we can put
something like this see your 10 and a
degree like 45 so when we do this what
we see is that we are activating the y
axis so this one over here refers to why
this one reflects two eggs so is if we
put 11 then we get this because we are
activating on both the x axis and the y
axis and the other one the other 0 is
only destroy mini-mental there are you
are the other one is the sitter plane so
now we get this and we can also make
them separated like 120 50
in 10 and we get sort of this boring
thing so before besides wrote a 3d we
also get translate and translate clothes
we use in X or in Y and and it simply
translates the element if we put a
negative value it will go this way and
if we put a positive value will go the
other way so it's pretty simple but we
can mix it as well with other axis so we
could put translate y and then mix x and
y and it most a little bit more and
besides we could use translate sita and
we could say just 200 pixels because
it's better to exaggerate when we are
trying out the stuff so we can see that
it kind of gets bigger so what does it
get bigger because if getting closer to
us that's really interesting and we can
sit better if we rotate the element
maybe 50 degrees and rotate in a way so
now with that so they translate theta
what it does is m to move this part this
axis of the element and in awaken any
closer to us which is really useful when
we do something like this we turn the
elements around and it gets closer to us
and farther from us in the process so
there it goes and it gets closer and
further
and translate also has the short version
which is simply translate 3d and we put
different values like five negatives
let's go up and the other one it could
be something like this so we have live
thing once we modify all that we apply
animations we can create something like
that letter over there so that is
definitely a little short and about
browser compatibility likely is kind of
nice it goes along with from form so
every rose or a half the problem with
drum for property will have it with
perspective and so in WebKit blink we
need prefix did say the next version of
Chrome will not need it so lightly will
will not need it later and Firefox is
okay and softly internet explorer
doesn't we perturb 3d so and we can use
more nicer and another thing to fix it
well that's basically all sorry was a
little short and so that's in case