um and before I really get started I
need to do this poll otherwise because I
don't know how to continue so let me get
my camera out because this is going to
be important I just need to document
this so how many of you guys want me to
call this a jiff and let's see a show of
hands for fuel to want me to call it a
gift cool so thank you for that I'm
going to try to remember not to
pronounce it the other way which I'd
never totally never do so hi I'm Pavel
um at Mac and I on Twitter I'm here
repping Vegas gs-r las vegas-based
javascript meetup group and here on
behalf of zappos com where I do backend
mobile API development in Java so when I
get home I'll be sure to tell them i
really enjoyed the java fest right right
i'm here with some buddies of mine dan
and Dashon dan is speaking later and you
might have heard dave speak at happy
JSON like versioning api's with happy if
you're in Vegas do stop by or look me up
and I'm not going to make any
presumptions that anybody here is a web
developer because javascript is
everywhere now right and I'm definitely
not going to make any assumptions that
you guys were web developers way back
when this was a thing because you all
look so useful it's not creepy right so
just in summary the the one by one pixel
gift is taking so nowadays we do
positioning on web pages with CSS it's
very powerful it's easy to move things
around and specify margins and padding
and XYZ position that maybe not z
positions well maybe in dance
presentation you can do Z positions but
XY positions on the page and it's really
nice but the back when the one by one
pixel gif workaround was created there
was no such thing you basically had page
full options of like down to the right
everything was down into the right so
the way to get around this was to take a
1 by
one pixel gif and just stretch it out
use that as a positioning and my monitor
hates this thing okay cool and so this
is what that looks like that's actually
a gift that's stretched out to whatever
like is it still a pixel if it's
stretched out because it's no longer
like one pixel it's like a whole
nevermind this is basically what the
code looked like so it worked it works
surprisingly well except for the fact
that then you had like all this this
extra these extra images in your code
and that violates something called like
the Semantic Web the guy who invented
the interwebs kind of likes that stuff
and and and what it is it's um it's that
you want want the the content of the
webpage take priority over the
presentation so it can be referenced
easily and used easily in parts by
machines and it's more usable and a an
image that's invisible has no semantic
meaning so it kind of made Tim
berners-lee cry a little bit does
anybody know who this guy is No so this
man is named Dave Segal andresito
seagull seagull so yeah no not different
guy a different guy and so if like Tim
berners-lee and Eric Myers are like the
patron saints of like semantic web and
like like I don't know like good web
design with standards this guy's more of
like a satanic priest with with goat
leggings it kind of like hops around and
pokes young web developers the
smoldering sticks to get them to do
stuff you can't really blame them so he
wrote this book called creating killer
websites as anybody has anybody read
this so this is this is written back in
1996 and it had actually so Dave Segal
invented 1 x 1 pixel gif trick according
to him and and so it was it was broke
into the world in this book so it's kind
of like one of those things but it's not
just that it wasn't just like this one
little trick to make your web you know
do this book is like packed with work
grounds of that sort with all kinds of
like
little insidious like hacks and like
using invisible tables for layout and
stuff like that you can't really blame
them though because you know at this
time he might have been actually the
first person ever to think about this as
the point of view of like a web designer
instead of a web developer and again
like down to the right is not very
flexible for somebody who came at it
from print design he had a lot of
interesting quotes I'm going to read
this to you because it's long and I know
like attention spans but this is one of
his quotes if you want machines to read
your web pages use things like
definition lists unordered list headers
etc if you want people to read them
don't do it they take away your
typographical control specify your own
font sizes when you want to size change
if you must use bullets make your own
bullets I don't see much point in
bullets if your vertical grouping is
good and try not to ever number your
list items it's hardly ever necessary so
he had some crazy ideas and you have
probably made Tim berners-lee cry a
little bit but again he was from print
design and he was just not I mean he
just wanted his web pages look good he
was not apologetic for it all I'm gonna
take you through a few of the tricks
that uh that I used back then and then
we're kind of popular like so I I was a
web developer back then and I've used
like probably all of these and done
worse things for a while I hosted one by
one gif net because i used the you know
the single pixel images so much there's
pretty bad web designer back that I'm
still pretty bad web designer but now
use CSS so that's cool so one of the
ways you can use these to indenture
paragraphs you just take like a short
and long gift it's invisible you put it
in front of your your paragraph it works
fine there was no other way of doing
this at the time you could add extra
spaces but then the white space was
cancelled out so this is kind of the way
it worked well except for the fact you
had to put it in front of every
paragraph and now you can just do that
with like text indent with CSS it's
beautiful you can do eam dashes you just
make it a visible gift and you stick it
in there now there's no that you could
do like to text ashes there were no
there wasn't a good way of doing this
and you could type
the good there's no space between
letters it's supposed to be it's like
how it's supposed to be from a
typographer standpoint it just wreaks
havoc on like copy paste and it's it's
weird now we have htmlentities you can
just drop in and and it works great
wasn't there back then you can control
line spacing so same thing as the
paragraph indent just you know vertical
and I should at this time point out that
the the V space and via line we have
there they don't work anymore not in
html5 but they would basically just add
spaces on the sides of them you can fake
it with width and height by the way
which is how I got this to render at all
so this works great there's another way
of doing this you could maybe at most
like double space your lines and stuff
but this gave you precise control of
your line spacing now you just use line
spacing it works really well this is
more of the other things were kind of
forgivable there's another way of doing
this is kind of like a what are you even
doing so he this is this is an actual
Dave example he made a decorative like
horizontal rule by using transparent
purple transparent sorry transparent
gifts and purple gifts and made this
weird thing that that um I don't even
know like you just constructed an image
using HTML there's no excuse for this it
was just like we had the technology is
just like just an image right and
probably the amount of space that that
one gift would take up even like a
really long one is less than all of this
markup it's horrible the other use
that's pretty common the mighty familiar
with our web bugs really call them were
creepy pixels for kind of tracking your
visitors this one this is kind of an
aside this one you might be familiar
with this is what google analytics sends
down like to track your visitors and but
considering that Google sends out like I
don't know really large numbers of these
per day you might think they want to
compress it down as much as possible and
that's pretty true so a few years ago
somebody over at probably programming
whose name is not mentioned at all on
the site so i can't really give credit
kind of looked into this
and looked up the the formula of a gif
image and tried to find out what the
smallest possible gift was and it turns
out like if you include all the
necessary things it's 43 bites the one
that Google sends out is 35 and it's a
it's a white pixel that's because they
excluded the the graphics control
extensions which make it transparent so
I like I don't know if this is true at
all but I like to think that there's
somebody at Google who's looked at the
numbers and was like you to extra bytes
like I would like to have a transparent
image but the savings of two bites are
just going to be too awesome and I don't
know if how that's working out for them
but that was there how am i doing on
time my good okay I just want to look at
maybe like one other horrible horrible
hack at me it's not that horrible
actually I use this one lock which is
rounded corners there was no good way of
doing this in like 97 so what we do is
we take these images in Photoshop and
give them a transfer sorry a white
background no sorry a white foreground
the upper left is white and the bottom
right is transparent and that way if you
put it up in the corner of one of your
tables you could change the color of the
table and the whole thing would change
is grounded and it worked pretty well I
think like as far as horrible markup
it's not that bad it's just like one
table but still not semantics not an
ideal solution and then script oculus
came out anybody anybody member script
tactless we have any fans yeah so I
think it's the best thing ever the
website kind of looks like it doesn't
look that much more modern than that
very first web site we were looking at
where this stuff was like centered in
the circles I think we were going
through some sort of like all right fine
we realize the images are bad and we're
going to trust anything except for a
bunch of images so script oculus made it
so that you could like have your markup
be clean but then there'd be some
JavaScript that would make your corners
magically round okay cool that's awesome
it's perfectly clean but the way it did
it was by inserting like stacks and
stacks of tiny tiny divs that's me
moving my mouse cursor up and down
across the the debugger fool so just
like so many divs for just these stupid
rounded corners
and it's like it's almost worse in a way
I think than just sticking an image in
there like you understand images were
bad and it's kind of like it definitely
a step in a different direction but
maybe not the the right one I don't know
and so like am I allowed to have like a
like a like a lesson or like something
are these supposed to be complete so if
there's a lesson to all of this I want
it to be this so if you make things kind
of hard for people for things hard for
people to do what they want they're
going to find ways of working around it
and so I mean that's good i'm not going
to discourage hacks hacks are like a
very proud tradition of computer land
people like we all love tax and stuff
but the thing is like you know if you
find a hack and then you you know use it
and it becomes like pretty convenient it
catches on other people use it maybe you
like right a kind of opportunity to book
about it and it gets out there and soon
like the hack becomes commonplace it's
going to kind of hurt the internet maybe
like or hurt javascript or something so
like do your hacks but i kind of want
you to be like a little bit little bit
thoughtful of them and so while you're
doing the hack think about like how
would i do this if the world is perfect
it was an ideal world because there are
longer-term solutions and like you can
take your your ideas and and just sort
of share them out there are this is the
extensible web manifesto if you guys are
read it so so like the people who write
browsers and rendering engines they
don't just like write them they work off
of standards and there's people to
contribute to these standards and like
those people could be you like you could
you read the manifesto it's really
inspiring and and like maybe read some
draft specifications look at them give
your commentary sign up to some mailing
lists you might like it you might make
like the future less painful for for
future you so that's all I got
I'm not going to mess with Futterman how