I'm Nathan Riley and I live in the san
francisco bay area have been for
all my life pretty much and i work at
automatic wordpress com also known as
and i've been there for about a year i
came over with the cloud up acquisition
with ki jaya or ouch and i primarily do
javascript over there you know we were
working on a new editor experience for
for making blog posts and they they're
relying on us to make that experience
happen so I've been doing JavaScript for
at least five years i would say i would
i would consider myself pretty
proficient in it primarily all of my
development work is in javascript or at
least something that compiles to
JavaScript for HTML and CSS which are
related but it's definitely my my
primary language so specifically we're
working on building the new editor
experience making blog posts and having
a really nice clean interface for
including embeds and you know youtube
things like that and also bringing over
some clawed up influences to the editor
as well like the drag and dropping of
files on the web browser and having them
being included in the post that way well
I mean it's touching wordpress com so
that's like a pretty big chunk of the
internet right I mean I mean WordPress
itself is like 20 over twenty percent of
the internet and wordpress com hold
holds a good chunk of that as well so
it's gonna be going into the hands of
you know millions of users right out
right off the gate so that I mean for me
that's nerve-racking but also exciting
and JavaScript because didn't be around
for a while web browsers have proved
that to us and the web browser is the
you know the primary platform of choice
these days so that's you know that's
javascript is really early option other
than these new you know compiled two
languages that you know are ultimately
just JavaScript in the end
well it's my third time here in
beautiful bunny series and I just can't
get enough of it every time you see mo
says we're coming back in like 20 hour
flight I'm there this is the most
beautiful javascript conference I've
ever been to hands down the designers
are off the chain I love all the pixel
art and the art work and I mean really
the production value is incredible live
streaming in the videos and I mean yeah