again hi my name is Andy I'm going to
talk to you about happy plugins so this
is me by the way I'm not related to the
royal family even though I am British
look at the name spellings different Who
am I I'm an engineer are and i work for
open table in the UK if you don't know
it in table our businesses restaurant
reservations our stack is mainly c-sharp
a node with Java a little bit of like go
and Ruby and closure and all that stuff
thrown in so a real mixed bag we've been
using happy for about what in our team
we've been using happy for about 12
months now I first heard about happy a
node user group meetup and then I was
given the opportunity to rewrite a an
awful dotnet legacy system and I was
like great let's use happy and we've
been using it ever since so we've got
but maybe a dozen api's now of varying
sizes and complexities usually it's all
internal api's there are a couple of
internal tools which internal websites
but our main business is AP is our stack
is happy running on ubuntu with a
MongoDB back-end and some Redis thrown
in there for good measure so as we've
learned happy and as we've learned as
we've grown our kind of happy stack we
start to coalesce shared code using the
plugins interface so I'm not going to
stand here and read you the docs because
that we really dull but they're going to
have a look what I'm going to do is just
show you some of the really simple stuff
that we've done that makes our lives
easier so the first plug-in I wrote was
pretty simple all it does is you point
at a directory it walks the directory
and says is there something in there
that looks like a routes file if so call
severed uproot on it basically was to
get rid of the boilerplate of calling
server da trute everywhere
the of the the main part parts of this
plug-in you've probably seen this
already a couple of times today but the
register function which takes the server
options and next call back so the key
bit there is the server so that server
object is exactly the same server object
that you get when you do new happy dot
server which means anything that you're
doing in your application code you can
wrap it in a plug-in and that's really
really powerful frankly it beats the
hell out of a pues so yeah the
registration code for registering a
plug-in you call server register you
give it a list of plugins each plug-in
has its own little options object and
then at the end you get a nice callback
that says if everything is good start
the server yeah so another one of the
plugins that we wrote was for versioning
now everybody you talk to has a
different attitude on versioning
internally opentable we have a
convention of using URL version which i
think is a bit icky but I wanted to
support head of versioning as well so
you create the little plugin that can
monkey with the request and say well if
it's if it looks like a URL versioned
URL then grab the version out of it and
you set the request prerequisite with
the with the data with the version this
code uses the on pre handler extension
point which is the interesting bit the
extension point there are six of them
which cover the request lifecycle so
you've got on request is the first and
then on pre auth on post off on pre
handler on post handler and on pre
response so basically anything you want
to do during the recycle the life cycle
of the request you can hook into one of
these extension points and boom you've
got the request
if you're if you're not covering things
that happen in the life cycle there are
the server events as well so you've got
the error log so any time server log is
called far as an event any time server
the arrow is called far as an event and
you've got the other interesting ones
you've got requests obviously and tail
so if you don't know about tail it's
basically when the request is just about
done and the response has been sent then
the tail event is fired so that's kind
of the the last event in the life cycle
on laptops gone to sleep come on oh
right good smashing yeah sorry so tail
is the last event in the life cycle and
it's stuff like this that makes happy
really lend itself to the kind of the
node way that fred was talking about it
yesterday you have small modules which
do small things and it means that you
get the composability because you've got
a fully so you've got a full server
object here which means anything you
want to do you can do there's no there's
no monkeying about you have to do got it
all up front another classic example
we've got so we use naji us for alerting
and we have a convention of using a
service status endpoint so for our team
what we do is we have a monitor which
has a path on it so it says right I'm
going to hit / food / bar / 1 and time
the request so it does a server that
inject times it and then you wrap the
response so you can you can really
easily just pop it just makes setting up
the Minaj eos monitors a case of
configuration so that's the response you
get out of it you get the response code
the time it took
off at hit and status the status is
either okay or failed and you just point
nagi us at that and away you go and it's
the server don't inject is only part of
it but most of the stuff i'm showing
here is kind of boilerplate extensions i
mean we have similar stuff for
initializing database doing feature
toggling doing health and heartbeat and
all that sort of thing and you can take
this to the logical conclusion as well
which is that everything in your
application can be a plug-in we saw it
earlier with John where your application
code is wrapped in a plug-in which means
it's got a standard interface to the
rest of the world if you want a really
good example of this I would recommend
you go and look at the code for mpms new
website because it's awesome and
I've been geeking out about it for a
while now so conclusion plugins are
awesome if you're not wrapping your
stuff in plugins and you're making more
work for yourself in the future because
you have to write the glue code over and
over again whereas if you if you're
using plugins then it's a standard
interface to the rest of the your
application or the rest of the world I
hope this has been the
interesting I realized I was in the
after lunch spot so hopefully