[Music]
my name is Gregor I'm an organizer of
the noches meetup in Hamburg and me and
my co-organizer are very passionate
about building a community around this
topic and as it happens to be the
community leased by the people right so
our main our main problem I would say to
provide to the community a good time at
our meetups is to find people to who are
willing to stay here and talk to the
others and they have usually all the all
the time the same concerns about like I
don't know what I'm talking about
or unscared maybe somebody who me out
and something like that and I just want
to say guys and girls and otherwise most
of the organizers including us working
our butts off to create a safe space for
you and know if you stay here nobody
wouldn't gonna judge you and you're
talking to the same people who are you
would talk about or to just at the cup
of coffee so don't care about anything
about judging and something like that
just come here and talk about whatever
you are passionate about because even if
you think it's not very interesting
topic or whatever I bet a bet with you
that there's always somebody in the
crowd
who is interested or didn't know about
this thing there's every about everyone
or every time somebody there who's just
starting or forgot about it or just like
to hear about the stuff he's passionate
about - so just shout out stop talking
and if you don't know if you want to be
here or is there's any interest in into
in your topic come to us we can we're
gonna help you I promise
yeah so that's my shoutout as an
organizer help us to help you to have a
good time thank you