alright so this is our final talk of the
evening in case it wasn't incredibly
obvious this has been a lie this is not
alex russell or fake alex russell or
anybody like that or maybe it is fake
alex for us as it they it is actually
fake alex russell so it isn't actually
technically a lie Pete's got a little
wonderful announcement hot on the heels
of another announcement this is our
final talk this is what some of us would
like to call the PS de resistance of
JavaScript in jazz comp if Andrew Lonnie
would be a little bit quieter oh nice
pants short it short it short it so is
the projector working it's not o net I
can just actually give my talk in front
of a blank screen because it's all in my
head sorry about the technical
difficulties it must use dojo back there
in the back end um which actually brings
me to to my announcement I am in case
you do not know or not aware of this i
am peter higgins a project lead of the
dojo toolkit yeah there's got mixed
emotions on that one um so and I
actually inherited it from alex russell
fake alex russell was fallax he he left
and i have since decided kind of falling
on the the shirt tales of john leaving
mozilla everyone knows about that John's
left Mozilla for the Khan Academy yeah
good good good stuff I'm actually taking
over his project lead of the jQuery
project
it's a very very exciting time for all
of us I'm renaming the tagline to the
right more do less library and we're
going with we're going with the
synchronous module system for node so
this is actually it was going to be my I
have a whole slide deck on my my
thoughts on the greatness that this
transition will be and just the whole
common brow if I don't know if anybody
was here for the the Berlin talk that I
did the same exact talk who's ultimately
the same exact talk in Berlin the common
browser j/s and how we need to kind of
unify and agree on a loader and agree on
a micro framework that we can start from
or I'll you didn't laugh at that one you
guys really like the micro framework
thing don't you ok that's good that's
good i'm having a tough crowd Chris why
can't I get my slides up there's all
sorts of funny in my slides gonna
need that back thanks
thank you for your time
hey everybody I'm the real out Russell
get a lot of that uh awesome so last
year they had Chris our inimitable
organizer had me followed Brendan which
was an incredibly tough act to follow
and many including myself will say I
didn't actually live up to the task so I
think as penance he decided to make him
do it again this year to see if I can do
better and we'll find out so uh
something like 3-4 months ago I started
something of a blog fight about our
favorite new Debbie God feature
detection which we've sort of all taken
as on the client side anyway the way to
do it right you know we want to build
robust sustainable web apps and
JavaScript frameworks that are going to
stand the test of time that aren't going
to be subject to significant drift as
the browser population upgrades as new
things get introduced into the world
like we want the future to look
different so we wanted to involve a lot
of new and different user agents we
don't want to just have the same ones
that we've always had we want
competition to work and we want to be
able to have the code that we write live
inside that world the way everything
else does so I posited that you don't
want to make Steve Souders mad Steve's a
really nice guy if you know him but you
don't really want to make him mad a
nicer don't because I work with him and
he can actually walk over to my desk and
sort of you know like look very
disappointed in me and that's that's
hard to take so Steve wrote a last fall
that the key to creating fast user
experience in today's web sites is to
render pages as quickly as possible and
to achieve this JavaScript loading an
execution have to be deferred right my
bad paraphrase uh but but his point here
is that in order to make anything fast
in the web today javascript winds up in
the way and it winds up in the way in a
couple of different different ways so I
tried to paint the picture for how we
might get around this right how we might
use some sort of a cache on
client-side to help us determine whether
or not we can do this and I think my
point was lost because what I didn't
discuss necessarily was enough of the
ways that the core of the browser
rendering pipeline makes life difficult
if you're going to be relying on
JavaScript for everything this is
JavaScript conference and for the second
year in a row in a row I'm here to tell
you to use a little bit less javascript
in places where it might be problematic
so things that blocks up right and those
include in a browser environment DNS
lookup right you can't go fetch any
resource until you actually go figure
out we're going to get it from you can't
necessarily do anything while javascript
is parsing and compiling if you're
actually counting on the result of that
of that evaluation script downloads
block rendering synchronous ex hrs block
everything of course and jobs to
execution again like synchronous xhr
blocks everything because there's the
you know run a completion model of
javascript in the browser so this
presents a series of challenges and
feature detection can really hurt you in
a bunch of these places so if you're
relying if you're building your
application based on a tall stack of
stuff that's going to have at the core
of it at the very front of it so I'm
feature detection to add classes or to
go set up the world for CSS or for other
parts of your application to go start to
play you're putting javascript in the
way in front of everything else and this
turns into a real problem specifically
when you're trying to get to a rich you
I in a constrained environment so let's
talk about those constraints because
this is the this is the new world right
this is the new promised land the mobile
web is where it's at and if you don't
think that that's where it's at then
you're probably not paying close enough
attention so um at the high end we're
getting significantly better hardware
every day the networks are getting
somewhat better but we're still limited
right we've got single core as the top
of the line right now we're about to get
to a core we've got limited RAM and it's
shared ram across everything in the
system right it's significantly better
than what I took to college with me but
um and that's how old I am but it's
still not great right compared to what
you're doing in your desktop where I
just got like dual quad core xeons with
16 gig of ram the other day okay that's
pretty good and it looks nothing like my
phone so the same sorts of techniques
that we're using might have to adapt a
little bit so there's a lot more that's
different right some of these things are
good some of these things are bad but
effectively if we think about the single
threaded rendering
execution model of the browser none of
these things do is a big favor when
they're better and a lot of them are
worse when they're not we don't have
better speculative execution on top of
ARM processors the bus bandwidth is
relatively lower we're in a world of
hurt um okay I'm sorry I can't do this
anymore this is really freaking boring I
can't be good yeah so um let's not talk
about that let's talk about something
much better and I want to apologize to
everyone who came here to hear the
feature detection talk we can do that
over beer later but future detection
like just ask Steve what'll make your
web app fast he'll he'll be happy to
tell you I don't need to do that for him
don't don't make stuff slow all right
but what I really want to talk about is
JavaScript and how we can get to a place
where when you write javascript in your
application it can sort of read like the
way you wanted to say what you met the
last several talks and a bunch of the
stuff that's talked about new features
for the language in the last couple of
days have been incredibly inspiring
about how we can move the language
forward about what sorts of things are
coming and teach 39 what sorts of things
are coming at the hest of libraries and
you know me right like the joke about
the the right more do less library is
not a so subtle dig at me in part
because I've attempted to work in this
world to try to make libraries a way to
get what we want right but they have
these constraints put on them so if your
library happens to live you know at the
top level in a page you know is it the
thing that's blessed you know the talk
we had yesterday about scope objects
extensions was amazing because it's set
up this incredible narrative about the
limited power of libraries to solve a
lot of the questions that we've got and
it set up the language as the only place
to necessarily solve the Tower of Babel
problem and this continues to this day
so I want to now you know bring out my
good friend and colleague Peter Hallam
to help fill us in on the rest of the
story and give you a sense for what it
is that we're doing on the chrome team
to help
you be able to say what you mean in
JavaScript thanks Alex everyone all
right um my name is Peter Hallam I work
at Google and a few months ago Alex kind
of put the word out that he was looking
for people to help him with the future
of JavaScript and I'm a language guy
spent 10 years at Microsoft working on C
sharp and when I heard that he was
looking for someone to work on languages
that was an offer that I just could not
refuse so that sort of brings me here it
continually amazes me what people can do
in the browser you know it's not just a
little event handlers anymore people are
actually writing real applications this
is a favorite of mine pac-man had a game
of that last night at the at the arcade
and you know as people are writing
larger and larger applications you're
seeing all these libraries that are
getting written to help to help people
write these large applications and and
over and over again you're seeing that
these libraries are solving the same
kinds of problems and when we're talking
about the future of length of JavaScript
you know this is kind of where we need
to start for finding you know what we
should be doing to the language this is
a quote by another famous language
designer Sharon's true strip library is
a language design is library design and
library design is language design so
everybody out there who's been working
on your favorite JavaScript library you
know you've really been taking the first
steps to basically designing the future
of JavaScript so I want to talk a little
bit I'm going to make this kind of short
cuz I'm we're going over time but a
little
but just a couple of things that you
know we're thinking of in terms of the
future of JavaScript you know obviously
we're working together with the folks at
Mozilla and everyone else in the
JavaScript community to move the
language forward but specifically we
want to talk about writing large
applications in JavaScript so when
you're talking about large applications
JavaScript I'm you know one of the
differentiating factors being small apps
and large apps is that you want to have
components you know and when we talk
about components we really mean is
reusable pieces of software we know with
strong boundaries that that that you can
reuse and you know one of the things
they're one of the smallest order units
of components in software's classes
today in in JavaScript if you want to
have a class you know you obviously
described described as a constructor
function and really this these two
things together the both a constructor
function and the prototype together are
the sort of reasonable component and yet
it doesn't really look like that when
you're right when you're writing your
code and of course you can use
prototypal inheritance you know this is
how you do a derived class which works
great until your constructor function
for your base class actually you know
take some parameters or or uses some
state or mutate some state and then all
of a sudden this really breaks down but
it does allow you to you know create a
create an instance of an object you know
inserting pac-man object is actually an
instance of the base class actor so the
problem with you know solution to that
of course is to do something like this
which was actually lifted from one of
the favorite libraries unfortunately you
know that actually does what you want
but it doesn't really read like pac-man
you know derives from actor and and we
really want to try and try and change
that
and of course you know the library
library author is already taken you know
the first steps to trying to solve this
problem and so you see all the libraries
doing that so you see closure library I
think that's prototype and of course
base to whoops and so I know all these
library authors you know have have you
know solved this problem but they all
solve it in a way that is not compose
it's not composable right they're not
compatible so you can't you can't take a
classic layer in one place and use it
another and that's really the you know I
think one of the benefits for what we'd
like to see is a syntax that actually
describes I'm reads like what the
intention that you want to express okay
you know another big issue for
components is modules and dave herman
did a great talk yesterday on on modules
and the benefits of modules again this
is something that you know all the
library authors have have solved you
know whether its closure whether it's
dojo and again once you put the syntax
in the language you get a lab you get
real reuse and you don't have to opt
into a single framework you can actually
use code from multiple frameworks once
you have this again this is another one
where we had a great talk by andrew de
pont on scoped object extensions again
it's a question of monkey patching is a
place you know where you get friction
with large application development you
know once you because all these shared
objects are mutable you can attach new
things to the new methods to them which
is great because it allows you to write
code like this
but the problem with that is is that
once you get into large software
development these monkey patches can
conflict and so some libraries take
great pains to not do any monkey
patching at all they provide the same
functionality but as you can see it
comes at a real syntactic cost you know
I think we'd all prefer to be able to
write the first one the first example
rather than the second but you know but
in today's JavaScript that's prohibitive
in large applications so what we'd like
to see is scoped object extensions which
is piggy backs off of a Foreman's
modulus proposal a scoped object
extension is like a monkey patch may
declare inside of a module and it's
available inside the module but outside
the module it's as if it wasn't even
there and because we want reusability we
want to be able to import them across
modules so that you can import these
monkey patches into your own into your
own source code another one I think this
that when we talk about is asynchronous
programming this is another situation
where you know this is a common program
pattern in JavaScript which is the
callback pattern you know because of
because most javascript javascript
embedded in single-threaded environments
you know we have the callback pattern
all long-running API calls take
callbacks so that we don't ever block
the main thread the problem with this is
that is that the that the callback
callbacks infect your API and they're
really not composable because you have
to pass these callbacks around
everywhere and so again this is a
situation where library authors have
taken the lead and to help alleviate
this problem with a deferred pattern
some folks also call it promises
basically a deferred object or
a deferred function represents a unit of
computation that allows you to attach a
call back to it once it completes and so
with with deferred you see this which
moves the call back out of the out of
the the parameter list of the animate
function but it's still really hard to
see what animate is actually trying to
do and the reason why is that you've
actually got to turn your your code
inside out into what's called a CPS
transformer or a continuation passing
transform can you ask and it turns out
that this is something that is actually
really tough to do by hand but is
actually something that the compiler can
automate for you and so what we really
like to be able to do is is allow you to
write code and instead of looking like
this looks a little bit more like this
where you've got what you're really
doing here is you're just you're just
iterating through a for loop setting the
margin on your element and then saying
hey I want to wait for five milliseconds
before I go through this again and of
course and this is the kind of this is
kind of code that we want to we'd like
we love to be able to see in billa
writing JavaScript and the question so
is that it answers no there's a whole
lot of things that are in sort of that
have been talked about in sort of
JavaScript next these are I think most
of the things that are I've been talked
about either in tc39 talked a lot about
a lot of these today and so we're hoping
that that you know there's a lot of
things you can do to JavaScript to to
make it better again we've talked about
this Brendan mentioned this issue of the
you know when can we use this stuff em
and and sort of when can you try this
out and the short answer is we really
want to we we really want to be able to
get feedback from library authors as
soon as possible into into the language
design process
because at the end of the day the leg
design only is successful if it lets you
write code that you want to write so
what I'm going to do here is I'm going
to come back to our deferred function
example one minute here
and so what we did is we actually wrote
a compiler for most of these new
features that translates it from the new
feature syntax into standard browser
JavaScript and actually this where I
want to do a shout out to some of the
guys that helped that wrote this other
other folks at Google Chris burrows
martin O'Malley John nester Lee Bob
Nystrom and of course someone you folks
all know Eric arvidson as you can see
you know the code that this compiler is
translate translating this into is
pretty wonky you wouldn't actually want
to write this stuff yourself but at the
end of the day this is the kind of thing
that callbacks actually forces you to do
now obviously you're not a compiler so
you're not going to write it quite like
this but at end of the day this is the
kind of thing that it forces you to do
and so we actually have this hooked up
so you can run it inside the browser and
get it working right now and so what we
really love is for everyone here to give
this a try give these new features a try
and give us feedback on whether this
whether this stuff is actually going to
solve your problems so what what we've
done we're so Google is open sourcing
tracer which is our in-browser
JavaScript to JavaScript compiler that
compiles from a sort of JavaScript next
down to browser JavaScript and it's yeah
so just open sourced it on code that
google com and the first short link is a
rep a loop that you can use to actually
try out this stuff in the browser right
now and the second link is is a link
that you can use to actually for the
slides themselves and you can actually
see the compiler running in the talk
all right I think that's it for me
thanks folks
so yeah we're really excited about
tracer and we're hoping that you'll try
it out and give us your feedback
especially about the new features it
can't implement everything as we've
mentioned and we hope that you'll give
it a shot let us know how it goes so
that we can get what you think is good
and bad fed back into the standards
process you can try it out today give it
a go and uh questions no questions about
any of that really come on okay beer all
right I get it all right here all right
well thanks did you remember the baby oh
no