okay yeah I so I have a bit of a cough
so I'm going to try to like get through
this as painlessly as possible so yeah
the name of the presentation is called
burn the museum's pretty good I work at
a company called Twitter I wore a shirt
so if you're not familiar there's like
the deferred stuff it's pretty cool you
should check it out it's in a city
called San Francisco and when I'm not
working and I actually at work too I all
I really do is I write libraries that's
all I've somehow convinced Twitter to
allow me to do that for like a job I
work on this library at work called
widgets j/s which does like tweet button
and follow button and tweet and beds and
like all that crazy and then I also
do a lot of open source libraries which
is what Alex was talking about so one
library is called bootstrap which you
might have heard of its kind of it's
kind of a big deal on github right now I
also work on another one which is that
Oh bootstrap is like a UI kind of thing
and then ender is another thing that I
work on and ender is like a package
manager it's like an attempt at a
client-side package management
piggybacks on NPM I saw Isaac actually
at some point at this confident I don't
know he's probably not here he's like
Jacob who's that loser I'm not going to
that dock and the the other library were
gone is called Hogan jazz with the very
brilliant rob sager just like all the
really cool stuff and I just kind of
like just pretend like I help out
sometimes and so when I got first asked
to like talk here I was like really
confident I was like I'll to talk about
bootstraps gonna be awesome so easy I
talk about all the time people say hey
you're the bootstrap guy like yeah and
then after we had to sing it Twitter
called tea time and after one of the tee
times dan webb was like who works at
Twitter it's like it's pretty cool he
came up to me he's like oh here you
might talk to Jess confidence
he's like it's Jay it's like it's
Jas comp you can't talk about
bootstrap like you have to talk about
something cool and like weird like talk
about bacon or like do something unique
and I was like oh like I do nothing
except for right libraries like I have
my lights last slide but I used to read
books sometimes so it I was like hey
that's all I got I'll talk about books
kind of but the books that I read when I
like went back to look at the books I
read they're like the worst books like
everyone hates these books and so at
school I studied futurism and data which
are like Eastern Central European
avant-garde books which are just the
most frustrating books to read or
encounter average just like people
writing things to be annoying kind of
and I often times I feel my I find
myself doing similar things so if you've
seen like bootstrap I don't add
semi-colons and it's really just to
annoy you but I'm going to talk a little
bit about these guys these are Italian
features they look really cool I was
really excited when I found this picture
I was like look at these guys so so cool
I could really just end the presentation
with these guys would be like man
successful successful Jays go best one
of it and so these are futurists were
crazy and they're really about one thing
which was eliminating the past doing
cool new stuff and I would talk to you
about that a little bit so to kind of
like set the stage it was early if early
20th century there's like telephones and
automobiles and airplanes and all this
new stuff and they were like freaking
out because you have artists who were
kind of unstable to begin with and then
like all just crazy cool new stuffs
happening and they're like oh my god
they're like losing their and so
look at there we go so there's this guy
Marin Eddie who's a poet and he he ends
up writing this feature is manifesto
where he talks about speed he actually
has this one poem where he like she was
freaking out through the whole thing
he's actually starts he's talking about
riding in a car at like 40 miles an hour
and how it's like the fastest anyone's
ever gone and how it's like so
incredible which now seems so dumb
because like
40 miles oh you're like stressing out
when the speed limit is 40 miles now now
but they were like freaking out because
they'd been on like horses in lame
like that and so and so here's a piece
of art from them and you can kind of see
like they're getting really excited
about like motion and bright colors and
this is called rise of the city and so
you have all this and these artists are
all freaking out and having a good time
and just about the same time there's
these anarchists like so there's like
Marx it's like a whole thing don't have
you've heard of marks and so these
Italian anarchist show up and they've
got bombs and they're freaking out there
so excited they're like oh my god the
future it's good it's so good we got to
destroy everything that's the past and
amidst this wild ecstasy of destruction
let man reborn is Java ba-ba-boom future
it's got to be great and unfortunately
this thing happens which is the world
war one and as you can imagine all these
Italian people that are like these crazy
artists are like yes the war that'll
clear everything out so soon as Italy
joins the war like all the future sir
like yeah war and they all like join but
they're artists so they suck at fighting
and they all die like this just movement
over like it's just done which is which
is kind of sad because they were come to
some cool stuff but luckily there's this
thing called data which is the other
stuff that I read which is it's awful um
is this these guys you can tell so
they're they're pretty great see clearly
which is you know it's good it's funny
sometimes um so during World War one
there was this neutral area in
Switzerland called Zurich and all the
kind of the artists that were like wait
turns out i'm pretty sure i'm going to
die if I got in the war I'll just go
chill out here and it turned into kind
of like a South by Southwest for artists
when I I had this like weird I went to
South by Southwest for the first time
this year and when I first got there I
was just like walking down the street
and I saw Alex Sexton like blackout
drunk just like walking I was like holy
is that Alex Sexton like oh my god so
I'm imagine it must have been the exact
same they were like oh my god I'll execs
then I freaked out it's a lot like
and so but the thing is all these
artists are here but they're not
relieved they're not like yeah I escaped
them like the war like hey good times
like you are at South by Southwest
they're like they're super pissed
they're like man I had this awesome flat
I was hauling at the sweet honey and
Paris it was great now I'm in the Zurich
like come on this sucks and so there are
all these really frustrated artists and
they have all this pent-up energy and
like they need an outlet and a place to
come together and there's this one guy
named Hugo Bob could I want to talk
about a lot um and he is that a pub and
he's having a drink with the faces like
mates or whatever and he's like this is
a guy kind of nice like nice place is
super empty it's probably like half the
size of this and he's like why is there
no one here the sex and the bartender's
like being really sad and emo because no
one's drinking at his buyer and he's
like a bartender don't worry I've got
some friends they'll calm one time a
night just one time neither artist
little weird no big deal but i bet i'll
make you a lot of money and you'll stay
in business um so littell does the
bartender no Hugo ball is crazy
he is just he is out of control crazy
and so this is him he's about to give he
gives his sound poems I'm which I turn
out to be really incredible and everyone
forget excuse me freaks out but he's a
little nuts um and later on he says this
this thing which like moved me in this
really crazy way and I want to talk
about for the rest of the time that I'm
allowed to talk to you guys which is we
should burn all the libraries and allow
to remain only that which and everyone
knows by heart and and the first time I
read that I was like yeah that sounds
awesome and then I was like I write
libraries actually
and actually that's kind of like all I
do so I just kind of sad as a weird
moment so I was like why do you why
would you say that like you sing like a
cool guys got that like cool costume on
it's probably pretty regular and so the
first thing i did like every good
english majors i went straight to
wikipedia and i said what like what's a
library like i wanted to know kind of
the history and libraries if you've ever
looked at the history of libraries are
so boring oh my god but luckily
wikipedia summed it up pretty easily or
like pretty simply as this which is why
Barry's mark the end of prehistory in
the start of history so if you think of
them as kind of like when we start
writing down stuff like Oh historians
can study that then we might collect it
it's like whole thing and I'm like okay
it makes sense this is just like a
future thing he's like futurism is like
the same time maybe but they were all
like they had the bombs they were just
trying to get rid of it but then I knew
that wasn't really true i was like lying
to myself totally owe something that my
dad so i was like well i can't i can't
look into libraries anymore because
they're boring as as i just said
and so what if I think about programming
libraries which are like the bee's knees
we all will use libraries they're
awesome they have to be cool cuz we work
on him so what's the history of
programming libraries back to Wikipedia
every everything I try to find on the
history of libraries just kept coming
back to this one book which ironically I
had to go to a real library to find even
though I tried so hard not to I was like
oh my god a library so bad I went there
and the worst part was i couldn't check
the book out i had to be there so to get
multiple trips to the library saddest of
times for me um but the book is really
interesting and it's actually not like a
book in the traditional sense it's
actually just kind of like it was a
conference that they had and they have
all these like crazy old people that I
had never heard of because I know
nothing about computer science talking
about computers and like how things are
going on and then there's this woman who
turns out she's a boss she does
like she's very important and you should
know who she is and
she's a Grace Hopper and I was like oh
my god this she's like she's like his
Navy woman she's knows all about
libraries this this whole thing it's
really crazy oh my gosh and so I'm
reading through her like a like her
conference talk thing I hope someday
there's a book made about this talk so
someone's just like so depressed reading
through it so the first instance of a
library that I'm going to say is is this
line right here which is I'd whistle a
dick and say can I have your sign
subroutine and I'd copied out of his
notebook the first time I read that I
was like holy the first library it
was Dick's notebook oh my gosh and she
doesn't even say your dick is and so it
just so mysterious and so cool I was
like yes why would even would burn that
it's so awesome Dick's notebook and so
this turned out to be about nineteen
forty four ish and that's that's crazy
that's a long time ago bo a lot there's
a quote it's cool and and as time goes
on they're like collecting these things
together dicks notebooks getting huge
and like there's coffee stains and it
looks really serious meanwhile in London
there's these guys these london bros who
are like oh yeah this is obviously this
is pretty failed dicks notebook and they
kind of design like a new like a like a
library that we would think of but
unfortunately there's no computer that
can like run their library so this write
a paper and they're like we've had two
libraries but it doesn't it didn't even
work it's not really a thing meanwhile
Grace Hopper the boss is like like I
this like she's she's running in all
these problems like people are writing
B's it's turning into the 13s Forza
turning into A's and eventually she like
writes the first compiler and it's crazy
and it's blew my mind and so basically
all with all that like means is that
after Hugo ball was like we should burn
all libraries half-century later we have
this whole new thing this whole new
library idea which is programming
libraries which is in ticks notebook
which is pretty cool and then about 50
years later them all this whole time
we've been like using more and more
libraries I actually looked into how
long jquery has been around because i
was just kind of I like
I like I don't know like like some time
turns out there's a history jquery
something very cool very useful in like
two thousand six well i think in 2005
john rzeznik was like but i might be
working on a library and then like a
year later he was like jquery boosh and
everyone like lost their shadows good um
so if you think about that that's like
like six years only really the jake
where's been around we've had libraries
for 50 years like what if we really just
started over like how crazy would that
be if you think about six years like how
far jquery's come from like John Rezac
just being like I wait you guys I'm
working on something pretty cool too
like oh my god everyone knows what
jQuery is it's like a household name in
like nerd households and and so so I
said in the beginning I work at a
Twitter and I have a lot of freedom
because like people don't really take me
seriously and they're like okay Jacob
you can like interview people sometimes
oh wow thank you and so what I started
doing was I'd walk in with like a smug
smile on my face and I have a marker and
I'd be like you have 45 minutes to write
jquery from scratch it as far as you can
so from whatever you like it's gonna be
great you're gonna love it um I tweeted
this out because I thought this was
awesome and that everyone should be
interviewing like this and Ray bango was
pretty quick to point out that I was
like losing it like you're evil no one
can do that it's awful and basically all
the internet agreed with him except for
Rick Waldron who was like yes he's like
like not only is that an awesome
question I'm going to just do it for fun
just because I want to see so props to
him I think it's cuz he's metal and has
a cool jacket if you see him looking at
jackets got like reflectors is the whole
thing is really cool so basically well
that what I got from that was
instinctual you'd say if we burned all
libraries we'd be screwed we would be
like oh my gosh we have no idea what's
going on we're totally screwed after
asking this question a few times the
whiteboards will also suggest we are
screwed
um people have no idea what's going on
like you say you know okay well like
there's a dollar take some things and
like gives you some stuff no one knows
what's going on is it's black box come
on Jake away good thing but what if we
just tried it like what if we just are
egomaniacs and we're like oh man like
jQuery it's a thing it's pretty good
this works perfectly I'm just going to
rewrite it whoo guys so I so I tied I
tried that actually with this guy named
Dustin d is we were like jQuery is
pretty awesome it does everything we
want we don't really have any major
complaints but what if we just started
rewriting like what we kind of knew by
heart and so we tried that and so that's
like a selector engine a events library
in the Dom utility and so the first
thing we kind of noticed was like the
things were smaller this was like during
the micro j/s like buzzword time and it
was good and so things were smaller
there's like more focus api's we're like
we're awesome we are like we're saving
the internet we're the best people ever
um which is always you should when you
feel like that you should say huh maybe
I'm missing something um and so horse
ebooks if you don't know who horse
ebooks is it's really like the Oracle
and Twitter and one time horse ebooks
tweeted Dalton dangerous at all times
and usually wholly unnecessary and I
read that and I was like oh my god horse
ebooks knows about John David Dalton oh
my god because literally the very like I
was feeling like about this I was like
as my swag was on max I was like I'm the
best JavaScript person ever I just
rewrote jquery its way smaller John
Dalton turns out popped up was like dad
is you you're wrong everywhere
everything is wrong there's so many bugs
because dalton has this really
profoundly interesting way of
approaching library developers and that
he points out something which is really
valid like your thing doesn't work in
Opera some old opera that no one uses in
this weird use case that's totally valid
and then posts like a really
frustrating animated gift which trolls
the out of you makes me feel like
an asshole and so the first like 15 or
so issues that he opens you're like this
guy ah you just close them you're like
block and what github I think they added
that feature for Dalton and but then
like as soon as you kind of cool down
and you're like okay like and you like
read the post there all he's right it's
just makes the gifts he hurt even more
and what it turns out is that starting
over is so hard it's so hard and a lot
of the value from things like jQuery no
libraries is that they're old which is
sad because I'm usually like hot old
people even though after coming up after
James and who's 19 now I feel like I'm
like a dinosaur appears stressing me out
it's just really hard but it's really
hard when you starting over from only
that which you know by heart because
everyone only kind of notes like that
special thing by heart right like they
have that really intimate relationship
with like something weird and there's
something like Dalton happens to know
like these really crazy things which is
great but it makes it really hard and so
is there a path forward I mean Dalton
can't comment on everything like you
can't be there to point out like hey
this will work like dude screwing up
natives or something and and I think
there is there's these things called
tests that you might have heard of
they're pretty useful it turns out crazy
right and so the second kind of
attempted just totally starting over was
this library that Rob's air and I worked
on which is called a ho Kang Jas if
you're familiar with it Hogan Jas is
essentially a of mustache and JavaScript
so when we said that when we first
released that people were like oh cool
story bro there's already mustache yes
it does the same thing like what are you
doing um and we're like no no listen
listen listen that's really good hold on
and I get some I skip a beat well
basically it's good because it's just
way better in every way and so what
mustache really enabled us to do was
they had this interesting model where
mustache templating instead of it being
like this is our like librarian it's
this implementation they open so they
have like a special project in there
like whole world which is the specs
directory which has all their specs laid
out in JSON and yamel so it makes it
really easy for different languages to
implement them and you have to implement
like and get all these tests passing in
order to be considered like running the
mustache like spec in like 4 10 and so
what that enabled for us to do was to
say okay like the reason why we
initially wanted to rewrite it I'm
assessed yes is because it was really
slow for us and particularly in ie7
because they were doing all the
compiling and all the parsing and
everything on the fly in JavaScript we
were like this is wrong like why would
you do it here like a precompiled doy
and like plus like let's speed up
everything and so we did that we wrote
Hogan which at exactly what mustache did
it was totally different we improved the
performance by like I just a stupid
amount like an embarrassingly a huge
amount the library size of small
everything was better there's the day we
released Hogan like if you didn't switch
over right away like come on like why
are you what are you waiting for it was
crazy and sorry there's some Spanish um
so oh my gosh totally lost method also
go to the next slide okay yeah so
basically what happens is we release
this thing it's really great and
mustache says oh most yes chance we
actually have someone who works on the
mustache jayus library this guy named
Michael Jackson at Twitter who's totally
awesome and he was like oh my god yeah
this is like just as all this things is
different and so mustache like changes
and they evolve and they had pre
compiling and they do a bunch of other
really cool stuff and now we have this
like really health healthy like
evolution of implementation towards a
common spec and we have this competition
around a common spec and so all of a
sudden like things for like comply users
like you guys just got so much better so
fast and it was amazing
and then like we like hugged it out and
things were really good and we're like
really happy there's like little hearts
and stuff so good so good girl and what
afterwards ok this is this will be all
right come hug time Oh time thank you
thank you hugs so good oh my god that
was like a football style hug all right
um oh my gosh I can't believe that
happened is good though Wow room
three-twelve if you want to continue
that later so so we got this awesome
thing we have these tests passing
mustache makes it really easy because
you can just like there's this test
suite and it's just awesome and we
didn't want to like just give a pull
request to you guys which was like
delete your library here's your new
library no because no one really wants
to see that like we've seen this nodejs
trolls to CoffeeScript and it didn't
turn out good like I don't want the like
so we had to release our libraries the
whole thing because people asked us that
often like why didn't you pull requests
like okay delete your library replace
applies kind of awkward um and so now
what yeah why would Hugo say that why
would he say you know like wanted to say
that um and I think after I thought
about this for a long time it's just
because things get better and I just let
that you get hugs which is great and
things just get better for everyone if
we like do this sort of stuff and so my
questions that I wanted to kind of end
this whole talk thing on we're really
why are we sharing all our tests like
why aren't we doing this thing that
mustache is doing more often like why
why isn't this a thing like why don't we
see this everywhere why don't we see
people coming together around spec in
order to implement a library um so like
common things that you would expect to
see this sort of thing in would be like
selector engines or dom utilities or
less for example my friend Alexi he's
like so tired of maintaining less he
recently added some other contributors
but I was like dude just why don't you
just write unit tests
be like whoever's you want like
implement this why isn't there like a
common thing for events xhr like all
these things that we use all the time
they're kind of is something that I kind
of soft for selector engines that was
called like slick shootout but then
there was like all this flame war around
it there's just not and it you want to
come up here tom okay sorry I heard him
Charlie this is not allowed come on um
oh it's just calling slick speed yeah
yeah and so like I mean once looks me
came out I was like oh yeah this looks
like about right John Resig was like all
know this is like totally F like you're
doing all these things wrong and valerio
and then that you know they have their
back and forth and so but basically out
I guess I'm wondering what if going
forward we define a library not so much
by its implementation but by its test
suite and and then a bigger ramification
of this kind of is like what happens if
we burn da library burned all libraries
without test Suites and like how amazing
that would be because I actually
originally had a slide which had called
out a bunch of like libraries with over
a thousand Watchers that were JavaScript
that had 0 unit tests which is sadly a
huge amount so if you're in this room
and you're like oh yeah I run this thing
it's awesome people love it use it every
day but units it's not my jam turns out
super important you should write them
real like right now I don't even go to
the next talk probably gonna be horrible
chest up no I'm kidding it's gonna be so
much better than the stock they're gonna
dig that's it just go just write unit
tests oh my god and so that's basically
it actually I was going to edit this
slide and I forgot so I want to do it on
the fly and so what that's basically the
morals sorry uh let me stay here fake
um but yeah that's basically that's all
I really had to say was like oh that's
Brenda larousse follow fake Angus yeah